<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Daniel Crawford &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Simon Johnson on Tim Geithner and Elizabeth Warren</title>
		<link>./../../2011/03/simon-johnson-on-tim-geithner-and-elizabeth-warren.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/03/simon-johnson-on-tim-geithner-and-elizabeth-warren.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Mar 2011 12:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Bank Crisis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bank failure]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Banks and Financial Institutions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Daniel Crawford]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Great Recession]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/03/simon-johnson-on-tim-geithner-and-elizabeth-warren.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Simon Johnson offers pointed criticism of the role Timothy Geithner has played to date in the Great Recession and bank regulation, in particular as an advisor and architect to the Obama economic team and how that policy is presented and pursued in Congress. Another worthwhile read.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a target="_blank" href="http://baselinescenario.com/2011/03/17/whos-afraid-of-elizabeth-warren/">Simon Johnson offers pointed criticism</a> of the role Timothy Geithner has played to date in the Great Recession and bank regulation, in particular as an advisor and architect to the Obama economic team and how that policy is presented and pursued in Congress.   Another worthwhile read.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/03/simon-johnson-on-tim-geithner-and-elizabeth-warren.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>WTO ruling: &#8216;free trade&#8217; and &#8216;state capitalism&#8217; needs broader discussion</title>
		<link>./../../2011/03/wto-ruling-free-trade-and-state-capitalism-needs-broader-discussion.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/03/wto-ruling-free-trade-and-state-capitalism-needs-broader-discussion.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2011 13:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Daniel Crawford]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[trade policy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WTO]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/03/wto-ruling-free-trade-and-state-capitalism-needs-broader-discussion.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[A recent ruling on countervailing duties and anti-dumping duties by the World Trade Organization:(bolding is mine) Senior Economist Ian Fletcher for the Coalition for a Prosperous America offers one point of view: The American position is that we are entitled to apply what are called “countervailing duties” against products that are subsidized by foreign governments. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a title="http://www.wto.org/" href="http://www.wto.org/english/tratop_e/dispu_e/379abr_conc_e.pdf">A recent ruling on countervailing duties and anti-dumping duties</a> by the <a href="http://www.wto.org/" target="-blank">World Trade Organization</a>:<br />(bolding is mine)</p>
<p>Senior Economist Ian Fletcher for the Coalition for a Prosperous America offers one point of view:
</p>
<blockquote><p>The American position is that we are entitled to apply what are called “countervailing duties” against products that are subsidized by foreign governments. And on top of that, we are also entitled to apply duties designed to counteract the practice of dumping, or selling a product below cost in order to destroy foreign competitors.<br />Both these responses on our part have long histories of being accepted as legitimate, both under international trade law and in economics. (This is why the WTO had originally accepted our position; the new ruling is actually the result of an appeal by China.)<br /><a name="more"></a><br />In terms of international law, one can trace the legitimacy of our policies at least as far back as the founding of the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade, the WTO’s predecessor, in 1947.<br />In terms of economics, their justifying logic is very simple.<br />In the case of subsidies, free trade only makes sense if it really is free, which means that a thumb on the scale at one end of the transaction justifies a tariff, or counter-subsidy, at the other end.<br />In the case of dumping, free trade is not justified if one side sells below cost in order to wipe out the other and thus eventually grab the market (or most of it) for itself. Even if the attempt fails, the damage done to our industries will be real, and by then it will be too late.<br />There’s no serious question about whether China engages in subsidies and dumping. That’s why, in this case, we imposed duties of up to 200 percent to offset their subsidies, plus up to 265 percent to counteract their dumping.<br /><strong>Enter state capitalism. The flashpoint of the current dispute centers on the vexed question of what price constitutes dumping in a non-free-market economy.</strong><br />In a free-market economy like our own, dumping is considered to occur when a product is sold abroad for either less than its production cost, or less than what it is sold for domestically. Unfortunately, in an economy like China’s, which is so tightly controlled by the government that many prices are essentially whatever the government says they are, this logic doesn’t work. There are no normal prices to observe in order to figure out how big the subsidy is. So the U.S. Government has been using various statistical techniques to calculate the relevant prices.<br />The WTO has ruled that our techniques are not legit. Bottom line? We&#8217;re supposed to overlook the vast panoply of subsidies—ranging from free land to cheap loans and a million different tax credits—because state capitalism makes them tricky to calculate.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/03/wto-ruling-free-trade-and-state-capitalism-needs-broader-discussion.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Pensions in the political economist world</title>
		<link>./../../2011/03/pensions-in-the-political-economist-world.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/03/pensions-in-the-political-economist-world.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2011 02:16:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Daniel Crawford]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[pensions]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/03/pensions-in-the-political-economist-world.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Center for Business Public Policy&#8217;s Jeffrey Brown wrote a simple economic critique of David Cay Johnston&#8217;s (Tax.com) piece on pensions. David Cay Johnston dropped by with some lengthy comments and replies. Well worth reading the entire thing, especially the comments.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a target="_blank" href="http://businesspublicpolicy.com/">Center for Business Public Policy&#8217;s</a> Jeffrey Brown wrote a simple economic critique of <a target="_blank" href="http://www.tax.com/taxcom/taxblog.nsf/Permalink/UBEN-8EDJYS">David Cay Johnston&#8217;s (Tax.com) piece on pensions</a>.</p>
<p>David Cay Johnston dropped by with some lengthy comments and replies.  Well worth reading the entire thing, especially the comments.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/03/pensions-in-the-political-economist-world.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Take a break &#8230;planning for efficiency</title>
		<link>./../../2011/03/take-a-break-planning-for-efficiency.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/03/take-a-break-planning-for-efficiency.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2011 14:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Daniel Crawford]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[efficiency]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[global economies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[supply chains]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/03/take-a-break-planning-for-efficiency.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Yves Smith at Naked Capitalism points us to exploring how the pursuit of &#8220;efficiency&#8221;, for example in supply chains, without assessing what other risks are involved and planning ahead can result in major problems: It isn’t all that hard to understand that stressing efficiency at all cost comes at the expense of safety. Engineers will [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a target="_blank" href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2011/03/japan-earthquake-shows-business-reengineering-relies-on-bogus-thinking-similar-to-financial-engineering.html">Yves Smith</a> at Naked Capitalism points us to exploring how the pursuit of &#8220;efficiency&#8221;, for example in supply chains, without assessing what other risks are involved and planning ahead can result in major problems:<br />
<blockquote>
<p>It isn’t all that hard to understand that stressing efficiency at all cost comes at the expense of safety. Engineers will tell you that efforts that are pro-safety involve various forms of buffers and redundancy and are thus costly. During the early days of the crisis, commentators often discussed the implications of Richard Bookstaber’s book A Demon of Our Own Design, in which he argued that systems that lacked breaks between various processes were tightly coupled, which meant that a failure at one point in the process would propagate through the entire system, as if one transformer failing would bring down an entire electrical grid.</p>
<p> <a name="more"></a>
<p>Anyone who has been on the periphery of manufacturing can see that all its fads can easily have pushed too many companies into failure-prone systems. Just in time inventory was a reversal of the historical propensity of manufactures to carry a lot of inventory to make life easier for managers. That practice in isolation might not be a bad thing. But over the years, many manufacturers have also concentrated on limiting the number of vendors to give them more bargaining leverage with them and squeeze them on costs. That increases dependence on suppliers while also increasing the riskiness of their operations. It has finally become fashionable to work with vendors or offshored factories in countries with low labor costs like China, Bangladesh, and Vietnam. Long transit times also increases business risk. </p>
<p>Now of course, like traders, top manager have every reason not to be terribly worried about long term risks. The prototype of the profitable but risky trading strategies that Nicholas Nassim Taleb likes to deride is that they work just fine on a day to day basis but blow up catastrophically periodically.<strong><em> And those blowups are predictable. </em></strong>But as long as they aren’t likely to happen every year or every other year, decision-makers have huge incentives that increase risk as long as the blow-up risk is not all that imminent (I am waiting for a quant to devise an optimal blow up metric as a covert trading strategy tool). So we should also regard the fact that business managers have acted exactly like reckless traders to be an expected outcome. </p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/03/take-a-break-planning-for-efficiency.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
