<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>taxes on pensions &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Town Hall Meetings on the Ryan Budget Raise Concerns</title>
		<link>./../../2011/04/town-hall-meetings-on-the-ryan-budget-raise-concerns.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/04/town-hall-meetings-on-the-ryan-budget-raise-concerns.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 29 Apr 2011 19:07:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[GOP Budget Proposal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health Care]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[House Budget Proposal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medicaid]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medicare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medicare vouchers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Renee Ellmers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[State Taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[taxes on pensions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[town hall meetings]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/04/town-hall-meetings-on-the-ryan-budget-raise-concerns.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Various congressional representatives held town hall meetings recently, and the news channels and print media were abuzz with the lively give-and-take, including shouting matches. See, e.g., House G.O.P. Members Face Voter Anger Over Budget, New York Times, Apr. 26, 2011; Republicans facing tough questions over Medicare overhaul in Budget Plan, Washington Post, Apr. 22, 2011. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Various congressional representatives held town hall meetings recently, and the news channels and print media were abuzz with the lively give-and-take, including shouting matches. See, e.g., <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/04/27/us/politics/27congress.html" target="_blank" _mce_href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/04/27/us/politics/27congress.html">House G.O.P. Members Face Voter Anger Over Budget</a>, New York Times, Apr. 26, 2011; <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/republicans-facing-tough-questions-over-medicare-overhaul-in-budget-plan/2011/04/22/AFjSRgRE_story.html" target="_blank" _mce_href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/republicans-facing-tough-questions-over-medicare-overhaul-in-budget-plan/2011/04/22/AFjSRgRE_story.html">Republicans facing tough questions over Medicare overhaul in Budget Plan</a>, Washington Post, Apr. 22, 2011.</p>
<p>The issue&#8211;the House&#8217;s adoption of the Ryan budget proposal and its clear agenda of overturning New Deal safety nets embodied in the current understanding of Medicaid, Social Security and Medicare.</p>
<p>Those at or near retirement are worried that the Ryan proposal will hurt everybody. The Ryan proposal comes with frequent disclaimers about protecting the already older population and needing to act now to protect our grandchildren, a clear effort to massage the message to appeal to current grandparents. See, e.g., <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/04/27/us/politics/27congress.html" target="_blank" _mce_href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/04/27/us/politics/27congress.html">House G.O.P. Members Face Voter Anger Over Budget</a>, New York Times, Apr. 26, 2011 (noting Webster&#8217;s statement that &#8220;not one senior citizen is harmed by this budget&#8221; while implying that it is necessary to prevent grandchildren from &#8220;looking at a bankrupt country&#8221;); <a href="http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2011/04/26/ap/national/main20057685.shtml" target="_blank" _mce_href="http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2011/04/26/ap/national/main20057685.shtml">Congressional Republicans go home to mixed reveiws</a>, CBS.com, Apr. 26, 2011 (noting North Carolina GOP Rep. Renee Ellmers&#8217;claim that &#8220;If you&#8217;re 55 and older, your Medicare and Social Security will not change&#8221;).<br /><a name="more"></a><br />But the Ryan proposal clearly envisions mechanisms that would likely lead to decimation of these programs&#8211;either through turning them into limited vouchers (Medicare proposal); turning the funds over to the states to use as they see fit (Medicaid proposal) or limiting benefits (Social Security proposal) in ways that will &#8211;probably sooner rather than later&#8211; hurt everybody.</p>
<p>
<ul>
<li>These proposals take place in a context of expansive, concerted attacks on these &#8220;entitlement&#8221; programs, often failing to acknowledge the historic support for these programs or their foundation in the recognition that federal support is required to protect against the abject poverty and humiliating degradation that accompanied the Great Depression;</li>
<li>Benefits for elderly and sick Americans are cut to provide savings to offset some of the loss of revenues from tax cuts for Big Business and the wealthy, both of whom already pay relatively low taxes, in what hardly seems a bargain to the working poor, the elderly or in fact the overwhelming majority of Americans who are not in the top 15% income or wealth distribution. (This in spite of Ryan&#8217;s claim that there is no huge tax cut for big corporations and the wealthy&#8211;he asserts that the proposed 25% rate is &#8220;in exchange for losing their tax shelters&#8221;. See, e.g., CBS.com <a href="http://www.cbsnews.com/video/watch/?id=7363939n&#038;tag=related;photovideo" target="_blank" _mce_href="http://www.cbsnews.com/video/watch/?id=7363939n&#038;tag=related;photovideo">Evening News coverage of Paul Ryan holding Wis. town meetings</a>, at <a href="http://www.cbsnews.com/video/watch/?id=7363939n&#038;tag=related;photovideo" _mce_href="http://www.cbsnews.com/video/watch/?id=7363939n&#038;tag=related;photovideo">http://www.cbsnews.com/video/watch/?id=7363939n&#038;tag=related;photovideo</a> )</li>
<li>In spite of the high cost for the vulnerable poor and elderly of these budget proposals, they don&#8217;t appear likely to achieve their proffered rationale of reducing debt and deficits&#8211;in fact, the CBO has said that the Ryan budget proposal will result in higher deficits and bigger debt burdens over the next decade.</li>
<p>
<li>It appears shortsighted to wring one&#8217;s hands about a &#8220;bankrupt country&#8221; while considering only one potential solution, especially when that solution is highly detrimental to the most vulnerable populations, and without considering the full facts regarding the amount of debt, the ability of the U.S. to weaken the dollar further to aid unemployment and debt payment, the ability of the U.S. to raise taxes judiciously rather then merely cutting spending, or the ability of the U.S. to let the tax law play out as it is currently slated to do (with the Bush tax cuts that were extended 2 more years over their originally intended short life due to sunset in 2012). As Jim Johnson, a former Ryan supporter who has &#8220;grown increasingly disgusted&#8221; with Ryan noted, &#8220;[Ryan] says Medicare is unsustainable. I&#8217;m thinking, &#8216;Yeah, it&#8217;s because medical costs are out of control.&#8217; &#8230;Why isn&#8217;t he attacking it at that level?&#8221; <a href="http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2011/04/26/ap/national/main20057685.shtml" target="_blank" _mce_href="http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2011/04/26/ap/national/main20057685.shtml">Congressional Republicans go home to mixed reviews</a>, CBS News.com</li>
<p>
<li>Any voucher system for health care will inevitably fail to cover increasing health care costs, resulting in rationing even the most basic health care by socio-economic class&#8211;the very problem that Medicare, Medicaid, and the limited health care reforms undertaken by the last Congress were intended to address. The Center for Budget and Policy Priorities concluded that <a href="http://www.cbpp.org/cms/index.cfm?fa=view&#038;id=3473">out-of-pocket medical costs would skyrocket for low-income seniors</a>; the Washington Post&#8217;s Fact Checker Glenn Kessler (in <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/fact-checker/post/gop-lawmakers-tout-medicare-reform-by-stretching-a-comparison-to-the-health-benefits-they-receive/2011/04/28/AFrRkM9E_blog.html">GOP Lawmakers tout Medicare reform by stretching a comparison to the health benefits they receive</a>, Apr. 29, 2011) notes that the CBO analysis concluded that the Ryan Medicare system would pay only 32% of health care costs by 2030, compared to 70-75% if traditional Medicare remained in place.</li>
<p>
<li>Addressing the problems in the U.S. health care system solely by market means that put the onus on health care recipients to seek cost-savings has failed miserably over the last forty years and cannot help but fail more spectacularly when the Medicaid backup is weakened and the nature of health care needs is such that one of the best antidotes to market problems (the only one permitted in radical market thinking that objects to regulatory safeguards)&#8211;informed consumers who can review options and select among competing providers&#8211;is simply not applicable. Car accident victims don&#8217;t shop for surgeons; cancer victims don&#8217;t know enough to select based on price; etc.</li>
<li>The Ryan proposal appears one-sided in its decision to cut spending on potentially vulnerable populations rather than to address the means through which health care is provided or to consider ways to control profit-taking in the health care system. The market ideology of the proposers leaves many options that might work better off the table (single payer; tax on excessive compensation; revamping the non-profit hospital system; attaching strings to the R&#038;D and other tax expenditures in the tax code; using the clout of a national system to negotiate better doctor and drug pricing for Medicare and Medicaid, etc.);</li>
<li>Many of those states that would acquire more control over the use of Medicaid funds are controlled now, as is the House, by people who have announced their intent to cut taxes on the wealthy and business while cutting or taxing pensions and health benefits for public employees and cutting funds available for Medicaid and other poverty-directed programs; it is not a difficult leap to see the interrelationship of these trends;</li>
<li>Plans to cut benefits for those who may enjoy them in the future pave the way in at least two ways for decisions shortly thereafter to cut benefits for those who currently enjoy them: first, by creating lowered expectations; second, by creating an unfair disparity that supports an &#8220;us against them&#8221; attitude between the current elderly and those who will get lesser benefits in the future. (Note that this resembles the way the right has encouraged an &#8220;us against them&#8221; attitude of <em>private workers</em>, who have been deprived of union benefits through the harsh anti-union tactics used by Big Business, against <em>public employees</em>, who have generally benefited in the past from more reasonable attitudes towards unions fostered in legislative bodies that have, in the past, understood the nature of the bargain that public employees make (which might be summarized as &#8216;work hard, get paid less than you could in the private sector, and accept later benefits in pensions and health care for lesser salary/percs now).</li>
</ul>
<p>
<p>Is is surprising that left-leaning activist groups like Move-On point to the Ryan budget proposal as a &#8220;naked, unapologetic attack on working Americans for the sake of Big Insurance and the riches of the rich&#8221; (quote from Move-On email on this matter)?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/04/town-hall-meetings-on-the-ryan-budget-raise-concerns.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
