<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>war tax &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>To pay for the next war&#8230;we raise taxes, cut spending elsewhere?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/06/to-pay-for-the-next-war-we-raise-taxes-cut-spending-elsewhere.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/06/to-pay-for-the-next-war-we-raise-taxes-cut-spending-elsewhere.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Jun 2012 12:22:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2012 elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[war tax]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/06/to-pay-for-the-next-war-we-raise-taxes-cut-spending-elsewhere.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The Armed Services full committee meeting in light of the end of the latest round of talks with Iran and harsher sanctions (oil embargo) scheduled to take effect, points us to the need to figure out how to pay for another conflict that is not quick and victorious. The Washington Post quotes Senator Leahy: At [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a target="_blank" href="http://armedservices.house.gov/index.cfm/hearings-display?ContentRecord_id=b3c53146-0c0e-4eea-b99e-3c1f308ad5a6&#038;ContentType_id=14f995b9-dfa5-407a-9d35-56cc7152a7ed&#038;Group_id=13e47ffa-0753-47a7-ad5e-1ba7592015c9">The Armed Services full committee meeting</a> in light of the end of the latest round of talks with Iran and harsher sanctions (oil embargo) scheduled to take effect, points us to the need to figure out how to pay for another conflict that is not quick and victorious.</p>
<p><a target="_blank" href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/national-security/somebody-in-government-finally-asks-a-taxing-question-about-the-next-war/2012/06/20/gJQA7HeLrV_story.html">The Washington Post</a> quotes Senator Leahy:</p>
<blockquote><p>At last, after 11 years of the United States at war, a few minutes of public discussion of a tax to pay for the fighting. But that would be for the next war.</p>
<blockquote><p>“What would be the impact of going to war again without committing to pay for that war with up-front taxes, something we did not do in either Iraq or Afghanistan, for the first time in the history of the country?” Sen. Patrick J. Leahy (D-Vt.) asked Defense Secretary Leon E. Panetta at a Senate Defense Appropriation subcommittee hearing on June 13.</p>
<p>That’s a question that should be asked before any president sends U.S. forces into a fight overseas or members of Congress propose legislation that authorizes some sort of military action abroad.</p>
<p>“We basically ran that war [Iraq] on a credit card,” Leahy told Panetta, who was there to discus the fiscal 2013 Defense Appropriations bill. “Now we find people who are calling for more military action in other parts of the world; at the same time, they do not want to consider any way of paying for it.”</p></blockquote>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/06/to-pay-for-the-next-war-we-raise-taxes-cut-spending-elsewhere.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
