<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>huckabee &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Fantasy: &#034;If only someone had a gun&#034;. Reality: Lakewood Wash Nov 29, 2009</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/fantasy-if-only-someone-had-a-gun-reality-lakewood-wash-nov-29-2009.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/fantasy-if-only-someone-had-a-gun-reality-lakewood-wash-nov-29-2009.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 20 Dec 2012 04:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[huckabee]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NRA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sandy hook shooting]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/fantasy-if-only-someone-had-a-gun-reality-lakewood-wash-nov-29-2009.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[&#8216;Horror scene&#8217; as 4 Lakewood police officers shot, killed LAKEWOOD, Wash. &#8211; Four uniformed police officers were shot and killed in a bloody Sunday morning attack at a Lakewood-area coffee shop, and investigators are seeking a person of interest in the killings, officials said.Pierce County Sheriff&#8217;s Office spokesman Ed Troyer said the person they are [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<h4><a href="http://www.komonews.com/news/local/78088192.html">&#8216;Horror scene&#8217; as 4 Lakewood police officers shot, killed</a></h4>
<blockquote><p>LAKEWOOD, Wash. &#8211; Four uniformed police officers were shot and killed in a bloody Sunday morning attack at a Lakewood-area coffee shop, and investigators are seeking a person of interest in the killings, officials said.Pierce County Sheriff&#8217;s Office spokesman Ed Troyer said the person they are seeking is Maurice Clemmons, who is a fugitive from Arkansas with a lengthy criminal record.</p></blockquote>
<p>Not to be flip but is there a more hardened target in America than a fricking DONUT SHOP known as a pre-shift COP SHOP? Are we to imagine that everything would have been fine if four kindergarten and first grade teachers/armed monitors from the nearest elementary school had been having some pre-school coffee and going over their paperwork just as the cops were? Or maybe if the girl behind the counter had been packing?</p>
<p>And if we didn&#8217;t need more irony we have this:</p>
<h4><a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2009/11/29/multiple-police-officers-_n_373119.html">Huckabee Granted Clemency To Maurice Clemmons, Person Of Interest, In Ambush That Killed 4 Cops</a></h4>
<blockquote><p>A man with an extensive criminal past &#8212; whose 95-year prison sentence was commuted in Arkansas nearly a decade ago by then-Gov. Mike Huckabee&#8211; was being sought Sunday as a &#8220;person of interest&#8221; in a deadly ambush on four police officers who were gunned down inside a coffee shop.</p></blockquote>
<p>Snip<br />
<blockquote>In 1989, Clemmons, then 17, was convicted in Little Rock for aggravated robbery. He was paroled in 2000 after then-Gov. Mike Huckabee commuted Clemmons&#8217; 95-year prison sentence. Huckabee, who was criticized during his run for the Republican presidential nomination in 2008 for the number of clemencies and commutations he granted, cited Clemmons&#8217; age at the time of the sentence.<br />After his release from prison, Clemmons violated his parole and was returned to prison in July 2001. He was released March 18, 2004, according to the Arkansas Democrat-Gazette newspaper .</p></blockquote>
<p>But even without the sickening hypocrisy of Huckabee blaming the Sandy Hook shooting on the failure of first graders to engage in state sponsored prayer, we have a case of four trained, armed police officers just minutes from going on patrol being caught mostly unaware by a shooter determined to kill. In light of that the suggestion that all would have been well if only that principal had a M-4 locked in a cabinet in her office ring pretty hollow.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/fantasy-if-only-someone-had-a-gun-reality-lakewood-wash-nov-29-2009.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
