<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Paul Ryan &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>John Boehner Needs a Dictionary</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/john-boehner-needs-a-dictionary.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/john-boehner-needs-a-dictionary.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2013 17:14:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Greg Sargent]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Boehner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mainstream-journalism gimmickry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitch McConnell]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[semantics gimmickry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Washington Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/john-boehner-needs-a-dictionary.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[All of these bipartisan discussions are encouraging, and Republicans hope they will lead to real solutions that help American families. But presidential leadership is really what’s needed. By shifting the focus from charm to courage, and eventually action, we can guarantee our children a future where everyone has the opportunity to find work and pursue [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">All of these bipartisan discussions are encouraging, and Republicans hope they will lead to real solutions that help American families. But presidential leadership is really what’s needed. By shifting the focus from charm to courage, and eventually action, we can guarantee our children a future where everyone has the opportunity to find work and pursue their piece of the American dream. That would be the grandest bargain of all.</div>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/john-boehner-obamas-intraparty-problem/2013/03/13/455e097e-8c19-11e2-b63f-f53fb9f2fcb4_story.html">Obama’s outreach is nice, but where’s the leadership?</a>, John Boehner, Op-ed, Washington Post, today</div>
<p>I have what I think is a better question, this one for the speaker: Where’s a dictionary?</p>
<p>One of the most pernicious aspects of these phony, sequential fiscal crises is, in my opinion, the Republicans’ tactic of selecting single words or short phrases that have an appealing meaning and using them to mean something else entirely&#8211;often something the opposite of what the word or phrase actually means.  It’s so clearly concerted, political-consultant-suggested, Madison Avenue-type sales gimmickry; every few days there’s a new messaging word or short phrase, redefined or otherwise-misleadingly used, and then repeated, repeated, repeated … repeated.   </p>
<p>Enter “leadership.”  And now, “courage.”  As in: the president should demonstrate these qualities by delegating to the Tea Party the fiscal policy of the United States, because the Tea Party is now the Republican Party and it wants to disassemble the federal government <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/plum-line/wp/2013/03/14/the-morning-plum-wheres-the-leadership-john-boehner/">and will settle for nothing less</a>.* </p>
<p>So I suggest that Obama offer Boehner a dictionary and ask him to point to where it defines leadership as abdication, and courage as cowering.  Whether you’re the president or, say, the Speaker of the House.  </p>
<p>Maybe more to the point, where in the dictionary definition of either leadership or courage does it define those words as including doing absolutely whatever is necessary to keep your position as House speaker, regardless of the consequences to the country you took an oath of office to serve?  Neither the Merriam-Webster’s nor the Oxford English limits those terms to references to the president of the United States.  The definitions do look broad enough to include the speaker.  And even the Senate minority leader.  Even ones who are petrified (literally, it appears from the look on his face these days) of being “primaried” by a Tea Party candidate.  </p>
<p>The Orwellian redefinition of words to mean the opposite of, or at least something entirely different than, their actual meaning is a standard propaganda and subterfuge tool of dictatorships. Mao Tse-tung was infamous for this.  And so, of course, was Hitler.  (The inscription in German, “Work will make you free,” remains above the front gate of Auschwitz in Oswiecim, Poland, a permanent reminder of the deeply sinister nature of extreme semantics games employed in the service of political propaganda.) </p>
<p>That so much of the proud-centrist punditry and fair-and-balanced mainstream media have assisted Boehner &#038; Friends in their sophistry in the last month is inexcusable, if no longer surprising.  If they agree with Boehner that the Ryan budget will guarantee our children a future where everyone has the opportunity to find work and pursue their piece of the American dream, then they should explain why.  If they believe instead that the Ryan budget will guarantee our children a future in which <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ayn_Rand">Atlas really </a><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ayn_Rand">has</a><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ayn_Rand"> shrugged and everyone lives inside The Fountainhead</a> (or maybe in the Pakistan of North America), then they should say that, and explain why. At least the news analysis writers and the centrist pundits should. </p>
<p>They won’t.  But maybe a few of them will point out that, with due respect to Mr. Boehner, the grandest bargain of all would be a free Webster’s Collegiate delivered to the Speaker’s office on Capitol Hill. </p>
<p>As for Obama, he got lucky in the last two days.  The Ryan budget will disabuse a clear majority of the next poll responders that the GOP should be trusted with determining what cuts to make to the federal budget, and when.  At least if the public actually learns the specifics.  (That, of course, would have been true for the last few years, had Obama deigned to apprise the public of the specifics.)  And the live &#8220;tweets&#8221; from the Republican House-member attendees during their meeting with him yesterday were so vile that Obama really needs now only to recite a few of them in order to fully open the public&#8217;s eyes, if and when he decides to speak to the public about the actual situation.  </p>
<p>And, who knows?  Maybe he will, now that he&#8217;s checked off the extend-an-olive-branch box on the mainstream press&#8217;s list of what Leaders (if not necessarily Courageous ones) do, and therefore may even have their permission to do so.</p>
<p>*See Greg Sargent&#8217;s terrific Morning Plum column in today&#8217;s Washington Post.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/john-boehner-needs-a-dictionary.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Oh. Guess the Paul Ryan Bubble Finally Has Burst. So Sorry For Your Loss, Paul.</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/oh-guess-the-paul-ryan-bubble-finally-has-burst-so-sorry-for-your-loss-paul.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/oh-guess-the-paul-ryan-bubble-finally-has-burst-so-sorry-for-your-loss-paul.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2013 23:16:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dana Milbank]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Joseph N. Welch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Washington Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/oh-guess-the-paul-ryan-bubble-finally-has-burst-so-sorry-for-your-loss-paul.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In subtle ways, Ryan’s budget acknowledges the results of November’s election. He isn’t seeking to do away with tax increases that have already been approved, and he accepts that tax revenue will be 19.1 percent of the economy in a decade, up from the 18.7 percent he assumed last year. But otherwise, he continues to peddle the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">In subtle ways, Ryan’s budget acknowledges the results of November’s election. He isn’t seeking to do away with tax increases that have already been approved, and he accepts that tax revenue will be 19.1 percent of the economy in a decade, up from the 18.7 percent he assumed last year.</div>
<div dir="ltr">But otherwise, he continues to peddle the same ideas: the partial privatization of Medicare; a 10 percent reduction in the federal workforce; and cuts to Medicaid, food stamps, education, job training and farm programs.</div>
<div dir="ltr">Public Radio International’s Todd Zwillich pointed out that Republicans lost the presidency, House seats and the combined popular vote in House races. “People outside this process might wonder if elections have consequences,” Zwillich said.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">“Look, whether the country intended it or not, we have divided government,” Ryan replied, suggesting that Republicans somehow won the debate while losing the election. “Are a lot of these solutions very popular, and did we win these arguments in the campaign?” Ryan asked himself. “Some of us think so.”</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/03/paul-ryan-is-joe-mccarthy-of-our-era.html">Paul Ryan’s magical budget</a>, Dana Milbank, Washington Post</div>
<p>And those very same some of us think upside-down is rightside-up and aliens from Mars ate their calculator and their voter tabulations.  They need antipsychotic medication.  </p>
<div dir="ltr">He proposes abolishing Obamacare — a futile gesture — but would pocket for other purposes $1 trillion in tax increases that came with the program. &#8230;</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">CNN’s Dana Bash asked whether Ryan was being “disingenuous” by including new taxes that he opposed.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">“We’re not going to refight the past,” he explained.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">If Ryan is “not going to fight the past,” Fox News’s Chad Pergram asked, why is he still trying to repeal Obamacare?</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">“This to us is something that we’re not going to give up on,” Ryan answered, “because we’re not going to give up on destroying the health-care system for the American people.”</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Even a skilled illusionist can have the occasional Freudian slip.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/03/paul-ryan-is-joe-mccarthy-of-our-era.html">Paul Ryan’s magical budget</a>, Dana Milbank, Washington Post</div>
<p>Game’s over.  The mainstream media has had enough. They’re finally calling this spade a spade. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joseph_N._Welch">Joe Welch</a> <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/03/paul-ryan-is-joe-mccarthy-of-our-era.html">would be proud</a>. </p>
<p>At long last, Congressman, the people who matter see that you have left no sense of decency. Nor a semblance of mental health. Like Joe McCarthy.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/oh-guess-the-paul-ryan-bubble-finally-has-burst-so-sorry-for-your-loss-paul.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Paul Ryan Is the Joe McCarthy of Our Era. Maybe the Mainstream Media Finally Will Recognize That. Then Again, Maybe It Won’t.</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/paul-ryan-is-the-joe-mccarthy-of-our-era-maybe-the-mainstream-media-finally-will-recognize-that-then-again-maybe-it-wont.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/paul-ryan-is-the-joe-mccarthy-of-our-era-maybe-the-mainstream-media-finally-will-recognize-that-then-again-maybe-it-wont.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2013 16:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Edward R. Murrow]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Joe MCarthy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mainstream news media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Matthew Yglesias]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Walter Cronkite]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/paul-ryan-is-the-joe-mccarthy-of-our-era-maybe-the-mainstream-media-finally-will-recognize-that-then-again-maybe-it-wont.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Paul Ryan is, in effect, the Joe McCarthy of our era.  He consistently spews outlandishly false statements of fact, never offers actual evidence in support of them and never refutes factual challenges using actual and full facts, and tries as a matter of routine to obfuscate his specific and broader objectives and therefore to trick [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Paul Ryan is, in effect, the Joe McCarthy of our era.  He consistently spews <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/moneybox/2013/03/12/paul_ryan_currency_debasement.html">outlandishly false statements of fact</a>, never offers actual evidence in support of them and never refutes factual challenges using actual and full facts, and <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/moneybox/2013/03/12/class_war_budgeting_paul_ryan_and_house_gop_want_more_money_for_the_rich.html">tries <i>as a matter of routine</i> to obfuscate his specific and broader objectives </a>and therefore to trick the public.  </p>
<p>He is a serious nutcase.  And yet he has garnered mainstream media attention as though what he puts out is credible.  We have a mainstream media that treats this nutjob as though he were a legitimate policy wonk. And that acts as though facts are legitimately in the eye of the beholder.  </p>
<p>If only Obama were more like Ike.  And if only there were an Edward R. Murrow around now, although a Walter Cronkite would do, too.  If only.  </p>
<p>Broadcast news, of course, no longer has nearly the power and audience it once had, but we now have the veritable <i>reverse</i> of what this country once had in its highest-profile journalists.  and we have a president who cowers in the face of whatever media juggernaut is currently saying &#8220;boo.&#8221;  </p>
<p>True, Ike was buoyed, not hindered, by the mainstream press when he helped end the McCarthy stranglehold.  And McCarthy and Eisenhower were, technically anyway, members of the same political party, so there was no insistence that Eisenhower humor McCarthy in the name of bipartisanship.  But there&#8217;s also no law that requires the president, this one or any other, to mindlessly do the mainstream media&#8217;s bidding if that bidding is in the name of bipartisanship.  At least not when bipartisanship means delegating fiscal policy to a rightwing faction of a minority party that a majority of voters recently pretty-darned-clearly  rejected.</p>
<p>This is getting really, really scary.  </p>
<p>&#8212;-<br /><i>The links are to two Matthew Yglesias posts in Slate this morning.</i></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/paul-ryan-is-the-joe-mccarthy-of-our-era-maybe-the-mainstream-media-finally-will-recognize-that-then-again-maybe-it-wont.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Killing Mitt Softly: His Not Being In a Position To show Leadership By Persuading Rightwing Republicans to Agree to Their Own Policy Proposals</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/killing-mitt-softly-his-not-being-in-a-position-to-show-leadership-by-persuading-rightwing-republicans-to-agree-to-their-own-policy-proposals.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/killing-mitt-softly-his-not-being-in-a-position-to-show-leadership-by-persuading-rightwing-republicans-to-agree-to-their-own-policy-proposals.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2013 16:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Ann Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Annie Lowrey]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chris Wallace]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Fox News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[leadership]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politico]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reid J. Epstein]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The New York Times]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the sequester]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the Tea Party]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/killing-mitt-softly-his-not-being-in-a-position-to-show-leadership-by-persuading-rightwing-republicans-to-agree-to-their-own-policy-proposals.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Both Romneys said he would be more effective at navigating the current political moment. “I’ll look at what’s happening right now, I wish I were there,” Mitt Romney said. “It kills me not to be there, not to be in the White House doing what needs to be done. The president is the leader of [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">Both Romneys said he would be more effective at navigating the current political moment.</p>
</div>
<div dir="ltr">“I’ll look at what’s happening right now, I wish I were there,” Mitt Romney said. “It kills me not to be there, not to be in the White House doing what needs to be done. The president is the leader of the nation. The president brings people together, does the deals, does the trades, knocks the heads together; the president leads. And — and I don’t see that kind of — of leadership happening right now.”</p>
</div>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://www.politico.com/story/2013/03/mitt-romney-it-kills-me-not-to-be-president-88332.html#ixzz2Ma3DAStm">Mitt Romney: &#8216;It kills me&#8217; not to be president</a>, Reid J. Epstein, Politico, this morning, reporting on Mitt and Ann Romney&#8217;s recorded interview with fox News&#8217; Chris Wallace,* aired yesterday</div>
<p>Seriously, Mitt?  <i>Seriously</i>?  </p>
<p>You ran on a Tea Party fiscal agenda of lowering tax rates by 20%&#8211;a <i>huge</i> tax break for the wealthy&#8211;and increasing defense spending, and absolutely gutting social-safety-net spending.  You chose as your running mate the very architect of most of this fiscal plan, the exceptions being the across-the-board 20% tax cuts and the increased defense spending, although the tax cuts, if not the increased defense spending, would probably be an easy sell to the Tea Party folks.  And you claim that your superior <i>leadership</i> <i>skills</i> would enable you to persuade the Republican congressional delegation to agree, grudgingly, of course, to go along with this?</p>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />Yes, it would be a tough, uphill battle.  But onward, Mormon soldier.  Especially one with leadership skills.</p>
<p>The easier part, I guess, would be persuading the Senate Democrats to go along with this, by throwing them a bone or two&#8211;e.g., I’ll agree to not completely gut the Medicaid subsidies to elderly nursing home residents, since many nursing home owners vote Republican, and I’ll persuade the Tea Party legislators to give in on that!&#8211;and by reminding them that we just held an election that amounted to a referendum on my proposed fiscal plan versus the Democrats’ fiscal plan, and I won.  </p>
<p>And by reminding the Dem senators who are up for reelection in 2014 that their electoral “district,” unlike the House members’ districts, can’t be gerrymandered.  Not without changing the boundaries of your state, anyway, which might be hard to do.</p>
<p>And, well, since the Dem senators aren’t, y’know, <i>Republican</i> senators, much less Republican House members, they would understand that in fact we did just have an electoral referendum on these very issues.  And they would have enough respect for the concept of democracy to agree to compromise somewhat.</p>
<p>Elsewhere in that interview, Romney attributed his loss to the 47% videotape and to a wholesale (my word; not his) rejection by racial minorities.  Which he was tremendously effective in navigating as part of the current political moment when, a week after the election, when he no longer was soliciting campaign contributions from very wealthy Republicans but was instead apologizing to the ones who donated generously, he effectively reiterated his hostility and condescension toward both the 47% and racial minorities by attributing his loss to minorities&#8211;mainly Hispanics&#8211;who were eager for the gifts (his word; not mine) Obama was giving them, especially the gift of “free” healthcare, through Obamacare. </p>
<p>Yup, that’s what made the difference in the election.  Not a rejection of the Tea Party/Ryan/Romney fiscal plan, but gifts to Hispanics via Obamacare.   </p>
<p>Cluelessness continues to be a hallmark of Romney’s better half, as well.  Wife Ann, not to be outdone by her husband in missing the message of this election&#8211;that, by about five million votes in the presidential election. about one and one-half million votes in congressional elections, and by a clear majority in Senate elections, as well, the electorate rejected what Romney says his leadership as president would lead to&#8211;said all that was necessary for her husband to have won was for the public to learn how kind he is to members of his church, and to others he knows personally, when they need some kindnesses. </p>
<p>Really, Ann?  You really think that? </p>
<p>In an article today in the New York Times titled <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/03/04/us/politics/poor-face-most-pain-as-automatic-budget-cuts-take-effect.html?partner=rss&#038;emc=rss&#038;src=ig&#038;_r=0%20As">As Automatic Budget Cuts Go Into Effect, Poor May Be Hit Particularly Hard</a>, Times reporter Annie Lowrey reports that federal housing vouchers, including to many disabled people, in New York City and Seattle and other high-rent cities, are about to be cut off, as are federal financial assistance to homeless shelters.  But few of the people, at least outside Utah, who will be affected are members of Romney’s church or know him personally.  So neither Romney’s kindnesses in his personal life nor his leadership skills as president, had he won the election, would have helped them, although his wife fails to understand this.  </p>
<p>The fact is that Romney is not in the White House because a majority of the electorate <i>disagrees with him, </i>and with the Tea Party<i>, </i>about what needs to be done.  We do nonetheless await with bated breath his more effective navigation of the current political moment.  Assisted by wife Ann, his navigator. </p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />*CORRECTION: This post originally said the interview was with NBC&#8217;s David Gregory.  My sincere apology, NBC and Mr. Gregory.  Obviously, I didn&#8217;t watch the interview; I just read about it.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/killing-mitt-softly-his-not-being-in-a-position-to-show-leadership-by-persuading-rightwing-republicans-to-agree-to-their-own-policy-proposals.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Yup, John Boehner and Paul Ryan Are Right: The economy contracted in the fourth quarter because #spendingstheproblem and Keynesian Economics Doesn’t Work.</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/yup-john-boehner-and-paul-ryan-are-right-the-economy-contracted-in-the-fourth-quarter-because-spendingstheproblem-and-keynesian-economics-doesnt-work.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/yup-john-boehner-and-paul-ryan-are-right-the-economy-contracted-in-the-fourth-quarter-because-spendingstheproblem-and-keynesian-economics-doesnt-work.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2013 17:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[#spendingstheproblem]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Boehner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Keynesian economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/yup-john-boehner-and-paul-ryan-are-right-the-economy-contracted-in-the-fourth-quarter-because-spendingstheproblem-and-keynesian-economics-doesnt-work.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Construction has been one of the more encouraging sectors, adding jobs each of the last four months. The hiring there was probably because of a combination of rebuilding from Hurricane Sandy, unseasonably warm weather that led to fewer work stoppages, and the nascent housing recovery, said Ian Shepherdson, chief economist at Pantheon Macroeconomic Advisors. Retailing, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">Construction has been one of the more encouraging sectors, adding jobs each of the last four months. The hiring there was probably because of a combination of rebuilding from <a href="http://topics.nytimes.com/top/reference/timestopics/subjects/h/hurricanes_and_tropical_storms/index.html?inline=nyt-classifier">Hurricane Sandy</a>, unseasonably warm weather that led to fewer work stoppages, and the nascent housing recovery, said Ian Shepherdson, chief economist at Pantheon Macroeconomic Advisors.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Retailing, health care and the wholesale trade also added positions in January, while the government again shed jobs. Government payrolls have been shrinking most months over the last four years.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/02/business/economy/us-adds-157000-jobs-unemployment-rate-edges-up-to-7-9.html?emc=na&#038;pagewanted=all">Job Growth Is Steady Amid Snags Holding Back Economy</a>, Catherine Rampell, New York Times, today</div>
<p><a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/01/paul-ryan-says-taxes-should-be-raised.html">Bring on</a> <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/01/john-boehner-says-defense-spending-is.html">the sequester</a>, I say!  Let’s get that economy <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/01/opinion/krugman-looking-for-mister-goodpain.html?_r=1&#038;">going again</a>! </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/yup-john-boehner-and-paul-ryan-are-right-the-economy-contracted-in-the-fourth-quarter-because-spendingstheproblem-and-keynesian-economics-doesnt-work.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Brian Williams Thinks Raising the Debt Ceiling Means Increasing BUDGET APPROPRIATIONS. O Peter Jennings, Walter Cronkite, and Edward R. Murrow, Where Art Thou? &#8212; [UPDATED]</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/brian-williams-thinks-raising-the-debt-ceiling-means-increasing-budget-appropriations-o-peter-jennings-walter-cronkite-and-edward-r-murrow-where-art-thou-updated.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/brian-williams-thinks-raising-the-debt-ceiling-means-increasing-budget-appropriations-o-peter-jennings-walter-cronkite-and-edward-r-murrow-where-art-thou-updated.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2013 15:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[austerity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Brian Williams]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Keynesian economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NBC Nightly News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Krugman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the debt ceiling]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The New York Times]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/brian-williams-thinks-raising-the-debt-ceiling-means-increasing-budget-appropriations-o-peter-jennings-walter-cronkite-and-edward-r-murrow-where-art-thou-updated.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I watched NBC Nightly News with Brian Williams last night.  Big Mistake. Big mistake. Because now I’m really confused.  I was pretty darn sure until then that “raising the debt ceiling” meant allowing the Treasury Department to pay financial obligations already incurred, such as interest on bonds, Medicare payments, and contract obligations, and to allow [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I watched NBC Nightly News with Brian Williams last night.  Big Mistake. </p>
<p>Big mistake. </p>
<p>Because now I’m really confused.  I was pretty darn sure until then that “raising the debt ceiling” meant allowing the Treasury Department to pay financial obligations already incurred, such as interest on bonds, Medicare payments, and contract obligations, and to allow continued payments for ongoing financial obligations such as Social Security payments, Veterans’ benefits, and salary payments to federal employees, some of whose jobs are sort of important.  (Think: air traffic controllers.)  I had thought that because I had followed the recurring-crisis news reports about it since 2011, when the first of the crises began.  And because Obama had actually explained it in his Jan. 14 press conference. </p>
<p>But now, well, I think I might have misunderstood, because after Williams reported that the Senate yesterday had approved the House bill to “suspend” the debt ceiling through May 19, he added, shaking his head in disapproval, something like: “This is Washington’s version of kicking the can down the road.  Our debt is now more than a trillion dollars.”</p>
<p>I suggest that next time Williams is onboard one of NBC’s corporate jets, he might read, say, Paul Krugman’s <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/01/opinion/krugman-looking-for-mister-goodpain.html?_r=0">column in today’s New York Times</a>.  It doesn’t explain the difference between the debt ceiling statute and budget-appropriations statutes, so Williams will continue to conflate the two until he digs deeper and reads earlier Krugman columns or other mainstream-media articles that did that.  But it does (yet again)&#8211;<a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/01/paul-ryan-says-taxes-should-be-raised.html">to borrow a phrase from Paul Ryan</a> in his Meet the Press interview aired last Sunday&#8211;debate the efficacy of Keynesian economics, and whether anti-Keynesian “austerity” measures reduce or instead increase national debt in real terms and, more important (although Williams apparently doesn’t know this), decrease or instead increase debt relative to GDP.</p>
<p>But if he is going to wait until he’s up there in the air in that Learjet to read the Krugman column, I hope the trip occurs before May 20.  </p>
<p>&#8212;-</p>
<p>UPDATE: Additional recommended reading for Brian Williams: Joe Scarborough, Paul Krugman and the economist-pundit divide on debt and deficits, Neil Irwin, Washington Post, yesterday. </p>
<p>Scarborough, though, at least knows what the debt ceiling law is, and that it isn’t the same as budget-appropriations legislation.  He does, after all, work for MSNBC, not, say, NBC News. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/brian-williams-thinks-raising-the-debt-ceiling-means-increasing-budget-appropriations-o-peter-jennings-walter-cronkite-and-edward-r-murrow-where-art-thou-updated.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Paul Ryan Says Taxes Should Be Raised to Pre-Bush-Tax-Cut Levels. But the Republicans Will Opt Instead For the “Sequester.” Unless, Of Course, the Koch Brothers Intervene.</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/paul-ryan-says-taxes-should-be-raised-to-pre-bush-tax-cut-levels-but-the-republicans-will-opt-instead-for-the-sequester-unless-of-course-the-koch-brothers-intervene.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/paul-ryan-says-taxes-should-be-raised-to-pre-bush-tax-cut-levels-but-the-republicans-will-opt-instead-for-the-sequester-unless-of-course-the-koch-brothers-intervene.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 31 Jan 2013 17:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[David Gregory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Keynesian economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Meet the Press]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the Koch brothers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the sequester]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/paul-ryan-says-taxes-should-be-raised-to-pre-bush-tax-cut-levels-but-the-republicans-will-opt-instead-for-the-sequester-unless-of-course-the-koch-brothers-intervene.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[There were three big political stories that came out of David Gregory’s fabulously interesting interview of Paul Ryan aired last Sunday on Meet the Press.  One was that Ryan said: Well, we can debate the efficacy of Keynesian economics or not. And I don’t obviously believe– I think the debt is pretty clear it doesn’t [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There were three big political stories that came out of David Gregory’s fabulously interesting interview of Paul Ryan aired last Sunday on Meet the Press.  One was that Ryan said: </p>
<div dir="ltr">Well, we can debate the efficacy of Keynesian economics or not. And I don’t obviously believe– I think the debt is pretty clear it doesn’t work.</div>
<p>Another was that he said that if Bill Clinton were president, we would have solved the budget-deficit problem, a statement that he presumably bases on the fact that when Bill Clinton was president, he solved the budget-deficit problem.</p>
<p>The third headline-grabber from that interview was that the Republicans will allow the “sequester” to take effect, presumably because they think it’s pretty clear that Keynesian economics doesn’t work, and because Bill Clinton is not longer president.  If Bill Clinton were president, the Republicans would allow him to raise tax rates to the level he did in 2001, this time without having to have the vice president cast the 51st vote in the Senate for the tax increase, and with enough Republican votes in the House to allow a vote on the tax increase.  </p>
<p>In other words, if Bill Clinton were president, Ryan and his compadres would not keep refusing to allow the Bush tax cuts on annual incomes of less than $450,000, and tax cuts on corporations, capital gains, and dividends, to expire.  But because Obama, rather than Clinton, is president, they won’t. They should be allowed to expire, Ryan says.  But they won’t be allowed to expire, because Obama is president.</p>
<p>Instead, the Republicans will opt to test out the the efficacy of Keynesian economics, or not&#8211;depending, probably, on whether <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/01/chuck-hagel-is-threat-to-americas.html">the Koch Brothers pick up the phone and disabuse Ryan of his belief that Keynesian economics doesn’t work</a>.  Before Wall Street does.  </p>
<p>Here’s what I obviously don’t believe: That if Ryan actually obviously doesn’t believe&#8211;thinks the debt is pretty clear it doesn’t work&#8211;he has even basic knowledge of past and current economic fact.</p>
<p>I’ll take his word for it that he was being truthful about his belief. But I sort of expect that the Koch brothers <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/business/economy/sequestration-looms-contractors-dont-fret/2013/01/30/3bcf60ea-6b0a-11e2-af53-7b2b2a7510a8_print.html">and others</a> will educate him and other congressional Republicans who hold that belief, very soon. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/paul-ryan-says-taxes-should-be-raised-to-pre-bush-tax-cut-levels-but-the-republicans-will-opt-instead-for-the-sequester-unless-of-course-the-koch-brothers-intervene.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Chuck Hagel Is a Threat to America’s National Security! And to the Koch Brothers’ Financial Interests.</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/chuck-hagel-is-a-threat-to-americas-national-security-and-to-the-koch-brothers-financial-interests.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/chuck-hagel-is-a-threat-to-americas-national-security-and-to-the-koch-brothers-financial-interests.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2013 19:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Chuck Hagel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CNBC]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Keynesian economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Meet the Press]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The American Future Fund]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the Koch brothers]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/chuck-hagel-is-a-threat-to-americas-national-security-and-to-the-koch-brothers-financial-interests.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The American Future Fund is an Iowa based 501(c)(4) tax-exempt organization affiliated with the Center to Protect Patient Rights, which in turn has reported ties to billionaires Charles G. Koch andDavid H. Koch. American Future Fund was founded by individuals who worked for Mitt Romney&#8216;s 2008 bid for the Republican U.S. Presidential nomination. Nick Ryan, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">The American Future Fund is an Iowa based <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/501(c)(4)">501(c)(4)</a> tax-exempt organization affiliated with the Center to Protect Patient Rights, which in turn has reported ties to billionaires <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_G._Koch">Charles G. Koch</a> and<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_H._Koch">David H. Koch</a>.</div>
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Future_Fund#cite_note-7"></a></p>
<div dir="ltr">American Future Fund was founded by individuals who worked for <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mitt_Romney">Mitt Romney</a>&#8216;s 2008 bid for the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republican_Party_(United_States)">Republican</a> U.S. Presidential nomination. Nick Ryan, an adviser to Republican US Representative <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jim_Nussle">Jim Nussle</a>, founded the organization in 2007, with Nicole Schlinger, a GOP leader in Iowa, as its president. Its current president is Iowa Republican state Sen. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sandra_Greiner">Sandra Greiner</a>.</div>
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Future_Fund#cite_note-10"></a>
<div dir="ltr">The fund &#8220;advocates <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conservative">conservative</a> and free-market principles&#8221; and energy positions that include support for drilling offshore and in the Alaska National Wildlife Refuge.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Activities </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">In 2010 the American Future Fund reported over 9 million dollars of independent campaign expenditures to the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal_Election_Commission">FEC</a>, and 100% of its expenditures benefited <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republican_Party_(United_States)">Republicans</a>.</div>
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Future_Fund#cite_note-WP_Future_Fund_2010_spending-13"></a>
<div dir="ltr">In 2012 the organization funded ads supporting <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mitt_Romney">Mitt Romney</a>&#8216;s bid for the U.S. presidency. In the same year, it also funded ads attacking Missouri Attorney General <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chris_Koster">Chris Koster</a> and in support of California&#8217;s Proposition 32, which would prevent unions from collecting political contributions as paycheck deductions. </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">The organization does not disclose the names of those who have provided its funding.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Future_Fund">Wikipedia</a></div>
<p>Add to the Activities list an anti-Chuck Hagel TV ad. </p>
<p>Okay.  So I happened to catch a segment on CNBC just now (don’t ask; catching segments on CNBC is not quite part of my normal daily routine) that ended with an ad blasting Hagel for … um … a whole lot of stuff geared toward making people think he would have lots of conflicts of interest if confirmed as Secretary of Defense, even if he sells all those financial interests in defense contractor companies that the ad says he has, and in that company that invests in Iran, and stops flying on corporate jets. </p>
<p>At the end of the ad, the viewer is told that it’s sponsored by The American Future Fund.  Which I couldn’t identify from memory, since the names of these organizations all sound alike.  And are all very interested in America’s future.  </p>
<p>But, having seen the ad, I now knew that Hagel would be a very dangerous guy to have as Defense Secretary.  I just didn’t know who exactly he posed a danger to.  But thanks to Wikipedia, I know now.</p>
<p>Sounds to me like Paul Ryan should have consulted the Koch brothers before he declared on Meet the Press last weekend that Keynesian economics has proved to be a failure.  If you get my drift.  Those oil and gas subsidies and defense contracts <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Koch_Industries">that the Koch businesses receive</a> are important to our national defense &#8230; and to the economy.*
<div></div>
<div>*<i>Edited for clarity after initial posting.</i>
<div></div>
<div></div>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/chuck-hagel-is-a-threat-to-americas-national-security-and-to-the-koch-brothers-financial-interests.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Oh, do tell us, Rep. Ryan, what exactly you think our spending priorities should be in order to avoid default if the debt ceiling isn&#8217;t increased. Pleeease.</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/oh-do-tell-us-rep-ryan-what-exactly-you-think-our-spending-priorities-should-be-in-order-to-avoid-default-if-the-debt-ceiling-isnt-increased-pleeease.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/oh-do-tell-us-rep-ryan-what-exactly-you-think-our-spending-priorities-should-be-in-order-to-avoid-default-if-the-debt-ceiling-isnt-increased-pleeease.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Jan 2013 22:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[debt ceiling]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The National Review]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/oh-do-tell-us-rep-ryan-what-exactly-you-think-our-spending-priorities-should-be-in-order-to-avoid-default-if-the-debt-ceiling-isnt-increased-pleeease.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Oh, do tell us, Rep. Ryan, what exactly you think our spending priorities should be in order to avoid default if the debt ceiling isn&#8217;t increased.  Pleeease.   Might they be similar to the priorities of the National Review’s editors?]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Oh, do tell us, Rep. Ryan, <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/weigel/2013/01/17/paul_ryan_government_can_avoid_default_prioritize_spending_if_we_hit_the.html">what exactly you think our spending priorities should be</a> in order to avoid default if the debt ceiling isn&#8217;t increased.  Pleeease.  </p>
<p>Might they be similar to <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/01/apparently-national-reviews-editors.html">the priorities of the National Review’s editors</a>? </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/oh-do-tell-us-rep-ryan-what-exactly-you-think-our-spending-priorities-should-be-in-order-to-avoid-default-if-the-debt-ceiling-isnt-increased-pleeease.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>On Being Jack Kennedy</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/on-being-jack-kennedy.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/on-being-jack-kennedy.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 12 Oct 2012 18:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dana Milbank]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jack Kennedy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Joe Biden]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lloyd Bentsen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Washington Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/on-being-jack-kennedy.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Biden’s use of the famous Lloyd Bentsen put-down of Dan Quail—“Senator, you’re no Jack Kennedy”—is getting pretty good play among the punditry. (Yay!)  Now, hopefully, Obama and Biden will educate the public about the tax rates on the wealthy and on capital gains in, say, 1963.  And on whether, y’know, America was a European-style socialist [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>Biden’s use of the famous Lloyd Bentsen put-down of Dan Quail—“Senator, you’re no Jack Kennedy”—is getting pretty good play among the punditry. (Yay!)  Now, hopefully, Obama and Biden will educate the public about the tax rates on the wealthy and on capital gains in, say, 1963. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And on whether, y’know, America was a European-style socialist country back then because of that—as Romney actually has claimed on several occasions during the last year.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And, in case you missed my update to my last post: The Washington Post&#8217;s Dana Milbank is the first pundit I know of thus far to <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/dana-milbank-in-vice-presidential-debate-biden-rattles-ryan/2012/10/12/427cd0c0-1430-11e2-be82-c3411b7680a9_story.html?hpid=z3">GET IT</a>.  </div>
<div></div>
<div>Go, Dana!</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/on-being-jack-kennedy.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
