<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Whittle a Beak &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The Tale Behind Whittle</title>
		<link>./../../2008/04/the-tale-behind-whittle.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/04/the-tale-behind-whittle.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2008 12:07:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Whittle a Beak]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/04/the-tale-behind-whittle.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This one is by ILSM, part of his Whittle a Beak series. &#8212; During my ill spent youth, many years ago, I served with a seasoned non commissioned officer from somewhere in the rural old south, foothills of the Appalachians. A colorful, experienced and outspoken commenter on the brass. One day he returned from a [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This one is by ILSM, part of his Whittle a Beak series.</p>
<p>&#8212;</p>
<p>During my ill spent youth, many years ago, I served with a seasoned non commissioned officer from somewhere in the rural old south, foothills of the Appalachians.  A colorful, experienced and outspoken commenter on the brass.</p>
<p>One day he returned from a visit with the top non com, with some now forgotten detail to do.  His only comment in my hearing was: &#8221; I would rather whittle a beak, strap it on and go out in the barn yard and peck @$%&#038; with the chickens.&#8221;  Saying this while he viewed his line up of smokes.</p>
<p>The job was some make work, look good detail designed by some smooth faced officer wanting to look good and &#8216;break starch&#8217;.  It was in this NCO&#8217;s veiw a wste of his time and talents.</p>
<p>In short &#8220;whittling a beak&#8221; is a measure of resources wasted in doing a job which never should be done and takes assets from more pressing needs.</p>
<p>He did do the job and never did &#8220;whittle a beak&#8221;.</p>
<p>That was long ago.  How many times had I whittled a beak would the taxpayer be better off! </p>
<p>The 95 weapons programs recently reviewed by GAO are all beaks that are being whittled at huge cost, resources that in every case should be used elsewhere.</p>
<p>&#8220;Whittle a beak&#8221; is code for opportunity lost and waste.</p>
<p>&#8212;</p>
<p>This one was by ILSM.</p>
<p>END</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/04/the-tale-behind-whittle.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>ILSM &#8211; The Generals Pile On The KC 145</title>
		<link>./../../2008/04/ilsm-the-generals-pile-on-the-kc-145.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/04/ilsm-the-generals-pile-on-the-kc-145.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Apr 2008 14:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Whittle a Beak]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/04/ilsm-the-generals-pile-on-the-kc-145.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This one is by ILSM&#8230; &#8212; In this article by James Wallace in the Seattle Post-Intelligencer, we learn that some generals have joined the PR battle on behalf of Northrop, writing to Defense Secretary Gates urging him to stand by the Air Force mistake on the KC-135 replacement. The generals present only arguments against the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This one is by ILSM&#8230;</p>
<p>&#8212;</p>
<p>In <a href="http://seattlepi.nwsource.com/business/357333_air02.html">this article</a> by James Wallace in the Seattle Post-Intelligencer, we learn that some generals have joined the PR battle on behalf of Northrop, writing to Defense Secretary Gates urging him to stand by the Air Force mistake on the KC-135 replacement.</p>
<p>The generals present only arguments against the protest process none that make any sense about the reasons for the protest.</p>
<p>You will hear about KC 135 corrosion problems &#8211; I will assert that the fix of the corrosion is cheap easy and done in a routine depot repair cycle, with the cost of a million or so dollars, decent material management and a few days extra time in the depot.</p>
<p>This argument between military industrialists reminds me of the following I saw over the weekend.</p>
<p>&#8220;Hey I can sell newer crap that doesn&#8217;t work than he can.&#8221; Jeff Huber comment at My Left Wing 30 Mar 08.</p>
<p>How about lining up all the brass to argue for their team against the other team?</p>
<p>Everything is PR!</p>
<p>Do not discuss how a 24% heavier aircraft like the Airbus could be the same acquisition and ownership costs while its added weight is needed only in the new mission of establishing &#8220;air bridges&#8221; around the world to project US power to the farthest and least hospitable corners of the world.</p>
<p>The reason the US is not airlifting support to Tibet is not that the KC 135 can&#8217;t refuel C-17&#8217;s, it is that it makes no sense. Won&#8217;t make any more sense with the Airbus.</p>
<p>Might as well whittle a beak&#8230;</p>
<p>&#8212;</p>
<p>This one was by ILSM.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/04/ilsm-the-generals-pile-on-the-kc-145.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>ILSM: Whittle a Break</title>
		<link>./../../2008/04/ilsm-whittle-a-break.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/04/ilsm-whittle-a-break.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2008 11:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[defense contractors]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[defense spending]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Whittle a Beak]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/04/ilsm-whittle-a-break.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This one is by ILSM&#8230; &#8212; I&#8217;d like to comment on this front page story in the Washington Post, published on April 1, 2008 by Dana Hedgpeth, a Washington Post Staff Writer. GAO Blasts Weapons BudgetCost Overruns Hit $295 Billion Government auditors issued a scathing review yesterday of dozens of the Pentagon&#8217;s biggest weapons systems, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This one is by ILSM&#8230;</p>
<p>&#8212;</p>
<p>I&#8217;d like to comment on <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/03/31/AR2008033102789.html?hpid=topnews">this front page story</a> in the Washington Post, published on April 1, 2008 by Dana Hedgpeth, a Washington Post Staff Writer.</p>
<blockquote><p>GAO Blasts Weapons Budget<br />Cost Overruns Hit $295 Billion</p>
<p>Government auditors issued a scathing review yesterday of dozens of the Pentagon&#8217;s biggest weapons systems, saying ships, aircraft and satellites are billions of dollars over budget and years behind schedule.</p>
<p>Auditors said the Defense Department showed few signs of improvement since the GAO began issuing its annual assessments of selected weapons systems six years ago. &#8220;It&#8217;s not getting any better by any means,&#8221; said Michael Sullivan, director of GAO&#8217;s acquisition and sourcing team. &#8220;It&#8217;s taking longer and costing more.&#8221;</p>
<p>&#8220;In most cases, programs also failed to deliver capabilities when promised &#8212; often forcing war fighters to spend additional funds on maintaining&#8221; existing weapons systems, the report says.</p></blockquote>
<p>This is somewhat misleading. In almost every case the reliability of new systems is poor, requires more people to repair it, resulting in lost utility, more maintenance equipment, parts and costing more than keeping the old system running. This will be the case with the Airbus tanker. The KC-135 even with more depot stays will be more useful and cheaper to operate than the Airbus.</p>
<blockquote><p>The GAO chose 72 systems to examine, based on high-dollar value and congressional interest. The various systems were at different stages of the acquisition process over the last year.</p>
<p>The GAO&#8217;s Sullivan said the reasons for the cost overruns and delays are threefold: There are too many programs chasing too few dollars; technologies are often not mature enough to go into production; and it takes too long to design, develop and produce a system.</p>
<p>&#8220;They&#8217;re asking for something that they&#8217;re not sure can be built, given existing technologies, and that&#8217;s risky,&#8221; Sullivan said in an interview.</p></blockquote>
<p>That engineering is faulty is cultural.  When a program goes into Full Development (the government manager knows what can be developed, built and sustained at given set of costs) the underlying technology is supposed to be proven.  NASA has a series of technology readiness levels which DoD has adopted.  The rush is to get into production to help the industry make money.  Money is the reason we see all these &#8220;do-overs&#8221;.  The profit is the same the third time around.</p>
<blockquote><p>Steven L. Schooner, co-director of the government procurement law program at George Washington University, said the GAO&#8217;s report reveals the recurring problems the Pentagon faces with its costly procurements.</p>
<p>&#8220;The nature of major weapon systems development is that you have to expect that the initial estimates, and typically the initial contracts, are overly optimistic and unrealistic,&#8221; he said. &#8220;Unfortunately the purchaser &#8212; the government &#8212; typically lacks the discipline to freeze the configuration such that the contractor has any reasonable chance of developing what it promised on time and for the price promised.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>This is a straw man, most of the specification changes are relieving the designer of requirements for things like quality manufacturing, technical data, eliminating testing and on occasion a new requirement is added to give the appearance that the added funding is not a bail out. An example, when the government requires a certain outcome which will cause the developer to lose money the developer asks the government to change the contract to pay again for the work already required. This seems to be a requirement change but it is not rooted in any technical aspect but in paying twice for the work to be done in a different manner a hidden &#8216;do over&#8217; to compensate for an overrun.</p>
<blockquote><p>Defense Department officials have tried to improve the procurement process, the GAO said, by doing more planning and review in the early stages of a contract. But &#8220;these significant policy changes have not yet translated into best practices on individual programs,&#8221; Gene L. Dodaro, acting comptroller general of the GAO, wrote in the report.</p>
<p>&#8220;Flagship acquisitions, as well as many other top priorities in each of the services, continue to cost significantly more, take longer to produce, and deliver less than was promised,&#8221; Dodaro said. &#8220;This is likely to continue until the overall environment for weapon system acquisitions changes.</p></blockquote>
<p>The DoD must, but won&#8217;t, require the contractors perform as promised in the development contracts or put them out of business not give a company overrunning and not delivering a 99% rating on &#8220;past performance&#8221; in the next competition. Also, DoD managers must consider the value to the taxpayer, not their career or some recondite agenda to &#8216;take care&#8217; of the soldier. </p>
<p>&#8212;</p>
<p>This one is by ILSM.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/04/ilsm-whittle-a-break.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
