<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>equality &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Due Process: Holder vs Colbert. Art or Reality. Choose.</title>
		<link>./../../2012/03/due-process-holder-vs-colbert-art-or-reality-choose.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/03/due-process-holder-vs-colbert-art-or-reality-choose.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Mar 2012 17:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[AG investigations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[equality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income equality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[reality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rule of law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wealth creation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[world bank]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/03/due-process-holder-vs-colbert-art-or-reality-choose.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This is the object:  No person shall be held to answer for a capital, or otherwise infamous crime, unless on a presentment or indictment of a Grand Jury,&#8230; nor be deprived of life, liberty, or property, without due process of law; It&#8217;s all one sentence. Any questions? This is Art: The lyrics of Grand Funk [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div></div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>This is the object: </div>
<p>
<blockquote>
<div>No person shall be held to answer for a capital, or otherwise infamous crime, unless on a presentment or indictment of a Grand Jury,&#8230; nor be deprived of life, liberty, or property, without due process of law;</div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div>It&#8217;s all one sentence.  Any questions?</div>
<div></div>
<div>This is Art:</div>
<div>The lyrics of Grand Funk Railroad&#8217;s <a href="http://www.songlyrics.com/grand-funk-railroad/paranoid-lyrics/">Paranoid </a></div>
<p>
<blockquote>
<div>Did you ever have that feeling in your life</div>
<div>That someone was watching you?</div>
<div>You don&#8217;t have no reason that&#8217;s right</div>
<div>But still he&#8217;s there watching you</div>
<div>Someone is waiting just outside the door</div>
<div>To take you away</div>
<div>Everybody knows just what he&#8217;s there for</div>
<div>To take you away</div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div>vs the lyrics of Red Rider&#8217;s <a href="http://www.songlyrics.com/red-rider/lunatic-fringe-lyrics/">Lunatic Fringe</a> </div>
<p>
<blockquote>
<div>Lunatic Fringe &#8211; in the twilight&#8217;s last gleaming</div>
<div>This is open season, but you won&#8217;t get too far</div>
<div>&#8216;Cause you got to blame someone for your own confusion</div>
<div>We&#8217;re all on guard this time against the Final Solution</div>
<div>all on guard this time</div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div>This is the reality. 44% of <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2007/10/human-capital-is-where-its-at.html">our wealth is due to rule of law.</a></div>
<div></div>
<div>World Bank study on wealth in 2005 stated:  </div>
<p>
<blockquote>
<div align="JUSTIFY">Worldwide, the study finds, &#8220;natural capital accounts for 5 percent of total wealth, produced capital for 18 percent, and intangible capital 77 percent.&#8221;  &#8220;Rich countries are largely rich because of the skills of their populations and the quality of the institutions supporting economic activity,&#8221; the study concludes. According to Hamilton&#8217;s figures, the rule of law explains 57 percent of countries&#8217; intangible capital. Education accounts for 36 percent.”  </div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div>Rule of law equates <a href="http://www.equalitytrust.org.uk/why/evidence/trust-and-community-life">to trust</a>.   </div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-nVZaff-ud1A/T1jYq6Jlz5I/AAAAAAAAASo/J_iYIXgAUWk/s1600/Trust+Graph.gif" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="229" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-nVZaff-ud1A/T1jYq6Jlz5I/AAAAAAAAASo/J_iYIXgAUWk/s320/Trust+Graph.gif" width="320"></a></div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<div>A nation can not generate $14 trillion per year if there is general suspicion throughout society.  </div>
<p>
<blockquote>“Trust” seems to be the real intangible the report is talking about. We as a whole can be educated to the hilt, but if we can&#8217;t trust that our efforts will be put to constructive use, we have problems. Think habeas corpus, FISA, election fraud, threatening of the press, intimidation of speech, extension of free speech to none human entities, the equating of one voice-one vote to spending of one&#8217;s money, K Street project, etc. Think of the use of fear. If only a few are educated to the hilt or have access to the governance, we can not build capital. </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><div><a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2007/10/human-capital-is-where-its-at.html">Daniel Becker 10/8/2007</a></div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>Which is art, which is reality?</div>
<p>
<blockquote>
<div>Due process and judicial process are not one in the same.  The Constitution guarantees due process, it does not guarantee judicial process.  Erik Holder 3/5/12*  </div>
</blockquote>
<p>
<blockquote>
<div>Due process just means there is a process that you do.  Steven Colbert 3/6/12*</div>
<div></div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<p>Which is art, which is reality? </p>
<blockquote><p>In response to the act perpetrated&#8230;Congress has authorized the President to use all necessary and appropriate force against those groups.  Because the United States is in an armed conflict&#8230; Eric Holder 3/5/12* 
<div></div>
</blockquote>
<p>
<blockquote>
<div>We&#8217;re at war with Terror.   Therefore, the President can blow up any American citizen he chooses until we win the war by defeating the idea of being afraid.  Steven Colbert, 3/6/12.*</div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<p>
<div>Is this art or reality?</div>
<p>
<blockquote>
<div><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Due_process">Due process developed</a> from clause 39 of the Magna Carta in England.</div>
<div><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Due_process"><br /></a></div>
<div>In clause 39 of the Magna Carta, John of England promised as follows: &#8220;No free man shall be seized or imprisoned, or stripped of his rights or possessions, or outlawed or exiled, or deprived of his standing in any other way, nor will we proceed with force against him, or send others to do so, except by the lawful judgment of his equals or by the law of the land.&#8221;</div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div>It appears in this War on Terror, England is not the only nation learning from another regarding how to<a href="http://downingstreetmemo.com/memos.html">“fix” the war</a>.  We too have obviously learned from England regarding war management.  We have learned how to manifest the feeling of “it&#8217;s only a piece of paper” (though not true that Bush 2 made such a statement regarding the Constitution which makes Obama et al&#8217;s position all the more surreal).     </div>
<div></div>
<blockquote><div>As the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Due_process">U.S. Supreme Court has explained</a>, a due process requirement in Britain was not &#8220;essential to the idea of due process of law in the prosecution and punishment of crimes, but was only mentioned as an example and illustration of due process of law as it actually existed in cases in which it was customarily used.&#8221;[11]  </div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>I can see how England&#8217;s approach to war fixing is a much better solution if your goal is to <a href="http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/conflate">conflate art and reality</a>.  There is no need to be clandestine.  Did you notice the closeness of the USA and England on the trust graph?</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>Which will you choose? Art or Reality?  Are you sure which one is which?  Be careful, it&#8217;s <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2007/10/human-capital-is-where-its-at.html">your economic future</a> that is at stake.</div>
<div></div>
<div><a href="http://www.colbertnation.com/the-colbert-report-videos/410085/march-06-2012/the-word---due-or-die%20">*Watch Steven&#8217;s</a> take on this.<a href="http://www.colbertnation.com/the-colbert-report-videos/410085/march-06-2012/the-word---due-or-die"></a></div>
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/03/due-process-holder-vs-colbert-art-or-reality-choose.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>It&#8217;s not how rich we are, it&#8217;s how equal we are.</title>
		<link>./../../2011/11/its-not-how-rich-we-are-its-how-equal-we-are.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/11/its-not-how-rich-we-are-its-how-equal-we-are.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2011 04:54:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[distributive justice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economic policy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[equality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Great Recession]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income inequality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[OWS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social insurance]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/11/its-not-how-rich-we-are-its-how-equal-we-are.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This is a 16 minute * lecture by Richard Wilkinson. It is posted at TED. I am posting it here, as I can not believe this information has not received more attention now that the US is awakening from the decades long delusion of prosperity which did not and as shown in the lecture could [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/richard_wilkinson.html">This is a 16 minute</a> * lecture by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_G._Wilkinson">Richard Wilkinson</a>.  It is posted at TED.  I am posting it here, as I can not believe this information has not received more attention now that the US is awakening from the decades long delusion of prosperity which did not and as shown in the lecture could not lead to greater justice (which implies equality) via the model of economics we have been using. </div>
<div></div>
<div>The model known by many aliases (Chicago School, Friedman, etc) has resulted in the thought that people are drowning in debt and that we have privatized the profits but socialized the losses. These are inaccurate metaphors. They are the results of the language of the delusion we have been living for 3 decades and thus by definition can not capture the truth of our condition. As the science presented in the lecture shows, if our all encompassing concern should be equality, then people are not drowning, they are <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2011/06/monetary-policy-im-not-only-not-feeling.html">dehydrating</a>. </div>
<div></div>
<div>The dehydration is the results of privatizing security in life and socializing the risks in life. We are not “drowning” in risk or losses. We of the 99% are lacking in the substance that reduces risk. One can certainly drown from too much water, but the natural risk in life is not having too much water, it is having too little. Thus is the realization of the delusional statement “drowning in debt” and “socialized the losses”. </div>
<p><a name="more"></a>
<div>The lack of reduction of life&#8217;s risks is the inequality, the social injustice&#8230;the diversion from the purpose expressed in the preamble to our Constitution. “We the People of the United States, in Order to form a more perfect Union, establish Justice, insure domestic Tranquility, provide for the common defence, promote the general Welfare, and secure the Blessings of Liberty to ourselves and our Posterity, do ordain and establish this Constitution for the United States of America.”</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>The following <a href="http://www.crimeandjustice.org.uk/wilkinsoninequality.html">concluding statement</a> from a different lecture by Professor Wilkinson summarizes the TED lecture. As you watch the lecture keep in mind the 4 goals I highlighted of the preamble and consider that they were put into a document that created an government 223 years ago this year (based on ratification). I have a greater respect for the intellect and their insight into the human experience of those who wrote and ratified our Constitution. </div>
<div></div>
<blockquote><p>“For thousands of years the best way of improving the quality of human life has been to raise material living standards. We are the first generation to have got to the end of that process. No longer does economic growth improve health, happiness, or wellbeing. If we are to improve the real quality of life further, we have to direct our attention to the social environment and the quality of social relations. But rather than continuing to tackle each problem separately, by spending more on medical care, more on police, social workers and drug rehabilitation units, we now know that it is possible to improve the psychosocial wellbeing and social functioning of whole societies. <strong>The quality of social relations is built on material foundations &#8211; on the scale of the material inequalities between us</strong>.” </p></blockquote>
<div></div>
<div>With information such as this research and that of the<a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2007/10/human-capital-is-where-its-at.html"> 2005 World Bank</a> paper on what produces wealth , considering our Constitution&#8217;s preamble, we should not be struggling looking for guidance as to what direction, what path, what solution we need for our self (our self as in We the People). </div>
<div></div>
<div>*I tried to embbed the video, but for some reason all that happened was all the code being published and not the video.</div>
<div> </div>
<div>(Dan here, h/t to rjs for the embed&#8230;</div>
<div></div>
<div>
<div> </div>
<div></div>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/11/its-not-how-rich-we-are-its-how-equal-we-are.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Screw Austerity, I have a new theme song</title>
		<link>./../../2011/07/screw-austerity-i-have-a-new-theme-song.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/07/screw-austerity-i-have-a-new-theme-song.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2011 17:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[austerity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[budget deficits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[debt ceiling]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[debt limit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economic fundamentals]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economic growth]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economic ideology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[equality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[governance]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/07/screw-austerity-i-have-a-new-theme-song.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Daniel Becker Being that we&#8217;re about to experience austerity because we are convinced we can&#8217;t spend money properly such that we actually end up with more after rather than less &#8230;  which is very depressing to me and defeatist in presentation, I present my new theme song:  That&#8217;s how it goes. I just find [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Daniel Becker</p>
<p>Being that we&#8217;re about to experience austerity because we are convinced we can&#8217;t spend money properly such that we actually end up with more after rather than less &#8230;  which is very depressing to me and defeatist in presentation, I present my new theme song:  That&#8217;s how it goes.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>I just find it fascinating that we will accept the argument that government needs to run as we run our own houses and thus need to not spend more than we have, blah, blah, blah yet we seem not willing to apply the concept that we apply daily in our own household to get ourselves an education, a house, our own business, improvement to our property and self.  We do this all the time because we understand it is building our wealth, and we do it even though we can&#8217;t print our own dollars like the government can.  (Yeah, we&#8217;re not Greece in that way.)</p>
<p>Really, just listen to both sides presenting the austerity program arguments.  Can&#8217;t you hear how disjointed the reasoning is?  Can&#8217;t you hear how selective they are in presenting examples of proof of their argument which is resulting is a totally disjointed line of reasoning.  Ask one question you are told we need to save to prosper.  Ask another question you are told we need to spend less just like you, to prosper.  Ask a third question and you are told we have no money, just like you.  Ask a forth question and we&#8217;re told the economy is growing (more money produced) NOT LIKE YOU.  Ask a fifth question and we are told to better yourself, NOT LIKE WE THE PEOPLE.  Ask a sixth question and we are told to get an education, NOT LIKE WE THE PEOPLE.  Ask a seventh question and we are told to&#8230;(fill in your own).</p>
<p>My favorite verses of the song and why it is my new theme song:</p>
<blockquote><p>I help you and you help me<br />That’s the way the world should  be<br />Tit for tat and give and take<br />Just be good for goodness sake<br />I’ll  pick you up if you should fall<br />It works both ways if it  works at all<br />Hold in your heart the people you love<br />Always thank the powers above<br />Everyone  deserves a share<br />So keep your promise, fair is fair</p>
<p>So gather ‘round me people<br />And help me while I sing this song<br />I’d  rather have you with me<br />Together as we travel along<br />It’s the feeling of the wind in your face<br />The sound of the music they play<br />The  friends you make along the way<br />Don’t you know, that’s how  it goes</p></blockquote>
<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/07/screw-austerity-i-have-a-new-theme-song.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>In Which I Hope I&#8217;m Gettying Pranked</title>
		<link>./../../2009/10/in-which-i-hope-im-gettying-pranked.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/10/in-which-i-hope-im-gettying-pranked.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 16 Oct 2009 02:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[equality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[marriage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[race]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/10/in-which-i-hope-im-gettying-pranked.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This cannot be true, can it? Louisiana Justice of the Peace Denies Marriage License to Interracial Couple: According to [Keith Bardwell, a justice of the peace in Tangipahoa Parish], he won&#8217;t support interracial marriages because he doesn&#8217;t feel that black or white society will accept the children of the couple once they are born. I [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This cannot be true, can it?</p>
<p><a target="_blank" href="http://www.associatedcontent.com/article/2289453/louisiana_justice_of_the_peace_denies.html">Louisiana Justice of the Peace Denies Marriage License to Interracial Couple</a>:<br />
<blockquote>According to [Keith Bardwell, a justice of the peace in Tangipahoa Parish], he won&#8217;t support interracial marriages because he doesn&#8217;t feel that black or white society will accept the children of the couple once they are born.</p></blockquote>
<p>I can&#8217;t find him in Martindale-Hubbell, but other articles note <a target="_blank" href="http://www.zimbio.com/Keith+Bardwell/articles/cL4BpHco2WS/Keith+Bardwell+Louisiana+Justice+Peace+Refuses">him saying</a>:<br />
<blockquote>&#8220;I&#8217;ve been a justice of the peace for 34 years and I don&#8217;t think I&#8217;ve mistreated anybody. I&#8217;ve made some mistakes, but you have too. I didn&#8217;t tell this couple they couldn&#8217;t get married. I just told them I wouldn&#8217;t do it.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>*Sigh*</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/10/in-which-i-hope-im-gettying-pranked.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
