<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>fascism &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Whole Foods, Half-Wit</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/whole-foods-half-wit.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/whole-foods-half-wit.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Jan 2013 01:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[fascism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Mackey Thom Hartmann]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obamacare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Sacks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[socialism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Whole Foods]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/whole-foods-half-wit.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[What a spot-on article Run 75441’s piece, “Healthcare Reform; Socialism or Fascism?” is. And what an informative Comments thread.  (Wow, Cynthia, who knew? I sure didn’t.) And, folks, don’t miss this takedown of Mackey, called “Dear Whole Foods CEO, This Is What a Fascist Looks Like,” by Thom Hartmann and Sam Sacks, via ReaderSupportedNews.   [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">What a spot-on article Run 75441’s piece, “<a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/01/healthcare-reform-socialism-or-fascism.html">Healthcare Reform; Socialism or Fascism?</a>” is. And what an informative Comments thread.  (Wow, Cynthia, who knew? I sure didn’t.) </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">And, folks, don’t miss<a href="http://readersupportednews.org/opinion2/277-75/15632-focus-dear-whole-foods-ceo-this-is-what-a-fascist-looks-like"> this</a> takedown of Mackey, called “Dear Whole Foods CEO, This Is What a Fascist Looks Like,” by Thom Hartmann and Sam Sacks, via ReaderSupportedNews.  </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">But I have my own suggestion to Mackey: Consider expanding your company to other countries. Australia, maybe.  Germany.  Canada.  Sweden. France. Britain.  Norway.  Holland.  Maybe even Israel and Poland, both of them countries whose healthcare system Mitt Romney praised last summer.  </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Or maybe Switzerland, where&#8211;as another reader commented in the earlier thread, in noting your praise of the Swiss health system, Mr. Mackey&#8211;you can see a fascist (or is it a socialist?) system at work, while admiring the beautiful mountainscape and maybe even skiing in it.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">And while you’re there, break a leg.</div>
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/whole-foods-half-wit.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Project for a New American Century</title>
		<link>./../../2009/08/project-for-a-new-american-century.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/08/project-for-a-new-american-century.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 26 Aug 2009 14:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[fascism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/08/project-for-a-new-american-century.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Statement of Principles June 3, 1997 American foreign and defense policy is adrift. Conservatives have criticized the incoherent policies of the Clinton Administration. They have also resisted isolationist impulses from within their own ranks. But conservatives have not confidently advanced a strategic vision of America&#8217;s role in the world. They have not set forth guiding [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a target="_blank" href="http://www.newamericancentury.org/statementofprinciples.htm">Statement of Principles</a></p>
<p>June 3, 1997 <br />
<blockquote>American foreign and defense policy is adrift. Conservatives have criticized the incoherent policies of the Clinton Administration. They have also resisted isolationist impulses from within their own ranks. But conservatives have not confidently advanced a strategic vision of America&#8217;s role in the world. They have not set forth guiding principles for American foreign policy. They have allowed differences over tactics to obscure potential agreement on strategic objectives. And they have not fought for a defense budget that would maintain American security and advance American interests in the new century.</p>
<p>We aim to change this. We aim to make the case and rally support for American global leadership.</p>
<p>As the 20th century draws to a close, the United States stands as the world&#8217;s preeminent power. Having led the West to victory in the Cold War, America faces an opportunity and a challenge: Does the United States have the vision to build upon the achievements of past decades? Does the United States have the resolve to shape a new century favorable to American principles and interests?</p>
<p>We are in danger of squandering the opportunity and failing the challenge. We are living off the capital &#8212; both the military investments and the foreign policy achievements &#8212; built up by past administrations. Cuts in foreign affairs and defense spending, inattention to the tools of statecraft, and inconstant leadership are making it increasingly difficult to sustain American influence around the world. And the promise of short-term commercial benefits threatens to override strategic considerations. As a consequence, we are jeopardizing the nation&#8217;s ability to meet present threats and to deal with potentially greater challenges that lie ahead.</p>
<p>We seem to have forgotten the essential elements of the Reagan Administration&#8217;s success: a military that is strong and ready to meet both present and future challenges; a foreign policy that boldly and purposefully promotes American principles abroad; and national leadership that accepts the United States&#8217; global responsibilities.</p>
<p>Of course, the United States must be prudent in how it exercises its power. But we cannot safely avoid the responsibilities of global leadership or the costs that are associated with its exercise. America has a vital role in maintaining peace and security in Europe, Asia, and the Middle East. If we shirk our responsibilities, we invite challenges to our fundamental interests. The history of the 20th century should have taught us that it is important to shape circumstances before crises emerge, and to meet threats before they become dire. The history of this century should have taught us to embrace the cause of American leadership.</p>
<p>Our aim is to remind Americans of these lessons and to draw their consequences for today. Here are four consequences:</p>
<p>• we need to increase defense spending significantly if we are to carry out our global <br />responsibilities today and modernize our armed forces for the future;</p>
<p>• we need to strengthen our ties to democratic allies and to challenge regimes hostile to our interests and values;</p>
<p>• we need to promote the cause of political and economic freedom abroad;</p>
<p>• we need to accept responsibility for America&#8217;s unique role in preserving and extending an international order friendly to our security, our prosperity, and our principles.</p>
<p>Such a Reaganite policy of military strength and moral clarity may not be fashionable today. But it is necessary if the United States is to build on the successes of this past century and to ensure our security and our greatness in the next.</p></blockquote>
<p>This is your Bush foreign policy program in a nutshell. As developed and endorsed by the following team already in place back in 1997. Lots of familiar names, in fact you have pretty much the whole Bush national security team. Less Condi and Powell, which is instructive in itself.<br />
<blockquote>Elliott Abrams    Gary Bauer    William J. Bennett    Jeb Bush</p>
<p>Dick Cheney    Eliot A. Cohen    Midge Decter    Paula Dobriansky    Steve Forbes</p>
<p>Aaron Friedberg    Francis Fukuyama    Frank Gaffney    Fred C. Ikle</p>
<p>Donald Kagan    Zalmay Khalilzad    I. Lewis Libby    Norman Podhoretz</p>
<p>Dan Quayle    Peter W. Rodman    Stephen P. Rosen    Henry S. Rowen</p>
<p>Donald Rumsfeld    Vin Weber    George Weigel    Paul Wolfowitz</p></blockquote>
<p>Never heard of the Kagans before the drumbeat to war picked up? Think Zalmay Khalilzad just happened to be available when the time came? The events of 2001 on just didn&#8217;t happen, they were shaped. By people with a program. This one.</p>
<p>Step one in the program below the fold.</p>
<p><a target="_blank" href="http://www.newamericancentury.org/iraqclintonletter.htm">Letter to President Clinton on Iraq</a> Jan 26, 1998<br />
<blockquote>Dear Mr. President:</p>
<p>We are writing you because we are convinced that current American policy toward Iraq is not succeeding, and that we may soon face a threat in the Middle East more serious than any we have known since the end of the Cold War.  In your upcoming State of the Union Address, you have an opportunity to chart a clear and determined course for meeting this threat.  We urge you to seize that opportunity, and to enunciate a new strategy that would secure the interests of the U.S. and our friends and allies around the world.  That strategy should aim, above all, at the removal of Saddam Hussein’s regime from power.  We stand ready to offer our full support in this difficult but necessary endeavor.</p>
<p>The policy of “containment” of Saddam Hussein has been steadily eroding over the past several months.  As recent events have demonstrated, we can no longer depend on our partners in the Gulf War coalition to continue to uphold the sanctions or to punish Saddam when he blocks or evades UN inspections.  Our ability to ensure that Saddam Hussein is not producing weapons of mass destruction, therefore, has substantially diminished.  Even if full inspections were eventually to resume, which now seems highly unlikely, experience has shown that it is difficult if not impossible to monitor Iraq’s chemical and biological weapons production.  The lengthy period during which the inspectors will have been unable to enter many Iraqi facilities has made it even less likely that they will be able to uncover all of Saddam’s secrets.  As a result, in the not-too-distant future we will be unable to determine with any reasonable level of confidence whether Iraq does or does not possess such weapons.</p>
<p>Such uncertainty will, by itself, have a seriously destabilizing effect on the entire Middle East.  It hardly needs to be added that if Saddam does acquire the capability to deliver weapons of mass destruction, as he is almost certain to do if we continue along the present course, the safety of American troops in the region, of our friends and allies like Israel and the moderate Arab states, and a significant portion of the world’s supply of oil will all be put at hazard.  As you have rightly declared, Mr. President, the security of the world in the first part of the 21st century will be determined largely by how we handle this threat.</p>
<p>Given the magnitude of the threat, the current policy, which depends for its success upon the steadfastness of our coalition partners and upon the cooperation of Saddam Hussein, is dangerously inadequate. The only acceptable strategy is one that eliminates the possibility that Iraq will be able to use or threaten to use weapons of mass destruction. In the near term, this means a willingness to undertake military action as diplomacy is clearly failing. In the long term, it means removing Saddam Hussein and his regime from power. That now needs to become the aim of American foreign policy.</p>
<p>We urge you to articulate this aim, and to turn your Administration&#8217;s attention to implementing a strategy for removing Saddam&#8217;s regime from power. This will require a full complement of diplomatic, political and military efforts. Although we are fully aware of the dangers and difficulties in implementing this policy, we believe the dangers of failing to do so are far greater. We believe the U.S. has the authority under existing UN resolutions to take the necessary steps, including military steps, to protect our vital interests in the Gulf. In any case, American policy cannot continue to be crippled by a misguided insistence on unanimity in the UN Security Council.</p>
<p>We urge you to act decisively. If you act now to end the threat of weapons of mass destruction against the U.S. or its allies, you will be acting in the most fundamental national security interests of the country. If we accept a course of weakness and drift, we put our interests and our future at risk.</p>
<p>Sincerely,</p></blockquote>
<p>. Still imagine that we went to war with Iraq based on 9/11? That the decision to go to war was really made by the Decider sometime in February 2003? That if Saddam had just been a little more cooperative this unpleasantness would have been avoided? Sorry, no way. This decision was made by the people who signed this letter along with those who signed the Statement of Principles above. And note the one name that is glaringly absent, though his brother made the cut. Looks like they had to settle for the second choice when it came time for a figurehead.<br />
<blockquote>Elliott Abrams    Richard L. Armitage    William J. Bennett</p>
<p>Jeffrey Bergner    John Bolton    Paula Dobriansky</p>
<p>Francis Fukuyama    Robert Kagan    Zalmay Khalilzad</p>
<p>William Kristol    Richard Perle    Peter W. Rodman</p>
<p>Donald Rumsfeld    William Schneider, Jr.    Vin Weber</p>
<p>Paul Wolfowitz    R. James Woolsey    Robert B. Zoellick</p></blockquote>
<p>(In reading the Statement did you get the odd feeling like something was missing, that a couple of future team members weren&#8217;t there? Say like Bolton, Perle and the other Kagan? Well have no fear, they were on board all along.)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/08/project-for-a-new-american-century.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>How to be a Communist and a Fascist at the Same Time</title>
		<link>./../../2009/08/how-to-be-a-communist-and-a-fascist-at-the-same-time.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/08/how-to-be-a-communist-and-a-fascist-at-the-same-time.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2009 16:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[communism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fascism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hayek]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/08/how-to-be-a-communist-and-a-fascist-at-the-same-time.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Bruce Webb Those of us with a passing knowledge of the development of Communism and Fascism within the larger context of the Popular Revolution vs Reaction tend to scratch our heads when people accuse Obama and his whole program of being both. After all in Europe, the historical cradle of each, the movements have [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Bruce Webb</p>
<p>Those of us with a passing knowledge of the development of Communism and Fascism within the larger context of the Popular Revolution vs Reaction tend to scratch our heads when people accuse Obama and his whole program of being both. After all in Europe, the historical cradle of each, the movements have seen to be the Left and Right anchors of a political spectrum that has various democratic flavors in between: Social Democrats, Liberal Democrats, Christian Democrats and the like. But that is the result of looking at his through a narrow lens focussing on who is in or out of political power and/or which party is holding the balance.  There are alternative analytical schema that break this down in very different ways. To illustrate the mind-set that animates some, but by no means all, of the fervent opposition to Obama I would like to give you this from a review of Friedrich Hayek&#8217;s <a target="_blank" href="http://mises.org/store/Road-to-Serfdom-The-P252C0.aspx">The Road to Serfdom</a></p>
<blockquote><p>This spell-binding book is a classic in the history of liberal ideas. It was singularly responsible for launching an important debate on the relationship between political and economic freedom. It made the author a world-famous intellectual. It set a new standard for what it means to be a dissident intellectual. It warned of a new form of despotism enacted in the name of liberation. And though it appeared in 1944, it continues to have a remarkable impact. No one can consider himself well-schooled in modern political ideas without having absorbed its lessons.</p>
<p>What F.A. Hayek saw, and what most all his contemporaries missed, was that every step away from the free market and toward government planning represented a compromise of human freedom generally and a step toward a form of dictatorship&#8211;and this is true in all times and places. He demonstrated this against every claim that government control was really only a means of increasing social well-being. Hayek said that government planning would make society less liveable, more brutal, more despotic. Socialism in all its forms is contrary to freedom.</p>
<p>Nazism, he wrote, is not different in kind from Communism. Further, he showed that the very forms of government that England and America were supposedly fighting abroad were being enacted at home, if under a different guise. Further steps down this road, he said, can only end in the abolition of effective liberty for everyone.</p>
<p>Capitalism, he wrote, is the only system of economics compatible with human dignity, prosperity, and liberty. To the extent we move away from that system, we empower the worst people in society to manage what they do not understand.</p></blockquote>
<p>For followers of Hayek&#8217;s tradition the enemy is statism and their bulwark, their strength is capitalism. To argue as many leftists do that opponents of health care reform or of increases in minimum wage or any other intevention by the State to improve social or economic justice are just arguing against their own material interests, and that in doing so they are just siding with the bosses fall on deaf ears. Once you have internalized the twin equations Capitalism=Freedom &#038; Statism=Tyranny you can well understand why Movement Conservatives first rejected the Eisenhower and Rockefeller Republicans who espoused Goo-Goo approaches (&#8216;Goo-Goo&#8217; being an old, somewhat derisive term for the Good Government movement). For people who followed Hayek the Interstate Highway System was not an instrument for good, the fact that it was government initiated, funded and maintained made it more like a Superhighway to Serfdom.</p>
<p>Not all the fury being exhibited has its total roots in this Hayek-Friedman-Libertarian soil, there are clearly cultural and racial roots to much of it as well. But if you think that somewhere behind that shouting face is the committment to one of the original rallying cries of Movement Conservatism, that of Barry Goldwater in his acceptance speech in 1964: &#8216;I would remind you that extremism in the defense of liberty is no vice! And let me remind you also that moderation in the pursuit of justice is no virtue!</p>
<p>Not my own cup of tea, I kind of believe in steady pursuit of justice. I just want to point out that this is not just mindless anger, there is at least some coherentness behind it. An insurance claims rep is an agent of capitalism and so an ally of Freedom. A government health care bureaucrat is an agent of statism and so an enemy of Freedom. Making an operational argument that either one is getting between you and your doctor doesn&#8217;t cut any ice. Either you are for Freedom or against Freedom, if that comes with some personal sacrifice sobeit.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/08/how-to-be-a-communist-and-a-fascist-at-the-same-time.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
