<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>AG investigations &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Due Process: Holder vs Colbert. Art or Reality. Choose.</title>
		<link>./../../2012/03/due-process-holder-vs-colbert-art-or-reality-choose.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/03/due-process-holder-vs-colbert-art-or-reality-choose.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Mar 2012 17:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[AG investigations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[equality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income equality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[reality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rule of law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wealth creation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[world bank]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/03/due-process-holder-vs-colbert-art-or-reality-choose.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This is the object:  No person shall be held to answer for a capital, or otherwise infamous crime, unless on a presentment or indictment of a Grand Jury,&#8230; nor be deprived of life, liberty, or property, without due process of law; It&#8217;s all one sentence. Any questions? This is Art: The lyrics of Grand Funk [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div></div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>This is the object: </div>
<p>
<blockquote>
<div>No person shall be held to answer for a capital, or otherwise infamous crime, unless on a presentment or indictment of a Grand Jury,&#8230; nor be deprived of life, liberty, or property, without due process of law;</div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div>It&#8217;s all one sentence.  Any questions?</div>
<div></div>
<div>This is Art:</div>
<div>The lyrics of Grand Funk Railroad&#8217;s <a href="http://www.songlyrics.com/grand-funk-railroad/paranoid-lyrics/">Paranoid </a></div>
<p>
<blockquote>
<div>Did you ever have that feeling in your life</div>
<div>That someone was watching you?</div>
<div>You don&#8217;t have no reason that&#8217;s right</div>
<div>But still he&#8217;s there watching you</div>
<div>Someone is waiting just outside the door</div>
<div>To take you away</div>
<div>Everybody knows just what he&#8217;s there for</div>
<div>To take you away</div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div>vs the lyrics of Red Rider&#8217;s <a href="http://www.songlyrics.com/red-rider/lunatic-fringe-lyrics/">Lunatic Fringe</a> </div>
<p>
<blockquote>
<div>Lunatic Fringe &#8211; in the twilight&#8217;s last gleaming</div>
<div>This is open season, but you won&#8217;t get too far</div>
<div>&#8216;Cause you got to blame someone for your own confusion</div>
<div>We&#8217;re all on guard this time against the Final Solution</div>
<div>all on guard this time</div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div>This is the reality. 44% of <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2007/10/human-capital-is-where-its-at.html">our wealth is due to rule of law.</a></div>
<div></div>
<div>World Bank study on wealth in 2005 stated:  </div>
<p>
<blockquote>
<div align="JUSTIFY">Worldwide, the study finds, &#8220;natural capital accounts for 5 percent of total wealth, produced capital for 18 percent, and intangible capital 77 percent.&#8221;  &#8220;Rich countries are largely rich because of the skills of their populations and the quality of the institutions supporting economic activity,&#8221; the study concludes. According to Hamilton&#8217;s figures, the rule of law explains 57 percent of countries&#8217; intangible capital. Education accounts for 36 percent.”  </div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div>Rule of law equates <a href="http://www.equalitytrust.org.uk/why/evidence/trust-and-community-life">to trust</a>.   </div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-nVZaff-ud1A/T1jYq6Jlz5I/AAAAAAAAASo/J_iYIXgAUWk/s1600/Trust+Graph.gif" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="229" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-nVZaff-ud1A/T1jYq6Jlz5I/AAAAAAAAASo/J_iYIXgAUWk/s320/Trust+Graph.gif" width="320"></a></div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<div>A nation can not generate $14 trillion per year if there is general suspicion throughout society.  </div>
<p>
<blockquote>“Trust” seems to be the real intangible the report is talking about. We as a whole can be educated to the hilt, but if we can&#8217;t trust that our efforts will be put to constructive use, we have problems. Think habeas corpus, FISA, election fraud, threatening of the press, intimidation of speech, extension of free speech to none human entities, the equating of one voice-one vote to spending of one&#8217;s money, K Street project, etc. Think of the use of fear. If only a few are educated to the hilt or have access to the governance, we can not build capital. </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><div><a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2007/10/human-capital-is-where-its-at.html">Daniel Becker 10/8/2007</a></div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>Which is art, which is reality?</div>
<p>
<blockquote>
<div>Due process and judicial process are not one in the same.  The Constitution guarantees due process, it does not guarantee judicial process.  Erik Holder 3/5/12*  </div>
</blockquote>
<p>
<blockquote>
<div>Due process just means there is a process that you do.  Steven Colbert 3/6/12*</div>
<div></div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<p>Which is art, which is reality? </p>
<blockquote><p>In response to the act perpetrated&#8230;Congress has authorized the President to use all necessary and appropriate force against those groups.  Because the United States is in an armed conflict&#8230; Eric Holder 3/5/12* 
<div></div>
</blockquote>
<p>
<blockquote>
<div>We&#8217;re at war with Terror.   Therefore, the President can blow up any American citizen he chooses until we win the war by defeating the idea of being afraid.  Steven Colbert, 3/6/12.*</div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<p>
<div>Is this art or reality?</div>
<p>
<blockquote>
<div><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Due_process">Due process developed</a> from clause 39 of the Magna Carta in England.</div>
<div><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Due_process"><br /></a></div>
<div>In clause 39 of the Magna Carta, John of England promised as follows: &#8220;No free man shall be seized or imprisoned, or stripped of his rights or possessions, or outlawed or exiled, or deprived of his standing in any other way, nor will we proceed with force against him, or send others to do so, except by the lawful judgment of his equals or by the law of the land.&#8221;</div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div>It appears in this War on Terror, England is not the only nation learning from another regarding how to<a href="http://downingstreetmemo.com/memos.html">“fix” the war</a>.  We too have obviously learned from England regarding war management.  We have learned how to manifest the feeling of “it&#8217;s only a piece of paper” (though not true that Bush 2 made such a statement regarding the Constitution which makes Obama et al&#8217;s position all the more surreal).     </div>
<div></div>
<blockquote><div>As the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Due_process">U.S. Supreme Court has explained</a>, a due process requirement in Britain was not &#8220;essential to the idea of due process of law in the prosecution and punishment of crimes, but was only mentioned as an example and illustration of due process of law as it actually existed in cases in which it was customarily used.&#8221;[11]  </div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>I can see how England&#8217;s approach to war fixing is a much better solution if your goal is to <a href="http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/conflate">conflate art and reality</a>.  There is no need to be clandestine.  Did you notice the closeness of the USA and England on the trust graph?</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>Which will you choose? Art or Reality?  Are you sure which one is which?  Be careful, it&#8217;s <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2007/10/human-capital-is-where-its-at.html">your economic future</a> that is at stake.</div>
<div></div>
<div><a href="http://www.colbertnation.com/the-colbert-report-videos/410085/march-06-2012/the-word---due-or-die%20">*Watch Steven&#8217;s</a> take on this.<a href="http://www.colbertnation.com/the-colbert-report-videos/410085/march-06-2012/the-word---due-or-die"></a></div>
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/03/due-process-holder-vs-colbert-art-or-reality-choose.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>More Caution and Skepticism About Federal Mortgage “Investigation”</title>
		<link>./../../2012/01/more-caution-and-skepticism-about-federal-mortgage-investigation.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/01/more-caution-and-skepticism-about-federal-mortgage-investigation.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2012 16:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[AG investigations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[federal regulation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mortgages]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[naked Capitalism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/01/more-caution-and-skepticism-about-federal-mortgage-investigation.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Yves Smith continues to follow the progress of investigations in  More Caution and Skepticism About Federal Mortgage “Investigation” While a large number of “liberal” groups, ranging from the official Democratic party outlets (the Center for American Progress) to ones that sometimes cross swords with the Administration (MoveOn, the Working Families Party) praised the Tuesday evening [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Yves Smith continues to follow the progress of investigations in    <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/01/more-caution-and-skepticism-about-federal-mortgage-investigation.html">More Caution and Skepticism About Federal Mortgage “Investigation”</a>  <br />
<blockquote>While a large number of “liberal” groups, ranging from the official Democratic party outlets (the Center for American Progress) to ones that sometimes cross swords with the Administration (MoveOn, the Working Families Party) praised the Tuesday evening announcement of mortgage “investigations” with Schneiderman co-chairing the effort, others who have been watching the mortgage legal fight closely were far more ambivalent about the creation of a new unit in <a href="http://rushprnews.com/2009/11/17/president-obama-establishes-interagency-financial-fraud-enforcement-task-force">an initiative </a>…which has done pretty much nothing since its creation in 2009 (boldface mine):</p>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />Attorney General Eric Holder, Treasury Secretary Tim Geithner, Housing and Urban Development (HUD) Secretary Shaun Donovan, and Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) Chairwoman Mary Schapiro today announced that President Barack Obama has established by Executive Order an interagency Financial Fraud Enforcement Task Force to strengthen efforts to combat financial crime. The Department of Justice will lead the task force and the Department of Treasury, HUD and the SEC will serve on the steering committee. The task force’s leadership, along with representatives from a broad range of federal agencies, regulatory authorities and inspectors general, <strong>will work with state and local partners</strong> to <strong>investigate and prosecute significant financial crimes</strong>, <strong>ensure just and effective punishment for those who perpetrate financial crimes</strong>, address discrimination in the lending and financial markets and <strong>recover proceeds for victims</strong>.<br /> …<br /> The Times identified the two red flags. First, why are the settlement talks still proceeding? This is ridiculous if the plan is to do investigations. The fact that they have not been halted calls this exercise into question. Second, if this is supposed to be a heavyweight investigation, why hasn’t Obama set up an independent prosecutor, a role much more likely to attract the sort of kick-ass litigator that the Times correctly thinks is necessary for the job? </p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/01/more-caution-and-skepticism-about-federal-mortgage-investigation.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
