<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Brenda Rosser &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The assumption that markets are &#8216;natural&#8217;</title>
		<link>./../../2012/06/the-assumption-that-markets-are-natural.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/06/the-assumption-that-markets-are-natural.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 27 Jun 2012 13:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Brenda Rosser]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[econospeak]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[markets]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/06/the-assumption-that-markets-are-natural.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Brenda Rosserre-posted from Econospeak with permission from the author The assumption that markets are &#8216;natural&#8217; I&#8217;ve just begun to browse the pages of David Graeber&#8217;s  2011 book entitled &#8216;Debt &#8211; The First 5,000 Years&#8217;.  Graeber is an anthropologist who makes no bones about the historical errors made by many economists on the evolution of [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Brenda Rosser<br />re-posted from <i>Econospeak</i> with permission from the author</p>
<p><a href="http://econospeak.blogspot.com/2012/06/assumption-that-markets-are-natural.html">The assumption that markets are &#8216;natural&#8217;</a></p>
<p>I&#8217;ve just begun to browse the pages of David Graeber&#8217;s  2011 book entitled &#8216;Debt &#8211; The First 5,000 Years&#8217;.  Graeber is an anthropologist who makes no bones about the historical errors made by many economists on the evolution of markets and the use and nature of money.<br />   <br />On pages 44-45 Graeber writes:    <br />&#8220;People continue to argue about whether an unfettered free market really will produced the results that [Adam] Smith said it would; <i>but no one questions whether &#8220;the market&#8221; naturally exists</i>&#8230;.we simply assume that when valuable objects do change hands, it will normally be because two individuals have both decided they would gain a material advantage by swapping them.  One interesting corollary is that, as a result, economists have come to see the very question of the presence or absence of money as not especially important, since money is just a commodity, chosen to facilitate exchange, and which we use to measure the value of other commodities.  Otherwise it has no special qualities.<br />    <br />&#8220;&#8230;.Call this the final apotheosis of economics as common sense.  Money is unimportant.  Economies &#8211; &#8220;real economies&#8221; &#8211; are really vast barter systems.  <i>The problem is that history shows that without money, such vast barter systems do not occur</i>&#8230;.It&#8217;s money that had made it possible for us to imagine ourselves in the way economists encourage us to do:  as a collection of individuals and nations whose main business is swapping things.  It&#8217;s also clear that the mere existence of money, in itself, is not enough to allow us to see the world this way. &#8230;<br />    <br />&#8220;The missing element is in fact&#8230;the role of government policy&#8230;&#8221;<br />  <br /><a name="more"></a><br />Graeber goes on to explain how government foster &#8216;the market&#8217;.  Laws, police, monetary policy, pegging the value of currency to precious metals, altering the amount of coins in circulation, regulating banks etc.    <br />On page 49 Graeber asks a key question: &#8220;&#8230;what exactly was the point of extracting the gold, stamping one&#8217;s picture on it, causing it to circulate among one&#8217;s subjects &#8211; and then demanding that those same subjects give it back again?&#8221;<br />    <br />&#8220;This does seem a bit of a puzzle.  But <i>if money and markets do not emerge spontaneously</i>, it actually makes perfect sense.  Because this is the simplest and most efficient way to bring markets into being.&#8221;    <br />Money brings markets into being.  Not the other way around, as most economists would have it.  If this is true then Graeber&#8217;s concluding thought has some authenticity:  &#8220;<i>Perhaps the world really does owe you a living</i>.&#8221;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/06/the-assumption-that-markets-are-natural.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
