<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>William Saletan &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>A Victory for the Reality-Based Community! Oh, Know! Er, Oh, No!</title>
		<link>./../../2012/11/a-victory-for-the-reality-based-community-oh-know-er-oh-no.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/11/a-victory-for-the-reality-based-community-oh-know-er-oh-no.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 09 Nov 2012 19:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Phillip Rucker]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Washington Post]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[William Saletan]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/11/a-victory-for-the-reality-based-community-oh-know-er-oh-no.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Every four years, the race for the White House ends in accusations of deceit. Each side says the other spent millions of dollars to lie and skew the outcome. This year’s post-election accounts of backstage calculations and fateful turning points continue that tradition. But if you read these accounts carefully, you’ll find a happy surprise [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>Every four years, the race for the White House ends in accusations of deceit. Each side says the other spent millions of dollars to lie and skew the outcome. This year’s post-election accounts of backstage calculations and fateful turning points continue that tradition. But if you read these accounts carefully, you’ll find a happy surprise beneath the spin and recriminations: Lies failed. Truth prevailed.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212; <i><a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/frame_game/2012/11/_2012_election_facts_in_the_obama_romney_showdown_truth_beat_lies_and_spin.html#comments">The Power of Truth: In the 2012 election,reality overwhelmed pretense, gamesmanship, and self-deception.</a></i>, William Saletan, Slate, today
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Saletan goes on to discuss the several critical points during the campaign that pundits say are what ultimately led to Romney’s defeat, including the impact of Hurricane Sandy and of Romney’s appalling Jeep-jobs-to-China ad in Ohio last week.  You know, the one that said, “<a href="http://www.politifact.com/truth-o-meter/statements/2012/oct/30/mitt-romney/mitt-romney-obama-chrysler-sold-italians-china-ame/" target="_blank">Obama took GM and Chrysler into bankruptcy and sold Chrysler to Italians who are going to build Jeeps in China</a>.”
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Saletan points to a delicious comment by a Romney fundraiser<a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/decision2012/life-after-defeat-for-mitt-romney-public-praise-private-questions/2012/11/07/4db3bc38-2916-11e2-96b6-8e6a7524553f_story.html"> to Washington Post reporterPhillip Rucker</a>—“A lot of people feel like Christie hurt, that we definitely lost four or five points between the storm and Chris Christie giving Obama a chance to be bigger than life,” a Romney fundraiser tells Rucker”—and nicely refutes its premise, voiced also by numerous pundits during the last week.  He points out that Obama wasn’t <i>acting</i>, or <i>looking</i>, presidential.  He was instead <i>being</i> presidential; he was performing his job.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Saletan’s article in mostly terrific.  But it—like most of the other pundit assessments—fails to mention the <i>actual</i> key factor for why Hurricane Sandy made it impossible for Romney to win: That the public learned of Romney’s primary-campaign statement that he wanted to remove disaster relief and all sorts of other federal programs as a federal responsibilities and place the responsibility for them on the states.  The very premise of this surely struck a large percentage of the population as nutty.  This ideology was at the very heart of Romney’s campaign, yet most people didn’t know that until a week before the election. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The Sandy effect, in other words, had less to do with Obama’s “looking presidential” than Obama’s being presidential, as Saletan notes, but that’s because the public learned then pretty much what the difference was between Obama’s idea of what the federal government, rather than the states, should do.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Another important factor was, as this article and many others point out, Romney’s appalling ad last week in Ohio about Chrysler and Jeep, but I think the ad’s importance went even beyond the obvious problem that it intended to perpetuate a clearly erroneous fact.  Everyone in any way connected to the auto industry knows that Chrysler could not have survived at all without its purchase by Fiat.  Everyone who is currently employed because of Chrysler’s continued existence—including employees of Chrysler’s parts suppliers—knows that there would be no Chrysler, and therefore no Jeep jobs to be sent to China, or not—were it not for the sale of Chrysler to Fiat. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>So the ad, in addition to being flatly false in suggesting that the Jeep factory in Toledo was being shuttered, made no sense.  And it made no sense in a way that everyone recognized made no sense.  The ad, although it ran only in Ohio, got lots of publicity nationwide because the auto executives’ stunned and angry refutation, and Obama’s comments in Toledo about the ad, were big political news around the country.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The only conceivable reason that the Romney campaign gambled by putting out an ad that so obviously could backfire exactly as it did is that they already knew they were losing in Ohio and were willing to try, literally, anything.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>These two factors, the hurricane and the Toledo Jeep factory, both of them coming in the closing ten days of the campaign, actually summed up the Romney campaign: mendacity as its prime <i>modus operandi,</i>and Tea Party ideology, <i>both</i> of which depend upon a concerted removal from the fact-based world.  
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I suspect that it will be a long time before another Republican presidential nominee tries either of these.  At least until he or she is inaugurated. 
</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/11/a-victory-for-the-reality-based-community-oh-know-er-oh-no.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Mad Hatter For President! (Pleeease, Obama campaign, do a Halloween Fun-House ad. Pleeeease.)</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/the-mad-hatter-for-president-pleeease-obama-campaign-do-a-halloween-fun-house-ad-pleeeease.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/the-mad-hatter-for-president-pleeease-obama-campaign-do-a-halloween-fun-house-ad-pleeeease.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2012 18:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Halloween]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Josh Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lewis Carroll. Obama campaign]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mad Hatter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[William Saletan]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/the-mad-hatter-for-president-pleeease-obama-campaign-do-a-halloween-fun-house-ad-pleeeease.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Have you heard the news? Mitt Romney met with editors of the Des Moines Register yesterday and dropped a bombshell. “Romney promises no abortion legislation,” says the Associated Press. “Romney: No abortion legislation,” says Politico. “Romney says no plans to restrict abortion,” says Agence France-Presse. Nope. That isn’t what Romney said. This is a man with a long history [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>Have you heard the news? Mitt Romney met with editors of the <em>Des Moines Register</em> yesterday and dropped a bombshell. “<a href="http://news.yahoo.com/romney-promises-no-abortion-legislation-004508435--election.html" target="_blank">Romney promises no abortion legislation</a>,” says the Associated Press. “<a href="http://www.politico.com/news/stories/1012/82225.html" target="_blank">Romney: No abortion legislation</a>,” says <em>Politico</em>. “<a href="http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5gS9JzyIMR83DWX2o5_NqwCA1YO8Q" target="_blank">Romney says no plans to restrict abortion</a>,” says Agence France-Presse.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Nope. That isn’t what Romney said. This is a man with a <a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/the_conversion/2012/02/mitt_romney_s_abortion_record_flip_flop_or_conversion_.html">long history of using technicalities to disguise his abortion views</a>. You have to read his exact words, with attention to the loopholes. So let’s back up and <a href="http://blogs.desmoinesregister.com/dmr/index.php/2012/10/09/mitt-romney-on-his-tax-cut-plan-the-math-works#fullaudio" target="_blank">listen to the full audio</a> of Romney’s remarks.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212; <i><a href="http://why/">Romney’s Abortion “Agenda”:  Don’t fall for his insinuation that he won’t restrict abortion. It’s full of weasel words</a>, </i>William Saletan, Slate, today</div>
<div></div>
<div>Saletan goes on to summarize what he brilliantly calls Romney’s Massachusetts-pol-days use of escape-clause language on the abortion issue—how he would calculatingly <i>appear</i> to state a position and then, for the sake of political expedience,  renege and point to some hedge he’d included in the contract—er, the campaign promise. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Saletan concludes his article by warning, “That’s why you need to spot the weasel words up front. In the end, with Romney, they’re all that matters.”
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Well, yes. That’s true on <i>every</i> issue, not just on that one.  We’re dealing here with the Mad Hatter.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>One of Romney’s sons, Josh,<a href="http://livewire.talkingpointsmemo.com/entry/josh-romney-dad-learned-how-to-debate-obstinate--1"> said yesterday</a> in an interview that Obama had lied about Romney’s positions.  The son was restating, but even more clearly, the father’s debate claim that Obama keeps stubbornly claiming that Romney has proposed things that Romney hasn’t proposed.  Except that Romney in fact has, repeatedly, proposed those things—like cutting taxes (not just tax rate, replaced with the closing of loopholes, but <i>tax payments</i>) for the wealthy by 20%.</p>
<p>This Orwellian strategy of saying that the person who says you said something you said is an “obstinate child” (Josh’s phrase) who is “lying” (Josh’s word) is downright scary.  It’s a direct attempt to pervert democracy. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The news media really, really, <i>really</i> should point that out.  Cleary.  But the Obama campaign needs to, too.  More effectively than it has in the last week. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And what better than a Halloween fun house—ghosts suddenly jumping out of nowhere; the floor suddenly dropping out from under you; fake smoke and real mirrors that distort your body shape (or his)—to illustrate the point?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Oh, and Romney’s Halloween costume?  The Mad Hatter, of course.  Romney wearing it to go trick-or-treating while spouting lines written by Lewis Carroll.  And by Josh Romney.  Who’s now made himself fair game.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/the-mad-hatter-for-president-pleeease-obama-campaign-do-a-halloween-fun-house-ad-pleeeease.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Romney Says He’ll Shoot Farm Price Supports, Draught Relief and Veterans’ Benefits, Right Along With Big Bird!</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/romney-says-hell-shoot-farm-price-supports-draught-relief-and-veterans-benefits-right-along-with-big-bird.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/romney-says-hell-shoot-farm-price-supports-draught-relief-and-veterans-benefits-right-along-with-big-bird.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 05 Oct 2012 17:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Federal budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[William Saletan]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/romney-says-hell-shoot-farm-price-supports-draught-relief-and-veterans-benefits-right-along-with-big-bird.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Slate’s William Saletan has a terrific article there today, with a terrific title: Tax Evasion: Romney’s preposterous arguments for not telling you which tax breaks he’d abolish.  And, yes, elsewhere, too, mainstream-media folks are showing some morning-after queasiness about their debate verdict, by getting into the “um … huh?” stuff now. But in pointing out that [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>Slate’s William Saletan has a terrific article there today, with a terrific title: <i><a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/politics/2012/10/romney_s_tax_deduction_plan_why_won_t_he_tell_you_which_loopholes_he_d_close_.html#comments">Tax Evasion:</a> </i><i><a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/politics/2012/10/romney_s_tax_deduction_plan_why_won_t_he_tell_you_which_loopholes_he_d_close_.html#comments">Romney’s preposterous arguments for not telling you which tax breaks he’d abolish</a>.</i>  And, yes, elsewhere, too, mainstream-media folks are showing some morning-after queasiness about their debate verdict, by getting into the “um … huh?” stuff now.</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>But in pointing out that Nixon really doesn’t have a plan to end the Vietnam War—er, I mean, that Romney doesn’t really have a plan to balance the budget—they’ve been talking mostly about Romney’s refusal to identify the tax loopholes and deductions he’ll end. They haven’t mentioned much Romney’s other demonstration of, um, willingness to be specific about extremely important budget matters: His statement that he’ll end all programs that, in his opinion, aren’t worth borrowing money from China for. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Which include Medicaid and Sesame Street.  But what <i>other </i>programs?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The effective end of federally supported Medicaid is obviously too serious a subject to joke about, and it needs much more attention from the news media than it’s getting—as well as from the Obama campaign, which should put up ads featuring nursing home residents and nursing home <i>owners</i>; i.e., small-business owners who are jobs creators, to explain the issue.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>But Obama also should say—yes, <i>say</i>—when he’s campaign in, maybe, Iowa, eastern Colorado, Wisconsin and North Carolina that Romney doesn’t think farm subsidies, flood insurance, hurricane and tornado disaster relief are worth borrowing money from China from. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And when campaigning in North Carolina, Virginia, Ohio and, well, everywhere else, he should say that Romney doesn’t think veterans’ benefits are worth borrowing money for China for.  And that that might make it harder to recruit those additional 100,000 people into the armed services that he says he wants to add, although of course he might just have a military draft in mind.  You never know; he’s not all that keen on revealing specifics, after all.  (Does Romney <i>ever</i> think beyond the end of whatever sentence he’s mouthing at the  moment?)
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Seriously. The only way to start to nail down Romney’s plans is to start actually filling in his blanks.  Say, outright, that Romney plans to end farm price supports, drought relief, disaster relief and veteran’s benefits.  Romney then will have to say that he has no such plans.  Great! Then say that Romney plans to shut down the FDA and the National Transportation Safety Board; a few hundred deaths from dangerous medications and airplane crashes each year aren’t worth borrowing money from China to prevent.  Not when you have more important needs, such as incessantly spiraling tax cuts for the wealthy. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Which, despite his Wednesday protestations, he does think are worth borrowing money from China for.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Or here’s another idea: Let’s develop a contest in which the winner accurately predicts Romney’s selections for Programs Worth Borrowing From China For.  And a bonus contest in which the winner correctly calls the tax loopholes and deductions eliminated in Romney’s tax-code revision plan.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The winners will be announced on the same day as the announcement of the Publishers Clearinghouse winner for 2015. The prize?  We can have another contest to guess that.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/romney-says-hell-shoot-farm-price-supports-draught-relief-and-veterans-benefits-right-along-with-big-bird.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Is Romney a Habitual Liar? Or Is He Instead Something Even More Dangerous: God-Awful Stupid? [Updated]</title>
		<link>./../../2012/09/is-romney-a-habitual-liar-or-is-he-instead-something-even-more-dangerous-god-awful-stupid-updated.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/09/is-romney-a-habitual-liar-or-is-he-instead-something-even-more-dangerous-god-awful-stupid-updated.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 13 Sep 2012 16:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[foreign policy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[William Saletan]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/09/is-romney-a-habitual-liar-or-is-he-instead-something-even-more-dangerous-god-awful-stupid-updated.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[At his press conference, Romney accused Obama of “having that embassy reiterate a statement effectively apologizing for the right of free speech.” Romney claimed that the embassy had said, in his paraphrase, “We stand by our comments that suggest that there&#8217;s something wrong with the right of free speech.&#8221; This, too, was a Romney lie. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div></div>
<div>At his press conference, Romney accused Obama of “having that embassy reiterate a statement effectively apologizing for the right of free speech.” Romney claimed that the embassy had said, in his paraphrase, “We stand by our comments that suggest that there&#8217;s something wrong with the right of free speech.&#8221; This, too, was a Romney lie. The embassy had declared <a href="http://egypt.usembassy.gov/pr091112.html" target="_blank"><i>five times</i></a> in <a href="https://twitter.com/usembassycairo/status/245621390626156545" target="_blank"><i>writing</i></a> that <a href="https://twitter.com/usembassycairo/status/245635156927467520" target="_blank"><i>free speech</i></a> was a <a href="https://twitter.com/usembassycairo/status/245472954052395008" target="_blank"><i>universal right</i></a>.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>What made Romney’s statement and press conference disturbing, however, was his repeated use of the words <em>sympathize</em> and <em>apology</em> to conflate three issues the Cairo embassy had carefully separated: bigotry, free speech, and violence. The embassy had <a href="https://twitter.com/usembassycairo/status/245635156927467520" target="_blank"><i>stipulated</i></a> that expressions of bigotry, while wrong, were protected by freedom of speech and didn’t warrant retaliatory violence. Romney, by accusing the embassy of “sympathizing with those who had breached” the compound, equated moral criticism of the Mohammed movie with support for violence. In so doing, Romney embraced the illiberal Islamist mindset that led to the embassy invasion: To declare a movie offensive is to authorize its suppression.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>“The Embassy of the United States issued what appeared to be an apology for American principles,” Romney asserted at the press conference. “It’s a terrible course for America to stand in apology for our values. … An apology for America&#8217;s values is never the right course.” Lest anyone miss his buzzwords, Romney called the embassy’s comments “a disgraceful statement on the part of our administration to apologize for American values.”
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>What, exactly, does Romney mean by “American values”? The embassy never apologized for free speech or diplomatic sovereignty. The only American offense it criticized was the movie’s “bigotry” and “efforts by misguided individuals to hurt the religious feelings of Muslims.” Does Romney regard this criticism as an “apology for American values”? Is bigotry an American value? Is it weak or un-American to repudiate slurs against Muslims?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I don’t know where you were born, Mr. Romney (<a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/frame_game/2012/08/romney_s_birther_joke_he_isn_t_using_bigotry_against_obama_it_just_looks_that_way_.html"><i>just kidding!</i></a>), but where I come from, there’s nothing more American than recognizing the idiocy of a man’s views and, at the same time, his right to express them. If you can’t tell the difference between those two things, the main threat to our values right now isn’t President Obama, the Egyptians, the Libyans, or our diplomats in Cairo. It’s you.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212; William Saletan, <a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/frame_game/2012/09/the_mohammed_movie_and_the_embassy_attacks_romney_betrays_free_speech_.html#comments">Slate</a>, today
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The political punditry and news media is finally catching on that Romney’s bizarre modus operandi of habitually mischaracterizing the meanings of basic statements of others (mainly, of course, of Obama) pose the question: Is Romney a habitual liar, or is he instead so dumbfoundingly stupid that he regularly misunderstands even completely clear statements and the definitions of common English-language words, and that he habitually conflates separate concepts and therefore misinterprets even the clearest of statements or comments?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I’ve hoped for a long time that the Obama campaign would pretend to take Romney at his word: Rather than suggest that Romney’s a habitual liar; just point out that, taking him at his word, he’s profoundly, dangerously stupid.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I mean … good grace.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I read somewhere last night—I can’t remember where—that members of Romney’s campaign team told reporters that he was genuinely outraged on Tuesday night by the Cairo embassy’s criticism of “efforts by misguided individuals to hurt the religious feelings of Muslims,” and that it was phrase “hurt the religious feelings” that really set him off.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>This focus by Romney on a single word or short phrase, removed from its context and redefined—this treatment by Romney of serious issues as cutesy word play—has been a real hallmark of Romney’s campaign throughout.  Hopefully, Obama and the news media will now point out truly dangerous it would be to have a president who either can’t understand and accurately interpret basic words, statements and concepts. Leave it up to Romney to protest that, no, he’s not really that dumb; he’s just playing games about the most serious of matters, presuming that a majority of voters won’t notice. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The most important aspect of what has transpired in the last two days is that now a majority of voters are likely to notice.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I&#8217;m pretty sure that the game&#8217;s over, and that Romney lost.</p>
<p>&#8212;&#8211;</p>
<div>UPDATE: Just to clarify, I want to repost here a comment I made in the Comments thread in response to reader PJR about whether Romney is a liar or instead just stupid.  I wrote:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Romney’s a liar, PJR. A casual, habitual liar.  That’s his modus operandi; it’s what he thinks gets him the love of the Tea Party folks—his bald willingness to regularly lie as a matter of campaign strategy.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>My point, though, is to encourage Obama and the media to decide to take Romney at his word—that he’s not lying; he’s just stating things as he understands them.  Which, if so, is a HUGE problem. Even George Bush wasn’t as jaw-droppingly stupid and routinely confused about the meaning of words and statements as Romney either is or feigns. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The bottom line, I think, is that Romney is a liar and is also too stupid to recognize that eventually people were going to figure that out.
</p>
</div>
</div>
<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/09/is-romney-a-habitual-liar-or-is-he-instead-something-even-more-dangerous-god-awful-stupid-updated.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
