<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>extractionism. money flows &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Romney&#8217;s Private Equity Magic Trick&#8211;equity manager&#8217;s gain, taxpayers&#8217; losses</title>
		<link>./../../2012/08/romneys-private-equity-magic-trick-equity-managers-gain-taxpayers-losses.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/08/romneys-private-equity-magic-trick-equity-managers-gain-taxpayers-losses.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Aug 2012 15:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[extractionism. money flows]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linda Beale (Tax law)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[private equity]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/08/romneys-private-equity-magic-trick-equity-managers-gain-taxpayers-losses.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Beale Romney&#8217;s Private Equity Magic Trick&#8211;equity manager&#8217;s gain, taxpayers&#8217; losses (Reich Video) Mitt Romney claims that his business experience at Bain Capital is a superb qualification for the presidency.  He implies that this experience will carry over to his economic policies, with the suggestion that he will become a &#8220;job creator-in-chief&#8221; like all [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Linda Beale</p>
<p>Romney&#8217;s Private Equity Magic Trick&#8211;equity manager&#8217;s gain, taxpayers&#8217; losses (Reich Video)</p>
<p>Mitt Romney claims that his business experience at Bain Capital is a superb qualification for the presidency.  He implies that this experience will carry over to his economic policies, with the suggestion that he will become a &#8220;job creator-in-chief&#8221; like all those one-percenters purportedly are in the private sector.<br />In reality, private equity experience is a recipe for disaster in the White House.  Think about what private equity firms do.  They take an ongoing business&#8211;usually one that is making decent profits and paying its workers decently&#8211;and they make it into one that can pay outsized &#8220;rent&#8221; profits to the private equity firm.  Usually, though not always, this means cutting costs and adding debt. </p>
<p>The debt is an elixir for private equity firms.  Because interest is deductible, it actually increases profits by lowering the company&#8217;s federal income taxes; yet because it isn&#8217;t required to be used by the firm to actually improve the products or services offered, it is often used instead to pay dividends to the private equity firms, paying off whatever actual investment the private equity firm made in the company. </p>
<p>Cutting costs is the way for private equity firms to extract even more gravy from their target company.  Cost cutting is most often directed at</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<ul>
<li>firing workers and making fewer workers do the same work that more workers used to do (that&#8217;s called a &#8220;productivity&#8221; gain, garnered, of course, by the private equity firm and not by the everyday workers), and/or </li>
<li>outsourcing jobs to other countries so that labor can be paid less than a going wage in this country (that&#8217;s often coupled with step one, since workers are no longer needed in this country&#8211;sometimes the US workers are even required to train their cheaper foreign counterparts before they are let go, and of course those &#8220;effiencicy&#8221; gains are garnered by the private equity firm and not by the remaining workers), and/or </li>
<li>cutting wages and benefits for the remaining workers (and shipping those extra &#8220;savings&#8221; out as dividends to the equity firm investors), and/or </li>
<li>innovating better administrative systems (this can be a good deal&#8211;for example, putting money  that the company didn&#8217;t have until the new &#8220;investors&#8221; came in into digital record systems or improved communications systems, but it can also be a bad deal, if the firm uses its new technology to game the federal system on taxes, or Medicare reimbursements, or federal contracting or similar items)
<ul>
<li>Consider the fact that Bain and other private equity firms purchased a for-profit hospital.  One of the &#8220;improvements was to redesign the coding system for patient services to increase the reimbursements from Medicare and thus hike up the hospital system&#8217;s profits, which are garnered by the private equity firm.  Julie Creswell and Reed Adelson, <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/08/15/business/hca-giant-hospital-chain-creates-a-windfall-for-private-equity.html">A Giant Hospital Chain is Blazing a Profit Trail</a>, New York Times (Aug. 15, 2012), at A1 (noting that Medicare reimbursements for the highest classifications surged to $949,000 in 2010 from $48,000 in 2006 at one hospital, in a story about Bain Capital and other equity firms&#8217;  profit improvements at HCA, where nurses and doctors express concerns about profit-making that is driving decisions that shortchange patients through understaffing and/or shortchange the government, as in the new coding system that caused the Medicare reimbursements to skyrocket); see also Steve Denning,<a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/stevedenning/2012/08/15/private-equity-wont-fix-health-care-either/">HCA: The unsustainable private equity bubble in US health care</a>, Forbes (Aug. 15, 2012). </li>
<li>As one commenter on the NY Times article noted, &#8220;To be more profitable as a healthcare facility requires &#8230; having more sick people to treat, or hav[ing] higher charges.  Both are inhumane.&#8221;  Munz, New York, NY.  And as one former HCA employee commented, &#8220;patient safety and medication safety came in a distant 2nd to conformity and [the] draconian measures to make care more efficient.&#8221;</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>These kinds of activities go hand in hand with the increasing consolidation into mega-business enterprises (regrettably aided by the tax code&#8217;s &#8220;tax-free reorganization&#8221; provisions, that were also made much more flexible during the Bush years in order to facilitate such consolidations).  Big businesses reap the productivity gains of their workers for the few managers and significant shareholders at the top, and either buy  or compete with local and family-owned small enterprises to put those smaller and shallower-pocketed (and less well-connected) business out of the way, thus separating more and more businesses from the communities in which they are located.  All in all, not good for America, and not the kind of skills one wants in the presidency, where we need someone who can see the relationship between the stability of small businesses, viable communities, and stable workers.</p>
<p>For a clear and understandable demonstration of the way private equity firms make their money and who wins (and who loses) from those methods, see Robert Reich&#8217;s video chat on the subject:</p>
<p>cross posted with <a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2012/08/-private-equity-magic-trick-equity-managers-gain-taxpayers-losses-reich-video.html">ataxingmatter</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/08/romneys-private-equity-magic-trick-equity-managers-gain-taxpayers-losses.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>extractionism</title>
		<link>./../../2011/12/extractionism.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/12/extractionism.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 18 Dec 2011 15:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[extractionism. money flows]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Yves Smith]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/12/extractionism.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Dylan Ratigan interviews Yves Smith on  where the money goes (h/t rjs): Smith: Investors Are Afraid of Suing the Big Banks for Fear the Government Will RetaliateOn this episode of Greedy Bastards Antidote, we’re covering a new term from our upcoming book. This week, we’re focusing on extractionism. Joining us to discuss it is Yves [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.dylanratigan.com/2011/12/12/extractionism-with-yves-smith-of-naked-capitalism/" title="http://www.dylanratigan.com/2011/12/12/extractionism-with-yves-smith-of-naked-capitalism/">Dylan Ratigan</a> interviews Yves Smith on  where the money goes (h/t rjs): <br />
<blockquote><strong></strong><br /><strong>Smith: Investors Are Afraid of Suing the Big Banks for Fear the Government Will Retaliate</strong><br /><strong><br /></strong><br /><strong>On this episode of Greedy Bastards Antidote, we’re covering a new term from our upcoming book. This week, we’re focusing on extractionism. Joining us to discuss it is Yves Smith of <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/">nakedcapitalism.com</a>. She is author of <a href="http://www.amazon.com/ECONned-Unenlightened-Undermined-Democracy-Capitalism/dp/0230114563/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&#038;qid=1323654084&#038;sr=8-1">ECONned: How Unenlightened Self Interest Undermined Democracy and Corrupted Capitalism</a>.</strong><br /><strong><br /></strong><br />This week, I talk with Yves Smith, and she opened my eyes to some radical stuff going on in the capital markets. Big Banks are extracting capital for themselves with such power that investors are actually afraid to go to the courts for redress.</p>
<p>Yves said that one prominent securities lawyer told her “he knows investors who he said if Jamie Dimon came into somebody’s house and killed the children of these people, he said they would be afraid to call the police.” That’s how bad the extraction has gotten. And that’s not capitalism.</p>
<p>But first, what is extraction, and how is it the opposite of capitalism? How can extractionist systems have all the characteristics of capitalism, while hiding the elimination of productive resources over time?</p></blockquote>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />
<blockquote>Greedy Bastards like to call themselves capitalists, but what they’re actually doing is the exact opposite: it’s <strong>extractionism: taking money from others without creating anything of value; anything that produces economic growth or improves our lives.</strong><br /><strong><br /></strong><br />Under an extractionist system, we find <em>lose</em> value at a faster rate over time, while we need to be creating it. Instead of giving people incentives to make good deals where both sides can benefit, extractionist systems rewards those who take and take some more, and give nothing in return. Sadly, extractionism has crept its way into every aspect of our economy — it’s everywhere, from trade to taxes to banking&#8230;</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/12/extractionism.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
