<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Mike Kimel &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Accountability</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/accountability.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/accountability.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2013 15:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Mike Kimel]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/accountability.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Mike Kimel Accountability Watching the slow motion train wreck that is the European economy right now, and the Argentine economy just about always, I started to wonder &#8211; should political leaders be personally liable for their failures? Obviously, there is no way that someone whose ineptitude puts a creates a crash that causes severe [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Mike Kimel</p>
<p>Accountability</p>
<p>Watching the slow motion train wreck that is the European economy right now, and the Argentine economy just about always, I started to wonder &#8211; should political leaders be personally liable for their failures?  Obviously, there is no way that someone whose ineptitude puts a creates a crash that causes severe economic hardship to other people can make the other affected people whole.  Additionally, in most cases, many of the other people affected share some of the blame. Don&#8217;t like the fact that GW started a war for seemingly no reason in Iraq and left behind an economic mess? Don&#8217;t like it that Obama has not only failed to failed to prosecute the scofflaws who created the mess, he has done as much as humanly possible to ensure they continue to profit using your tax dollars?    Too bad, because if you&#8217;re over reading this you probably voted for at least one of those two guys.</p>
<p>Holding people accountable also faces the problem of mis-placed blame. There are several think tanks, some which have been around for decades, whose primary purpose in practice appears to be &#8220;proving&#8221; that the period of fastest measured real economic growth in this country&#8217;s history, a period that came scarcely four years after the biggest meltdown in this country history, was the height of economic mismanagement.   The end result, of course, is that we haven&#8217;t so much as had a debate on using the solutions that worked so well in the previous meltdown this time around, and the economy is still shaky. (For reasons that are obscure to me, much of Europe is actually trying the exact opposite approach to the policies that have worked historically.)</p>
<p>But let us say it was possible to correctly assign blame where it is due.  Should we then hold those people who create big economic or political disasters accountable?  If their actions lead to the senseless deaths of tens or hundreds of thousands, or the reasonless penury of millions, should they be held accountable?  Sure, you could never extract the trillions in lost economic output from those whose decisions made and/or enabled the mess, but it should be possible to punish them in some ways, enough so that the next people in the same position face a different set of incentives.</p>
<p>Bear in mind:  leading a nation, holding the fate of one&#8217;s compatriots in one&#8217;s hands is not a right, its a privilege, and arguably, the ultimate privilege.  People put huge sums of money and a lot of effort into attaining that privilege, or even just influencing who gets that privilege.  Those who do get it, or even are somewhat close to it, not only enjoy that privilege but also profit immensely.  Put another way &#8211; being a national leader apparently has nothing but upside.  Is that really a good thing?  Does it encourage especially inept or corrupt people to seek public office, and make it more likely that such people will win?   And what should we do about it?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/accountability.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Revealed Preference</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/revealed-preference.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/revealed-preference.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2013 12:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Mike Kimel]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/revealed-preference.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Mike Kimel Revealed Preference This week came news that Rob Portman, a Republican senator from Ohio, is bucking his party and reversing his own long-held position on gay marriage. Now that his son has come out as gay, he supports it. From an article in the Cleveland Plain Dealer by reporter Sabrina Eaton: Republican [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by<strong> Mike Kimel</strong><br /><strong><br /></strong> <strong>Revealed Preference</strong> </p>
<p>This week came news that Rob Portman, a Republican senator from Ohio, is bucking his party and reversing his own long-held position on gay marriage. Now that his son has come out as gay, he supports it. From an article in the <a href="http://www.cleveland.com/open/index.ssf/2013/03/sen_rob_portman_comes_out_in_f.html">Cleveland Plain Dealer by reporter Sabrina Eaton</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>Republican U.S. Sen. Rob Portman on Thursday announced he has reversed his longtime opposition to same-sex marriage after reconsidering the issue because his 21-year-old son, Will, is gay. </p>
<p>Portman said his son, a junior at Yale University, told him and his wife, Jane, that he&#8217;s gay and &#8220;it was not a choice, it was who he is and that he had been that way since he could remember.&#8221; </p>
<p>&#8220;It allowed me to think of this issue from a new perspective, and that&#8217;s of a Dad who loves his son a lot and wants him to have the same opportunities that his brother and sister would have &#8212; to have a relationship like Jane and I have had for over 26 years,&#8221; Portman told reporters in an interview at his office. </p>
<p>The conversation the Portmans had with their son two years ago led to him to evolve on the issue after he consulted clergy members, friends including former Vice President Dick Cheney, and the Bible.</p></blockquote>
<p>I personally favor the concept of allowing any rational consenting adults to get married, though I doubt it would  personally affect any of my closest acquaintances. (I am still waiting for someone to explain how the wedding of two people of the same gender diminishes my own marriage to my wife, or what business it is of mine who someone else wants to marry.) That said, some random thoughts:</p>
<p>1. Portman&#8217;s new views seem to be a case of him caring for his own but not for others. After all, he could have given the issue thought at any time and reached the same conclusion. He just had to muster up compassion for other people the way he did for his son, but that, apparently, was outside his capability. One wonders what other positions he holds that he might reverse himself on were it to affect a family member and what other convictions he holds would be abandoned for self-gain. If he discovers one of his other children enjoys forging other people&#8217;s signatures on checks, can we expect the senator to abandon his long-held beliefs on certain types of fraud or theft? If that sounds like an extreme example, bear in mind that Portman co-sponsored a bill banning same-sex marriage, and did what he could to make it harder for same-gender couples to adopt children. This was not a lightly held belief. Can we know which of his other core convictions are up for grabs for private gain? Can we know which aren&#8217;t?</p>
<p>2. The article indicates he consulted with Dick Cheney, who famously supported gay marriage after one of his daughters was revealed to be gay. But Dick Cheney is also an example of someone who will abandon his stated convictions. During his various terms in different government offices, both pre and post his private sector stints, Cheney did what he could to prevent Americans from having dealings with Iran. Of course, Cheney made exceptions when it would benefit himself or his friends. GOP congressman Warren Rudman <a href="https://www.blogger.com/%3Ca%20href=" irancontraaffair_key_figures="irancontraaffair_dick_cheney&#038;timeline=irancontraaffair" timeline.jsp="" www.historycommons.org="">noted of the Iran Contra hearings</a>:</p>
<p>“It was obvious that Dick Cheney and others were more interested in protecting the president than in finding out what had happened.” Later, Halliburton, while led by Dick Cheney, did business directly with Iran. Essentially, Cheney&#8217;s behavior shows us that as far as he is concerned, putting the screws on Iran is an endeavor that was and is worth the cost, provided the costs are not paid by Cheney or his friends.</p>
<p>I don&#8217;t have much else to say about this, except that, despite the fact that Portman has now come out supporting a position I have long held, I trust him to do the right thing less now than I did before.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/revealed-preference.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Republican Party and the National Debt</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/the-republican-party-and-the-national-debt.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/the-republican-party-and-the-national-debt.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2013 12:59:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Mike Kimel]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/the-republican-party-and-the-national-debt.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Mike Kimel from Angry Bear 2007 described another aspect to be kept in mind during the current austerity policy debates. The Republican Party and the National Debt Posted by cactus &#124; 12/04/2007 Public Agenda is asking bloggers to contribute to a discussion on the National Debt they call Facing Up. These are my thoughts on [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a hef="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2007/12/republican-party-and-national-debt.html" href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/" target="_blank">Mike Kimel</a> from Angry Bear 2007 described another aspect to be kept in mind during the current austerity policy debates. </p>
<p><a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2007/12/republican-party-and-national-debt.html">The Republican Party and the National Debt</a></p>
<p>Posted by <strong>cactus</strong> | 12/04/2007 </p>
<p><a href="http://publicagenda.org/">Public Agenda</a> is asking bloggers to contribute to a discussion on <a href="http://www.facingup.org/">the National Debt they call Facing Up</a>. These are my thoughts on the subject&#8230;<br />    <br />The White House’s Office of Management and Budget <a href="http://www.whitehouse.gov/omb/budget/fy2008/hist.html">Table 7.1</a> shows data on the National Debt going back to 1940. There’s gross debt, debt held by the public, debt held by Federal Government Accounts, and debt held by the Federal Reserve. And the data is provided in dollars and as a percentage of GDP. The size of the debt looks different depending on which measure one chooses.<br />    <br />So what is the most useful way to look at the size of debt? Well, on the one hand, you don’t want to count money owed from one branch of the Federal government to another, so debt held by the public makes more sense than gross debt. Furthermore, if the average person borrowed $1 million, they’d have some trouble paying it back, whereas Bill Gates would have no such issues. Therefore, debt as a percentage of income makes more sense than debt in dollars.<br />  <br /><a name="more"></a>   <br />With all that said, here’s what Debt held by the Public as a percentage of GDP looks like, going back to 1940:    <br /><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_yBU2IH33oeM/R1VTl704KiI/AAAAAAAAA5I/foHks_jZkac/s1600-h/cactus+on+debt,+figure+1,+debt+as+a+percentage+of+GDP,+line+graph.jpg"><img alt="" border="0" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_yBU2IH33oeM/R1VTl704KiI/AAAAAAAAA5I/foHks_jZkac/s320/cactus+on+debt,+figure+1,+debt+as+a+percentage+of+GDP,+line+graph.jpg"></a>    </p>
<p> The graph indicates that debt exploded with the start of World War 2 – by 1946, the debt, at 109% of GDP, was almost two and a half times greater than it was in 1940. Presumably, a country fighting for its collective life could be excused in taking such a financial gamble.<br />     <br />After World War 2, the debt declined until 1974, bottoming out at just under 24% of GDP. Since then, its generally risen… quickly in some years, not so quickly in others. What’s the cause of this? No doubt there are many, but one cause is obvious, when you play with the data a wee bit. The graph below shows the Debt held by the Public as a percentage of GDP in the last full year of each Presidential administration, color coded by Political Party, following the end of World War 2:<br />    <br /><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_yBU2IH33oeM/R1VTcr04KhI/AAAAAAAAA5A/eiYG-8gNNVY/s1600-h/cactus+on+debt,+figure+2,+debt+as+a+percentage+of+GDP,+bar+graph.jpg"><img alt="" border="0" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_yBU2IH33oeM/R1VTcr04KhI/AAAAAAAAA5A/eiYG-8gNNVY/s320/cactus+on+debt,+figure+2,+debt+as+a+percentage+of+GDP,+bar+graph.jpg"></a>    </p>
<p> And here is a slightly different look – the next graph shows the annualized percentage change in the Debt held by the Public as a percentage of GDP from the end of one administration to the end of the next:<br />    <br /><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_yBU2IH33oeM/R1VTKr04KgI/AAAAAAAAA44/D5-YoS6fUfQ/s1600-h/cactus+on+debt,+figure+3,+annualized+change+in+debt+as+a+percentage+of+GDP,+bar+graph.jpg"><img alt="" border="0" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_yBU2IH33oeM/R1VTKr04KgI/AAAAAAAAA44/D5-YoS6fUfQ/s320/cactus+on+debt,+figure+3,+annualized+change+in+debt+as+a+percentage+of+GDP,+bar+graph.jpg"></a>    <br />Note… a negative decrease in the debt is, obviously, an increase in the debt.    </p>
<p> The last five Democratic Presidents, Clinton, Carter, LBJ, JFK, and Truman all reduced the debt, and one has to go back sixty years to find a Democratic President who, facing the Great Depression and World War 2, allowed the debt to increase. On the other hand, the last four Republican Presidents, GW Bush, GHW Bush, Reagan, and Ford all oversaw an increase in the country’s indebtedness. It has been more than thirty years since a Republican President left office (albeit in a scandal) having reduced the National Debt. In the last few decades, somewhere along the way, the Republican Party has become the Party of fiscal irresponsibility.<br />    <br />It doesn’t have to be that way. Lord knows I’m no Republican, and it seems to me that many of what currently seem to be core Republican policies appear almost designed to increase the debt. Even so, there’s still something in the Republican DNA that believes fiscal responsibility is a good thing. All else being equal, Republican voters appear to prefer a lower debt over a higher one, and they seem to believe (even if that belief is mistaken) that they are more likely to get it from Republican politicians. President Bush himself, in the <a href="http://www.whitehouse.gov/news/usbudget/blueprint/bud01.html">Economic Blueprint for his Presidency</a>, promised to retire “an historic $2 trillion in debt over… 10 years.” His debt-fighting plan was so ambitious that he expected annual surpluses to “outstrip the amount of maturing debt starting in 2007.”<br />    <br />But as he said elsewhere in his <a href="http://www.whitehouse.gov/news/usbudget/blueprint/bud01.html">Economic Blueprint</a>, <br />
<blockquote>Government must be results-oriented—guided not by process, but by performance. There comes a time when programs must be judged by how well they achieve their purpose. Where we find success, we should reward it, and make it the standard. Government action that fails in its purpose must be reformed or ended.</p></blockquote>
<p>Its time to apply that standard to the policies that Republican politicians promise us will reduce the debt.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/the-republican-party-and-the-national-debt.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Reminder</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/a-reminder.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/a-reminder.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2013 11:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Mike Kimel]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/a-reminder.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Mike Kimel A Reminder My wife was talking to a friend of hers who gets paid by the school district her son attends to bring the boy to school because, given where they live, it would be inconvenient to provide bus service to where they live. We worked out the numbers, and my best [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Mike Kimel</p>
<p>A Reminder</p>
<p>My wife was talking to a friend of hers who gets paid by the school district her son attends to bring the boy to school because, given where they live, it would be inconvenient to provide bus service to where they live. We worked out the numbers, and my best guess is that she&#8217;s paid about the average cost of of transporting a pupil to school. The family isn&#8217;t poor and the child isn&#8217;t disabled. I&#8217;m all in favor of giving everyone a fair chance in life, but let this be a reminder &#8211; sometimes when the far right is railing against something, they have a point.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/a-reminder.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>What it Takes to Get a Mortgage These Days</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/what-it-takes-to-get-a-mortgage-these-days.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/what-it-takes-to-get-a-mortgage-these-days.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 27 Feb 2013 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Mike Kimel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mortgages]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/what-it-takes-to-get-a-mortgage-these-days.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Mike Kimel What it Takes to Get a Mortgage These Days About six months ago I got a job that required relocation. To make a long story short, we just purchased a new home. As part of the process, the lenders required a lot of paperwork. Not a surprise. But some of the paperwork [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Mike Kimel</p>
<p>What it Takes to Get a Mortgage These Days</p>
<p>About six months ago I got a job that required relocation.  To make a long story short, we just purchased a new home.  As part of the process, the lenders required a lot of paperwork.  Not a surprise. But some of the paperwork was surprising.  For example, they wanted a signed letter explaining a deposit in the amount of 0.05%  of the amount of the loan, made prior to the sellers and ourselves agreeing to the sale of the house.  One half of one percent.  I can understand getting suspicious if we made an unexplained deposit equal to, say,<br />ten percent or so of the amount of the loan, but 5% of 1% of the loan?<br />And it wasn&#8217;t the only senseless thing we had to provide.</p>
<p>I worry about this means &#8211; it means the lenders probably aren&#8217;t concerned about important things that they should be concerned about. That didn&#8217;t work out so well the last time.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/what-it-takes-to-get-a-mortgage-these-days.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Markets Need Regulators &#8211; Food Edition</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/markets-need-regulators-food-edition.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/markets-need-regulators-food-edition.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 23 Feb 2013 13:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[market]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mike Kimel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[regulators]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/markets-need-regulators-food-edition.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Mike Kimel Markets Need Regulators &#8211; Food Edition Back in college, I had a chat with one of my more libertarian economics professors about the need for regulation. He thought regulation was completely un-necessary. &#8220;But what about mislabeled food?&#8221; I asked, &#8220;How do we even know that what is labeled on the side of [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Mike Kimel</p>
<p>Markets Need Regulators &#8211; Food Edition</p>
<p>Back in college, I had a chat with one of my more libertarian economics professors about the need for regulation.  He thought regulation was completely un-necessary.</p>
<p>&#8220;But what about mislabeled food?&#8221; I asked, &#8220;How do we even know that what is labeled on the side of the box or the can is what is inside?&#8221;</p>
<p>His reply was one I&#8217;ve heard, in one variation or another, many times since, &#8220;A company that sells customers something than they ordered will quickly go out of business.&#8221;</p>
<p>I&#8217;ve known it was BS every time I heard that, but it is interesting and unfortunate to see validation lately.</p>
<p>In the US, we have <a href="http://articles.chicagotribune.com/2013-02-21/news/ct-met-phony-fish-20130221_1_seafood-fraud-fish-fraud-grouper-samples">mislabeledfish</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>Chicago diners who think they are eating red snapper may actually be munching on goldbanded jobfish.</p>
<p>Those who order Alaskan cod may really be tucking into a threadfin slickhead. And fans of yellowtail could just be getting a fish tale.</p>
<p>These are some of the findings of a Chicago fish fraud investigation to be released Thursday by conservancy group Oceana.</p>
<p>After its troubling seafood fraud investigations in East and West Coast cities over the last two years, the group expanded its testing to other cities, including Chicago. Thirty of 93 fish samples taken from Chicago restaurants, retail chains and sushi bars were mislabeled, mirroring percentages found in other cities.</p>
<p>Eight of nine Chicago red snapper samples tested by Oceana turned out to be different fish, the report said. And none of the three<br />yellowtail samples tested was actually yellowtail. Single samples sold as corvina, jack, mackerel and even perch did not match those descriptions, according to Oceana&#8217;s DNA tests.</p>
<p>The ocean conservancy organization does not list the names of the restaurants or stores where it bought the fish because &#8220;we didn&#8217;t know where, along the supply chain, the mislabeling first occurred,&#8221; said Beth Lowell Oceana&#8217;s seafood fraud campaign director.&#8221;So we didn&#8217;t want to call out businesses that may not have known their fish was mislabeled.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>This comes in the heel of the horsemeat (and occasionally donkey meat) sold as beef scandal in Europe.</p>
<p>What is interesting is that a) these behaviors have been going on for a long time and b) they were either spotted by a shrunken regulator (in Europe) or a non-profit (in the US).  The market&#8217;s incentives didn&#8217;t stop any of the players involved.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Now, one could respond that &#8220;this didn&#8217;t actually harm anyone&#8217;s health.&#8221;  That may be true, but it is fraud. Lack of damage isn&#8217;t true of all cases.  We&#8217;ve all read about cases where adulterated food products did kill, where mechanical components that didn&#8217;t meet stated standards caused deadly accidents, or pharmaceuticals that weren&#8217;t as stated caused tremendous harm.  Different fields have different stories.  Decades ago, I knew people who worked with blood banks, buying and selling blood products for use in medical and pharmaceutical tests and manufacturing.  Apparently it wasn&#8217;t uncommon for low quality, poorly tested, and badly identified blood from East Germany to be surreptitiously mislabeled as its high quality, tested-to-the-nines West German equivalent, and with a wink and a nod, enter the bloodstream so to speak.  Who knows how many people were harmed by that?  More familiar to most Americans these days is the mislabeling of financial products &#8211; there were an awful lot of risky financial products mislabeled as being AAA safe.</p>
<p>For commerce to work, confidence in the products being sold needs to exist.  But the marketplace by itself can&#8217;t provide that &#8211; the financial incentive apparently is just a bit too strong for some of the players.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/markets-need-regulators-food-edition.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Reproduction, Income, and the Future</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/reproduction-income-and-the-future.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/reproduction-income-and-the-future.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 18 Feb 2013 00:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[families]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mike Kimel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[reproduction]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/reproduction-income-and-the-future.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Mike Kimel Reproduction, Income, and the Future A comment on a post at EconLog, a very libertarian website&#8230; I can say that in my lifetime, I have not earned enough money for me to have kids. I&#8217;m 36. I know some have had kids on my income or less but it certainly is not [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Mike Kimel</p>
<p>Reproduction, Income, and the Future</p>
<p>A <a href="http://econlog.econlib.org/archives/2013/02/why_have_kids_m.html#comments">comment on a post at EconLog</a>, a very libertarian website&#8230;<br />
<blockquote>I can say that in my lifetime, I have not earned enough money for me to have kids. I&#8217;m 36. I know some have had kids on my income or less but it certainly is not enough money for me. I can&#8217;t imagine how it would have been if I had kids.</p></blockquote>
<p>And this <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/02/14/the-kids-are-alright/?comments#permid=128">comment on a post by Paul Krugman, on the liberal side of the spectrum</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>I personally have never had the stability in my life where I thought it was okay for me to go off and spawn a family the way my parents did beginning in 1953. My father worked hard, and loved to work, had good employment and good pay, without a college degree. </p>
<p>Where as, he sent me to private schools, I got honor roll grades, bachelors degree, doctorate degree, I re-engineered manufacturing systems at some of America&#8217;s largest companies, but still I never felt secure in my employment, nor was I. </p>
<p>I am unemployed now, as I was in 2010, as I was in 2006, as I was in 1991, as I was for a time in 1984, 1983 and 1982 &#8211; when I graduated.</p>
<p>The current generation is facing a geometrically greater challenge than I did. So I can see why traditional family life is in decline. </p></blockquote>
<p>Interesting how the problem is the framed the same way at different ends of the political spectrum.  I note that this framing also fits my life &#8211; my wife and I got married late and had one child (one and done) very late.  Economic worries were a big part of the decision making process.  On paper, my wife and I are doing relatively well financially, but we are extremely aware that a job loss &#8211; something that has become extremely common in recent years &#8211; or one financial mis-step could mean the difference between whether our son will have far greater opportunity in life than either my wife or I did growing up, or far less opportunity.  There doesn&#8217;t seem to be much in-between.   In talking with my parents, they also seem to believe outcomes are more stark for families today.  Many of my friends tell me the same thing.  And when I talk to people ten or twenty years younger than I, in general, their costs seem to be higher than those I faced, and the potential opportunities fewer.</p>
<p>The result is that most people I know within ten years of my age have between zero and two kids.   While there are exceptions, in general, people I can name with three or more kids either are in the top 2% or so, income-wise (and most of them are in finance or have inherited wealth or both), or are well below the median.  (Note &#8211;  I went looking for data on number of children by income level in the US but couldn&#8217;t find any.)  I wonder if that&#8217;s a portent of things to come, and what it implies for the stability of society going forward.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/reproduction-income-and-the-future.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Paul Krugman, Angry Bear, and Jazzbumpa</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/paul-krugman-angry-bear-and-jazzbumpa.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/paul-krugman-angry-bear-and-jazzbumpa.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Feb 2013 15:54:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Beverly Mann]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bruce Webb]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jazzbumpa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mike Kimel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NYT]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Krugman]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/paul-krugman-angry-bear-and-jazzbumpa.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Update: Noahpinion takes on the same in How to win arguments by pretending to be stupid.  The comments section offers other points of view. Ron T. aka Jazzbumpa received an unusual thank you from Paul Krugman for this post on a Mish Shedlock post about debating PK. Krugman recommended Beverly Mann  on January 15th this year [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Update: <a href="http://noahpinionblog.blogspot.com/2013/02/how-to-win-arguments-by-pretending-to.html" target="_blank">Noahpinion</a> takes on the same in <i>How to win arguments by pretending to be stupid.  </i>The comments section offers other points of view.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/02/how-to-debae-paul-krugman.html">Ron T. aka Jazzbumpa</a> received an unusual thank you from Paul Krugman for this post on a Mish Shedlock post about debating PK.</p>
<p>Krugman recommended <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/01/15/short-takes-2" target="_blank">Beverly Mann</a>  on January 15th this year as part of a  recommended reading post.  </p>
<p>Other <i>Angry Bear</i> contributors gaining mention and recommendation by name in the recent past that immediately come to mind are <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/04/what-is-question-responding-to-paul.html" target="_blank">Mike Kimel</a> and <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/01/15/early-social-security-projections/" target="_blank">Bruce Webb</a>.</p>
<p><img alt="" src="https://mail.google.com/mail/u/0/images/cleardot.gif"><a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/02/03/despicable-me/">Despicable Me &#8211; Paul Krugman</a></p>
<blockquote><p>Funny: <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/02/how-to-debae-paul-krugman.html?utm_source=feedburner&#038;utm_medium=feed&#038;utm_campaign=Feed%3A+blogspot%2FHzoh+%28Angry+Bear%29">Angry Bear</a> finds some of the usual suspects explaining <a href="http://globaleconomicanalysis.blogspot.com/2013/01/how-to-debate-paul-krugman-ask.html">How to Debate Paul Krugman</a>, and the answer appears to be this: invent a straw man who bears no resemblance at all to the economist/columnist of the same name, and ridicule that imaginary person. I have to say, never in my wildest dreams did I imagine that I could play the role of History’s Greatest Monster to so many people. Thank you for the honor!</p>
<p>Aside from the silliness of the exercise, this little exchange is another illustration of a point I’ve noticed before: the way hard-right commentators assume that the other side must be <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/10/12/i-am-not-your-mirror-image/">their mirror image</a>. They insist that no government intervention is ever justified; so liberals must support any and all government interventions. They want smaller government, as a principle; liberals must want bigger government, never mind what for. They believe that deficits and printing money are always evil; liberals must be for deficits and money-printing under all circumstances.</p>
<p>An hour spent browsing this blog would quickly refute all of this, together with the bizarre charge that I never look at evidence; you may not agree with my conclusions, but I sure do post a lot of numbers. But obviously looking at what I actually write would just be too painful.</p>
<p>Anyway, thanks guys, you made my day.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/paul-krugman-angry-bear-and-jazzbumpa.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>If Guns are Cheap, Criminals Will Have Guns</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/if-guns-are-cheap-criminals-will-have-guns.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/if-guns-are-cheap-criminals-will-have-guns.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2013 03:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[guns]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mike Kimel]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/if-guns-are-cheap-criminals-will-have-guns.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Mike Kimel If Guns are Cheap, Criminals Will Have Guns If guns are outlawed, only outlaws will have guns. We&#8217;ve all heard that many times. But is it true? Well, it is certainly a tautology. But there is another way to ensure that outlaws have guns. Namely, keep them cheap. From the 2009 Firearms Used [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Mike Kimel</p>
<p>If Guns are Cheap, Criminals Will Have Guns</p>
<p>If guns are outlawed, only outlaws will have guns.  We&#8217;ve all heard that many times.  But is it true?  Well, it is certainly a tautology. But there is another way to ensure that outlaws have guns.  Namely, keep them cheap.</p>
<p>From the <a href="http://oag.ca.gov/sites/all/files/pdfs/publications/Firearms_Report_09.pdf">2009 Firearms Used in the Commission of Crimes</a> focusing specifically on guns used in the commission of crimes in rural parts of California:</p>
<blockquote><p>Of the 147 firearms examined, there were 120 (81.6<br />percent) handguns, 13 (8.8 percent) rifles, 11 (7.5 percent) shotguns,<br />and 3 (2 percent) machine guns. </p></blockquote>
<p>The <a href="http://oag.ca.gov/sites/all/files/pdfs/publications/Firearms_Report_10.pdf">2010</a> <a href="http://oag.ca.gov/sites/all/files/pdfs/publications/Firearms_Report_10.pdf">version of the same report</a> paints a similar picture:</p>
<blockquote><p>Of the 175 firearms reported, there were 158 (90.3 percent) handguns, 12 (6.9 percent) rifles, 4 (2.3 percent) shotguns, and 1 (0.6 percent) full-auto firearm.</p></blockquote>
<p>The reason handguns are more often used in the commission of a crime than other types of weapons is not because the typical criminal doesn&#8217;t think it would be tres cool to use a belt fed machine gun or a shoulder launched missile.  Its because those types of weapons are very, very hard to come by.  With some digging, you can get your hands on a belt fed machine gun, but you are very unlikely to do it for less than $10K for a cheapo model.   Instead, what often happens is that armed criminals are most often armed with what one can best be described as lousy guns.  Don&#8217;t believe me?  <a href="http://www.tonyrogers.com/news/top_10_crime_guns.htm">Here</a> is a post from someone who clearly cannot be described as pro-gun control, commenting on the list of top ten guns used in crimes according to the ATF.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Descriptions include:</p>
<blockquote><p>An absolute piece of crap that sells for less than $120 retail. No real shooter would even warrant this &#8220;gun&#8221; as a legitimate target to even shoot at.</p></blockquote>
<p>Here&#8217;s another:</p>
<blockquote><p>Another piece of shit that sells for less than $110 retail, and is worth less than the pipsqueak ammunition you can try to feed it.</p></blockquote>
<p>And another:</p>
<blockquote><p>The cheapest 12-guage on the market, designed for people who cannot afford a real shotgun. Not even close to being considered a &#8220;fighting&#8221; shotgun. No offense to Mossberg, but there is a reason that  these Wal-Mart grade firepoles are given away at Ducks Unlimited as door prizes. Most do (and should) end up being traded up at gun shops for real shotguns.</p></blockquote>
<p>Some of the other descriptions are even more creative.  My favorite is number ten on the list:</p>
<blockquote><p>This one takes the cake as the &#8220;most prone to never fire, ever&#8221; firearm that was ever produced. Apparently they had a street price of $60 in Miami at one point, which would have been better spent on a wristrocket or a billyclub if you planned to actually use one in a legitimate crime. They eventually had to fight lawsuits from prosecutors and criminals at the same time because of their inherent defectiveness.</p></blockquote>
<p>To quote that post further:</p>
<blockquote><p>Though most teenage gangbangers wouldn&#8217;t be caught dead with a Smith and Wesson .38 revolver, an old fashioned six shooter, it nonetheless claims the lead on the top ten list. That&#8217;s because there are literally millions in existence; Smith and Wesson introduced the .38 in 1899, and since then, models have proliferated, transforming the name &#8220;Smith and Wesson .38&#8221; into a generic label for a particular style of gun, even clones that aren&#8217;t made by Smith and Wesson. Similarly, the Smith and Wesson .357 revolver, which was introduced in 1935, and the venerable Mossberg shotgun made the list based on the sheer volume in circulation.</p>
<p>But street criminals are interested almost exclusively in semiautomatics, preferring their superior firepower. (Semiautomatics hold at least seven and often as many as ten or twelve rounds of ammunition. &#8211;Or 18 if you can spend the extra dinero made from a 7-11 heist on a Beretta)</p>
<p>Gun traffickers like to peddle cheap semiautomatics to teenagers because they can tack on a hefty mark-up (of ten bucks) and still offer a weapon that costs less than an upscale gun like a Ruger or Smith and Wesson semiautomatic. That&#8217;s why inexpensive semiautomatics dominate the top ten list. As it happens, many of the companies on that list have links to George Jennings, founder of the now-defunct Raven Arms and his clan. Jennings&#8217; son Bruce founded Bryco in 1992. According to the ATF, Jennings&#8217; son-in-law Jim Davis founded Davis Industries, and Lorcin Engineering was launched by Jim Waldorf, Bruce Jennings&#8217; high school friend. These companies and several others also linked to Jennings are known in the trade as the &#8220;ring of fire.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>The point is, criminals use the guns they do because they&#8217;re available, and the guns that are available are usually available because they&#8217;re cheap.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/if-guns-are-cheap-criminals-will-have-guns.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Question About Apple</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/a-question-about-apple.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/a-question-about-apple.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 23 Jan 2013 13:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Apple]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mike Kimel]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/a-question-about-apple.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Mike Kimel A Question About Apple My wife has been an Apple user for a long time. I on the other hand have tended to avoid purchasing Apple products for myself &#8211; I just cannot get around the concept of a single button on a mouse, nor why I should be interested in buying [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Mike Kimel</p>
<p>A Question About Apple</p>
<p>My wife has been an Apple user for a long time. I on the other hand have tended to avoid purchasing Apple products for myself &#8211; I just cannot get around the concept of a single button on a mouse, nor why I should be interested in buying a product whose manufacturer apparently makes conscious decisions to remove features based on someone&#8217;s aesthetic sense rather than usability. That said, I did notice that Apple products had a tendency to be reliable, though that reliability certainly came at a price.</p>
<p>Recently, my wife convinced to ditch my Droid for an i-Phone so we could use facetime. Perhaps because of that, I&#8217;ve become overly sensitive to issues involving Apple products as of late. My mom has a keyboard for her iPad which seems to have stopped working. (I was the one who originally recommended she buy an iPad as I figured it would be easy enough for someone as technologically unsavvy as her to use easily.) The only way I can get my iPhone to admit I have a voice-mail is to power it off completely and then turn it on again. It&#8217;s been that way from day one &#8211; at first I chalked it up to yet another thing about the phone, but my wife told me it wasn&#8217;t supposed to behave that way. And I notice my wife has been complaining about her Mac &#8211; something that didn&#8217;t happen except rarely with its umpteen predecessors. </p>
<p>Is this just something from my immediate circle (i.e., random anecdotes) or are the company&#8217;s products becoming less reliable? Anyone else notice anything?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/a-question-about-apple.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
