<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>FEMA &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The Public Learns Disaster Relief Was Etched Out of the Sketch. Uh-Oh.</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/the-public-learns-disaster-relief-was-etched-out-of-the-sketch-uh-oh.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/the-public-learns-disaster-relief-was-etched-out-of-the-sketch-uh-oh.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 29 Oct 2012 20:46:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Bill Keller]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[disaster relief]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Etch-A-Sketch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[FEMA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Matthew Yglesias]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New York Times]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/the-public-learns-disaster-relief-was-etched-out-of-the-sketch-uh-oh.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[MITT ROMNEY: &#8220;Every time you have an occasion to take something from the federal government and send it back to the states, that&#8217;s the right direction. And if you can go even further, and send it back to the private sector, that&#8217;s even better. Instead of thinking, in the federal budget, what we should cut, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>MITT ROMNEY: &#8220;Every time you have an occasion to take something from the federal government and send it back to the states, that&#8217;s the right direction. And if you can go even further, and send it back to the private sector, that&#8217;s even better. Instead of thinking, in the federal budget, what we should cut, we should ask the opposite question, what should we keep?&#8221;
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>DEBATE MODERATOR JOHN KING: Including disaster relief, though?&#8221;
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>ROMNEY: We cannot &#8212; we cannot afford to do those things without jeopardizing the future for our kids. It is simply immoral, in my view, for us to continue to rack up larger and larger debts and pass them on to our kids, knowing full well that we&#8217;ll all be dead and gone before it&#8217;s paid off. It makes no sense at all.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212; <i>Republican primary campaign debate last year
</p>
<p></i></div>
<div></div>
<div>Slate’s Matthew Yglesias points to that today <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/moneybox/2012/10/29/romney_s_fema_cuts.html">andcomments</a>:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>More prosaically, though the Romney campaign was understandably <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/10/28/mitt-romney-fema_n_2036198.html" target="_blank">circumspect over the weekend about his spending plans</a> the fact is that his overall budget requires sharp cuts in everything. The central issue is that Romney wants to cap government spending at 20 percent of GDP while boosting military spending to 4 percent of GDP and leaving Social Security harmless. That <a href="http://www.cbpp.org/cms/?fa=view&#038;id=3658" target="_blank">means a 34 percent across-the-board cut in other programs</a> according to the Center on Budget and Policy Priorities. Unless, that is, Medicare is also exempted from the cuts in which case you&#8217;d need a 53 percent cut. …
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>If a storm damages basic physical infrastructure (power lines, bridges) and imperils human life it would be the height of penny-wise, pound-foolish thinking to suppose that the afflicted area should wait months or years to repair the damage. Ultimately, anyplace is going to go back to robust wealth creation faster if basic stuff gets fixed up faster. But that requires financing by an entity capable of rapidly financing expensive projects—i.e., the federal government. Left to its own devices a storm-ravaged Delaware or Louisiana is going to be squeezed between balanced budget rules and falling sales tax receipts and be forced into an increasing state of dilapidation.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>How about a storm-ravaged <i>Florida</i>?  According to current polls, slightly more than half of Florida voters want their state to take over disaster relief, at least until arrangements can be made for the private sector to take it over.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And, about that question Romney asked: What should we KEEP?  Well, in addition to the Bush tax cuts for the wealthy and defense spending for private contractors, what DOES Romney think we should keep?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>We cannot – we cannot afford to do things like disaster relief without jeopardizing the future of our kids.  We CAN, though, afford to give massive additional tax cuts to the wealthy, and huge additional contracts to Republican defense contractors, without jeopardizing the future of our kids.  Right?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>What’s truly unconscionable is that it’s taking Hurricane Sandy to educate the public about the plans Romney and Ryan have stated so clearly.  I’ve been utterly unable to understand why the Obama campaign hasn’t been running video clips of Romney’s primary-campaign statements as the foundation of their ads.  I’ve thought all along that this is all Obama would need to do in order to win.  I think Sandy will prove me right.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And, here’s a shout-out to New York Time columnist Bill Keller for <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/10/29/opinion/keller-the-no-agenda-myth.html?_r=0">exposing for the absurd myth that it is</a> the punditry’s “in” refrain that we don’t know what either of the two candidates would use the office to do in the next four years, because, well, neither has specified sufficiently.  As Keller says, actually <i>both</i> have specified sufficiently. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And Romney’s <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/10/did-romney-begin-to-reverse-etch-sketch.html">already begun to reverse-sketch his etchings</a>.  Suffice it to say that he’s not spent the last week promising “BIG CHANGE” because he plans to etch out of his sketch all those primary-campaign promises. 
</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/the-public-learns-disaster-relief-was-etched-out-of-the-sketch-uh-oh.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Disaster Aid Disaster Averted, barely</title>
		<link>./../../2011/09/disaster-aid-disaster-averted-barely.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/09/disaster-aid-disaster-averted-barely.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2011 18:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2012 Presidential elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[budget deficits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diasaster relief]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[FEMA]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/09/disaster-aid-disaster-averted-barely.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[By Linda Beale Disaster Aid Disaster Averted, barely. Once again, Republicans intent on obstructing the normal operation of the federal government unless they can extract cuts to programs they don&#8217;t like (in the name of deficit reduction) applied the combination of House recalcitrance and Senate anti-majoritarian filibuster to threaten a government shutdown and siderail needed [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By <strong>Linda Beale</strong></p>
<p><a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2011/09/disaster-aid-disaster-averted-barely.html" target="_BLANK">Disaster Aid Disaster Averted, barely</a>.</p>
<p>Once again, Republicans intent on obstructing the normal operation of the federal government unless they can extract cuts to programs they don&#8217;t like (in the name of deficit reduction) applied the combination of House recalcitrance and Senate anti-majoritarian filibuster to threaten a government shutdown and siderail needed funding for emergency assistance to ordinary Americans until they could get at least some of their objectives. A compromise that will get money to FEMA and keep the government funded for a spell has been reached.</p>
<p>(AP video at <em>ataxingmatter</em>, see link&#8230;I am still mostly missing my internet connections)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/09/disaster-aid-disaster-averted-barely.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Federal emergency Aid and no borrowing of funds for relief efforts</title>
		<link>./../../2011/08/federal-emergency-aid-and-no-borrowing-of-funds-for-relief-efforts.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/08/federal-emergency-aid-and-no-borrowing-of-funds-for-relief-efforts.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2011 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[debt ceiling]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Eric Cantor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[federal spending]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[FEMA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[size of government]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/08/federal-emergency-aid-and-no-borrowing-of-funds-for-relief-efforts.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[If these words translate to actions in the Congress on emergency aid, I believe it is a significant departure from past policies. And Virginia, Cantor&#8217;s home state, is predicted to be impacted. We will know soon enough if political capital is spent on this idea. A spokesperson for House Majority Leader Eric Cantor (R-VA) said [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-VKFTRMd5Gw8/TlfFP0Va4JI/AAAAAAAAAr8/GeVXMd42Rt4/s1600/irene.jpg"><img src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-VKFTRMd5Gw8/TlfFP0Va4JI/AAAAAAAAAr8/GeVXMd42Rt4/s200/irene.jpg" border="0" alt=""></a><br />
<br />If these words translate to actions in the Congress on emergency aid, I believe it is a significant departure from past policies.  And Virginia, Cantor&#8217;s home state, is predicted to be impacted.  We will know soon enough if political capital is spent on this idea.<br />
<br />
<blockquote>A spokesperson for House Majority Leader Eric Cantor (R-VA) said that if there is any damage caused by Hurricane Irene requiring federal disaster funding, the money would have to be balanced out by spending cuts elsewhere in government. </p>
<p>&#8220;We aren&#8217;t going to speculate on damage before it happens, period,&#8221; his spokesperson Laena Fallon told TalkingPointsMemo. &#8220;But, as you know, Eric has consistently said that additional funds for federal disaster relief ought to be offset with spending cuts.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>Read more at <a target="_blank" href="http://www.businessinsider.com/eric-cantor-hurricane-disaster-relief-will-have-to-be-offset-by-spending-cuts-2011-8#ixzz1W9R9w4rN">Business insider</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/08/federal-emergency-aid-and-no-borrowing-of-funds-for-relief-efforts.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
