<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>tax plans &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>GOP candidates&#8217; policies would raise federal debt by whopping trillions</title>
		<link>./../../2012/02/gop-candidates-policies-would-raise-federal-debt-by-whopping-trillions.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/02/gop-candidates-policies-would-raise-federal-debt-by-whopping-trillions.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2012 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2012 Presidential elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linda Beale (Tax law)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax plans]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/02/gop-candidates-policies-would-raise-federal-debt-by-whopping-trillions.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Beale GOP candidates&#8217; policies would raise federal debt by whopping trillions The GOP likes to pretend to take the high road, proclaiming itself to be against increasing the federal debt, running big deficits, or otherwise not running our government like a person runs their household. Pundits on the right tend to look at [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Linda Beale  </p>
<p><a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2012/02/gop-candidates-increase-debt-across-the-board.html">GOP candidates&#8217; policies would raise federal debt by whopping trillions</a> </p>
<p>The GOP likes to pretend to take the high road, proclaiming itself to be against increasing the federal debt, running big deficits, or otherwise not running our government like a person runs their household. Pundits on the right tend to look at Greece and warn&#8211;watch out, America, you&#8217;re gonna be there next.</p>
<p>Of course, there&#8217;s a big difference in a family on a limited budget and the federal government. The government can print money to pay its bills; when people do that, it&#8217;s called counterfeiting. The amount of quantitative easing is limited, though where the limits are difficult to establish with any certainty&#8211;at some point. And there&#8217;s a big difference between the US and Greece. Unlike Greece, we have a sovereign money supply (Greece is tied to the European Union, unless it decides to break away and suffer the consequences). And unlike Greece, though our debt is high, it is still only about 70% of GDP. And lucky for us, the foreign nations who buy our debt need somewhere to put all those dollars that they&#8217;ve acquired through their cheap exports to us.</p>
<p>There&#8217;s another big difference between the US and Greece. We have a long history of a stable and workable tax system&#8211;in spite of the frequent tinkering that Congress has done over the years. We have at times had politicians in office who recognize their responsibilities to the system and enact new tax laws, in spite of the intense lobbying by Big Business and wealthy interests to try to derail all tax increases. We can and should increase taxes now, especially on those most able to pay.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />So is that what the GOP candidates are proposing, after all their whining about how Democrats are fiscally irresponsible and blaming Obama for increasing our debt load? Nope, not at all. Except for Ron Paul, who wants to harshly cut every government activity, the rest of the GOP candidates have enormous tax cuts and middling spending cuts (mostly to programs that benefit ordinary Americans) and would add to the deficit by trillions of dollars, according to the Committee for a Responsible Federal Budget. See <a href="http://crfb.org/document/primary-numbers-gop-candidates-and-national-debt">Primary Numbers: The GOP Canddiates and the National Debt </a>(Feb. 24, 2012). Gingrich would have the biggest increase&#8211;about $7 trillion in new debt over a two-term presidency. Santorum would increase the debt by about $4.5 trillion, and Romney would increase it by about $2.6 trillion (unless he really comes up with some offsets as promised). All three of them are likely depending on the laughable Laffer Curve idea to help them achieve their promises&#8211;the assumption that their tax cuts for the wealthy would result in more growth and therefore more tax revenues.</p>
<p>crossposted with <a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/" title="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/">ataxingmatter</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/02/gop-candidates-policies-would-raise-federal-debt-by-whopping-trillions.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Romney&#8217;s Tax Plan Helps the 1%, Hurts the Bottom 40%</title>
		<link>./../../2012/01/romneys-tax-plan-helps-the-1-hurts-the-bottom-40.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/01/romneys-tax-plan-helps-the-1-hurts-the-bottom-40.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2012 14:46:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2012 Presidential elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linda Beale (Tax law)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax plans]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/01/romneys-tax-plan-helps-the-1-hurts-the-bottom-40.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Beale Romney&#8217;s Tax Plan Helps the 1%, Hurts the Bottom 40% In spite of having to suffer some closer view of his Bain Capital time&#8211;during which the self-proclaimed &#8220;job creator&#8221; businessman did a lot of job cutting and destruction of going concerns so that his investors could make more money, Romney continues on [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Linda Beale</p>
<p>Romney&#8217;s Tax Plan Helps the 1%, Hurts the Bottom 40%</p>
<p>In spite of having to suffer some closer view of his Bain Capital time&#8211;during which the self-proclaimed &#8220;job creator&#8221; businessman did a lot of job cutting and destruction of going concerns so that his investors could make more money, Romney continues on his well-financed cruise to the GOP nomination.</p>
<p>It&#8217;s perhaps an appropriate time to bring out the Urban Institute/Tax Policy Center&#8217;s analysis of the Romney 59-point tax plan.  They have produced a <a href="http://www.taxpolicycenter.org/numbers/displayatab.cfm?Docid=3257" target="_blank">table</a> (T12-0004) showing &#8220;Mitt Romney&#8217;s Tax Plan Baseline: Current Policy Distribution of Federal Tax Change by Cash Income Percentile, 2015.&#8221;  The table looks at individual and corporate income, payroll (Medicare and Social Security) and estate taxes to determine the change in the total federal taxes for the various quintiles under Romney.</p>
<p>Who would have federal tax increases under Romney? Not the rich who have captured more and more of the income over the last decades.  Treating corporate shareholders as the payers of the corporate income tax, the table shows that the top one percent would get an average federal tax cut of $86,535 under Romney&#8217;s plan, while the top one-tenth of one percent would get an average tax cut of $432,940.   </p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>But guess what, the bottom two quintiles&#8211;made up of the poorest Americans who are struggling to make ends meet and who can be pushed off kilter by a single illness or other unexpected expenditure&#8211;will be the ONLY ones in the distribution who will pay more federal taxes under Romney&#8217;s plan than under the current policy baseline.  About 18% in that lowest quintile will pay almost a thousand more in taxes.  About 13% in the lowest quintile will pay about $125 less in taxes.  Similarly, in the second lowest quintile, about 18% will pay almost a thousand more; however, at least for this quintile about a third will pay almost $500 less, so that the overall increase averaged across these groups is less.</p>
<p>This is an unacceptable result.  The New York Times recently reported on various studies on inequality and a survey that shows that more and more people, across the spectrum of ideologies, ages, gender and other lines, now consider the conflict between rich and non-rich as important.  Survey Finds Rising Perception of Class Tension, New York Times, Jan. 11, 2012. </p>
<p>The demographics were surprising, experts said. While blacks were still more likely than whites to see serious conflicts between rich and poor, the share of whites who held that view increased by 22 percentage points, more than triple the increase among blacks. The share of blacks and Hispanics who held the view grew by single digits.</p>
<p>What is more, people at the upper middle of the income ladder were most likely to see conflict. Seventy-one percent of those who earned from $40,000 to $75,000 said there were strong conflicts between rich and poor, up from 47 percent in 2009. The lowest income bracket, less than $20,000, changed the least.</p>
<p>The reason the rich are getting richer is because the country has followed policies, essentially since Reagan, that favor the rich&#8211;from deregulation to relaxation of anti-trust to reduction in tax burdens to privatization to deunionization.  To add further rich-friendly policies to our tax code at this point should not be countenanced.</p>
<p>originally published at <a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2012/01/romneys-tax-plan-helps-the-1-hurts-the-bottom-40.html" target="_blank">ataxingmatter<strike></strike>a></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/01/romneys-tax-plan-helps-the-1-hurts-the-bottom-40.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
