<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Marco Rubio &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Is all of this LEGAL? &#8212; Specifics added, 2/16</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/is-all-of-this-legal-specifics-added-216.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/is-all-of-this-legal-specifics-added-216.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2013 17:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Chris Christie]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Huffington Post]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jason Cherkis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jesse Jackson Jr. Rod Blagojevich]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Marco Rubio]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ryan Grimm]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/is-all-of-this-legal-specifics-added-216.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[By “this,” I mean this.  I don’t know, but it sounds to me like some of it is not.   Wish I could ask Chris Christie, a former (very high-profile) U.S. Attorney for the District of New Jersey (2001-2008).  He would know.   &#8212;-UPDATE:  In light of the comments to this post, saying that Florida [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By “this,” I mean <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2013/02/13/marco-rubio-finances_n_2678744.html">this</a>.  I don’t know, but it sounds to me like some of it is not.  </p>
<p>Wish I could ask Chris Christie, a former (very high-profile) U.S. Attorney for the District of New Jersey (2001-2008).  He would know.  </p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />UPDATE:  In light of the comments to this post, saying that Florida law allows the type of influence-peddling that Rubio has engaged in (presumably, unless there’s some overt quid pro quo)&#8211;something that the article I linked to does make clear&#8211;I want to clarify what I think may be illegal (i.e., violate federal law, thus my reference to Chris Christie).  From the article: </p>
<div dir="ltr">For Rubio, a rising star in the Republican Party, more government did indeed create more opportunities. As <a href="http://www.tampabay.com/news/politics/national/marco-rubios-personal-finances-clash-with-call-for-fiscal-discipline/1129566">the Tampa Bay Times</a> reported during his U.S. Senate run in 2010, it&#8217;s hard to determine with Rubio where politics stops and the private begins:</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">As Rubio climbed the ranks, he began to use little-noticed political committees to fund his travel and other expenses and later had a Republican Party of Florida credit card.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">What emerged, records show, is a pattern of blending personal and political spending. Over and over again Rubio proved sloppy, at best, in complying with disclosure requirements.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Virtually broke, the 31-year-old lawmaker began campaigning to be House speaker in 2003 and created a political committee &#8212; Floridians for Conservative Leadership &#8212; to help elect other Republican candidates and curry their support.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">With his wife serving as treasurer, Rubio did not wait for the state to authorize the committee before accepting campaign donations.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">The committee listed its address as Rubio&#8217;s home, a modest place he and his wife bought in West Miami in 2002, but reported spending nearly $85,000 in office and operating costs and $65,000 for administrative costs.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Over 18 months, nearly $90,000 went for political consultants, $51,000 went for credit card payments and $4,000 went to other candidates. That&#8217;s less than the $5,700 that went to his wife, Jeanette, much of it for &#8220;gas and meals.&#8221; (Mrs. Rubio does not work and the couple file joint tax returns.)</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Virtually broke, the 31-year-old lawmaker began campaigning to be House speaker in 2003 and created a political committee &#8212; Floridians for Conservative Leadership &#8212; to help elect other Republican candidates and curry their support.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">With his wife serving as treasurer, Rubio did not wait for the state to authorize the committee before accepting campaign donations.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">The committee listed its address as Rubio&#8217;s home, a modest place he and his wife bought in West Miami in 2002, but reported spending nearly $85,000 in office and operating costs and $65,000 for administrative costs.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Over 18 months, nearly $90,000 went for political consultants, $51,000 went for credit card payments and $4,000 went to other candidates. That&#8217;s less than the $5,700 that went to his wife, Jeanette, much of it for &#8220;gas and meals.&#8221; (Mrs. Rubio does not work and the couple file joint tax returns.)</div>
<p>Some of this sounds to me like taxable (but probably undeclared) income for him and his wife, beyond just his wife’s salary and actual expenses related to the PAC.  The PAC also sounds like it was largely a fraud; its stated purpose was to help elect other Republicans to the state legislature, and I guess some of the consulting was used by or for other candidates, although the article doesn’t make that clear, but just a tiny percentage of the donations were given to other candidates.</p>
<p>But also, two other things the article mentions sound like they violate federal law:</p>
<ul>
<li dir="ltr">Rubio <a href="http://www.tampabay.com/news/politics/elections/rubios-campaign-image-belies-history-of-250-million-in-pork-requests/1078548">earmarked money</a> to Florida International University and later got an unadvertised job as a part-time professor at the school. The former school president, Mitch Maidique, said Rubio was &#8220;worth every penny.&#8221;</li>
</ul>
<p>
<ul>
<li dir="ltr">After appropriating millions of dollars to Miami Children&#8217;s and Jackson Memorial Hospitals, Rubio formed a lobby shop and<a href="http://big.assets.huffingtonpost.com/RubioHerald.pdf"> got contracts</a> with the hospitals.</li>
</ul>
<p>Some of these things sound like things that Jesse Jackson Jr. and his wife <a href="http://www.politico.com/story/2013/02/jesse-jackson-jr-to-plead-guilty-to-federal-charges-87716.html?hp=f3">were formally charged with yesterday</a>, albeit on a much quieter scale, and some of the other things sound similar in nature, if not scale, to what former Illinois governor Rod Blagojevich was convicted of.  </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/is-all-of-this-legal-specifics-added-216.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>John Boehner Should Travel More. To Australia.</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/john-boehner-should-travel-more-to-australia.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/john-boehner-should-travel-more-to-australia.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2013 21:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Greg Sargent]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Boehner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Marco Rubio]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Matthew Miller]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[minimum wage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Washington Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/john-boehner-should-travel-more-to-australia.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Yesterday, both sides drew their battle lines in the coming war over the minimum wage. After Obama called for a minimum wage hike in his State of the Union speech, House Republicans dug in against it, casting their opposition as grounded in concern for the plight of low wage workers. John Boehner asked: “Why would [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">Yesterday, both sides drew their battle lines in the coming war over the minimum wage. After Obama called for a minimum wage hike in his State of the Union speech, House Republicans dug in against it, casting their opposition as grounded in concern for the plight of low wage workers. John Boehner <a href="http://livewire.talkingpointsmemo.com/entry/boehner-shoots-down-obamas-minimum-wage-hike">asked</a>: “Why would we want to make it harder for small employers to hire people?”</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/plum-line/wp/2013/02/14/the-morning-plum-dems-to-use-minimum-wage-against-gop-in-2014/">Dems to use minimum wage against GOP in 2014</a>, Greg Sargent, Washington Post, this morning</div>
<p>To me, one of the great frustrations in Obama’s failure during most of his first term to communicate, effectively or at all, the basic premises of Keynesian and other liberal economics-related arguments (including on healthcare) was his apparent resistance to mentioning&#8211;early, often, or ever&#8211;specific other countries’ successes or failures that illustrate the point. </p>
<p>But there’s no time like the present for him and the congressional Dems to start to do do this, by maybe mentioning these facts: that Australia’s minimum wage is $15 U.S. and that its unemployment rate is 5.4%, and that the United States has (surprise!) the largest gap between the minimum wage and the median wage of any advanced economy in the world.</p>
<p>I learned those facts yesterday when I read Washington Post columnist <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/matt-miller-raise-the-minimum-wage/2013/02/06/34857264-7066-11e2-8b8d-e0b59a1b8e2a_story.html">Matthew Miller’s Feb. 6 column</a>.  He mentioned it and linked to it in <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/matt-miller-obamas-hollow-speech/2013/02/13/d928c944-75a5-11e2-95e4-6148e45d7adb_story.html">his column yesterday</a> about Obama’s State of the Union address.  In yesterday’s column, he suggested seemingly, facetiously, that it was his February 6 column that had persuaded Obama to include a minimum-wage-hike proposal in his address.  But after reading the earlier column, I suspect that it was not only what convinced Obama to make the call but also was what caused Obama to even think of it.  </p>
<p>Both of Miller’s columns say that the $9/hr. figure that Obama proposed in his speech would still leave the minimum wage at $1.68 below what the value of the minimum wage was in 1968.  The first column, Miller also mentions that several CEOs of large corporations support a rise in the minimum wage and that a prominent conservative, the editor of American Conservative magazine, suggests raising the minimum wage to $12/hr.  Of course, the Republicans will showcase their own CEOs, and some small-business owners, to support their own position.</p>
<p>Which is where Australia comes in.  Or at least where invoking it should come in. The special beauty of using Australia as an example&#8211;whether in support of an increase in the minimum wage or in refuting the Obamacare-is-socialism/makers-vs.-takers mantra&#8211;is that few Americans associate Australia with, um, socialism.  They associate it instead with free-enterprise economics and a high standard of living.  And soon, hopefully, also with a higher minimum wage that corresponds to a low unemployment rate.  </p>
<p>Maybe Marco Rubio and John Boehner could get a travel discount <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/02/marco-rubio-needs-to-travel-more.html">if they booked their reservations</a> together. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/john-boehner-should-travel-more-to-australia.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Marco Rubio Needs to Travel More. Seriously. [Updated and lightly edited.]</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/marco-rubio-needs-to-travel-more-seriously-updated-and-lightly-edited.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/marco-rubio-needs-to-travel-more-seriously-updated-and-lightly-edited.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2013 19:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Chris Christie]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jonathan Martin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Marco Rubio]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Krugman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politico]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The New York Times]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/marco-rubio-needs-to-travel-more-seriously-updated-and-lightly-edited.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Mr. President, I still live in the same working-class neighborhood I grew up in. My neighbors aren’t millionaires. They’re retirees who depend on Social Security and Medicare. They’re workers who have to get up early tomorrow morning and go to work to pay the bills. They’re immigrants, who came here because they were stuck in [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">Mr. President, I still live in the same working-class neighborhood I grew up in. My neighbors aren’t millionaires. They’re retirees who depend on Social Security and Medicare. They’re workers who have to get up early tomorrow morning and go to work to pay the bills. They’re immigrants, who came here because they were stuck in poverty in countries where the government dominated the economy.</div>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; Marco Rubio, last night. </div>
<p>I lifted that quote from <a href="http://dyn.politico.com/printstory.cfm?uuid=6A9DCC73-62AF-402E-9EED-3F327BE18F7B">a Politico article by Jonathan Martin</a> that went on to say that Rubio left school with more than $100,000 in student-loan debt, which he finished paying off only a few months ago. Presumably, those loans were government-sponsored.  Although maybe at the age of 18, he had some collateral to offer the bank.</p>
<p>Rubio’s parents, like so many of his working-class neighbors now, emigrated from Cuba before 2001, when the first of the two sets of Bush tax cuts were passed.  Apparently, he hasn’t checked the federal income tax rates on individuals and corporations when his parents and his neighbors came here because they were stuck in poverty in countries where the government dominated the economy.  Because, best as I can tell, that comment about immigrants from countries where the government dominated the economy was intended as a warning about Obama’s and the congressional Democrats’ plans to have the government dominate the economy.  </p>
<p>So I’d like some specifics.  What policies and programs, current and proposed, does he have in mind?  Exactly?  Maybe next time he’s interviewed by some high-profile journalist, he’ll be asked that.  And maybe he’ll answer.  But I doubt it.</p>
<p>Anyway, for now, I’m left to speculate that he means raising tax rates to Clinton-era tax levels for people with non-investment incomes above $250,000 a year, and on corporations, and on investment income.  He also might mean Obamacare, but that’s questionable unless he thinks that only people who qualify for Medicare get cancer or other serious illnesses, because he also said this last night:</p>
<div dir="ltr">[Medicare] provided my father the care he needed to battle cancer and ultimately die with dignity.  And it pays for the care my mother receives now.</div>
<p>But the title of this post suggests that Rubio travel more.  Both within this country and outside of it.  First he should visit communities where immigrants from, say, Pakistan and Central America live.  People who came here to escape poverty but whose homeland governments did not, and do not, dominate the economy.*  </p>
<p>Then, if he has a passport, he might consider traveling outside the United States.  Maybe to Canada, or Germany, or Sweden, or Holland, or Australia.  Or France. Or, for that matter, Singapore.  Or Taiwan.  Or he could save the plane fare and just use the Internet to check the rates of poverty in those countries, the tax rates there, the social safety nets there, the education systems there, the healthcare systems there. </p>
<p>I didn’t watch the Rubio Show last night, so I missed the reaching-for-a-water-bottle-but-wishing-it-were-a-Vodka-bottle-instead moment.  I wish I’d watched, but I didn’t.  So I’m relying on tidbits reported by others.  And <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/02/13/marco-rubio-has-learned-nothing/">Paul Krugman provides one</a> that, unlike the quotes above, have not garnered much attention.  It’s this:</p>
<div dir="ltr">This idea – that our problems were caused by a government that was too small – it’s just not true. In fact, a major cause of our recent downturn was a housing crisis created by reckless government policies.</div>
<p>Krugman points out that numerous studies, as well as observation by, say, ordinary folks, dispel that claim. Specifically, Krugman writes:<br /><a name="more"></a>
<div dir="ltr">OK, leave on one side the caricature of Obama, with the usual mirror-image fallacy (we want smaller government, therefore liberals just want bigger government, never mind what it does); there we go with the “Barney Frank did it” story. Deregulation, the explosive growth of virtually unregulated shadow banking, lax lending standards by loan originators who sold their loans off as soon as they were made, had nothing to do with it — it was all the Community Reinvestment Act, Fannie, and Freddie.</div>
<div dir="ltr">Look, this is one of the most thoroughly researched topics out there, and every piece of the government-did-it thesis has been refuted; see <a href="http://rortybomb.wordpress.com/2011/11/01/bloombergs-awful-comment-what-can-we-say-for-certain-regarding-the-gses/">Mike Konczal for a summary.</a> No, the CRA wasn’t responsible for the epidemic of bad lending; no, Fannie and Freddie didn’t cause the housing bubble; no, the “high-risk” loans of the GSEs weren’t remotely as risky as subprime.</div>
<p>So I guess I was wrong when I said above that Rubio must have had only tax rates and Obamacare in mind.  He apparently also had finance-industry regulation in mind, too. And on this he was specific. </p>
<p>But on this too, I suggest some overseas travel&#8211;either physically, or virtually, on the Internet. He&#8217;d learn that Spain, Ireland and Iceland must have had a Fannie Mae and a Freddie Mac. Not to mention a Barney Frank. Because those countries’ current and recent fiscal and economic woes were caused entirely by a housing bubbles virtually identical to, or worse than, ours, spurred by Deregulation, the explosive growth of virtually unregulated shadow banking, lax lending standards by loan originators who sold their loans off as soon as they were made. </p>
<p>Then Rubio might consider returning to Canada and Germany, physically or virtually, and checking out why those countries had little or no such bubble.  And before he leaves, or after he returns, he should travel to Texas.  Yes, Texas, of all states.  It had almost no housing bubble.  Something to do with government involvement in the economy, i.e., legislation regulating the mortgage industry, post-savings-and-loan debacle, circa 1989.  State government, in this case. </p>
<p>What is the national debt of Canada and Germany?  And the poverty levels and standards of living in those countries?  </p>
<p>The Politico article, by the way, is called “Marco Rubio as the anti-Romney.”  The title of Krugman’s post indicates disagreement with that assessment. It’s called “Marco Rubio Has Learned Nothing.”  </p>
<p>But a majority of Americans, I think, have.  They’ve learned that you can’t judge a book by it’s jacket cover. And that ideology can’t substitute for fact. 
<div></div>
<div>&#8212;-<br />UPDATE:  Oh, dear. As I said, I didn’t watch Rubio last night.  I also haven’t read a transcript of his speech.  And I didn’t know until just now, when I read Jazzbumpa’s post below, that Rubio said that proposals to deal with climate change, including trying to slow its progression, are attempts to have the government “control the weather.”</p>
<p>Um.  Yeah.  That’s the idea.  </p>
<p>Yikes.</p></div>
<div>Why do I think Chris Christie is the happiest person in America today?</p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />UPDATE II:  I’m getting the strong feeling that there are a lot of people who are downright dumbfounded by that speech last night&#8211;that this guy who’s being touted as the Republican savior went on national television and established himself as stunningly stupid. </p>
<p>We’re going to elect a global warming denier as president in 2016?  We’re going to elect as president someone who is unaware of such things as financial derivatives, and the role they played in the financial meltdown?  We’re going to elect as president someone who seems not to know that student loans and Medicare are government programs&#8211;or at least what it means that they are?  We’re going to elect as president someone who thinks Clinton-era tax rates are a government-dominated economy?</p>
<p>I’ll certainly agree that he’s no Romney.  Romney isn’t stupid, by any stretch.  He just pretended to be.  With Rubio, it’s apparently no act. </p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />*<i>Paragraph edited for clarity</i>. 2/14. (I figured that since this post is getting a decent number of &#8220;hits&#8221; and Google+ links, it should be edited so that typos and such are corrected.)</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/marco-rubio-needs-to-travel-more-seriously-updated-and-lightly-edited.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Thus Spake the Rube</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/thus-spake-the-rube.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/thus-spake-the-rube.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2013 17:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2016 presidential elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jazzbumpa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Marco Rubio]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Republican brand]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tea Party]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/thus-spake-the-rube.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[For the hundredth time the foreign-born Muslim commie Nazi extends an olive branch across the aisle, and for the hundredth time it&#8217;s dashed to the floor, stomped on and set ablaze &#8211; along with the latest spokes-liars trousers.   It became a conflagration that the infamous water-stop could not staunch. Early in Marco Rubio&#8217;s alleged rebuttal [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For the hundredth time the foreign-born Muslim commie Nazi extends an  olive branch across the aisle, and for the hundredth time it&#8217;s dashed  to the floor, stomped on and set ablaze &#8211; along with the latest  spokes-liars trousers.   It became a conflagration that the infamous  water-stop could not staunch.</p>
<p>Early in Marco Rubio&#8217;s  alleged rebuttal to B. Hoover Obama&#8217;s latest exercise in political  theater it became painfully obvious that his pants were on fire.  This  was even before it became obvious that his diatribe was utterly  incoherent.  <a href="http://maddowblog.msnbc.com/_news/2013/02/13/16948495-putting-the-rube-in-rubio?lite">Steve Benen explains</a>.</p>
<blockquote><div>By  any sensible measure, Rubio&#8217;s entire pitch was incoherent gibberish. He  thinks President Obama is hostile to free enterprise and wants to  increase the deficit, neither of which makes any sense. Rubio thinks the  housing crisis was caused by big government, <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/02/13/marco-rubio-has-learned-nothing/?smid=tw-NytimesKrugman&#038;seid=auto">which is simply idiotic</a>.  Rubio celebrates his family&#8217;s history of dependence on government  social programs like student loans and Medicare, while articulating a  policy agenda that guts government social programs like student loans  and Medicare.</div>
<div>Forget  ideology, subjectivity, and areas of opinion &#8212; the fact is Marco  Rubio&#8217;s speech was filled with a series of claims with no meaningful  connection to reality. The senator even thinks combating the climate  crisis means asking government to &#8220;control the weather,&#8221; which is just  genuinely dumb.</div>
</blockquote>
<p>Part  way through I started taking notes, and discovered an unappetizing  platter of rewarmed left-overs [or more accurately: right-overs] of  Romney&#8217;s failed presidential campaign, where <a href="http://jazzbumpa.blogspot.com/2012/10/strategic-lying-as-political-art.html">lying and incoherence were the norm</a>.  It was deja vu all over again. Viz:</p>
<p>Obama&#8217;s obsession with raising taxes<br />Solyndra [God help us &#8211; I am not making this up]<br />We should open Federal lands to energy exploration<br />Grow Energy industry [but not renewables]<br />Lower Corp tax rate [Highest in the world, don&#8217;t cha know]<br />Incentivise school districts<br />Schools of choice<br />Solve the debt problem [As if BHO ignored it &#8211; or, more importantly &#8211; as if it were a real problem]<br />Obama created the debt with excessive spending  [my personal favorite]<br />Need a balanced budget amendment  [the ignorance &#8211; it burns, too]<br />Obama&#8217;s in favor of leaving Medicare just the way it is [though he clearly stated otherwise]<br />He also wants to unconstitutionally undermine 2nd amendment rights<br />The President&#8217;s devastating cuts to our military [Seriously &#8212; WTH?!?]<br />Moral breakdown in society &#8211; need more faith<br />Economic liberty</p>
<p>That&#8217;s  what I was able to capture as Rubio&#8217;s litany of [mostly] decades old  Republican clap-trap spewed forth almost faster than I could record it.</p>
<p>One  of the MSNBC commentators pointed out that this nonsense wasn&#8217;t  directed to the American public, who I hope are beginning to see through  the smoke screen, but to the hard-core right-wing base.  As such, it&#8217;s  Rubio&#8217;s first gambit in his run for the 2016 presidential nomination.</p>
<p>I don&#8217;t know if I should laugh, cry, or drink myself into a stupor.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/thus-spake-the-rube.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Paul Krugman Steps on Marco Rubio’s Parade. And Kills My Entertainment.</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/paul-krugman-steps-on-marco-rubios-parade-and-kills-my-entertainment.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/paul-krugman-steps-on-marco-rubios-parade-and-kills-my-entertainment.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2013 22:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Marco Rubio]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Krugman]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/paul-krugman-steps-on-marco-rubios-parade-and-kills-my-entertainment.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Just a quick observation: for the past couple of days I’ve been seeing in a lot of places, including comments on this blog, the assertion that federal spending has risen 37 percent under Obama — that specific number. Does anyone know where it’s coming from? Because if I look at the actual data, I see [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">Just a quick observation: for the past couple of days I’ve been seeing in a lot of places, including comments on this blog, the assertion that federal spending has risen 37 percent under Obama — that specific number. Does anyone know where it’s coming from? </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Because if I look at the <a href="http://research.stlouisfed.org/fred2/data/W019RCQ027SBEA.txt">actual data</a>, I see federal spending rising from $3.475 trillion in fourth-quarter 2008 to $3.917 trillion in fourth-quarter 2012 — a rise of 12.7 percent.</p>
</div>
<div dir="ltr">Obviously this is coming from somewhere, and being broadcast by Rush or somebody. But it’s still kind of amazing how a totally wrong number can become part of what everyone on the right just knows to be true.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/02/12/where-do-facts-come-from/">Where Do “Facts” Come From?</a>, Paul Krugman, New York Times, today</div>
<p>Damn.  Now Marco Rubio will have to scratch that line from his response to the State of the Union address tonight.  Depriving those of us who enjoy political comedy of the fun of watching Rubio explain this fact during the next couple of days, after the CEO of Chrysler Corp. makes a public statement that federal spending has risen 12.7 percent, not 37 percent, since the fourth quarter of 2008.  And that Chrysler has absolutely no plans whatsoever to close the Ohio Jeep plant that it just spent more than $1 million expanding in order to hire 1,200 new workers, and ship those jobs to China. </p>
<p>You shouldn’t have let that cat out of the bag today, Prof. Krugman!</p>
<p>Sheeesh.  You’d almost think the Republicans hired me as their statistician/mathematician.  Hmm.  Maybe I’ll apply to Fox News for consulting work.  My math abilities are every bit as good as those of the person who did the math on that statistic.  Trust me.</p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />Okay, okay.  I don’t actually know that Rubio planned to include this hot statistic in his response tonight.  It’s just my speculation. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/paul-krugman-steps-on-marco-rubios-parade-and-kills-my-entertainment.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
