<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>evidenced based medicine &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>George Engles and medical thinking and models</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/george-engles-and-medical-thinking-and-models.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/george-engles-and-medical-thinking-and-models.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Jul 2012 10:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[disorders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[evidenced based medicine]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/george-engles-and-medical-thinking-and-models.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Via Alternet, Andrew Weil pays homage to a little known but profound man, George Engles, who decades ago in 1977 proposed thinking differently on the medical model common to the US practices. I want you to consider the possibility that the basic assumptions of mainstream psychiatric medicine are obsolete and no longer serve us well. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Via Alternet, Andrew Weil pays homage to a little known but profound man, <a href="http://www.alternet.org/story/156160/we_have_happy_pills%2C_anxiety_drugs%2C_and_therapists_galore%3A_so_why_are_we_more_stressed_and_depressed_than_ever?page=1" target="_blank">George Engles</a>, who decades ago in 1977 proposed thinking differently on the medical model common to the US practices. <br />
<blockquote>I want you to consider the possibility that the basic assumptions of mainstream psychiatric medicine are obsolete and no longer serve us well. Those assumptions constitute the biomedical model of mental health and dominate the whole field.</p>
<p>In 1977, the journal Science published a provocative article titled “The Need for a New Medical Model: A Challenge for Biomedicine.” I consider it a landmark in medical philosophy and the intellectual foundation of today’s integrative medicine. The author, George L. Engel, M.D., was a professor of psychiatry at the University of Rochester (New York) School of Medicine. Determined to overcome the limiting influence of Cartesian dualism, which assigns mind and body to separate realms, Engel envisioned medical students of the future learning that health and illness result from an interaction of biological, psychological, social, and behavioral factors, not from biological factors alone. He fathered the field of psychosomatic medicine and devoted much of his career to broadening our understanding of disease. He was particularly interested in mental health.</p>
<p>George Engel died in 1999 with his vision largely unrealized. In fact, the field of psychosomatic medicine ran out of steam sometime before his death and was never able to challenge the ascendancy of biological medicine.</p></blockquote>
<p>Ah well&#8230;.I will be losing electricity shortly and this note will have to suffice for now.   Anyway, a much younger Mrs. Rdan was part of this team at the University of Rochester in the early seventies&#8230;.good to see the name George Engles again.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/george-engles-and-medical-thinking-and-models.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Health Care Thoughts: Evidence Based Medicine</title>
		<link>./../../2012/01/health-care-thoughts-evidence-based-medicine.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/01/health-care-thoughts-evidence-based-medicine.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2012 03:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[evidenced based medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health care reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health care thoughts]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/01/health-care-thoughts-evidence-based-medicine.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt Health Care Thoughts: Evidence Based Medicine Evidence based medicine is one of the center pieces of PPACA (Obamacare) and is generally viewed as THE enlightened way to practice medicine and to direct dollars more effectively. Problem is, there is a &#8220;whose ox just got gored&#8221; issue. The American Psychiatric Association [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt</p>
<p>Health Care Thoughts: Evidence Based Medicine</p>
<p>  Evidence based medicine is one of the center pieces of PPACA (Obamacare) and is generally viewed as THE enlightened way to practice medicine and to direct dollars more effectively.  Problem is, there is a &#8220;whose ox just got gored&#8221; issue.</p>
<p>  The American Psychiatric Association is currently revising guidelines for autism spectrum diagnoses, and early research indicates some high cognition youngsters may have their diagnosis dropped or altered. This could result in an alteration or loss of services (caveat: it is very early in the process).</p>
<p>  It has been suggested over the past couple of decades the diagnosis was expanded, perhaps past the bounds of science, as parents scrambled and pleaded for help.  Parents and educators are concerned. What parent can blame them? <br /><a name="more"></a>In 2009 new recommendations were published for breast cancer treatment and there was a firestorm of criticism. Breast cancer is an emotional topic (justifiably so).</p>
<p>We tend to associate less treatment with neglect or negligence.  </p>
<p>But, if we are to follow evidence based medicine then we have to go with evidence. Right?  Many difficult decisions lie ahead.  (My own physician has cut back testing at my annual physical based on new guidelines, so I have a personal stake in this.)</p>
<p>  PS: New guidelines on bone densiometry (osteoporosis test) are coming soon and will probably indicate less testing for women once a baseline is established.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/01/health-care-thoughts-evidence-based-medicine.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
