<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Barack Obama &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>WHISKEY SOUR: No, Sen. Alexander, and, no, Ruth Marcus, Mitch McConnell Is Not Everett Dirksen. So Sorry.</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/whiskey-sour-no-sen-alexander-and-no-ruth-marcus-mitch-mcconnell-is-not-everett-dirksen-so-sorry.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/whiskey-sour-no-sen-alexander-and-no-ruth-marcus-mitch-mcconnell-is-not-everett-dirksen-so-sorry.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2013 19:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Everett M. Dirksen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Boehner; Lamar Alexander]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lyndon Baines Johnson; Mitch McConnell]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Manu Rafu; Kate Nocera; Jonathan Allen; Politico; Ruth Marcus; The Washington Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/whiskey-sour-no-sen-alexander-and-no-ruth-marcus-mitch-mcconnell-is-not-everett-dirksen-so-sorry.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Everett McKinley Dirksen (January 4, 1896 – September 7, 1969) was an American politician of the Republican Party. He represented Illinois in the U.S. House of Representatives (1933–1949) and U.S. Senate (1951–1969). As Senate Minority Leader for a decade, he played a highly visible and key role in the politics of the 1960s, including helping [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">Everett McKinley Dirksen (January 4, 1896 – September 7, 1969) was an <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States">American</a> politician of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republican_Party_(United_States)">Republican Party</a>. He represented <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Illinois">Illinois</a> in the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_House_of_Representatives">U.S. House of Representatives</a> (1933–1949) and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Senate">U.S. Senate</a> (1951–1969). As <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Party_leaders_of_the_United_States_Senate">Senate Minority Leader</a> for a decade, he played a highly visible and key role in the politics of the 1960s, including helping to write and pass the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Civil_Rights_Act_of_1964">Civil Rights Act of 1964</a> and the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_Housing_Act_of_1968">Open Housing Act of 1968</a>, both landmarks of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/African-American_Civil_Rights_Movement_(1955%E2%80%931968)">civil rights</a> legislation. He was also one of the Senate&#8217;s strongest supporters of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vietnam_War">Vietnam War</a> and was known as &#8220;The Wizard of Ooze&#8221; for his oratorical style.</div>
<p>That’s <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Everett_Dirksen">the Wikipedia version</a> of how LBJ was able to get the Civil Rights Act through Congress in 1965.  But it’s inaccurate.  Here’s the accurate version: </p>
<div dir="ltr">Speaking to reporters after the meeting, Senate Minority Leader Mitch McConnell said the onus is on the president.</p>
</div>
<div dir="ltr">“You can’t do it without presidential leadership and we’re all hopeful he’ll be prepared to provide that leadership,” McConnell said. “The president needs to deliver his side.”</div>
<div dir="ltr">Other senators also cited the leadership meme.</p>
</div>
<div dir="ltr">“The point that was consistently made to the president was that in the absence of his leadership, issues that are important to the people of America will not be addressed,” [Sen. Jerry] Moran said. “I really think it was rather a bland conversation. No fireworks on either tone. This wasn’t memorable, it was the opposite of that.”</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Alexander brought up meetings between President Lyndon Johnson and GOP Senate leader Everett Dirksen.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">“I told him that every great crisis in our history has been solved by presidential leadership or not at all,” he said. “I’ve been around here a long time and this is the kind of thing that used to happen when President Johnson would show up unexpectedly in Dirksen’s office for a drink because Dirksen wouldn’t go down to the White House. As a result the next year they passed the Civil Rights bill.”</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212;  <a href="http://dyn.politico.com/printstory.cfm?uuid=2CD9DA5E-7756-456A-BC84-F8938FD974A3">Obama to Democrats: Chill out</a>, Manu Rafu, Kate Nocera, Jonathan Allen, Politico, yesterday</div>
<p>OK.  I grew up in a household with two liberal Democratic political junkies (my parents), one of them a journalist (horrors!), both of them lifelong Illinoisans, one of whose ancestors on both sides were Illinoisans dating back to not long after the Civil War.  </p>
<p>So I grew up knowing, for example, that the only thing “Jerksen” ever did in his political career, before his surprising aggressive support of the Civil Rights Act and his assistance to LBJ in the aftermath of the Kennedy assassination in getting it enacted, was to get the Marigold declared the official state flower (when he was a top State legislator, or something).  So all you Illinoisans who didn’t know that your state even has an official flower, and who are reading this post, must be glad you read AB occasionally, because now you know.  (I can also tell you extremely detailed information about, say, Chicago politics dating back to about the early 1900s, but you’ve had your Illinois-political-history fill for the day, I’m sure. And you’ll probably agree, as I do, that the Marigold is a pretty flower.  Even my mother, she of “Jerksen” coinage, agreed; she just didn’t think it was necessary to have an official state flower.)</p>
<p>My point in all this, of course, is that while Sen. Alexander has been around there a long time, that time isn’t quite long enough for him to know that, contrary to what he apparently thinks&#8211;or at least what his choice of analogy implies&#8211;Lyndon Johnson did not cave to the Republicans and finally agree reluctantly to support the Civil Rights Act.  Johnson himself actually strongly supported enactment of the Act and obtained the assistance of the Republican Senate Minority Leader in bringing along enough members of their respective parties to vote for it.  </p>
<p>That included, on Johnson’s part, persuading some Southern Democrats in the House and Senate to vote for it despite the very substantial risk to their own political careers, and, on Dirksen’s part, doing the same with Republicans from mostly-rural states.  And while he first had to persuade Dirksen himself, Dirksen was not going to be “primaried” by a Tea Party candidate, or by some “out there” equivalent of the 1960s.  Nor did he have to fear, as both McConnell and John Boehner do, the loss of their leadership roles if they, y’know, actually act as leaders.  </p>
<p>Nor is it clear that, had he had to worry about these things, he would have shown the leadership he showed, helping write two really strong, landmark civil rights laws and helping shepherd them through to enactment. There was no “compromise” in the enactment of the 1960s civil rights laws; the nature of those laws were, all or nothing.  Dirksen chose the “all” option.  McConnell and Boehner won’t even choose the “compromise” one, choosing a new  and ludicrous definition of “leadership”&#8211;one that they’ve sold to analysis-challenged members of the centrist punditry.  </p>
<p>Such as Ruth Marcus, who <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/ruth-marcus-obama-has-to-be-dealmaker-in-chief/2013/03/14/9714cff4-8cce-11e2-b63f-f53fb9f2fcb4_story.html">writes today</a> in the Washington Post: </p>
<div dir="ltr">Speaking to [George] Stephanopoulos, the president sounded distinctly pessimistic about the prospects for such a bargain and disturbingly unconcerned about failing to reach one. That, he said, would be more missed opportunity than “crisis.”</p>
</div>
<div dir="ltr">Perhaps he’s posturing; if the president is seen as coveting a deal too much, he won’t be able to get the kind he wants. Perhaps it’s simple realism; Republicans’ refusal to consider revenue raised by curtailing loopholes is unacceptable, and the president shouldn’t accept a cuts-only deal.</p>
</div>
<div dir="ltr">But failure would not only tarnish Republicans; it would also stain Obama’s legacy. Great presidential leadership entails figuring out how to deal with even those who do not like you. </div>
<p>Indeed it does.  Maybe Marcus has in mind the option of dealing with those in Congress who don’t like him by, say, informing the public that federal spending is now at its lowest level in more than 50 years; that the budget deficit had declined substantially since he took office (after initially rising); that the 2011 and 2012 debt ceiling and fiscal cliff agreements included large reductions in spending; that he and the Dems are now proposing further reductions in spending; and that taxes on the wealthy are at historically low levels dating back to pre-WWII, with the single exception being the decade of the 2000s. And that there actually is no good reason at all to have a balanced federal budget, and it’s just being used as a way to gut the federal budget. And that he could even directly inform the public of what the Ryan budget actually proposes.  
<div></div>
<div>But I doubt it. Marcus&#8217;s op-ed piece, after all, isn’t titled ”Obama has to be dealmaker in chief,” for nothing.</p>
<p>Great presidential leadership entails figuring out how to deal with even those who do not like you. And certainly Obama hasn’t yet figured out how to deal with even those who do not like him. Or how to deal with even those who themselves are in leadership positions and whose very political careers depend now entirely on being the <i>un</i>-Dirksen.  </p>
<p>Those who, say, wouldn’t engage in actual leadership&#8211;as opposed to Leadership&#8211;if Everett Dirksen himself reappeared as a ghost in the Capitol and defined it for them.  And who are buttressed in this <i>every single time some &#8220;name&#8221; pundit claims otherwise.</i>  </p>
<p>The centrist-pundit crowd should not be held harmless in this.  They are not harmless. </p></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/whiskey-sour-no-sen-alexander-and-no-ruth-marcus-mitch-mcconnell-is-not-everett-dirksen-so-sorry.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>John Boehner Needs a Dictionary</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/john-boehner-needs-a-dictionary.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/john-boehner-needs-a-dictionary.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2013 17:14:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Greg Sargent]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Boehner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mainstream-journalism gimmickry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitch McConnell]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[semantics gimmickry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Washington Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/john-boehner-needs-a-dictionary.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[All of these bipartisan discussions are encouraging, and Republicans hope they will lead to real solutions that help American families. But presidential leadership is really what’s needed. By shifting the focus from charm to courage, and eventually action, we can guarantee our children a future where everyone has the opportunity to find work and pursue [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">All of these bipartisan discussions are encouraging, and Republicans hope they will lead to real solutions that help American families. But presidential leadership is really what’s needed. By shifting the focus from charm to courage, and eventually action, we can guarantee our children a future where everyone has the opportunity to find work and pursue their piece of the American dream. That would be the grandest bargain of all.</div>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/john-boehner-obamas-intraparty-problem/2013/03/13/455e097e-8c19-11e2-b63f-f53fb9f2fcb4_story.html">Obama’s outreach is nice, but where’s the leadership?</a>, John Boehner, Op-ed, Washington Post, today</div>
<p>I have what I think is a better question, this one for the speaker: Where’s a dictionary?</p>
<p>One of the most pernicious aspects of these phony, sequential fiscal crises is, in my opinion, the Republicans’ tactic of selecting single words or short phrases that have an appealing meaning and using them to mean something else entirely&#8211;often something the opposite of what the word or phrase actually means.  It’s so clearly concerted, political-consultant-suggested, Madison Avenue-type sales gimmickry; every few days there’s a new messaging word or short phrase, redefined or otherwise-misleadingly used, and then repeated, repeated, repeated … repeated.   </p>
<p>Enter “leadership.”  And now, “courage.”  As in: the president should demonstrate these qualities by delegating to the Tea Party the fiscal policy of the United States, because the Tea Party is now the Republican Party and it wants to disassemble the federal government <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/plum-line/wp/2013/03/14/the-morning-plum-wheres-the-leadership-john-boehner/">and will settle for nothing less</a>.* </p>
<p>So I suggest that Obama offer Boehner a dictionary and ask him to point to where it defines leadership as abdication, and courage as cowering.  Whether you’re the president or, say, the Speaker of the House.  </p>
<p>Maybe more to the point, where in the dictionary definition of either leadership or courage does it define those words as including doing absolutely whatever is necessary to keep your position as House speaker, regardless of the consequences to the country you took an oath of office to serve?  Neither the Merriam-Webster’s nor the Oxford English limits those terms to references to the president of the United States.  The definitions do look broad enough to include the speaker.  And even the Senate minority leader.  Even ones who are petrified (literally, it appears from the look on his face these days) of being “primaried” by a Tea Party candidate.  </p>
<p>The Orwellian redefinition of words to mean the opposite of, or at least something entirely different than, their actual meaning is a standard propaganda and subterfuge tool of dictatorships. Mao Tse-tung was infamous for this.  And so, of course, was Hitler.  (The inscription in German, “Work will make you free,” remains above the front gate of Auschwitz in Oswiecim, Poland, a permanent reminder of the deeply sinister nature of extreme semantics games employed in the service of political propaganda.) </p>
<p>That so much of the proud-centrist punditry and fair-and-balanced mainstream media have assisted Boehner &#038; Friends in their sophistry in the last month is inexcusable, if no longer surprising.  If they agree with Boehner that the Ryan budget will guarantee our children a future where everyone has the opportunity to find work and pursue their piece of the American dream, then they should explain why.  If they believe instead that the Ryan budget will guarantee our children a future in which <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ayn_Rand">Atlas really </a><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ayn_Rand">has</a><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ayn_Rand"> shrugged and everyone lives inside The Fountainhead</a> (or maybe in the Pakistan of North America), then they should say that, and explain why. At least the news analysis writers and the centrist pundits should. </p>
<p>They won’t.  But maybe a few of them will point out that, with due respect to Mr. Boehner, the grandest bargain of all would be a free Webster’s Collegiate delivered to the Speaker’s office on Capitol Hill. </p>
<p>As for Obama, he got lucky in the last two days.  The Ryan budget will disabuse a clear majority of the next poll responders that the GOP should be trusted with determining what cuts to make to the federal budget, and when.  At least if the public actually learns the specifics.  (That, of course, would have been true for the last few years, had Obama deigned to apprise the public of the specifics.)  And the live &#8220;tweets&#8221; from the Republican House-member attendees during their meeting with him yesterday were so vile that Obama really needs now only to recite a few of them in order to fully open the public&#8217;s eyes, if and when he decides to speak to the public about the actual situation.  </p>
<p>And, who knows?  Maybe he will, now that he&#8217;s checked off the extend-an-olive-branch box on the mainstream press&#8217;s list of what Leaders (if not necessarily Courageous ones) do, and therefore may even have their permission to do so.</p>
<p>*See Greg Sargent&#8217;s terrific Morning Plum column in today&#8217;s Washington Post.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/john-boehner-needs-a-dictionary.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Douglas Holtz-Eakin: Balancing the Budget Is Just a Sales Gimmick to Gut the Federal Government. And We Republicans Think It Will Work! [UPDATED]</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/douglas-holtz-eakin-balancing-the-budget-is-just-a-sales-gimmick-to-gut-the-federal-government-and-we-republicans-think-it-will-work-updated.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/douglas-holtz-eakin-balancing-the-budget-is-just-a-sales-gimmick-to-gut-the-federal-government-and-we-republicans-think-it-will-work-updated.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2013 14:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Annie Lowrey]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Douglas Holtz-Eakin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The New York Times]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/douglas-holtz-eakin-balancing-the-budget-is-just-a-sales-gimmick-to-gut-the-federal-government-and-we-republicans-think-it-will-work-updated.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[But several right-leaning fiscal experts described a balanced budget as a tool to force a fractious Congress to tackle the nation’s long-term budget problems. “It is important to reduce the debt, and balancing gets you there faster,” said Douglas Holtz-Eakin, a former director of the Congressional Budget Office and a prominent Republican economist. “That’s paramount.” [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">But several right-leaning fiscal experts described a balanced budget as a tool to force a fractious Congress to tackle the nation’s long-term budget problems.</p>
</div>
<div dir="ltr">“It is important to reduce the debt, and balancing gets you there faster,” said Douglas Holtz-Eakin, a former director of the Congressional Budget Office and a prominent Republican economist. “That’s paramount.”</p>
</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">He said a balanced budget is a goal everyone could understand. “It gives Congress a way to say no,” he said. “Transparency and political buy-in are important, and people understand balanced budgets. It has a lot of virtues.”</div>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/03/13/us/politics/balanced-budget-fight-is-philosophical-and-fiscal.html?pagewanted=all&#038;_r=1&#038;">Dispute Over a Balanced Budget Is Philosophical as Much as Fiscal</a>, Annie Lowrey, New York Times, today</div>
<p>So there we have it.  Balancing the budget is just a sales gimmick by Republicans to gut the federal government.  And they think it will work.  As both a sales gimmick and of course as a way to gut the federal government.  </p>
<p>People may understand what balanced budgets are, but they do not understand balanced budgets.  They would, if we had a president willing and able to explain such complexities to the masses, and to explain exactly what Holtz-Eakin just has, to the readers of today’s New York Times: that, while it is important to keep budget deficits below a certain level relative to revenue and relative to GDP over the long haul, it is not important to actually balance the federal budget. But the Republicans can convince the public that it is, because people understand the concept of balanced budgets, and can thereby, via semantics trickery, accomplish the Republican goal of gutting the federal government.</p>
<p>But we don’t.  Have a president who is willing and able to explain such complexities to the masses, that is. </p>
<p>We do, though, now have Douglas Holtz-Eakin, who has just provided a nice quote, should other Dem politicians recognize its value and decide to use it.  Here’s hoping. 
<div></div>
<div>&#8212;-</p>
<p>UPDATE: Regular AB reader and commenter rjs and I just had the following exchange in the Comments to my post:</p>
<p>rjs:  as an economist, he should know that <a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/goldmans-jan-hatzius-on-sectoral-balances-2012-12">as long as we&#8217;re running trade defcits, it impossible for the feederal government to run a balanced budget while the private sector is deleveraging</a>&#8230;</p>
<p>Me:  He probably does know. But he also knows that the public doesn&#8217;t know that. (I didn&#8217;t.) And when you&#8217;re goal is really to gut the federal government, and you think you&#8217;ve found a way to con the public into thinking your goal is something else, that&#8217;s all that matters.</p>
<p>These people are downright diabolical.</p></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/douglas-holtz-eakin-balancing-the-budget-is-just-a-sales-gimmick-to-gut-the-federal-government-and-we-republicans-think-it-will-work-updated.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>John Dickerson Halts This Week&#8217;s Nonsense Juggernaut. Or At Least He Tries To.</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/john-dickerson-halts-this-weeks-nonsense-juggernaut-or-at-least-he-tries-to.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/john-dickerson-halts-this-weeks-nonsense-juggernaut-or-at-least-he-tries-to.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2013 19:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate; John Dickerson; Barkley Rosser]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/john-dickerson-halts-this-weeks-nonsense-juggernaut-or-at-least-he-tries-to.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[By turning his efforts to the inside game, the president is momentarily turning away from the “campaign style” tours around the country, which he had hoped would help put pressure on Washington lawmakers. Some might suggest the switch renders a final verdict on the folly of pursuing that kind of outside game. It doesn’t. Campaigning [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">By turning his efforts to the inside game, the president is momentarily turning away from the “campaign style” tours around the country, which he had hoped would help put pressure on Washington lawmakers. Some might suggest the switch renders a final verdict on the folly of pursuing that kind of outside game. It doesn’t. Campaigning for policies is not antithetical to leadership, it is leadership. All great presidents have done this. Republicans who decry Obama’s tactics might remember that George Bush took 66 trips around the country to sell his Social Security plan. The failure of that effort highlights again that the key question should be about effectiveness. The problem is not the method itself but whether the president is using it at the right moment.</div>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/politics/2013/03/barack_obama_s_invites_republicans_to_the_white_house_the_president_s_effort.single.html">Welcome to the White House: Obama reaching out to Republicans isn’t anything new. It’s just that he’s never made it work</a>., John Dickerson, Slate, today</div>
<p>I’m a longtime Slate devotee, and as part of that devotion I’ve had a longtime love-hate relationship with John Dickerson, Slate’s chief political correspondent. By which I mean that I either love or hate his columns, in about even percentages.  </p>
<p>Today’s column is one of the best political analyses I’ve read in a while.  It’s long, and really deconstructs several of the incessant political-pundit truisms, sophisms, false analogies, and outright falsehoods that masquerade right now as political analysis concerning Obama, political &#8220;leadership,” and political leadership.  </p>
<p>No redundancy in that last sentence.  Really.  Which is Dickerson’s point. </p>
<p>That quote, above, is from the latter part of the column, and it speaks for itself.  It also speaks for me, since I’ve been saying that, repeatedly, here in AB.  But I want to add this to that quote: It’s absolutely true that the problem is not the method itself, if by “method” he means campaigning for policies.  But it’s also true that there is more to the likelihood of its success than whether the president is using it at the right moment.  How he campaigns publicly for policies, as well as when he campaigns publicly for policies, is crucial.  And a hallmark of Obama’s presidency is, in my opinion, stupifying ineptitude in both respects. </p>
<p>The first part of Dickerson’s article proves false the lazy political analogies offered by so many pundits between Obama’s situation and LBJ’s, and between Obama’s situation and Reagan’s, as the pundits offer those analogies: The earlier presidents’ effective working of the “inside game.”  But it is the outside game&#8211;the persuading-the-public part&#8211;where Obama incomprehensibly and repeatedly fails and where he should be unflatteringly compared with past presidents.  With virtually all part presidents, in fact&#8211;including George W. Bush, who Dickerson points out campaigned extensively for his Social Security privatization policy proposal in 2005 and lost the policy argument.</p>
<p>These presidents&#8211;none of them&#8211;failed to educate the public about what their policy proposals were, and, when relevant, what the opposition’s policy proposals were.   And&#8211;incredibly important concerning issues on which the public does not have the basic facts relevant to the policy proposal&#8211;these presidents (no other president, I’d bet) failed, on issue after issue after issue, to educate the public about the facts necessary to assess the policy proposal or the competing policy proposals. </p>
<p>Last week, <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/02/only-6-of-public-knows-deficit-is.html">Dan Crawford linked to</a> <a href="http://econospeak.blogspot.com/2013/02/only-6-of-public-knows-deficit-is.html">a Barkley Rosser post</a> at Econospeak from Feb. 27 saying that polling indicates that only 6% of the public knows that the deficit is declining.  Here’s what Rosser said:</p>
<div dir="ltr">Yes, here we go again, massive public ignorance post # I forget how many.  This has been floating around out there for awhile but was on Rachel Maddow last night, and here is a link with suitable discussion of relevant facts from Dave Johnson, perhaps important as this silly sequester is about to land on us supposedly driven by the overwhelming need to get the deficit under control,<a href="http://blog.ourfuture.org/20130226/deficit-is-falling-dramatically-but-only-6-know-that">http://blog.ourfuture.org/20130226/deficit-is-falling-dramatically-but-only-6-know-that</a> .  As it is, apparently 62% think it is rising, while 28% think it is constant.  </p>
</div>
<div dir="ltr">Among things that the public is wrong about, this one sticks out for being so far off from the facts.  And as is noted, not only is the deficit declining, but it is doing so at a very dramatic rate.  Without doing anything we should be able to stabilize the debt/GDP ratio within about two to three years, although to maintain that down the road, further adjustments would need to be made.  Being an austerian is one thing, but being completely out of touch with reality is quite another.</div>
<p>Obama consistently cedes public opinion to the right by allowing the right to profoundly misinform the public about critical facts.  Why does he do this? </p>
<p>Last week, a day or two before the sequester took hold, he went to a town near a naval base in Virginia to stand among people who stood to lose their jobs or be furloughed temporarily from the sequester.  It was, of course, supposed to illustrate that the sequester would hurt the economy.  But most people don’t live near a military base and most people don’t work for a defense contractor.  </p>
<p>What he needed to do instead is what he’s needed to do all along: explain Keynesian economics; use statistics to show that a key reason why the economy has been so slow to recover is that governments at all levels have reduced their spending (state and local governments, dramatically); show the public, using charts and specifics, that the 2011 debt ceiling deal included huge spending cuts and no tax increases; and make clear what tax increases, and on whom and what, you are proposing (e.g., what loopholes you’re proposing to close).  </p>
<p>The only headway he’s made politically on this was from his one recent foray into meaningfully explaining some of this to the public, in a press conference in (I think) mid-January.  The centrist pundits were deeply offended by it, but it got enough publicity that the general public understood important facts that they did not before.  </p>
<p>I don’t expect that Obama will actually speak live on TV to the public during primetime for about 10 minutes (which is all it would take) to actually provide important information in a way that would reach a lot of people. That would be just so LBJ.  Or Ronald Reagan.  Or Bill Clinton.  Or George W. Bush.  It’s much better, or at least (apparently) a lot easier, to give away the store, because the centrist pundits will applaud.  So that is what I expect that Obama will decide to do, and what he will do if the Senate Dems allow it.  </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/john-dickerson-halts-this-weeks-nonsense-juggernaut-or-at-least-he-tries-to.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>John Boehner Lists Our Presidential Thieves&#8211;And Ronald Reagan Is Among Them!</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/john-boehner-lists-our-presidential-thieves-and-ronald-reagan-is-among-them.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/john-boehner-lists-our-presidential-thieves-and-ronald-reagan-is-among-them.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2013 19:09:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Ashley Parker]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bill Clinton]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Boehner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ronald Reagan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the 2014 elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The New York Times]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the sequester]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/john-boehner-lists-our-presidential-thieves-and-ronald-reagan-is-among-them.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[“The revenue issue is now closed,” Mr. Boehner said Thursday, before the House left town for the weekend without acting on the cuts and a Senate attempt to avert them died. Mr. Boehner said the dispute with Democrats amounted to a question of “how much more money do we want to steal from the American [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">“The revenue issue is now closed,” Mr. Boehner said Thursday, before the House left town for the weekend without acting on the cuts and a Senate attempt to avert them died. Mr. Boehner said the dispute with Democrats amounted to a question of “how much more money do we want to steal from the American people to fund more government.”</p>
</div>
<div dir="ltr">“I’m for no more,” he said.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <i><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/03/01/us/politics/house-republicans-cheer-boehners-refusal-to-negotiate-on-cuts.html?pagewanted=all&#038;_r=0">Boehner Halts Talks on Cuts, and House G.O.P. Cheers</a></i>, Ashley Parker, New York Times, today</div>
<p>So Ronald Reagan was a thief.  Who knew?  </p>
<p>And so, it&#8217;s now clear, was every president beginning with Abraham Lincoln.  Until George W. Bush, that is.  Teddy Roosevelt? Yup.  Calvin Coolidge? Uh-huh.  Harry Truman?  I guess that&#8217;s what they meant by &#8220;hell&#8221; that he was giving &#8217;em.  They each stole from the American people via income taxes to fund the federal government. </p>
<p>But since FDR was the one who initiated the stealing to pay for such specifics as Social Security, the Tennessee Valley Authority and other New Deal programs, we’ll start with him.  He also stole&#8211;a lot&#8211;from American people to pay for WWII.  </p>
<p>Dwight Eisenhower, JFK, LBJ, Richard Nixon, Gerald Ford, and Jimmy Carter perpetuated this theft. Big time.  Of course, Nixon, who assured the country that he was not a crook, did turn out to be one after all, so in retrospect, his theft from the American people was just in character.  And we knew all along that Dwight Eisenhower was the perpetrator of the theft from Americans that established a Soviet-style interstate highway system&#8211;or so Florida Rep. John Mica, the last Congress’s chairman of the House Transportation Committee, would describe <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/local/trafficandcommuting/amtrak-carried-record-passengers-i%20n-2012/2013/03/01/657cc2d0-81e8-11e2-a350-49866afab584_story.html?hpid=z">the socialist ownership</a> of the interstate highways. (That <i>is</i> the way he described Amtrak.  And he wasn&#8217;t talking about its slowness and disrepair.)*</p>
<p>That controversial statue of Eisenhower that’s planned for D.C. should be scratched, not because of its design, which his ancestors dislike, but because of his criminality.</p>
<p>LBJ, of course, stole a lot of money from American people in order to fund the Vietnam War, a theft that this country did pay a very high price for, although not in a lengthy prison sentence after indictment and conviction for grand larceny.  But if that weren’t bad enough&#8211;from a criminal-law standpoint, that is&#8211;he also stole lots of money to fund the student-loan program that helped so many baby boomers go to college and graduate school.  Some of them&#8211;the ones who became hedge fund managers, anyway&#8211;would now be in imminent danger of becoming crime victims themselves, rather than the beneficiaries of thefts past, but John  Boehner has infiltrated the den of thieves and had has called the FBI, which, luckily, still has some agents working full-time schedules, despite the sequester. </p>
<p>And we won’t even get into George H.W. Bush, who, as we all know, lost his reelection bid to Bill Clinton partly because he had firmly and repeatedly promised during his first campaign to not steal more from the American people than was already being stolen, only to turn around and rob the American people blind. Luckily, he son was available eight years later to provide restitution, although his Department of Justice never did indict his father.  </p>
<p>And, speaking of Bill Clinton&#8211;well, they didn’t call him Slick Willie for nothing, did they?</p>
<p>But Reagan? Reagan?  Et tu?  Yup.  I keep forgetting that tax rates were much higher during Reagan’s time as president then they are now, and that after lowering tax rates, he raised some.  He’s dead now, so he can’t be indicted.  And anyway, I think the statute of limitations has run.  Which is too bad.</p>
<p>But Bill Clinton is very much alive, and active.  And since Obama seems unwilling to rebut Boehner’s and other Republicans’ intended inferential misrepresentation that Obama’s and the congressional Democrats’ tax-increase proposals, now and the ones enacted as part of the “fiscal cliff” resolution in early January, would tax Americans other than Americans who are quite wealthy, or who have income from capital gains or dividends and who still pay taxes for that income at lower rates than during the Reagan or the Clinton era, or who are corporate Americans.  </p>
<p>The Republicans expect that they will get a majority of Americans to believe falsely that the Dems are proposing to raise their taxes.  If Obama remains mute instead of correcting this misrepresentation, Clinton should step in and do that.  He should hang the taxes-as-stealing statement around John Boehner’s neck, and then tighten the noose by answering the question Boehner posed: How much more money do we want to steal from the American people to fund more government?  He then should answer the questions, from which American people, and for what? And he should be specific.</p>
<p>But he also should ask this: Since when is it theft of Americans to institute tax increases that a majority of Americans who voted in the recent election actually specifically voted for? And he should point out that what Boehner really thinks the crime is is that public prefers that the federal government continue to fund Medicare and other social safety-net programs, as well as myriad other services, agencies and perks of being an American; the National Institutes of Health, the National Parks Service, FEMA, and the EPA come quickly to mind, but of course there are many others. </p>
<p>As criminality goes, the aggressive attempts to undermine the very nature of democratic government, through an unremitting series of stunts and use of bizarre language and concerted campaigns of disinformation, strike me as more serious ones than the theft of wealthy Americans through tax increases that would remain substantially lower than they were during most of the 20th Century.  </p>
<p>But, by all means, Speaker Boehner, bring on the theft language, again and again.  Keep it up, all the way through the 2014 midterm elections. Please. But if you don&#8217;t feel like it, hopefully the Dem congressional candidates will  pick up the slack and help you out with that, in their TV and Internet commercials.  </p>
<p>It should help them steal some elections.</p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />*<i>Parenthetical added after initial posting.</i></p>
<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/john-boehner-lists-our-presidential-thieves-and-ronald-reagan-is-among-them.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Dr. Richard Wolff on the Sequester</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/dr-richard-wolff-on-the-sequester.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/dr-richard-wolff-on-the-sequester.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2013 04:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[budget and tax proposal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[congress]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deficit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[President Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the sequester]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/dr-richard-wolff-on-the-sequester.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I watched  Dr. Wolff (Professor emeritus, UMass) on this past week  episode with Bill Moyers.   At the end of this show, Mr. Moyers invited the viewers to submit questions to Dr. Wolf who has agreed to return in a couple of weeks to answer them.  Here is he with an interview by Julianna Forlano of [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I watched  Dr. Wolff (Professor emeritus, UMass) on this past week  episode with<a href="http://billmoyers.com/episode/full-show-taming-capitalism-run-wild/" target="_blank"> Bill Moyers</a>.   At the end of this show, Mr. Moyers invited the viewers to submit questions to Dr. Wolf who has agreed to return in a couple of weeks to answer them.</p>
<p> Here is he with an interview by <a href="http://www.youtube.com/user/IronicNewsReport" target="_blank">Julianna Forlano</a> of Absurdity Today report.  If you are not familiar with Julianna, she does a very funny short news broadcast on the issues of the moment.  I am a subscriber.  It&#8217;s is worth your time for sure.</p>
<p>This is the first part of 4.  It is about 12 minutes.  I want to say, at the end, Dr. Wolff is also pointing out that the cuts do not come all at once.<br />       </p>
<p> I figure this video is also posted in response to the video rjs linked to in comments to <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/02/obamas-inexplicable-failure-to-explain.html" target="_blank">Bev&#8217;s post</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/dr-richard-wolff-on-the-sequester.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Obama’s Inexplicable Failure to Explain and Clarify What the Sequester IS&#8211;and What the Respective Sides Want to Replace It WITH.</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/obamas-inexplicable-failure-to-explain-and-clarify-what-the-sequester-is-and-what-the-respective-sides-want-to-replace-it-with.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/obamas-inexplicable-failure-to-explain-and-clarify-what-the-sequester-is-and-what-the-respective-sides-want-to-replace-it-with.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 27 Feb 2013 18:34:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Greg Sargent]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NBC/WSJ poll]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the sequester]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Washington Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/obamas-inexplicable-failure-to-explain-and-clarify-what-the-sequester-is-and-what-the-respective-sides-want-to-replace-it-with.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This is the political atmosphere within which the battle will unfold over who is to blame for the damage done by the sequester. Now, in fairness, Republicans are favored on the deficit and controlling government spending. But even here, when you drill down deeper, you find that fifty two percent say the automatic across the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">This is the political atmosphere within which the battle will unfold over who is to blame for the damage done by the sequester. Now, in fairness, Republicans are favored on the deficit and controlling government spending. But even here, when you drill down deeper, you find that fifty two percent say the automatic across the board cuts to the budget are a bad idea; only 21 percent say they’re a good idea. Republicans will take solace from the finding that a plurality wants the sequester replaced by a plan with “more cuts.” But the poll question doesn’t inform respondents of the option of replacing the sequester cuts in part with eliminating tax breaks enjoyed by the rich and corporations, an oversight that casts doubt on the value of this finding. Many surveys that accurately poll the two parties’ positions on curbing the deficit — cuts only versus a mix of cuts and new revenues — show a solid advantage for the Dem position.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; Greg Sargent, Washington Post, <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/plum-line/wp/2013/02/27/the-morning-plum-hows-that-gop-makeover-going/">discussing a newly released NBC/WSJ poll</a>, this morning</div>
<p>The poll’s failure to inform respondents of the option of replacing the sequester cuts in part with eliminating tax breaks enjoyed by the rich and corporations, and asking <i>only</i> about the <i>Republicans</i>’ replacement proposals, and doing so entirely generically, is &#8230; dismaying.  </p>
<p>But it would be so very, very easy for Obama to explain, in specifics, what that pollster couldn&#8217;t trouble itself to do, even slightly. After all, Boehner keeps proudly advertising the fact that the House twice passed a replacement bill late last year&#8211;although, of course, he doesn’t advertise the specifics; i.e., that the bill replaces all of the defense cuts with a gutting of virtually every other “discretionary spending” program and operation.  I.e., the bill replaces the sequester’s spending cuts with … much deeper spending cuts to almost everything except defense. All Obama has to do is <i>tell the public this</i>. </p>
<p>Does the public <i>really</i> want to replace the sequester’s cuts with “more cuts”?  Probably not, but when the sequester is incessantly billed as very bad, and the argument is that it should be replaced, and the only replacement option seemingly offered&#8211;at least by this pollster&#8211;is “more cuts,&#8221; generically speaking, of course, well, then, why yes! They want &#8220;more cuts&#8221;! Who wouldn&#8217;t?!  (A majority of the people who actually understand what this is about, and what the respective options are, probably.) </p>
<p>This is truly nonsense.  NBC and the WSJ might consider hiring a different polling organization next time.  But Obama might consider actually explaining the situation to the public.  The entire public&#8211;not just the public at a Virginia military base, to people who are among the few who already know.</p>
<p>Good grace.  I know that explaining anything complicated to the general public is not Obama’s thing.  But, I mean, really ….</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/obamas-inexplicable-failure-to-explain-and-clarify-what-the-sequester-is-and-what-the-respective-sides-want-to-replace-it-with.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Large Number of Hedge Fund Managers Near Fort Rucker, Ala. (A Suggested Response to the Republicans’ Simple Response(s).)</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/the-large-number-of-hedge-fund-managers-near-fort-rucker-ala-a-suggested-response-to-the-republicans-simple-responses.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/the-large-number-of-hedge-fund-managers-near-fort-rucker-ala-a-suggested-response-to-the-republicans-simple-responses.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Feb 2013 18:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Fort Rucker]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jim VandeHei]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Boehner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jonathan Weisman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mike Allen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politico]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rep. Martha Roby]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The New York Times]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the sequester]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Wall Street Journal]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/the-large-number-of-hedge-fund-managers-near-fort-rucker-ala-a-suggested-response-to-the-republicans-simple-responses.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[It’s unconscionable to use our military men and women in uniform as a bargaining chip to raise our taxes. &#8212; Rep. Martha Roby, (R. Ala.) Our taxes, huh?  Ours!  This actually is unexpectedly good financial news for most of, um, us. Not to mention very surprising news. According to The New York Times today, Roby [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">It’s unconscionable to use our military men and women in uniform as a bargaining chip to raise our taxes.</p>
</div>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; Rep. Martha Roby, (R. Ala.)</div>
<p>Our taxes, huh?  Ours!  This actually is unexpectedly <i>good</i> financial news for most of, um, <i>us</i>.  Not to mention very <i>surprising</i> news.</p>
<p>According to <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/21/us/politics/gop-resisting-obama-on-tax-increase.html?nl=todaysheadlines&#038;emc=edit_th_20130221&#038;_r=0&#038;pagewanted=all">The New York Times today</a>, Roby made the comment in an interview yesterday after a visit to the town just outside the Army’s Fort Rucker.  And presumably, she, and her family (thus, the &#8220;our&#8221; rather than a &#8220;my&#8221;), have substantial income from capital gains and dividends.  Or maybe she or her husband is a hedge fund manager and would lose the &#8220;carried-interest&#8221; tax deduction, because the tax loopholes that Obama and the congressional Dems are proposing to close are those and similar ones.  And she did say “raise our taxes.”  </p>
<p>Maybe <i>both</i> are hedge fund managers.  She part-time, of course.  </p>
<p>Maybe not, though, since, by using that phrase, she intended to convey, falsely, that Obama was using our military men and women in uniform as a bargaining chip to raise the taxes of the our military men and women in uniform, most of whom have spouses who are hedge fund managers, and of the residents of the town just outside of Fort Rucker, most of whom live off of their capital gains and dividends, and none of whom, whether working or unemployed, receive assistance from the the federal food-assistance program.  </p>
<p>I know that latter fact to be true because the New York Times article says that House Republicans say they believe that the have “politically inoculated themselves against claims they are responsible for the cuts by approving measures last year that would have substituted reductions in government programs like food stamps for the lower Pentagon spending.”</p>
<p>Which itself undoubtedly is true.  Especially since Mitt Romney and Paul Ryan ran on just such a proposal last fall, and won.  I mean, lost.  By about 5 million votes.  </p>
<p>The Republicans must have received their inoculation serum through the Web.  From a company in Afghanistan, maybe. </p>
<p>Roby also said in that interview referenced in the Times article:</p>
<div dir="ltr">The president says he has to have tax increases to head off the sequester. Well, he already got his tax increase. </div>
<p>Indeed, he did.  He got a tax increase on individuals with non-investment income of at least $400,000, and on couples with non-investment income of at least $450,000, to Clinton-era rates, and slight raises on some investment income, to less than Clinton-era rates.  Clinton-era rates being rates at which we were able to have a budget surplus, without using our military men and women in uniform as a bargaining chip  for anything, and without cutting food assistance programs, including the assistance that goes to Alabamans, a few of whom may live in that town near Fort Rucker.  </p>
<p>So, I have two suggestions for Obama.  Serious ones.  </p>
<p>Seriously.<br /><a name="more"></a><br />One is that he travel to that town near Fort Rucker and explain, among other things, that salaries for our men and women in uniform are exempt from the sequester, and that, while we’re on the subject, of unconscionable political conduct, it’s probably a good idea to include the dispensing of false information to the contrary as fitting comfortably within that category.  He also should explain to the group assembled in the audience at the high school gym, or wherever, who it is exactly that will have their taxes raised by the tax raises included in the “fiscal cliff” agreement, and, especially, who it is exactly&#8211;exactly&#8211;that would have their taxes raised under Obama’s proposal to replace the sequester.  </p>
<p>Then he should ask for a show of hands, first, by those in the audience who will have their taxes raised under the “fiscal cliff” deal, and then by those who would have their taxes raised under a current proposal to replace the sequester.  His own proposal or the Senate Democrats’ or the House Democrats’.  In other words, a show of hands by “us”&#8211;as in “raise our taxes.”  </p>
<p>He also could, and should, explain how, and why, the sequester law came about&#8211;and what would have happened to this country’s credit rating and the financial system and the economy beginning in August 2011 without it.  I.e., explain again, as he did at his successful press conference in mid-January, what the debt ceiling, and raising it, are.</p>
<p>Obama of course instead could make these points in a short primetime TV address, one advantage of which would be a national audience.  That&#8217;s my other suggestion.  He could do this in an address of under 10 minutes.  </p>
<p>If he took that avenue, he could even take advantage of the national audience to point out, within that under-10-minute address, that John Boehner wasn’t quite accurate when he said in <a href="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424127887323495104578314240032274944.html?mod=WSJ_Opinion_LEADTop">a Wall Street Journal op-ed</a> yesterday that: </p>
<div dir="ltr">[A]s the president&#8217;s outrage about the sequester grows in coming days, Republicans have a simple response: Mr. President, we agree that your sequester is bad policy. What spending are you willing to cut to replace it?</div>
<p>Yes, some&#8211;but not all&#8211;Republicans’ simple response is to fail to acknowledge that Obama is proposing replacing some of the sequester’s cuts with increased tax revenues achieved by closing tax loopholes on wealthy individuals and corporations.  Martha Roby is a Republican who does acknowledge this.  Her simple response is, rather than pretending that this is not so&#8211;that Obama has not proposed an offset by raising more revenue in the manner that he and the congressional Dems in fact have proposed&#8211;to instead misrepresent to all or most of her constituents that their (“our”) taxes would go up.  It&#8217;s a statement either unconscionably deliberately deceptive or instead reflecting dismaying ignorance of the sources and amounts of income of at least some, probably most, of her constituents, unless her district is among the wealthier ones in this country.* </p>
<p>Which, for all I know, it may be.  But if so, most of the residents of the town close to the Army base probably are not among the hedge fund managers in her district.  Nor even among the Apple shareholders. </p>
<p>Obama could of course both travel to the town near Fort Rucker and address the nation on primetime TV.  But only if the matter is really important.  Really important.  Which Obama may or may not think it is.  I mean … to each his own. </p>
<p>What I don’t understand about this White House is its failure to grasp that what matters is actual explanations and refutations of the Republicans’ incessant misrepresentations of fact&#8211;killing the Repubs’ constant representation of cliché  and generic slogans as facts&#8211;rather than silly <a href="http://dyn.politico.com/printstory.cfm?uuid=A22E8106-D4AF-436E-84DB-77354D107AA4">Twitter tweets, attractive photos of Obama at work or play, or appearances on The View or interviews on 60 Minutes</a> that do not explain substance and do not refute the opposition on issues of substance.</p>
<p>Actually, this one’s pretty easy to explain:  Raise our taxes?  Then the tax raise must also be on our income.  I guess we’re all hedge fund managers now.  (Seeee?  I <i>told</i> you this was good financial news for <i>us</i>.  Not to mention <i>surprising</i> financial news for <i>us</i>.  And surprising <i>employment</i> news for, well, at least those of <i>us</i> whose tax raise will come from the elimination of the &#8220;carried-interest&#8221; deduction.)</p>
<p>Of course, now that I think about it, that little explanation in that last paragraph would fit in a Twitter post.  So maybe Twitter’s the way to explain and refute, after all.  At least when you’re camera shy.  Or just shy.</p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />*<i>This paragraph was edited slightly for clarity, as were two or three sentences elsewhere.</i></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/the-large-number-of-hedge-fund-managers-near-fort-rucker-ala-a-suggested-response-to-the-republicans-simple-responses.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>John Boehner Should Travel More. To Australia.</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/john-boehner-should-travel-more-to-australia.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/john-boehner-should-travel-more-to-australia.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2013 21:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Greg Sargent]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Boehner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Marco Rubio]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Matthew Miller]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[minimum wage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Washington Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/john-boehner-should-travel-more-to-australia.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Yesterday, both sides drew their battle lines in the coming war over the minimum wage. After Obama called for a minimum wage hike in his State of the Union speech, House Republicans dug in against it, casting their opposition as grounded in concern for the plight of low wage workers. John Boehner asked: “Why would [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">Yesterday, both sides drew their battle lines in the coming war over the minimum wage. After Obama called for a minimum wage hike in his State of the Union speech, House Republicans dug in against it, casting their opposition as grounded in concern for the plight of low wage workers. John Boehner <a href="http://livewire.talkingpointsmemo.com/entry/boehner-shoots-down-obamas-minimum-wage-hike">asked</a>: “Why would we want to make it harder for small employers to hire people?”</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/plum-line/wp/2013/02/14/the-morning-plum-dems-to-use-minimum-wage-against-gop-in-2014/">Dems to use minimum wage against GOP in 2014</a>, Greg Sargent, Washington Post, this morning</div>
<p>To me, one of the great frustrations in Obama’s failure during most of his first term to communicate, effectively or at all, the basic premises of Keynesian and other liberal economics-related arguments (including on healthcare) was his apparent resistance to mentioning&#8211;early, often, or ever&#8211;specific other countries’ successes or failures that illustrate the point. </p>
<p>But there’s no time like the present for him and the congressional Dems to start to do do this, by maybe mentioning these facts: that Australia’s minimum wage is $15 U.S. and that its unemployment rate is 5.4%, and that the United States has (surprise!) the largest gap between the minimum wage and the median wage of any advanced economy in the world.</p>
<p>I learned those facts yesterday when I read Washington Post columnist <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/matt-miller-raise-the-minimum-wage/2013/02/06/34857264-7066-11e2-8b8d-e0b59a1b8e2a_story.html">Matthew Miller’s Feb. 6 column</a>.  He mentioned it and linked to it in <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/matt-miller-obamas-hollow-speech/2013/02/13/d928c944-75a5-11e2-95e4-6148e45d7adb_story.html">his column yesterday</a> about Obama’s State of the Union address.  In yesterday’s column, he suggested seemingly, facetiously, that it was his February 6 column that had persuaded Obama to include a minimum-wage-hike proposal in his address.  But after reading the earlier column, I suspect that it was not only what convinced Obama to make the call but also was what caused Obama to even think of it.  </p>
<p>Both of Miller’s columns say that the $9/hr. figure that Obama proposed in his speech would still leave the minimum wage at $1.68 below what the value of the minimum wage was in 1968.  The first column, Miller also mentions that several CEOs of large corporations support a rise in the minimum wage and that a prominent conservative, the editor of American Conservative magazine, suggests raising the minimum wage to $12/hr.  Of course, the Republicans will showcase their own CEOs, and some small-business owners, to support their own position.</p>
<p>Which is where Australia comes in.  Or at least where invoking it should come in. The special beauty of using Australia as an example&#8211;whether in support of an increase in the minimum wage or in refuting the Obamacare-is-socialism/makers-vs.-takers mantra&#8211;is that few Americans associate Australia with, um, socialism.  They associate it instead with free-enterprise economics and a high standard of living.  And soon, hopefully, also with a higher minimum wage that corresponds to a low unemployment rate.  </p>
<p>Maybe Marco Rubio and John Boehner could get a travel discount <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/02/marco-rubio-needs-to-travel-more.html">if they booked their reservations</a> together. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/john-boehner-should-travel-more-to-australia.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>This was the best State of the Union address in my memory.</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/this-was-the-best-state-of-the-union-address-in-my-memory.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/this-was-the-best-state-of-the-union-address-in-my-memory.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2013 04:54:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the State of the Union address]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/this-was-the-best-state-of-the-union-address-in-my-memory.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I’m so surprised, and so happy.  There were three or four lines in there early on that I was so happy about, and just so surprised at, that they they brought tears to my eyes.  And that last few minutes of the speech&#8211;the part that segued from voting rights to gun violence issues and victims, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’m so surprised, and so happy.  There were three or four lines in there early on that I was so happy about, and just so surprised at, that they they brought tears to my eyes.  And that last few minutes of the speech&#8211;the part that segued from voting rights to gun violence issues and victims, and back again to voting rights&#8211;was just plain magnificent.  </p>
<p>And as someone who repeatedly mocked the people-as-props thing here on AB during the last week, I have to say that this time it was done really beautifully.  The story of the 15-year-old high school majorette who returned home to the south side of Chicago from performing with her team at the inauguration, only to be gunned down randomly in a park near her home, had really grabbed me emotionally when I first read about it, and her mother’s presence there tonight was incredibly effective in illustrating the essential point.  And the live video of the 101-year-old Miami lady who waited in line for hours to vote was a moment I’ll remember for a long time.  </p>
<p>This was a beautiful speech, beautifully delivered.  </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/this-was-the-best-state-of-the-union-address-in-my-memory.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
