<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>aguanomics &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The political-economy of water…all in auctions</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/the-political-economy-of-waterall-in-auctions.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/the-political-economy-of-waterall-in-auctions.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 21 Dec 2012 17:16:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[aguanomics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[David Zetland. water economics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/the-political-economy-of-waterall-in-auctions.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[From David Zetland comes this re-posting from  Aguanomics on addressing issues in the political economy for  water. The political-economy of water&#8230;all in auctions I&#8217;ve been working on this idea for 5-6 years, and I think it has great potential for reallocating water while respecting the rights of existing users. It just came out in the Journal of Environmental [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>From David Zetland comes this re-posting from  <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/">Aguanomics</a> on addressing issues in the political economy for  water.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/12/all-in-auctions-is-published.html" target="_blank">The political-economy of water&#8230;all in auctions</a></p>
<p>I&#8217;ve been working on this idea for 5-6 years, and I think it has great potential for reallocating water while respecting the rights of existing users. It just came out in the <i>Journal of Environmental Management</i>. </p>
<p>Abstract: This paper proposes a novel mechanism for reallocating temporary water flows or permanent water rights. The All-in-Auction (AiA) increases efficiency and social welfare by reallocating water without harming water rights holders. AiAs can be used to allocate variable or diminished flows among traditional or new uses. AiAs are appropriate for use within larger organizations that distribute water among members, e.g., irrigation districts or wholesale water agencies. Members would decide when and how to use AiAs, i.e., when transaction costs are high, environmental constraints are binding, or allocation to outsiders is desired. Experimental sessions show that an AiA reallocates more units with no less efficiency that traditional two-sided auctions.</p>
<p>Those of you with an academic subscription can download it <a href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0301479712005956">here</a>. Those of you without can download my author&#8217;s copy [<a href="http://www.kysq.org/pubs/AiA_Final.pdf">pdf</a>]</p>
<p>Here&#8217;s <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2011/10/all-in-auctions-video.html">an earlier post</a> that links to other presentations of the AiA.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/the-political-economy-of-waterall-in-auctions.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Watch Donald. He&#8217;s worth your time</title>
		<link>./../../2012/08/watch-donald-hes-worth-your-time.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/08/watch-donald-hes-worth-your-time.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 25 Aug 2012 13:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[aguanomics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[David Zetland]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[math]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/08/watch-donald-hes-worth-your-time.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Via David Zetland&#8217;s Aguanomics comes this reminder (1959) of &#8216;why math is fun&#8217; worked for kids.  He didn&#8217;t see it till taking calculus.  Can you imagine it being produced now?]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Via David Zetland&#8217;s <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/" target="_blank">Aguanomics</a> comes this reminder (1959) of &#8216;why math is fun&#8217; worked for kids.  He didn&#8217;t see it till taking calculus.  Can you imagine it being produced now?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/08/watch-donald-hes-worth-your-time.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Miya Water&#8217;s quest to plug leaks</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/miya-waters-quest-to-plug-leaks.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/miya-waters-quest-to-plug-leaks.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 24 Jul 2012 13:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[agriculture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[aguanomics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[David Zetland]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[urban water]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[water]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/miya-waters-quest-to-plug-leaks.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Via David Zetland&#8217;s Aguanomics. I continue to follow David&#8217;s thinking on how to plan, price, and ultimately use water in a 21st century manner. He offers interesting notions on the roles of government/pricing (and markets). There is currently big bucks involved and only to grow in importance and critical decisions to be made. Water is [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Via David Zetland&#8217;s <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2011/07/miya-waters-quest-to-plug-leaks.html" target="_blank">Aguanomics</a>.  I continue to follow David&#8217;s thinking on how to plan, price, and ultimately use water in a 21st century manner.  He offers interesting notions on the roles of government/pricing (and markets).  There is currently big bucks involved and only to grow in importance and critical decisions to be made.  Water is also an intensely watershed based arena (local) except when it is not. Re-posted with permission.</p>
<p>Miya Water&#8217;s quest to plug leaks</p>
<p>While in Jerusalem, I had the opportunity to speak with Tami Gaoni Feldman of <a href="http://www.miya-water.com/">Miya Water</a>.     <br />Her company is in the business of reducing non-revenue water (NRW), or water that goes into pipes but never <strike>reaches a customer&#8217;s meter</strike> gets paid for.<br />    <br />Well-managed water systems might have a NRW rate of 5 percent (due to fire hydrants, flushing the system, minor leaks, etc.). In a poorly-managed and maintained system, NRW rates range from 40 to 90 percent. The most common causes of high NRW rates are theft of water, non-payment of bills, leaking pipes and miscalibrated meters.<br />    <br /><a href="http://www.ib-net.org/">IBNET</a> tracks NRW rates for about 2,000 utilities.<br />    <br />Tami told me that Miya is working with one of two utilities in Manila, where the 300 staffers in the NRW division tackle 100 leaks per day and overall system losses of 300 ML per day (about 240 acre feet per day). Miya has had some success so far in reducing NRW from 67 to 50 percent.     <br />Miya uses three main tools to reduce NRW: monitor and fix leaks, manage system pressure to reduce leaks in low-demand periods (middle of the night), and increase payment for services. As a first step, Miya makes sure there are water meters at big junctions, to make it easier to track down branches with high 24/7 baseline use.<br />  <br /><a name="more"></a>  <br />These technical details were interesting, but Miya faces an additional problem: water managers and politicians facing water shortages prefer to increase supply (via desalination, reclamation, groundwater pumping, etc.) instead of reducing NRW losses.<br />     <br />This behavior does not make sense from a cost-benefit perspective. A decent NRW program will increase revenue per unit of treated water pumped into the system. Those revenues mean that NRW programs &#8220;pay for themselves.&#8221;<br />     <br />I hate to say it, but this feature is even more attractive than my &#8220;raise prices&#8221; recommendation: it&#8217;s an engineering solution (water managers like those) that will not increase prices (politicians like those).     <br />So why is it hard for Miya to sell its services?<br />     <br />I see two main reasons. First, a good NRW program requires up-front financing to pay for staff, software, meters, and so on. For most cash-strapped utilities, additional money is hard to come by. So why not get a loan from a bank or development agency? Because (according to Tami, but within my understanding) bankers are not familiar with NRW programs. They are more comfortable with making loans on physical assets like desalination plants that can be pledged as collateral.<br />     <br />Now stop and think about this for a second. What happens if a water utility fails to repay a loan on a NRW program? There&#8217;s no collateral to grab. What happens if it fails to repay a loan on a plant? Yes, there&#8217;s collateral, but then what? Are the bankers going to drag a plant from Dhaka back to Geneva? So the &#8220;collateral excuse&#8221; is hollow.<br />     <br />That leaves conservatism and one other excuse: managers and politicians <i>like</i> new facilities that they can pose in front of, cut ribbons for, etc. There&#8217;s no photo opportunity at a non-leaking pipe.    <br />We couldn&#8217;t think of any other reasons, but maybe you can.<br />    <br />Until then, I will conclude that NRW reduction programs are an underutilized method of improving utility performance.<br />    <br />Bottom Line: Every water utility should have a program to track, report and reduce its NRW rate &#8212; for its financial stability, environmental stability, and the good of its customers</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/miya-waters-quest-to-plug-leaks.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Full cost pricing, the poor, or both?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/05/full-cost-pricing-the-poor-or-both.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/05/full-cost-pricing-the-poor-or-both.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 08 May 2012 11:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[aguanomics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[David Zetland]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/05/full-cost-pricing-the-poor-or-both.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by David Zetlandreposted with permission from Aguanomics Full cost pricing, the poor, or both?On 19 April in Berlin, I joined a debate in favor of the following proposition: Is cost recovery pricing the best way to ensure the poor have access to good water services? I was seconded by Dr William Muhairwe, Managing Director of [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by<strong> David Zetland</strong><br />reposted with permission from <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2011/05/full-cost-pricing-poor-or-both.html">Aguanomics</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2011/05/full-cost-pricing-poor-or-both.html">Full cost pricing, the poor, or both?</a>On 19 April in Berlin, I joined a debate in <i>favor</i> of the following proposition: <br />
<blockquote>Is cost recovery pricing the best way to ensure the poor have access to good water services?</p></blockquote>
<p>I was seconded by Dr William Muhairwe, Managing Director of the NWSC Uganda.  <br />Arguing against full cost pricing were Wenonah Hauter (Executive Director of Food and Water Watch) and Anil Naidoo (Blue Planet Project Organizer for the Council of Canadians). Wenonah and Anil are colleagues of Maude Barlow.*  </p>
<p>The conference used the provocative URL of &#8220;<a href="http://www.watermeetsmoney.com/">water meets money</a>,&#8221; and that name alone was enough to attract <a href="http://www.globalwaterintel.com/insight/water-meets-money-meets-street-protest.html">15-20 anti-corporate greed protestors</a> (there were about 450 attendees at the conference).** Their attendance was particularly ironic, since it was corporate money that upgraded Berlin&#8217;s water system over the past ten years (at lower cost than was expected of the previous, public-only management).  </p>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />We won the debate. That was not such a surprise with a crowd that has fought to get adequate money for water services. What I thought interesting was the way that Wenonah and Anil chose to argue their position.  </p>
<p>Rather than pay attention to the ongoing failures of water service, governance and political leadership in places where the poor lack water service, they claimed that corporations should pay more taxes. Although it sounded like they were presenting talking points instead of responding to the position that William and I presented, I guess that they were thinking that this pot of money combined with the UN-backed human right to water would deliver services. But their argument was weak on several levels:  
<ol>
<li>They failed to address governance failures. </li>
<li>They failed to acknowledge successes of full cost pricing in places like Uganda (and many others). </li>
<li>They failed to consider how higher tax revenues on corporations (should they even be collected!) would somehow get to water providers, and THEN support water services to the poor.</li>
</ol>
<p>I concentrated on two points:  
<ol>
<li>Subsidies to the poor (via income transfers or even <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2009/05/fixed-and-variable-costs-redux.html">some for free, pay for more</a> water prices) are not incompatible with full cost pricing within a water utility. </li>
<li>Subsides from the central government (or aid agencies) are unstable and come with strings attached. Given the problems that governments face (from the US to India), it seems folly to link water services to political games that would rank water way down the list of priorities.***</li>
</ol>
<p>My partner, William, presented even stronger points. He spoke from experience of delivering water to the largest cities in Uganda. Compared to him, Anil sounded way more &#8220;let&#8217;s sing kumbaya, guys&#8221; than realistic.   </p>
<p>But don&#8217;t believe me, listen to the whole debate <a href="http://www.globalwaterintel.com/great-water-debate-2011/">here</a> [<a href="http://www.kysq.org/docs/2011.04.19_Great_water_debate.mp3">MP3 backup</a>]. The first few minutes of my statement were not recorded. Here are <a href="http://www.kysq.org/docs/Zetland_outline.pdf">my notes</a> [pdf]; I didn&#8217;t use them all.    </p>
<p>Wenonah also made some funny claims about my previous ideas (she totally misunderstood all-in-auctions and called me a Stalinist for my idea of pricing water per person). <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/wenonah-hauter/the-next-big-thing-in-ind_b_854796.html%20">Here&#8217;s her take</a> on the debate, which includes the classic line &#8220;&#8230;is it any surprise that we lost 75% to 25%? Anyway, Anil and I knew we won the debate on the merits and ethics of our arguments.&#8221; Sounds like something that Gaddafi, Mugabe or Mubarak would say (as defenders of Their People).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/05/full-cost-pricing-the-poor-or-both.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The water data hub is LIVE!</title>
		<link>./../../2012/03/the-water-data-hub-is-live.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/03/the-water-data-hub-is-live.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2012 15:17:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[agriculture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[aguanomics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[urban water]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[water]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/03/the-water-data-hub-is-live.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Who gets water at what prices in the US still appears to be considered a local issue in the US at its core, and at best regional during droughts that cross borders or as it pertains to agricultural use and &#8216;retail&#8217; (cities and burbs).  The issue of private versus public ownership is not very visible [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Who gets water at what prices in the US still appears to be considered a local issue in the US at its core, and at best regional during droughts that cross borders or as it pertains to agricultural use and &#8216;retail&#8217; (cities and burbs).</p>
<p> The issue of private versus public ownership is <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/search?q=drought+2007" target="_blank">not very visible yet in US news</a>, nor our need to <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2010/12/water.html" target="_blank">repair our infrastructure</a> (see my series on water  <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/search?q=water" target>links to Part 1-5</a>) .  And our friends in Texas haven&#8217;t sent any recent alerts to me on their current problems (have any of us followed any other drought concerns on the national stage?).  Water distribution questions did actually make national news in 2007/2008 droughts along the east coast and southwest but quickly disappeared.  However, the fault lines on who has access to water, news on how we actually obtain fresh water,  and questions on price structures became quite sharp and very legal in a only a year or two.</p>
<p>The question on an international scale remains largely invisible to US and perhaps is time to revisit.  The IMF and World Trade Organization ownership rules are considered arcane and not relevant unless it involves the occasional town water supply and a company like Nestle&#8217;s.</p>
<p>Ian Wren and David Zetland have begun the <a href="http://waterdatahub.org/">Water Data Hub</a> to help centralize primary source material worldwide.  The authors announced the hub to help centralize data at David&#8217;s <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/03/water-data-hub-is-live.html" title="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/03/water-data-hub-is-live.html">Aguanomics</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>I&#8217;ve been looking for a centralized source of water data for over a year, a place where I could go to find data on any kind of water question.</p>
<p>Although that quest led me to <a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=ibnet&#038;sitesearch=aguanomics.com#hl=en&#038;sclient=psy-ab&#038;q=ibnet%7Cib-net+site:aguanomics.com&#038;oq=ibnet%7Cib-net+site:aguanomics.com&#038;aq=f&#038;aqi=&#038;aql=1&#038;gs_sm=3&#038;gs_upl=13081l14906l0l15625l7l7l0l0l0l0l67l364l7l7l0&#038;gs_l=serp.3...13081l14906l0l15625l7l7l0l0l0l0l67l364l7l7l0.efis.1.&#038;pbx=1&#038;bav=on.2,or.r_gc.r_pw.r_cp.r_qf.,cf.osb&#038;fp=c0e94774f9e948be&#038;biw=1480&#038;bih=835">IBNET</a> &#8212; a fantastic resource on water utility data in many countries &#8212; I was unable to find a good centralized index of water data.    <br />Even more depressing, I was unable to get any interest or support out of organizations (USGS, World Bank, OECD, et al.) whose missions might imply support for just such an idea.</p>
<p>So, I decided to set up my own water data hub (WDH) &#8212; a central location that links to water data, no matter where it is, who owns it, or what dimension of water it describes.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Last November, I <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2011/11/bleg-drupal-programmer.html">asked for help</a> on this project, and Ian Wren (from San Francisco) joined me.</p>
<p>It&#8217;s thanks to Ian&#8217;s hard work (weekends and evenings!) that I can now invite you to visit <a href="http://waterdatahub.org/">waterdatahub.org</a>!</p>
<p>So, please go there and <i>add</i> data sources. The WDH, like <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/03/how-networks-grow-and-then-shrink-in.html">any network</a>, gains value with the number of links.</p>
<p>Oh, and don&#8217;t forget that <i>anyone</i> can add a link to the hub. You only need a <a href="http://waterdatahub.org/user/register">WDH account</a> (free and easy to set up). So, go ahead and add your favorite data source from the World Bank, Exxon-Mobile, the Nature Conservancy, et al.</p>
<p>Note by my wording that the WDH does <i>not</i> host, own or control data. It&#8217;s basically an index of data controlled by other organizations.<br />  <br />The big goal <i>now</i> is to make a census of data, so that we know what exists, what&#8217;s missing and what overlaps.<br />Future developments:
<ul>
<li>WDH 1.1: You can add records for data that exist but are not available to the public. This will make it easier to contact data owners to ask for access and &#8212; hopefully &#8212; to pressure them to release it to the public.</li>
<li>WDH 1.2: Anyone can comment on the <i>quality</i> of data sources held elsewhere; this will help everyone understand the uses and limitations of data &#8212; information that is not necessarily available from data owners.</li>
<li>WDH 2.0 (2013): We will start the very difficult process of &#8220;normalizing&#8221; data from many sources (using translation tables) to make it possible to assemble a data table from 2+ sources linked to the WDH.</li>
</ul>
<p>Note that the WDH will make it easier for <i>anyone</i> who analyzes data to do their job; analysis is too difficult to automate.</p>
<p>As you might expect, I am running WDH as a stand-alone, academic, non-profit. At the moment, we do not need money as much as your <i>time</i>.</p>
<p>Bottom Line: Please add new spokes to the WDH (get it?) and tell others about the water data hub.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/03/the-water-data-hub-is-live.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
