<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>John Boehner &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>John Boehner says “we do not have an immediate debt crisis.”</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/john-boehner-says-we-do-not-have-an-immediate-debt-crisis.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/john-boehner-says-we-do-not-have-an-immediate-debt-crisis.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2013 12:14:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[federal debt]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[federal deficit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Boehner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rand Paul]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/john-boehner-says-we-do-not-have-an-immediate-debt-crisis.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Via Salon, David Sirota points to statements by John Boehner and Rand Paul: America owes this debt of gratitude to Boehner after he finally came clean on yesterday’s edition of ABC’s “This Week” and admitted that “we do not have an immediate debt crisis.” (His admission was followed up by Budget Committee Chairman Paul Ryan, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Via <i>Salon</i>, <a href="http://www.salon.com/2013/03/18/boehners_debt_confession_reveals_gops_intentions/" title="http://www.salon.com/2013/03/18/boehners_debt_confession_reveals_gops_intentions/">David Sirota</a> points to statements by John Boehner and Rand Paul:</p>
<blockquote><p>America owes this debt of gratitude to Boehner after he finally came clean on yesterday’s edition of <a href="http://www.realclearpolitics.com/video/2013/03/17/boehner_agrees_with_obama_we_do_not_have_an_immediate_debt_crisis.html">ABC’s “This Week”</a> and admitted that “we do not have an immediate debt crisis.” (His admission was followed up by Budget Committee Chairman Paul Ryan, who quickly echoed much the same sentiment on <a href="http://www.mediaite.com/tv/paul-ryan-tells-cbs-bob-schieffer-we-do-not-have-a-debt-crisis/">CBS’ Face the Nation</a>).</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/john-boehner-says-we-do-not-have-an-immediate-debt-crisis.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>John Boehner Needs a Dictionary</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/john-boehner-needs-a-dictionary.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/john-boehner-needs-a-dictionary.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2013 17:14:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Greg Sargent]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Boehner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mainstream-journalism gimmickry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitch McConnell]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[semantics gimmickry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Washington Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/john-boehner-needs-a-dictionary.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[All of these bipartisan discussions are encouraging, and Republicans hope they will lead to real solutions that help American families. But presidential leadership is really what’s needed. By shifting the focus from charm to courage, and eventually action, we can guarantee our children a future where everyone has the opportunity to find work and pursue [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">All of these bipartisan discussions are encouraging, and Republicans hope they will lead to real solutions that help American families. But presidential leadership is really what’s needed. By shifting the focus from charm to courage, and eventually action, we can guarantee our children a future where everyone has the opportunity to find work and pursue their piece of the American dream. That would be the grandest bargain of all.</div>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/john-boehner-obamas-intraparty-problem/2013/03/13/455e097e-8c19-11e2-b63f-f53fb9f2fcb4_story.html">Obama’s outreach is nice, but where’s the leadership?</a>, John Boehner, Op-ed, Washington Post, today</div>
<p>I have what I think is a better question, this one for the speaker: Where’s a dictionary?</p>
<p>One of the most pernicious aspects of these phony, sequential fiscal crises is, in my opinion, the Republicans’ tactic of selecting single words or short phrases that have an appealing meaning and using them to mean something else entirely&#8211;often something the opposite of what the word or phrase actually means.  It’s so clearly concerted, political-consultant-suggested, Madison Avenue-type sales gimmickry; every few days there’s a new messaging word or short phrase, redefined or otherwise-misleadingly used, and then repeated, repeated, repeated … repeated.   </p>
<p>Enter “leadership.”  And now, “courage.”  As in: the president should demonstrate these qualities by delegating to the Tea Party the fiscal policy of the United States, because the Tea Party is now the Republican Party and it wants to disassemble the federal government <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/plum-line/wp/2013/03/14/the-morning-plum-wheres-the-leadership-john-boehner/">and will settle for nothing less</a>.* </p>
<p>So I suggest that Obama offer Boehner a dictionary and ask him to point to where it defines leadership as abdication, and courage as cowering.  Whether you’re the president or, say, the Speaker of the House.  </p>
<p>Maybe more to the point, where in the dictionary definition of either leadership or courage does it define those words as including doing absolutely whatever is necessary to keep your position as House speaker, regardless of the consequences to the country you took an oath of office to serve?  Neither the Merriam-Webster’s nor the Oxford English limits those terms to references to the president of the United States.  The definitions do look broad enough to include the speaker.  And even the Senate minority leader.  Even ones who are petrified (literally, it appears from the look on his face these days) of being “primaried” by a Tea Party candidate.  </p>
<p>The Orwellian redefinition of words to mean the opposite of, or at least something entirely different than, their actual meaning is a standard propaganda and subterfuge tool of dictatorships. Mao Tse-tung was infamous for this.  And so, of course, was Hitler.  (The inscription in German, “Work will make you free,” remains above the front gate of Auschwitz in Oswiecim, Poland, a permanent reminder of the deeply sinister nature of extreme semantics games employed in the service of political propaganda.) </p>
<p>That so much of the proud-centrist punditry and fair-and-balanced mainstream media have assisted Boehner &#038; Friends in their sophistry in the last month is inexcusable, if no longer surprising.  If they agree with Boehner that the Ryan budget will guarantee our children a future where everyone has the opportunity to find work and pursue their piece of the American dream, then they should explain why.  If they believe instead that the Ryan budget will guarantee our children a future in which <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ayn_Rand">Atlas really </a><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ayn_Rand">has</a><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ayn_Rand"> shrugged and everyone lives inside The Fountainhead</a> (or maybe in the Pakistan of North America), then they should say that, and explain why. At least the news analysis writers and the centrist pundits should. </p>
<p>They won’t.  But maybe a few of them will point out that, with due respect to Mr. Boehner, the grandest bargain of all would be a free Webster’s Collegiate delivered to the Speaker’s office on Capitol Hill. </p>
<p>As for Obama, he got lucky in the last two days.  The Ryan budget will disabuse a clear majority of the next poll responders that the GOP should be trusted with determining what cuts to make to the federal budget, and when.  At least if the public actually learns the specifics.  (That, of course, would have been true for the last few years, had Obama deigned to apprise the public of the specifics.)  And the live &#8220;tweets&#8221; from the Republican House-member attendees during their meeting with him yesterday were so vile that Obama really needs now only to recite a few of them in order to fully open the public&#8217;s eyes, if and when he decides to speak to the public about the actual situation.  </p>
<p>And, who knows?  Maybe he will, now that he&#8217;s checked off the extend-an-olive-branch box on the mainstream press&#8217;s list of what Leaders (if not necessarily Courageous ones) do, and therefore may even have their permission to do so.</p>
<p>*See Greg Sargent&#8217;s terrific Morning Plum column in today&#8217;s Washington Post.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/john-boehner-needs-a-dictionary.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>John Boehner Lists Our Presidential Thieves&#8211;And Ronald Reagan Is Among Them!</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/john-boehner-lists-our-presidential-thieves-and-ronald-reagan-is-among-them.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/john-boehner-lists-our-presidential-thieves-and-ronald-reagan-is-among-them.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2013 19:09:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Ashley Parker]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bill Clinton]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Boehner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ronald Reagan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the 2014 elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The New York Times]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the sequester]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/john-boehner-lists-our-presidential-thieves-and-ronald-reagan-is-among-them.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[“The revenue issue is now closed,” Mr. Boehner said Thursday, before the House left town for the weekend without acting on the cuts and a Senate attempt to avert them died. Mr. Boehner said the dispute with Democrats amounted to a question of “how much more money do we want to steal from the American [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">“The revenue issue is now closed,” Mr. Boehner said Thursday, before the House left town for the weekend without acting on the cuts and a Senate attempt to avert them died. Mr. Boehner said the dispute with Democrats amounted to a question of “how much more money do we want to steal from the American people to fund more government.”</p>
</div>
<div dir="ltr">“I’m for no more,” he said.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <i><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/03/01/us/politics/house-republicans-cheer-boehners-refusal-to-negotiate-on-cuts.html?pagewanted=all&#038;_r=0">Boehner Halts Talks on Cuts, and House G.O.P. Cheers</a></i>, Ashley Parker, New York Times, today</div>
<p>So Ronald Reagan was a thief.  Who knew?  </p>
<p>And so, it&#8217;s now clear, was every president beginning with Abraham Lincoln.  Until George W. Bush, that is.  Teddy Roosevelt? Yup.  Calvin Coolidge? Uh-huh.  Harry Truman?  I guess that&#8217;s what they meant by &#8220;hell&#8221; that he was giving &#8217;em.  They each stole from the American people via income taxes to fund the federal government. </p>
<p>But since FDR was the one who initiated the stealing to pay for such specifics as Social Security, the Tennessee Valley Authority and other New Deal programs, we’ll start with him.  He also stole&#8211;a lot&#8211;from American people to pay for WWII.  </p>
<p>Dwight Eisenhower, JFK, LBJ, Richard Nixon, Gerald Ford, and Jimmy Carter perpetuated this theft. Big time.  Of course, Nixon, who assured the country that he was not a crook, did turn out to be one after all, so in retrospect, his theft from the American people was just in character.  And we knew all along that Dwight Eisenhower was the perpetrator of the theft from Americans that established a Soviet-style interstate highway system&#8211;or so Florida Rep. John Mica, the last Congress’s chairman of the House Transportation Committee, would describe <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/local/trafficandcommuting/amtrak-carried-record-passengers-i%20n-2012/2013/03/01/657cc2d0-81e8-11e2-a350-49866afab584_story.html?hpid=z">the socialist ownership</a> of the interstate highways. (That <i>is</i> the way he described Amtrak.  And he wasn&#8217;t talking about its slowness and disrepair.)*</p>
<p>That controversial statue of Eisenhower that’s planned for D.C. should be scratched, not because of its design, which his ancestors dislike, but because of his criminality.</p>
<p>LBJ, of course, stole a lot of money from American people in order to fund the Vietnam War, a theft that this country did pay a very high price for, although not in a lengthy prison sentence after indictment and conviction for grand larceny.  But if that weren’t bad enough&#8211;from a criminal-law standpoint, that is&#8211;he also stole lots of money to fund the student-loan program that helped so many baby boomers go to college and graduate school.  Some of them&#8211;the ones who became hedge fund managers, anyway&#8211;would now be in imminent danger of becoming crime victims themselves, rather than the beneficiaries of thefts past, but John  Boehner has infiltrated the den of thieves and had has called the FBI, which, luckily, still has some agents working full-time schedules, despite the sequester. </p>
<p>And we won’t even get into George H.W. Bush, who, as we all know, lost his reelection bid to Bill Clinton partly because he had firmly and repeatedly promised during his first campaign to not steal more from the American people than was already being stolen, only to turn around and rob the American people blind. Luckily, he son was available eight years later to provide restitution, although his Department of Justice never did indict his father.  </p>
<p>And, speaking of Bill Clinton&#8211;well, they didn’t call him Slick Willie for nothing, did they?</p>
<p>But Reagan? Reagan?  Et tu?  Yup.  I keep forgetting that tax rates were much higher during Reagan’s time as president then they are now, and that after lowering tax rates, he raised some.  He’s dead now, so he can’t be indicted.  And anyway, I think the statute of limitations has run.  Which is too bad.</p>
<p>But Bill Clinton is very much alive, and active.  And since Obama seems unwilling to rebut Boehner’s and other Republicans’ intended inferential misrepresentation that Obama’s and the congressional Democrats’ tax-increase proposals, now and the ones enacted as part of the “fiscal cliff” resolution in early January, would tax Americans other than Americans who are quite wealthy, or who have income from capital gains or dividends and who still pay taxes for that income at lower rates than during the Reagan or the Clinton era, or who are corporate Americans.  </p>
<p>The Republicans expect that they will get a majority of Americans to believe falsely that the Dems are proposing to raise their taxes.  If Obama remains mute instead of correcting this misrepresentation, Clinton should step in and do that.  He should hang the taxes-as-stealing statement around John Boehner’s neck, and then tighten the noose by answering the question Boehner posed: How much more money do we want to steal from the American people to fund more government?  He then should answer the questions, from which American people, and for what? And he should be specific.</p>
<p>But he also should ask this: Since when is it theft of Americans to institute tax increases that a majority of Americans who voted in the recent election actually specifically voted for? And he should point out that what Boehner really thinks the crime is is that public prefers that the federal government continue to fund Medicare and other social safety-net programs, as well as myriad other services, agencies and perks of being an American; the National Institutes of Health, the National Parks Service, FEMA, and the EPA come quickly to mind, but of course there are many others. </p>
<p>As criminality goes, the aggressive attempts to undermine the very nature of democratic government, through an unremitting series of stunts and use of bizarre language and concerted campaigns of disinformation, strike me as more serious ones than the theft of wealthy Americans through tax increases that would remain substantially lower than they were during most of the 20th Century.  </p>
<p>But, by all means, Speaker Boehner, bring on the theft language, again and again.  Keep it up, all the way through the 2014 midterm elections. Please. But if you don&#8217;t feel like it, hopefully the Dem congressional candidates will  pick up the slack and help you out with that, in their TV and Internet commercials.  </p>
<p>It should help them steal some elections.</p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />*<i>Parenthetical added after initial posting.</i></p>
<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/john-boehner-lists-our-presidential-thieves-and-ronald-reagan-is-among-them.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mitch McConnell Says the Congressional Republican Caucuses Are “The American People.” Got That, American People?</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/mitch-mcconnell-says-the-congressional-republican-caucuses-are-the-american-people-got-that-american-people.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/mitch-mcconnell-says-the-congressional-republican-caucuses-are-the-american-people-got-that-american-people.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2013 18:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Greg Sargent]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Boehner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mainstream-journalism gimmickry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Michael D. Shear]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitch McConnell]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The New York Times]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Washington Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/mitch-mcconnell-says-the-congressional-republican-caucuses-are-the-american-people-got-that-american-people.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[[O]ne thing Americans simply will not accept is another tax increase to replace spending reductions we already agreed to. &#8212; Senate Minority Leader Mitch McConnell, yesterday He’s right, of course, since, by “Americans,” he means the roughly 278 Americans who comprise the House and Senate Republican caucuses.   As Greg Sargent points out this morning, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">[O]ne thing Americans simply will not accept is another tax increase to replace spending reductions we already agreed to.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; Senate Minority Leader Mitch McConnell, <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/28/us/politics/white-house-believes-gop-will-bend-as-cuts-take-hold.html?pagewanted=all">yesterday</a></div>
<p>He’s right, of course, since, by “Americans,” he means the roughly 278 Americans who comprise the House and Senate Republican caucuses.  </p>
<p>As Greg Sargent <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/plum-line/wp/2013/02/28/the-morning-plum-how-both-sides-really-view-the-sequester/">points out</a> this morning, a recent Pew poll suggests that about ¾ of the remainder of Americans&#8211;the ones who are not among the “we” who already agreed to tax rate increases on couples with incomes of more than $450,000 and individuals with incomes of more that $400,000&#8211;actually beg to differ with Sen. McConnell on that assessment of what the American people will ever accept. </p>
<p>So, obviously, McConnell doesn’t mean those American people.  Even assuming that those American people are even Americans.  Or even people.  (No one’s polls corporate people, as far as I know, but I suspect that many of them would side with McConnell, so we’ll give him that. But that doesn’t meant that the Americans who were polled were people.  They may be cyborgs.  <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/02/an-organization-that-provides-food.html">Or dogs</a>.) </p>
<p>He also doesn’t mean the American people who voted by a majority of about 5 million last November for the presidential candidate who campaigned on a platform of raising tax rates on incomes of more than $250,000 for couples and $250,000 for individuals, and on closing tax loopholes and eliminating deductions available mostly to the wealthy.  Rest assured; he <i>definitely</i> does not mean those American people, most of whom committed voter fraud by voting in the election, since although they are people, they are, by virtue of their vote for Obama, not really Americans, whether or not they were born in Hawaii (or California or New York or New Mexico or New Hampshire) or instead in Kenya.  </p>
<p>Nor does he mean the American people who voted by substantial aggregate majorities to decrease rather than increase the number of Republican senators and representatives in the current Congress&#8211;a Congress whose members are not, by the way, the “we” in the “we already agreed to.” </p>
<p>The article I linked to above for that quote is one by Michael D. Shear in today’s New York Times, called “White House Counts on G.O.P. to Bend as Cuts’ Effects Are Felt.”  It’s chock full of great points, including that “[s]trategists for [John] Boehner believe that Republicans have been successful in branding the cuts as Mr. Obama’s idea.”  I hope so, since proposal of  “the cuts” at issue were the only alternative to a Republican-forced default on America’s already-incurred debt, including on treasury bonds, and since the cuts that were Obama’s idea probably are more popular than the cuts that are the Republicans’ idea-none to the Defense Department’s budget and draconian ones to almost every other discretionary program and agency.  </p>
<p>Which brings me to the newest journalistic gimmick in reporting on all this.  Well, I’ll just quote Shear illustrate: </p>
<div dir="ltr">In accepting the inevitability of an extended Washington stalemate, the White House is risking the possibility that Americans may eventually blame the president, not members of Congress, for job losses, smaller paychecks, longer lines at airports, a reduction in government services and a less well-equipped military.</div>
<p>Uh-huh.  The White House is risking the possibility that Americans may eventually blame the president, not members of Congress, for job losses, smaller paychecks, longer lines at airports, a reduction in government services and a less well-equipped military.  And the likelihood that that will happen is very high, since the Republicans are unwilling to trade more tax revenue from the wealthy and from profits-hoarding corporations for fewer job losses, no reduction in paychecks, ordinary-length lines at airports, little or no reduction in government services and a well-equipped military.  </p>
<p>Er, I mean, the American people are unwilling to make that trade.  But they won’t blame themselves.  Instead, they’ll blame Obama.  Who is, although certainly a person, not an American one. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/mitch-mcconnell-says-the-congressional-republican-caucuses-are-the-american-people-got-that-american-people.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>National Journal Editorial Director* Ron Fournier Missed Eighth-Grade Civics Class the Day They Discussed the Separation-of-Powers Thing. He Should Now Get a Tutor.</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/national-journal-editorial-director-ron-fournier-missed-eighth-grade-civics-class-the-day-they-discussed-the-separation-of-powers-thing-he-should-now-get-a-tutor.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/national-journal-editorial-director-ron-fournier-missed-eighth-grade-civics-class-the-day-they-discussed-the-separation-of-powers-thing-he-should-now-get-a-tutor.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 22 Feb 2013 20:22:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Darren Samuelsohn]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ezra Klein]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Greg Sargent]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Boehner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jonatha Chait]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Krugman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politico]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ron Fournier]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Scott Wong]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The National Journal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the sequester]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/national-journal-editorial-director-ron-fournier-missed-eighth-grade-civics-class-the-day-they-discussed-the-separation-of-powers-thing-he-should-now-get-a-tutor.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[It’s hard to know who will end up taking the biggest political hit if the latest Washington-induced crisis moves from theoretical to real — but the answer may well lie in which side can get the public to buy into its finger-pointing at the other side. That’s why the excuses matter: Polls show Obama has [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">It’s hard to know who will end up taking the biggest political hit if the latest Washington-induced crisis moves from theoretical to real — but the answer may well lie in which side can get the public to buy into its finger-pointing at the other side.</div>
<div dir="ltr">That’s why the excuses matter: Polls show Obama has the upper hand now over unpopular lawmakers, but much can change if sequestration upends the country’s economic recovery and Americans lose their jobs and access to popular government services.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://www.politico.com/story/2013/02/sequestration-excuses-excuses-excuses-87924.html#ixzz2Le8LVAVd">Sequestration: Excuses, excuses, excuses</a>, Darren Samuelsohn and Scott Wong, Politico, yesterday</div>
<p>I agree.  If the sequester upends the country’s economic recovery and Americans lose their jobs and access to popular government services because of its deep cuts in federal spending, the public  may well rage against Obama for refusing to accede to the Republicans’ demand that federal spending be cut much more dramatically (except for the Defense Department’s spending, which would not be cut at all)&#8211;therefore costing at least as many Americans their jobs and further denying access to those popular government services and to additional ones.  They may well be livid with Obama that he wanted to lessen the number of job losses and the loss of access to popular government services by claiming more tax revenues from wealthy individuals and corporations.  </p>
<p>Especially since about three-fourths of the public supports Obama&#8217;s proposed route.  The public may be marching in the streets, demanding impeachment.   And demanding further deep spending cuts in order to cut more jobs and popular services, and lower taxes on the wealthy and on corporations.  At least if they&#8217;re really, <i>really</i> angry about the job losses, the damage to the economy, and the loss of popular government services. </p>
<p>It isn’t a certainty that they will, though, even <i>if</i> they&#8217;re really, really angry about the job losses, the damage to the economy, and the loss of popular government services.  Which is why the Politico piece says only that it’s hard to tell whether or <i>not</i> they will.  Such things just can’t be predicted with reasonable accuracy. </p>
<p>One thing John Boehner is right about: The public does understand&#8211;his word, not mine&#8211;that tax increases are off the table, because the Republicans agreed to $600 billion in tax increases on people with very high incomes as part of the “fiscal cliff” deal seven weeks ago.  </p>
<p>They also understand exactly why further tax revenue from the very wealthy is off the table.  And they know that it&#8217;s not actually because the Republicans agreed to $600 billion in tax increases on people with very high incomes as part of the “fiscal cliff” deal seven weeks ago.  </p>
<p>The Politico piece, which I’m betting was not the idea of the two reporters but was instead an assignment handed to them, along with an opening script, by top management there&#8211;it is not a reporting piece at all&#8211;is an interesting variation on the highly-in-vogue-this-season pseudo-journalism pox-on-both-their-houses sequestration/fiscal-cliff/debt-ceiling/shut-down-the-government routine.  It passes for journalism.  But it is not journalism.  It is propaganda.  </p>
<p>The Politico piece subtlely varies the usual technique. Instead of saying, as most of the genre’s pieces do, that these crises really are the fault of both sides&#8211;equally, of course&#8211;this article says the public probably can’t distinguish between suddenly and dramatically cutting federal spending, causing substantial job losses and gutting popular government services, and cutting federal spending less and more slowly and helping to reduce the budget deficit by raising more tax revenue from the wealthy individuals and corporations.  </p>
<p>But most members of this Lewis-Carroll-as-journalists crowd do the straight from of it.  In fact, a few of them seem more like the Mad Hatter than like the Mad Hatter’s creator.  Ron Fournier appears to be among them.<br /><a name="more"></a><br />For those of you who don’t know, and there probably are few of you who don’t, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ron_Fournier">Ron Fournier is</a> a Republican-leaning, somewhat controversial Washington political journalist who a few years ago was himself major news in journalism circles when he was appointed the Associated Press’s acting Washington bureau chief.  (Until I read his Wikipedia page a few minutes ago, I wasn’t aware that it was intended as just a temporary appointment.)  The Wikipedia paragraph about this explains the controversy:</p>
<div dir="ltr">In May 2008, Fournier was named the acting Washington bureau chief, replacing his &#8220;mentor&#8221; Sandy Johnson. Since taking over the position, Fournier has led a dramatic shift in the AP&#8217;s policy, moving it away from the neutral and objective tone it had become known for and toward a more opinionated style that would make judgments when conflicting opinions were presented in a story.</div>
<p>The judgments Fournier favored were ones that the Republican Party favored as well, if I remember right.  It wasn’t a hit with Fournier’s AP colleagues, nor apparently with many of the AP’s news media clients.  So he left the AP to become editor at the venerable <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Journal">National Journal</a>, which, for those of you who don’t know, and there probably are a few of you who don’t, is a (mainly) print journal that at least in recent years quietly leans Republican but that clothes itself as neutral.  </p>
<p>Sort of like <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Politico">Politico</a>.  Except that, unlike Politico, no one outside Washington reads it and no one outside Washington cares about it.  Which is understandable, since no one outside Washington has ever heard of it. (Except me, but I do qualify as someone who doesn’t read it and someone who doesn’t care about it.)</p>
<p>Anyway, Greg Sargent, who is inside Washington and who does read the National Journal, <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/plum-line/wp/2013/02/22/the-morning-plum-questions-for-the-blame-it-on-both-sides-crowd/">writes this morning</a>:</p>
<div dir="ltr">To summarize, Fournier and Pfeiffer argued over who is to blame for the sequester. Pfeiffer criticized <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/22/opinion/brooks-the-dc-dubstep.html?hp">David Brooks’ “pox on both houses” column this morning</a> and noted that only one side (the GOP) is not willing to compromise to avoid the sequester. Fournier, who also tweeted a link to Brooks’ column, replied with several tweets arguing that it’s on the President to secure compromise from the opposition, such as <a href="https://twitter.com/ron_fournier/status/304927154578272256">this one</a>: “only one side is president. Both sides should be ashamed.”</p>
<p>This echoes Fournier’s <a href="http://mobile.nationaljournal.com/politics/you-may-be-right-mr-president-but-this-is-crazy-20130220">recent column</a> arguing that while Republicans have adopted a fundamentally uncompromising position (which to Fournier’s credit he’s been willing to acknowledge), “in any enterprise, the chief executive is ultimately accountable for success and failure.” Brooks’s column, meanwhile, argues that both sides are to blame, because Obama doesn’t have a plan to avert the sequester (which is <a href="http://www.whitehouse.gov/sites/default/files/docs/deficit_reduction_table_bucketed_r8.pdf">false</a>). So, some questions for the “blame it on both sides” crowd:</p>
</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">1) Let’s grant Fournier’s premise that a president should do all he can to secure cooperation from the other side. What more, if anything, could Obama actually do to win cooperation from today’s Republican Party on averting the sequester, short of giving in to the GOP demand that we replace it only with spending cuts? Republicans say no compromise to avert the sequester is acceptable. That’s not an exaggeration: It’s the party’s explicit, publicly stated position. What more specifically could Obama do to change this? If the answer is “nothing,” then why are both sides equally to blame?</div>
<p>Okay, look.  The president can be appropriately analogized to the CEO of the executive branch of the federal government.  It’s not a perfect analogy; obviously, there are laws that limit the president’s control over the executive branch&#8211;the Federalist Society’s silly Reagan-era “unitary executive” theory of law (don’t ask) to the contrary, notwithstanding.  But it’s a useful analogy nonetheless.  </p>
<p>But unless you recognize that Congress is not the president’s subordinate, whose membership he can hire and fire, and that federal fiscal policy is not established by fiat of top management, or unless you realize this but aren’t astute enough to understand that these are, to use a favorite word of lawyers, “material” differences between corporate CEOs and the president of the United States, you do know that it is deeply stupid to say that “in any enterprise, the chief executive is ultimately accountable for success and failure,” and not realize that some enterprises actually don’t have a chief executive and that the federal government is among those enterprises that do not.</p>
<p>I guess this is confusing, because, after all, the president is the chief of the executive branch of the federal government.  You have to know that this particular enterprise has three separate branches that, as per the Constitution, operate independent of one another, in order to understand the difference between being the chief of the executive branch and being the chief executive.  And Fournier apparently does not. </p>
<p>Greg Sargent, Paul Krugman, The New Yorker’s Jonathan Chait, Slate’s Matthew Yglesias, and a few other political writers have been sounding sirens of alarm and utter dismay at this increasingly dangerous and perverted juggernaut by so many self-styled neutral mainstream political journalists, including two days ago a Washington Post editorial writer, to engage in a campaign of deceit and propaganda in reporting on these sequential Republican-orchestrated federal fiscal crises.  </p>
<p>In my opinion, the very best of the deconstruction-of-the-pretzel-positions pieces&#8211;and one of the most piercing and quietly eloquent political opinion pieces I’ve ever read&#8211;is <a href="http://nymag.com/daily/intelligencer/2013/02/beltway-brain-fever-sequester-edition.html">this one</a>, from Wednesday, by Chait, which Yglesias linked to on Wednesday and which Sargent links to today. Yglesias&#8217;s excellent posts are <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/moneybox/2013/02/20/bipartisanthink_and_the_seriousness_principle.html">here</a> and <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/moneybox/2013/02/21/romney_and_the_sequester_bipartisanthink_takes_the_counterfactual_turn.html">here</a>.</p>
<p>I think we’re about to reach an epiphany point, at which enough important journalists become genuinely scared of what is by now creepily similar to a government-controlled mainstream press in totalitarian countries that this will cease.  No, not by the stupid Ron Fournier or by the silly, robotic David Brooks.  But maybe at least by the Washington Post’s editorial writers and by reporters who certainly need their current jobs but who also are young enough to need reputations as credible and intelligent journalists, going forward.</p>
<p>And once that happens, maybe mainstream journalism will have a similar epiphany about the austerity juggernaut.  Or, <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/wonkblog/wp/2013/02/20/the-problem-with-alan-simpson/">as Ezra Klein points out</a>, mainstream journalism&#8217;s <i>really weird</i> role in it.</p>
<p>As for Fournier, according to Wikipedia, he&#8217;s won several prestigious journalism awards.  But never one for commentary.  Maybe this year.  </p>
<p>*<i>Originally, this post said Fournier was the National Journal&#8217;s title was editor</i>.</p>
<p>&#8212;<br />POSTSCRIPT: I hadn’t seen <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/02/21/alan-simpson-and-bernie-madoff/">this pos</a>t of Paul Krugman’s from yesterday until just now. Talk about cutting to&#8211;cutting into, really&#8211;the heart of something slimy yet seemingly ever-evading analysis and puncture!</p>
<p>Enough.  Enough.  Time now to end it.  Psychiatrists are standing by to offer withdrawal counseling. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/national-journal-editorial-director-ron-fournier-missed-eighth-grade-civics-class-the-day-they-discussed-the-separation-of-powers-thing-he-should-now-get-a-tutor.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Large Number of Hedge Fund Managers Near Fort Rucker, Ala. (A Suggested Response to the Republicans’ Simple Response(s).)</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/the-large-number-of-hedge-fund-managers-near-fort-rucker-ala-a-suggested-response-to-the-republicans-simple-responses.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/the-large-number-of-hedge-fund-managers-near-fort-rucker-ala-a-suggested-response-to-the-republicans-simple-responses.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Feb 2013 18:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Fort Rucker]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jim VandeHei]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Boehner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jonathan Weisman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mike Allen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politico]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rep. Martha Roby]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The New York Times]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the sequester]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Wall Street Journal]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/the-large-number-of-hedge-fund-managers-near-fort-rucker-ala-a-suggested-response-to-the-republicans-simple-responses.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[It’s unconscionable to use our military men and women in uniform as a bargaining chip to raise our taxes. &#8212; Rep. Martha Roby, (R. Ala.) Our taxes, huh?  Ours!  This actually is unexpectedly good financial news for most of, um, us. Not to mention very surprising news. According to The New York Times today, Roby [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">It’s unconscionable to use our military men and women in uniform as a bargaining chip to raise our taxes.</p>
</div>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; Rep. Martha Roby, (R. Ala.)</div>
<p>Our taxes, huh?  Ours!  This actually is unexpectedly <i>good</i> financial news for most of, um, <i>us</i>.  Not to mention very <i>surprising</i> news.</p>
<p>According to <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/21/us/politics/gop-resisting-obama-on-tax-increase.html?nl=todaysheadlines&#038;emc=edit_th_20130221&#038;_r=0&#038;pagewanted=all">The New York Times today</a>, Roby made the comment in an interview yesterday after a visit to the town just outside the Army’s Fort Rucker.  And presumably, she, and her family (thus, the &#8220;our&#8221; rather than a &#8220;my&#8221;), have substantial income from capital gains and dividends.  Or maybe she or her husband is a hedge fund manager and would lose the &#8220;carried-interest&#8221; tax deduction, because the tax loopholes that Obama and the congressional Dems are proposing to close are those and similar ones.  And she did say “raise our taxes.”  </p>
<p>Maybe <i>both</i> are hedge fund managers.  She part-time, of course.  </p>
<p>Maybe not, though, since, by using that phrase, she intended to convey, falsely, that Obama was using our military men and women in uniform as a bargaining chip to raise the taxes of the our military men and women in uniform, most of whom have spouses who are hedge fund managers, and of the residents of the town just outside of Fort Rucker, most of whom live off of their capital gains and dividends, and none of whom, whether working or unemployed, receive assistance from the the federal food-assistance program.  </p>
<p>I know that latter fact to be true because the New York Times article says that House Republicans say they believe that the have “politically inoculated themselves against claims they are responsible for the cuts by approving measures last year that would have substituted reductions in government programs like food stamps for the lower Pentagon spending.”</p>
<p>Which itself undoubtedly is true.  Especially since Mitt Romney and Paul Ryan ran on just such a proposal last fall, and won.  I mean, lost.  By about 5 million votes.  </p>
<p>The Republicans must have received their inoculation serum through the Web.  From a company in Afghanistan, maybe. </p>
<p>Roby also said in that interview referenced in the Times article:</p>
<div dir="ltr">The president says he has to have tax increases to head off the sequester. Well, he already got his tax increase. </div>
<p>Indeed, he did.  He got a tax increase on individuals with non-investment income of at least $400,000, and on couples with non-investment income of at least $450,000, to Clinton-era rates, and slight raises on some investment income, to less than Clinton-era rates.  Clinton-era rates being rates at which we were able to have a budget surplus, without using our military men and women in uniform as a bargaining chip  for anything, and without cutting food assistance programs, including the assistance that goes to Alabamans, a few of whom may live in that town near Fort Rucker.  </p>
<p>So, I have two suggestions for Obama.  Serious ones.  </p>
<p>Seriously.<br /><a name="more"></a><br />One is that he travel to that town near Fort Rucker and explain, among other things, that salaries for our men and women in uniform are exempt from the sequester, and that, while we’re on the subject, of unconscionable political conduct, it’s probably a good idea to include the dispensing of false information to the contrary as fitting comfortably within that category.  He also should explain to the group assembled in the audience at the high school gym, or wherever, who it is exactly that will have their taxes raised by the tax raises included in the “fiscal cliff” agreement, and, especially, who it is exactly&#8211;exactly&#8211;that would have their taxes raised under Obama’s proposal to replace the sequester.  </p>
<p>Then he should ask for a show of hands, first, by those in the audience who will have their taxes raised under the “fiscal cliff” deal, and then by those who would have their taxes raised under a current proposal to replace the sequester.  His own proposal or the Senate Democrats’ or the House Democrats’.  In other words, a show of hands by “us”&#8211;as in “raise our taxes.”  </p>
<p>He also could, and should, explain how, and why, the sequester law came about&#8211;and what would have happened to this country’s credit rating and the financial system and the economy beginning in August 2011 without it.  I.e., explain again, as he did at his successful press conference in mid-January, what the debt ceiling, and raising it, are.</p>
<p>Obama of course instead could make these points in a short primetime TV address, one advantage of which would be a national audience.  That&#8217;s my other suggestion.  He could do this in an address of under 10 minutes.  </p>
<p>If he took that avenue, he could even take advantage of the national audience to point out, within that under-10-minute address, that John Boehner wasn’t quite accurate when he said in <a href="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424127887323495104578314240032274944.html?mod=WSJ_Opinion_LEADTop">a Wall Street Journal op-ed</a> yesterday that: </p>
<div dir="ltr">[A]s the president&#8217;s outrage about the sequester grows in coming days, Republicans have a simple response: Mr. President, we agree that your sequester is bad policy. What spending are you willing to cut to replace it?</div>
<p>Yes, some&#8211;but not all&#8211;Republicans’ simple response is to fail to acknowledge that Obama is proposing replacing some of the sequester’s cuts with increased tax revenues achieved by closing tax loopholes on wealthy individuals and corporations.  Martha Roby is a Republican who does acknowledge this.  Her simple response is, rather than pretending that this is not so&#8211;that Obama has not proposed an offset by raising more revenue in the manner that he and the congressional Dems in fact have proposed&#8211;to instead misrepresent to all or most of her constituents that their (“our”) taxes would go up.  It&#8217;s a statement either unconscionably deliberately deceptive or instead reflecting dismaying ignorance of the sources and amounts of income of at least some, probably most, of her constituents, unless her district is among the wealthier ones in this country.* </p>
<p>Which, for all I know, it may be.  But if so, most of the residents of the town close to the Army base probably are not among the hedge fund managers in her district.  Nor even among the Apple shareholders. </p>
<p>Obama could of course both travel to the town near Fort Rucker and address the nation on primetime TV.  But only if the matter is really important.  Really important.  Which Obama may or may not think it is.  I mean … to each his own. </p>
<p>What I don’t understand about this White House is its failure to grasp that what matters is actual explanations and refutations of the Republicans’ incessant misrepresentations of fact&#8211;killing the Repubs’ constant representation of cliché  and generic slogans as facts&#8211;rather than silly <a href="http://dyn.politico.com/printstory.cfm?uuid=A22E8106-D4AF-436E-84DB-77354D107AA4">Twitter tweets, attractive photos of Obama at work or play, or appearances on The View or interviews on 60 Minutes</a> that do not explain substance and do not refute the opposition on issues of substance.</p>
<p>Actually, this one’s pretty easy to explain:  Raise our taxes?  Then the tax raise must also be on our income.  I guess we’re all hedge fund managers now.  (Seeee?  I <i>told</i> you this was good financial news for <i>us</i>.  Not to mention <i>surprising</i> financial news for <i>us</i>.  And surprising <i>employment</i> news for, well, at least those of <i>us</i> whose tax raise will come from the elimination of the &#8220;carried-interest&#8221; deduction.)</p>
<p>Of course, now that I think about it, that little explanation in that last paragraph would fit in a Twitter post.  So maybe Twitter’s the way to explain and refute, after all.  At least when you’re camera shy.  Or just shy.</p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />*<i>This paragraph was edited slightly for clarity, as were two or three sentences elsewhere.</i></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/the-large-number-of-hedge-fund-managers-near-fort-rucker-ala-a-suggested-response-to-the-republicans-simple-responses.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>John Boehner Should Travel More. To Australia.</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/john-boehner-should-travel-more-to-australia.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/john-boehner-should-travel-more-to-australia.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2013 21:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Greg Sargent]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Boehner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Marco Rubio]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Matthew Miller]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[minimum wage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Washington Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/john-boehner-should-travel-more-to-australia.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Yesterday, both sides drew their battle lines in the coming war over the minimum wage. After Obama called for a minimum wage hike in his State of the Union speech, House Republicans dug in against it, casting their opposition as grounded in concern for the plight of low wage workers. John Boehner asked: “Why would [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">Yesterday, both sides drew their battle lines in the coming war over the minimum wage. After Obama called for a minimum wage hike in his State of the Union speech, House Republicans dug in against it, casting their opposition as grounded in concern for the plight of low wage workers. John Boehner <a href="http://livewire.talkingpointsmemo.com/entry/boehner-shoots-down-obamas-minimum-wage-hike">asked</a>: “Why would we want to make it harder for small employers to hire people?”</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/plum-line/wp/2013/02/14/the-morning-plum-dems-to-use-minimum-wage-against-gop-in-2014/">Dems to use minimum wage against GOP in 2014</a>, Greg Sargent, Washington Post, this morning</div>
<p>To me, one of the great frustrations in Obama’s failure during most of his first term to communicate, effectively or at all, the basic premises of Keynesian and other liberal economics-related arguments (including on healthcare) was his apparent resistance to mentioning&#8211;early, often, or ever&#8211;specific other countries’ successes or failures that illustrate the point. </p>
<p>But there’s no time like the present for him and the congressional Dems to start to do do this, by maybe mentioning these facts: that Australia’s minimum wage is $15 U.S. and that its unemployment rate is 5.4%, and that the United States has (surprise!) the largest gap between the minimum wage and the median wage of any advanced economy in the world.</p>
<p>I learned those facts yesterday when I read Washington Post columnist <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/matt-miller-raise-the-minimum-wage/2013/02/06/34857264-7066-11e2-8b8d-e0b59a1b8e2a_story.html">Matthew Miller’s Feb. 6 column</a>.  He mentioned it and linked to it in <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/matt-miller-obamas-hollow-speech/2013/02/13/d928c944-75a5-11e2-95e4-6148e45d7adb_story.html">his column yesterday</a> about Obama’s State of the Union address.  In yesterday’s column, he suggested seemingly, facetiously, that it was his February 6 column that had persuaded Obama to include a minimum-wage-hike proposal in his address.  But after reading the earlier column, I suspect that it was not only what convinced Obama to make the call but also was what caused Obama to even think of it.  </p>
<p>Both of Miller’s columns say that the $9/hr. figure that Obama proposed in his speech would still leave the minimum wage at $1.68 below what the value of the minimum wage was in 1968.  The first column, Miller also mentions that several CEOs of large corporations support a rise in the minimum wage and that a prominent conservative, the editor of American Conservative magazine, suggests raising the minimum wage to $12/hr.  Of course, the Republicans will showcase their own CEOs, and some small-business owners, to support their own position.</p>
<p>Which is where Australia comes in.  Or at least where invoking it should come in. The special beauty of using Australia as an example&#8211;whether in support of an increase in the minimum wage or in refuting the Obamacare-is-socialism/makers-vs.-takers mantra&#8211;is that few Americans associate Australia with, um, socialism.  They associate it instead with free-enterprise economics and a high standard of living.  And soon, hopefully, also with a higher minimum wage that corresponds to a low unemployment rate.  </p>
<p>Maybe Marco Rubio and John Boehner could get a travel discount <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/02/marco-rubio-needs-to-travel-more.html">if they booked their reservations</a> together. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/john-boehner-should-travel-more-to-australia.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The National Review Invites Obama to Nip the Call-For-A-Balanced-Budget-Amendment Gimmickry In the Bud Tomorrow Night. Really.</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/the-national-review-invites-obama-to-nip-the-call-for-a-balanced-budget-amendment-gimmickry-in-the-bud-tomorrow-night-really.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/the-national-review-invites-obama-to-nip-the-call-for-a-balanced-budget-amendment-gimmickry-in-the-bud-tomorrow-night-really.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2013 21:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[a balanced-budget amendment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Greg Sargent]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Boehner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Cornyn]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitch McConnell]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The National Review]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the State of the Union address]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/the-national-review-invites-obama-to-nip-the-call-for-a-balanced-budget-amendment-gimmickry-in-the-bud-tomorrow-night-really.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The National Review scoops the Senate GOP’s next move, and note in particular the last paragraph: Frustrated by the months of non-stop budget fights, Senate Republicans are set to mount a fiscal counteroffensive this week with the reintroduction of a balanced-budget amendment. Senate minority leader Mitch McConnell and minority whip John Cornyn are leading the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">The National Review <a href="http://www.nationalreview.com/corner/340317/gop-renews-push-balanced-budget-amendment-robert-costa">scoops the Senate GOP’s next move</a>, and note in particular the last paragraph:</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Frustrated by the months of non-stop budget fights, Senate Republicans are set to mount a fiscal counteroffensive this week with the reintroduction of a balanced-budget amendment.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Senate minority leader Mitch McConnell and minority whip John Cornyn are leading the effort. They hope to unveil a bill by Thursday with unanimous Republican support. [&#8230;]</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">House Republican aides say most conservatives in the lower chamber are going to support the Senate’s plan. Speeches and media appearances are being arranged for later this week. [&#8230;]</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">According to a Senate GOP aide, the legislation would cap federal spending at 18 percent of GDP. It would also require a supermajority for tax hikes and debt-limit increases.</div>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/plum-line/wp/2013/02/11/no-end-to-the-gops-fiscal-gimmickry/?hpid=z3">No end to the GOP’s fiscal gimmickry</a>, Greg Sargent, today</div>
<p>Okay, why would the National Review, or any high-profile non-mainstream source, put this out a day before the State of the Union address, if not to give Obama a chance to mention it, along with an accompanying explanation of how such an amendment would, say, cause recessions to spiral into depressions&#8211;during which time the availability of, say, unemployment compensation would decrease rather than increase, and emergency FEMA funds for, say, the destruction of South Carolina’s coastal region after a major hurricane would have to be offset by cuts in, say, veteran’s benefits or payments to active military personnel? </p>
<p>Any alternative theories about why the National Review did this today?  I can’t think of any.</p>
<p>If Obama doesn’t take this ball, this magnificent gift, and run with it tomorrow&#8211;if he doesn’t expose this crowd for the unremittingly sophomoric gimmick-a-day ignoramuses that they are&#8211;then I’m throwing up my hands.  </p>
<p>The National Review’s editors and staff must be starting to really fear the sequester.  And I’m not saying that facetiously. 
<div></div>
<div>They also must actually recognize the likelihood that last November&#8217;s election results weren&#8217;t a fluke.  A majority of the public even in some seemingly-safely gerrymandered Republican congressional districts and red states with Senate elections next year are not necessarily going to want to hand a box of matches to lunatics and mental adolescents, now that they&#8217;re learning that that&#8217;s what these people are. 
<div></div>
<div></div>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/the-national-review-invites-obama-to-nip-the-call-for-a-balanced-budget-amendment-gimmickry-in-the-bud-tomorrow-night-really.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The People-as-Props That Obama SHOULD Use During His Speech Tomorrow Night: John Boehner and Joe Barton. And They’re Already Invited!</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/the-people-as-props-that-obama-should-use-during-his-speech-tomorrow-night-john-boehner-and-joe-barton-and-theyre-already-invited.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/the-people-as-props-that-obama-should-use-during-his-speech-tomorrow-night-john-boehner-and-joe-barton-and-theyre-already-invited.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2013 19:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[#obamaquester]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#pleasegrowupspeakerboehner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#spendingstheproblem]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Glenn Thrush]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Greg Sargent]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Joe Baarton]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Boehner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Krugman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the State of the Union address]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/the-people-as-props-that-obama-should-use-during-his-speech-tomorrow-night-john-boehner-and-joe-barton-and-theyre-already-invited.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Speaker John Boehner  @SpeakerBoehner House GOP has voted to replace the president’s sequester twice. Here’s why, courtesy @whitehouse: http://j.mp/WzhNgY #obamaquester &#8212; Twitter, h/t Politico, Boehner’s office dubs it “Obamaquester,” Feb. 8 Oh, dear.  I guess this is going to be a regular thing.  A few days earlier, our dignified House Speaker created the twitter hashtag #spendingstheproblem. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr"><a href="https://twitter.com/SpeakerBoehner?tw_i=299963148268621826&#038;tw_p=tweetembed">Speaker John Boehner  @SpeakerBoehner</a></div>
<div dir="ltr">House GOP has voted to replace the president’s sequester twice. Here’s why, courtesy <a href="https://twitter.com/whitehouse">@whitehouse</a>: <a href="http://t.co/vbir4JzR">http://j.mp/WzhNgY </a><a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23obamaquester&#038;src=hash">#obamaquester</a></div>
<p>     &#8212; Twitter, h/t Politico, <a href="http://www.politico.com/politico44/2013/02/boehners-office-dubs-it-obamaquester-156511.html">Boehner’s office dubs it “Obamaquester</a><a href="http://www.politico.com/politico44/2013/02/boehners-office-dubs-it-obamaquester-156511.html">,”</a> Feb. 8</p>
<p>Oh, dear.  I guess this is going to be a regular thing.  A few days earlier, our dignified House Speaker <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/02/yup-john-boehner-and-paul-ryan-are.html">created the twitter hashtag #spendingstheproblem</a>. Which it certainly is when you deliberately dramatically reduce revenues by drastically cutting taxes, especially on the wealthy and on corporations, and wage two wars, significantly increase expenditures on homeland security, and expand the Medicare program to include prescription drugs.  </p>
<p>And which it surely is when those tax cuts are called, obviously tongue-in-cheek, temporary and are enacted only a decade before the huge baby-boomer generation begins to retire and to qualify for Medicare, and then are in fact mostly not allowed to expire because some of the folks who brought you the tax cuts in the first place, and <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/02/yup-john-boehner-and-paul-ryan-are.html">who think spendingstheproblem</a>, keep blocking attempts to raise revenues even by closing egregious loopholes that benefit only the wealthy.  </p>
<p>Something about the Democrats having to take those tax cuts from their cold dead hands, I guess.  Which if the sequester actually does occur, the Democrats will have little trouble doing, because the Repubs’ political hands will be very cold and very dead.  </p>
<p>The Republicans delude themselves into thinking otherwise, based upon the presumption that the public doesn’t even yet grasp that spendingistheproblem only when you reduce tax rates to historically low levels and allow mega-loopholes through which hedge fund managers and Mitt Romney fly their private or chartered jets through on their way from one of their several homes to another one.  The public, though, does grasp that, and showed it last November 6.  And in the late December polls during the “fiscal cliff” crisis.  And in the polls last month during the debt-ceiling crisis.  </p>
<p>Yet if the Boehner’s Tweet is any indication, he still thinks that all the Repubs have to do is vote to replace the president’s sequester.  And they’ve done that.  Twice.  </p>
<p>No matter what they voted to replace the sequester with.  Nope.  What matters is that they voted to replace the sequester, and that they did so twice.  And that the sequester is “the president’s.”  And that in fact it’s not even a sequester; it’s Obamaquester.  The substance of what they want to enact won’t matter to the public.  All that will matter to the public is that the House Republicans voted to replace the sequester with something and that therefore the Senate Dems and Obama are obligated to adopt it.  That’s because the Republicans won the election last November&#8211;er, because there’s now a cutesy, juvenile twitter hashtag out there saying that the sequester is Obamaquester.  First things first, you know.<br /><a name="more"></a><br />The Speaker, as Paul Krugman pointed out <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/02/07/the-undecade/">on Thursday</a> and again <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/08/opinion/krugman-kick-that-can.html?_r=0">on Friday</a>, suffers not just from short-term memory problems but also from long-term memory problems. Boehner said last week that the budget deficit has continued to increase throughout his 22-year tenure in Congress. Which, of course, is why in 2001 and again in 2003, as the wars in Iraq and Afghanistan accellerated rather than wound down, and after we began to spend considerably more on homeland security in the wake of 9/11, and after Medicare was expanded to include prescription drug coverage, he joined nearly all his Republican colleagues to vote for the drastic tax cuts, most of it benefiting the wealthy and large corporations.  </p>
<p>I guess that’s because #spendingstheproblem even when the budget deficit has recently been eliminated with the help of tax rate increases mostly on upper-income folks. And even when the huge baby boomer generation is beginning to retire.  </p>
<p>Longtime House member Joe Barton (R-Texas), who apparently doesn’t favor a strategy of posting juvenile twitter posts, does nonetheless agree with Boehner that we should simply allow the sequester to take effect unless the Senate Dems and Obama agree to rubberstamp the House Repubs’ offered substitute for the sequester.  The one they passed.  Twice.  He <a href="http://dyn.politico.com/printstory.cfm?uuid=F5E99E93-7EC0-49FE-8A8C-86EB5FD8FEDE">explained to Politico</a> why he favors the sequester, despite pleas from constitutions who will be furloughed as a result:</p>
<div dir="ltr">I’m a lot more concerned about trillion-dollar deficits every year stretching to infinity. That’s obviously a more indirect issue to somebody who’s about to lose their job or has lost their job, and I respect that 100 percent.</div>
<p>It’s the next generation that he’s concerned about, he said.  Which is why he refuses to consider raising taxes on this generation of wealthy taxpayers and corporations by closing loopholes through which hedge fund managers and cutely offshore-based-for-tax-purposes American corporations fly their Learjets. </p>
<p>Politico’s Glenn Thrush <a href="http://www.politico.com/story/2013/02/state-of-the-union-2013-obama-aggressive-87440.html?hp=t1_3">reports this morning</a> that Obama plans to be forceful tomorrow night in explaining his economic-policy position and in refuting the Republicans’.  But, as Greg Sargent <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/plum-line/wp/2013/02/11/the-morning-plum-go-on-offense-mr-president/?hpid=z3">says today</a>, Obama’s preference for pussyfooting, generic, brief catchphrases, such as “self-inflicted wounds” and “We can’t cut our way to prosperity,” need actual several-sentence explanations.  They’re worthless unless they’re spelled out, with actual clarity and specificity. </p>
<p>But here’s something else&#8211;something absolutely critical&#8211;that Obama needs to make clear.  To make clear.  That the Republicans have settled on a strategy of pretending that additional tax revenue doesn’t decrease the budget deficit, and of pushing that strategy via the tactic of simply making repeated public comments that ignore that additional tax revenue does exactly that.  Thus, #spendingstheproblem, the sequester is <a href="http://www.politico.com/politico44/2013/02/boehners-office-dubs-it-obamaquester-156511.html">#obamaquester</a>, and neither the Clinton presidency nor the G.W. Bush presidency happened. </p>
<p>Both Boehner and Barton will be in the audience tomorrow night.  They won’t be sitting next or right in back of Michelle, special guests of the president.  But they’ll be there.  And Obama should address them by name, in a comment along the lines of: </p>
<div dir="ltr">Rep. Barton, you’ve said you’re a lot more concerned about trillion-dollar deficits every year stretching to infinity than you are about the jobs of the National Weather Service employees and air traffic controllers and food safety inspectors who live in your district.  And you’re a lot more concerned about keeping income tax rates at 15% for hedge fund managers, and about keeping the corporate offshoring tax advantages intact, than you are about trillion-dollar deficits every year stretching to infinity.  Even though, in light of the fiscal-cliff compromise that the Democrats forced at the beginning of the year, and the economic recovery that will continue if you and your colleagues stop the sequential Russian roulette and start taking your oath of office at least a little bit seriously, infinity could turn out to be not that far away after all.</div>
<p>Of course, the president could instead create a hashtag on twitter.  My suggestion: #pleasegrowupspeakerboehner.</p>
<p>Or maybe he should just sit tight.  Doesn’t the tornado season begin in Texas right about the time that the sequester does?  And in Ohio soon after?  </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/the-people-as-props-that-obama-should-use-during-his-speech-tomorrow-night-john-boehner-and-joe-barton-and-theyre-already-invited.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Yup, John Boehner and Paul Ryan Are Right: The economy contracted in the fourth quarter because #spendingstheproblem and Keynesian Economics Doesn’t Work.</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/yup-john-boehner-and-paul-ryan-are-right-the-economy-contracted-in-the-fourth-quarter-because-spendingstheproblem-and-keynesian-economics-doesnt-work.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/yup-john-boehner-and-paul-ryan-are-right-the-economy-contracted-in-the-fourth-quarter-because-spendingstheproblem-and-keynesian-economics-doesnt-work.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2013 17:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[#spendingstheproblem]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Boehner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Keynesian economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/yup-john-boehner-and-paul-ryan-are-right-the-economy-contracted-in-the-fourth-quarter-because-spendingstheproblem-and-keynesian-economics-doesnt-work.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Construction has been one of the more encouraging sectors, adding jobs each of the last four months. The hiring there was probably because of a combination of rebuilding from Hurricane Sandy, unseasonably warm weather that led to fewer work stoppages, and the nascent housing recovery, said Ian Shepherdson, chief economist at Pantheon Macroeconomic Advisors. Retailing, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">Construction has been one of the more encouraging sectors, adding jobs each of the last four months. The hiring there was probably because of a combination of rebuilding from <a href="http://topics.nytimes.com/top/reference/timestopics/subjects/h/hurricanes_and_tropical_storms/index.html?inline=nyt-classifier">Hurricane Sandy</a>, unseasonably warm weather that led to fewer work stoppages, and the nascent housing recovery, said Ian Shepherdson, chief economist at Pantheon Macroeconomic Advisors.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Retailing, health care and the wholesale trade also added positions in January, while the government again shed jobs. Government payrolls have been shrinking most months over the last four years.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/02/business/economy/us-adds-157000-jobs-unemployment-rate-edges-up-to-7-9.html?emc=na&#038;pagewanted=all">Job Growth Is Steady Amid Snags Holding Back Economy</a>, Catherine Rampell, New York Times, today</div>
<p><a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/01/paul-ryan-says-taxes-should-be-raised.html">Bring on</a> <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/01/john-boehner-says-defense-spending-is.html">the sequester</a>, I say!  Let’s get that economy <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/01/opinion/krugman-looking-for-mister-goodpain.html?_r=1&#038;">going again</a>! </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/yup-john-boehner-and-paul-ryan-are-right-the-economy-contracted-in-the-fourth-quarter-because-spendingstheproblem-and-keynesian-economics-doesnt-work.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
