<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>down sizing &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Outsourced within the USA</title>
		<link>./../../2008/02/outsourced-within-the-usa.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/02/outsourced-within-the-usa.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 18 Feb 2008 19:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[down sizing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jobs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[labor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[outsourcing]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/02/outsourced-within-the-usa.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[What do you think of a job that use to pay $13/hr, three years latter paying that same person now $11/hour? What do you think of that same job having other people being paid $9.56/hr. It is a union hospital job cleaning rooms after the patient goes home. Cleaning as in washing walls, floor, beds, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>What do you think of a job that use to pay $13/hr, three years latter paying that same person now $11/hour? What do you think of that same job having other people being paid $9.56/hr.</p>
<p>It is a union hospital job cleaning rooms after the patient goes home. Cleaning as in washing walls, floor, beds, etc. It includes doing “trash and linen”; collecting the bags of linen and throwing them into a cage that gets piled high, throwing trash into a dumpster but, not on a regular bases. They have a young man for that. Just one man for the heavy work during the week. He&#8217;s on vacation. They have another male, but only on weekends (works 2 jobs, 49 yrs old). He&#8217;s had enough. He&#8217;s leaving.</p>
<p>They are not allowed to strike as they are considered essential to the operations. The company can not keep help, especially male help.</p>
<p>We hear about people having downsized their incomes when they have to make a change of job, but this is a downsizing within the same employment. How did this happen? The hospital outsourced the maintenance and then the company was sold&#8230;not to an outside the nation company.</p>
<p>My brother-in-law use to earn $80,000/yr. They cut his job. He ended up working for a company that filled a contract that a second company had for a third company who outsourced the department to the second company. He was paid $45,000/yr, was part of a team of 5 who replaced 15 people who were all making what he use to make.</p>
<p>Maybe it&#8217;s time we start understanding that “outsourcing” is not just a process of moving a job out of the country. It is also a shell game within the country.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/02/outsourced-within-the-usa.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
