<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>whittle a break &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Whittle a beak series</title>
		<link>./../../2008/04/whittle-a-beak-series.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/04/whittle-a-beak-series.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2008 12:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[War profiteering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[whittle a break]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/04/whittle-a-beak-series.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Ilsm continues his whittle the beak series: Professor Theodore Postol, MIT, is a continuing and outspoken critic of Missile Defense Agency, Star Wars and numerous related components such as Patriot and newer science projects. He made news in 1992 pointing out that 37 of 38 disintegrating SCUD missiles fired by Iraq during Gulf War II [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Ilsm continues his whittle the beak series:</p>
<p>Professor Theodore Postol, MIT, is a continuing and outspoken critic of Missile Defense Agency, Star Wars and numerous related components such as Patriot and newer science projects. He made news in 1992 pointing out that 37 of 38 disintegrating SCUD missiles fired by Iraq during Gulf War II were missed by the patriot interceptor missiles.</p>
<p>Postol&#8217;s latest <a href="http://www.boston.com/bostonglobe/editorial_opinion/oped/articles/2008/04/15/troubling_questions_about_missile_defense/">Op Ed Apr 15 2008 in the Boston Globe</a>, is about the utter dismissal of outcomes of star wars tests of interceptors against &#8216;decoys&#8217;. </p>
<p>He states that of two tests attempted neither gave any positive results and failed against the least difficult decoys. He also states that there are allegations that the missile defense agency hid these dismal results and caused researchers to eliminate all references to failed intercept tests.</p>
<p>This shows one of the great foundations of weapon testing: tests &#8216;not failed&#8217; are passed. Goes for tests not done and ignored. </p>
<p>Missile defense agency&#8217;s very busy public affairs office responded that there have been 5 tests of decoyed targets and all have provided &#8220;actionable&#8221; results. Got lots of things to fix. Tests are supposed to show things work, not show what is wrong with the object being tested. There is huge scrap and rework, and it is far more expensive to fix design errors after the system is in the field, but the tests succeed in justifying more money for these wooden beaks.</p>
<p>Star wars is so important it will be funded, built and deployed in Poland and be as useful as the Maginot Line.</p>
<p>Tests are success oriented. Never will a failure slow the profits. Disregard the failed tests full speed ahead! Scrap and rework is business development, revenue growth reward for failure.<br />This is not new, in Fall 2000 the Director of Operational Test stated that the MV 22 Osprey did not complete effectiveness tests and failed reliability and maintenance tests. The DoD was going to build it anyway, despite the negative report until an MV 22 crashed killing the crew in Dec 2000.</p>
<p>Congress needs to sustain these superlative design companies. As the interceptors are deployed no tests have been done to show that the interceptors can launch from alert with no script, will complete a mission cycle and get to target if needed. All the tests are highly scripted, and look like shuttle launches delayed for maintenance weather or what ever. Good thing North Korea cannot feed their children lest they might nuke us through star wars.</p>
<p>Might as well whittle a beak for all the good the untested interceptors will do.<br />&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
<p>This by ilsm.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/04/whittle-a-beak-series.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>ILSM &#8211; Whittling a Break</title>
		<link>./../../2008/04/ilsm-whittling-a-break.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/04/ilsm-whittling-a-break.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2008 12:16:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[whittle a break]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/04/ilsm-whittling-a-break.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This one is by ILSM &#8212; The best laid schemes o&#8217; Mice an&#8217; Men, Gang aft agley,&#8221; Robert Burns. Justifying staying with the escalation, Iraqi and Afghanistan surge scams. &#8220;The gains&#8230;&#8230;&#8230;..should not be allowed to unravel.&#8221; Robert Gates C-SPAN 10 Apr 2008 One of the Kagans demands that withdrawal advocates have to prove the impossible: [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This one is by ILSM</p>
<p>&#8212;</p>
<p>The best laid schemes o&#8217; Mice an&#8217; Men, Gang aft agley,&#8221; Robert Burns.</p>
<p>Justifying staying with the escalation, Iraqi and Afghanistan surge scams.</p>
<p>&#8220;The gains&#8230;&#8230;&#8230;..should not be allowed to unravel.&#8221; Robert Gates C-SPAN 10 Apr 2008</p>
<p>One of the Kagans demands that withdrawal advocates have to prove the impossible: that the vague bad things that might happen when the US withdraws from Iraq, how fearsome and frightening, are not more costly than continuing the expensive, bloody war with no strategy and no prospects of achieving anything.</p>
<p>Does Kagan write for Gates?</p>
<p>This is common to how D0D excuses worthless weapon system projects where the money is continually wasted because if the useless weapon is not delivered the consequences will be &#8220;bleak&#8221;. So, like Iraq and Afghanistan, the taxpayers&#8217; money is shoveled into money pits the results are accepting things that do not work, cost too much and break too often. Good thing we do not suffer the bleakness of not buying the useless junk!</p>
<p>Fearsome consequences like shutting down an inept engineering houses are &#8220;bleak&#8221;.</p>
<p>It is as if you have to &#8216;prove the money should not be spent&#8217; as opposed to proving the outcome is worth the taxpayers&#8217; money.</p>
<p>This is opposite decent business and economic decision theory. You do not send good money after bad.</p>
<p>See of &#8220;Mice and Economics&#8221; Dan Seligman, Forbes Magazine Aug 1998, explanatory note <a href="http://www.maxvalue.com/tip041.htm">here</a>.</p>
<p>Another foundation of the culture of waste in industrial complex waste.</p>
<p>Justify war and the tools of war with faulty economic logic. </p>
<p>The company engineering departments and the Army may as well whittle beaks with your social security trust fund. </p>
<p>&#8212;</p>
<p>This one was by ILSM.</p>
<p>END</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/04/ilsm-whittling-a-break.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>ILSM on the Culture of Waste</title>
		<link>./../../2008/04/ilsm-on-the-culture-of-waste.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/04/ilsm-on-the-culture-of-waste.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2008 15:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[whittle a break]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/04/ilsm-on-the-culture-of-waste.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This one is by ILSM &#8212; This post is on GAO 08 621, which discusses waste. Waste is like its companions fraud and abuse, only in a lesser sense. It is somewhat between them. It is not criminal misrepresentation of material facts. Close! What I think they are saying: &#8216;you cannot say a decision based [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This one is by ILSM</p>
<p>&#8212;</p>
<p>This post is on <a href="http://www.gao.gov/new.items/d08621t.pdf">GAO 08 621</a>, which discusses waste. </p>
<p>Waste is like its companions fraud and abuse, only in a lesser sense. It is somewhat between them. It is not criminal misrepresentation of material facts. Close!</p>
<p>What I think they are saying: &#8216;you cannot say a decision based on statistics, faulty hypothesis tests is a misrepresentation&#8217;, nor can one say that stating the gold plated, worst case and making it sound like the absolutely ciritical drop dead requiremnet without regard for opportunity costs debate is lying, either. See appendix II of the GAO for a good discussion.</p>
<p>A couple of old Army views.</p>
<p>&#8220;Paying your schilling&#8221;. This is the culture of &#8216;going along to get along&#8217;. Agreeing with the naked emperor and participating in fraud and waste, you know they are wrong but you succumb to the Melian dialog and put self interest ahead of truth and justice. You use the excuse when I get up there I will do right. Only you never get up there.</p>
<p>&#8220;Breaking Starch&#8221;: Being the emperor with no clothes. Keeping a starched uniform in the day room and when the CO is coming to your area jump into the uniform. Better paint all the rocks in the company area so that the place looks good and the CO thinks you are combat ready when all you can do is look good.</p>
<p>Both of these traditions and more are widespread not only in the DoD but other government organizations and it flourishes because there is money being made and no one wants to press for good management if it will change the culture and alter comfortable careers.</p>
<p>The culture of waste insists upon avoiding a clear and direct discussion of opportunity costs. Overcoming this culture with its allies in industry and PAC&#8217;s will be difficult. As GAO points out a return to the old icon of the independent, questioning civil servant protected by the Pendalton Act is needed. However, DoD is experimenting with an &#8220;improved&#8221; modern performance management which empowers managers to demand their schillings.</p>
<p>No one will ever ask if it would be better to &#8216;whiittle a beak&#8217; than spend the money on a vaguery which will cost too much and not work.</p>
<p>&#8212;</p>
<p>This one was by ILSM.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/04/ilsm-on-the-culture-of-waste.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
