<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Scott Walker &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>United Citizens and Wisconsin</title>
		<link>./../../2012/06/united-citizens-and-wisconsin.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/06/united-citizens-and-wisconsin.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Jun 2012 11:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[run 75441]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Scott Walker]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wisconsin]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/06/united-citizens-and-wisconsin.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Run 75441 United Citizens and Wisconsin Heading into the Tuesday vote Mayor Barrett with ~$4million in election funds of which 26% is drawn from out of state sources faces off with the under siege Governor Walker having ~$30 million in funds with 2/3rds coming from out of state sources. Again the Koch Bros are [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Run 75441</p>
<p>United Citizens and Wisconsin</p>
<p>Heading into the Tuesday vote Mayor Barrett with ~$4million in election funds of which 26% is drawn from out of state sources faces off with the under siege Governor Walker having ~$30 million in funds with 2/3rds coming from out of state sources. Again the Koch Bros are kicking in with a sizeable contribution of $1 million as well as the multi-billionaire owner of the Sands, Sheldon Adelson, with another sizeable sum ($1 million?). The unions and citizens of Wisconsin are hard pressed to support Barrett in a similar fashion. So much for payroll wages versus corporate profits. Tuesday election may be a bellwether for the Democrats and the November elections as the 99-percenters and labor take on corporate interests and the &#8220;1-percenters&#8217; who are both investing heavily in Walker intending to sway the state into the Red column.</p>
<blockquote><p>Tuesday’s recall election of Republican Gov. Scott Walker is the most expensive in Wisconsin history. More than $63.5 million has been spent by candidates and independent groups, the overwhelming majority underwritten by out-of-state sources.</p>
<p>The record spending total was made possible thanks to the <em>Citizens United</em><i> U.S. Supreme Court decision — which had the effect of invalidating Wisconsin’s century-old ban on independent expenditures by corporations and unions — and a state law that allows unlimited contributions to the incumbent in recall elections.&#8221; <a href="http://www.iwatchnews.org/2012/06/03/9039/wisconsin-recall-breaks-record-thanks-outside-cash" target="_blank">Election a national referendum on public sector unions</a></i></p></blockquote>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />Having amassed a sizeable war chest directly resulting from United Citizen&#8217;s opening the donation flood gates for corporate interests and a state law allowing recalled Governor Walker unlimited contributions, Walker has a slight lead and is favored to win. While this may end the recall efforts by angered unions and others, Walker&#8217;s troubles may not be over as he faces indictment over fundraising efforts by aides and his choice for Lieutenant Governor Brett Davis. There is quite a bit of speculation how this will all play out and it is not the first time the former Milwaukee County Executive has found himself in trouble for questionable activities.</p>
<p>
<blockquote><i><i>Kelly Rindfleisch said she was hired to campaign illegally for Scott Walker on taxpayer time</i>,&#8217; Democratic Party of Wisconsin Chair Mike Tate said Tuesday. “<i>With his admission that Rindfleisch was hired to do what &#8216;she was expected to do,’ has Scott Walker now implicated himself in the criminal conspiracy that was central to his rise to political power? </i></i></p></blockquote>
<p><i><br /><a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/rickungar/2012/06/03/is-scott-walker-facing-indictment-and-does-it-really-matter-to-walkers-wisconsin-supporters/" target="_blank">Is Scott Walker Facing Indictment And Does It Really Matter To Walker&#8217;s Wisconsin Supporters?</a>  Forbes</p>
<p><a href="http://www.wuwm.com/news/wuwm_news.php?articleid=10528" target="_blank">John Doe Judge Grants Immunity to Walker&#8217;s Former Spokeswoman</a>  WUWM Public Radio</i>
<div><i><br /></i></div>
<div><i><a href="http://www.politiscoop.com/us-politics/wisconsin-politics/1406-breaking-scott-walker-says-aide-indicted-was-doing-what-she-was-expected-to-do.html" target="_blank">Scott Walker Says Aide Indicted Was Doing What She Was Expected To Do</a>  Politiscoop</i></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/06/united-citizens-and-wisconsin.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
