<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Meet the Press &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Paul Ryan Says Taxes Should Be Raised to Pre-Bush-Tax-Cut Levels. But the Republicans Will Opt Instead For the “Sequester.” Unless, Of Course, the Koch Brothers Intervene.</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/paul-ryan-says-taxes-should-be-raised-to-pre-bush-tax-cut-levels-but-the-republicans-will-opt-instead-for-the-sequester-unless-of-course-the-koch-brothers-intervene.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/paul-ryan-says-taxes-should-be-raised-to-pre-bush-tax-cut-levels-but-the-republicans-will-opt-instead-for-the-sequester-unless-of-course-the-koch-brothers-intervene.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 31 Jan 2013 17:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[David Gregory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Keynesian economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Meet the Press]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the Koch brothers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the sequester]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/paul-ryan-says-taxes-should-be-raised-to-pre-bush-tax-cut-levels-but-the-republicans-will-opt-instead-for-the-sequester-unless-of-course-the-koch-brothers-intervene.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[There were three big political stories that came out of David Gregory’s fabulously interesting interview of Paul Ryan aired last Sunday on Meet the Press.  One was that Ryan said: Well, we can debate the efficacy of Keynesian economics or not. And I don’t obviously believe– I think the debt is pretty clear it doesn’t [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There were three big political stories that came out of David Gregory’s fabulously interesting interview of Paul Ryan aired last Sunday on Meet the Press.  One was that Ryan said: </p>
<div dir="ltr">Well, we can debate the efficacy of Keynesian economics or not. And I don’t obviously believe– I think the debt is pretty clear it doesn’t work.</div>
<p>Another was that he said that if Bill Clinton were president, we would have solved the budget-deficit problem, a statement that he presumably bases on the fact that when Bill Clinton was president, he solved the budget-deficit problem.</p>
<p>The third headline-grabber from that interview was that the Republicans will allow the “sequester” to take effect, presumably because they think it’s pretty clear that Keynesian economics doesn’t work, and because Bill Clinton is not longer president.  If Bill Clinton were president, the Republicans would allow him to raise tax rates to the level he did in 2001, this time without having to have the vice president cast the 51st vote in the Senate for the tax increase, and with enough Republican votes in the House to allow a vote on the tax increase.  </p>
<p>In other words, if Bill Clinton were president, Ryan and his compadres would not keep refusing to allow the Bush tax cuts on annual incomes of less than $450,000, and tax cuts on corporations, capital gains, and dividends, to expire.  But because Obama, rather than Clinton, is president, they won’t. They should be allowed to expire, Ryan says.  But they won’t be allowed to expire, because Obama is president.</p>
<p>Instead, the Republicans will opt to test out the the efficacy of Keynesian economics, or not&#8211;depending, probably, on whether <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/01/chuck-hagel-is-threat-to-americas.html">the Koch Brothers pick up the phone and disabuse Ryan of his belief that Keynesian economics doesn’t work</a>.  Before Wall Street does.  </p>
<p>Here’s what I obviously don’t believe: That if Ryan actually obviously doesn’t believe&#8211;thinks the debt is pretty clear it doesn’t work&#8211;he has even basic knowledge of past and current economic fact.</p>
<p>I’ll take his word for it that he was being truthful about his belief. But I sort of expect that the Koch brothers <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/business/economy/sequestration-looms-contractors-dont-fret/2013/01/30/3bcf60ea-6b0a-11e2-af53-7b2b2a7510a8_print.html">and others</a> will educate him and other congressional Republicans who hold that belief, very soon. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/paul-ryan-says-taxes-should-be-raised-to-pre-bush-tax-cut-levels-but-the-republicans-will-opt-instead-for-the-sequester-unless-of-course-the-koch-brothers-intervene.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Chuck Hagel Is a Threat to America’s National Security! And to the Koch Brothers’ Financial Interests.</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/chuck-hagel-is-a-threat-to-americas-national-security-and-to-the-koch-brothers-financial-interests.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/chuck-hagel-is-a-threat-to-americas-national-security-and-to-the-koch-brothers-financial-interests.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2013 19:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Chuck Hagel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CNBC]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Keynesian economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Meet the Press]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The American Future Fund]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the Koch brothers]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/chuck-hagel-is-a-threat-to-americas-national-security-and-to-the-koch-brothers-financial-interests.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The American Future Fund is an Iowa based 501(c)(4) tax-exempt organization affiliated with the Center to Protect Patient Rights, which in turn has reported ties to billionaires Charles G. Koch andDavid H. Koch. American Future Fund was founded by individuals who worked for Mitt Romney&#8216;s 2008 bid for the Republican U.S. Presidential nomination. Nick Ryan, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">The American Future Fund is an Iowa based <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/501(c)(4)">501(c)(4)</a> tax-exempt organization affiliated with the Center to Protect Patient Rights, which in turn has reported ties to billionaires <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_G._Koch">Charles G. Koch</a> and<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_H._Koch">David H. Koch</a>.</div>
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Future_Fund#cite_note-7"></a></p>
<div dir="ltr">American Future Fund was founded by individuals who worked for <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mitt_Romney">Mitt Romney</a>&#8216;s 2008 bid for the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republican_Party_(United_States)">Republican</a> U.S. Presidential nomination. Nick Ryan, an adviser to Republican US Representative <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jim_Nussle">Jim Nussle</a>, founded the organization in 2007, with Nicole Schlinger, a GOP leader in Iowa, as its president. Its current president is Iowa Republican state Sen. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sandra_Greiner">Sandra Greiner</a>.</div>
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Future_Fund#cite_note-10"></a>
<div dir="ltr">The fund &#8220;advocates <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conservative">conservative</a> and free-market principles&#8221; and energy positions that include support for drilling offshore and in the Alaska National Wildlife Refuge.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Activities </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">In 2010 the American Future Fund reported over 9 million dollars of independent campaign expenditures to the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal_Election_Commission">FEC</a>, and 100% of its expenditures benefited <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republican_Party_(United_States)">Republicans</a>.</div>
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Future_Fund#cite_note-WP_Future_Fund_2010_spending-13"></a>
<div dir="ltr">In 2012 the organization funded ads supporting <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mitt_Romney">Mitt Romney</a>&#8216;s bid for the U.S. presidency. In the same year, it also funded ads attacking Missouri Attorney General <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chris_Koster">Chris Koster</a> and in support of California&#8217;s Proposition 32, which would prevent unions from collecting political contributions as paycheck deductions. </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">The organization does not disclose the names of those who have provided its funding.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Future_Fund">Wikipedia</a></div>
<p>Add to the Activities list an anti-Chuck Hagel TV ad. </p>
<p>Okay.  So I happened to catch a segment on CNBC just now (don’t ask; catching segments on CNBC is not quite part of my normal daily routine) that ended with an ad blasting Hagel for … um … a whole lot of stuff geared toward making people think he would have lots of conflicts of interest if confirmed as Secretary of Defense, even if he sells all those financial interests in defense contractor companies that the ad says he has, and in that company that invests in Iran, and stops flying on corporate jets. </p>
<p>At the end of the ad, the viewer is told that it’s sponsored by The American Future Fund.  Which I couldn’t identify from memory, since the names of these organizations all sound alike.  And are all very interested in America’s future.  </p>
<p>But, having seen the ad, I now knew that Hagel would be a very dangerous guy to have as Defense Secretary.  I just didn’t know who exactly he posed a danger to.  But thanks to Wikipedia, I know now.</p>
<p>Sounds to me like Paul Ryan should have consulted the Koch brothers before he declared on Meet the Press last weekend that Keynesian economics has proved to be a failure.  If you get my drift.  Those oil and gas subsidies and defense contracts <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Koch_Industries">that the Koch businesses receive</a> are important to our national defense &#8230; and to the economy.*
<div></div>
<div>*<i>Edited for clarity after initial posting.</i>
<div></div>
<div></div>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/chuck-hagel-is-a-threat-to-americas-national-security-and-to-the-koch-brothers-financial-interests.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
