<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>robotics &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Shedlock on automation</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/shedlock-on-automation.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/shedlock-on-automation.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Dec 2012 07:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[automation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mish Shedlock]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[robotics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/shedlock-on-automation.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Mish Shedlock points to this video of an automated Greek slaughter house, and opines: Automation Rules What can be automated, will. The number of things that can be automated increases every month]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://globaleconomicanalysis.blogspot.com/2012/12/what-can-be-automated-will-be-automated.html">Mish Shedlock</a> points to this video of an automated Greek slaughter house, and opines:<br />
<blockquote>Automation Rules</p>
<p>What can be automated, will.</p>
<p>The number of things that can be automated increases every month</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/shedlock-on-automation.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The laying on of scorn</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/the-laying-on-of-scorn.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/the-laying-on-of-scorn.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 15 Dec 2012 19:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[robotics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/the-laying-on-of-scorn.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Dan Crawford notes Paul Krugman&#8217;s change of heart on the increasing importance of automated systems, in particular robotics: In the past discussions at Angry Bear on the impacts automation might have on our lives, and the economics involved, gathered comments such as &#8220;You are a neo luddite&#8221;. As if widespread use of automated systems was [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Dan Crawford notes <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/12/paul-krugman-changes-his-mind-on.html" target="_blank">Paul Krugman&#8217;s change of heart</a> on the increasing importance of automated systems, in particular robotics:</p>
<blockquote><p>In the past discussions at Angry Bear on the impacts automation might have on our lives, and the economics   involved,  gathered comments such as &#8220;You are a neo luddite&#8221;. As if widespread use of automated systems was automatically good for us overall because we would have access to &#8216;more higher wage and higher skilled jobs&#8217;, cheaper goods, and robots need a work force to maintain them&#8230;of course, there was no offering of numbers of jobs and whether the wage premium for a college education would be maintained.   This is the time to pay more attention as &#8216;insourcing&#8217; gains traction as a buzz word&#8230;</p></blockquote>
<p>Peter Frasure <a href="http://www.peterfrase.com/2012/12/robots-and-liberalism/">Robots and Liberalism</a>, Sociology, CUNY Graduate Center responds, and offers a post as a lesson in scorn, and he was kind to me, tough with others:</p>
<blockquote><p>What I mainly find interesting is what all this interest in technology and jobless growth says about the limits of contemporary liberalism. We can all hope that Gavin Mueller’s reverie of Paul Krugman dropping LSD and becoming a Marxist will come to pass, but in the meantime his type seems to have no real answer. Nor do those of a more labor-liberal bent, like Dan Crawford at Angry Bear, who laments being called a neo-luddite and scornfully says: “As if widespread use of automated systems was automatically good for us overall”. As if a world in which we hold back technical change in order to keep everyone locked into deadening jobs is a vision that will rally the masses to liberalism.</p></blockquote>
<p>So exactly who is the man actually talking to??  What am I missing? </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/the-laying-on-of-scorn.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Paul Krugman changes his mind on impacts of automation</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/paul-krugman-changes-his-mind-on-impacts-of-automation.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/paul-krugman-changes-his-mind-on-impacts-of-automation.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 09 Dec 2012 12:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Paul Krugman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[robotics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/paul-krugman-changes-his-mind-on-impacts-of-automation.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In the past discussions at Angry Bear on the impacts automation might have on our lives, and the economics   involved,  gathered comments such as &#8220;You are a neo luddite&#8221;. As if widespread use of automated systems was automatically good for us overall because we would have access to &#8216;more higher wage and higher skilled [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the past discussions at <i>Angry Bear</i> on the impacts automation might have on our lives, and the economics   involved,  gathered comments such as &#8220;You are a neo luddite&#8221;.  As if widespread use of automated systems was automatically good for us overall because we would have access to &#8216;more higher wage and higher skilled jobs&#8217;, cheaper goods, and robots need a work force to maintain them&#8230;of course, there was no offering of numbers of jobs and whether the wage premium for a college education would be maintained.   This is the time to pay more attention as &#8216;insourcing&#8217; gains traction as a buzz word,</p>
<p><a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/12/08/rise-of-the-robots/" target="_blank">Paul Krugman</a> calls for a new look at the economics of robotics and economics :<br />
<blockquote>Catherine Rampell and Nick Wingfield write about the <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/12/07/technology/apple-to-resume-us-manufacturing.html?_r=0&#038;adxnnl=1&#038;adxnnlx=1354969645-6W1egOcP1AYVFCPICjjejA">growing evidence</a> for “reshoring” of manufacturing to the United States. They cite several reasons: rising wages in Asia; lower energy costs here; higher transportation costs. In a <a href="http://economix.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/12/07/when-cheap-foreign-labor-gets-less-cheap/?partner=rss&#038;emc=rss">followup piece</a>, however, Rampell cites another factor: robots.<br />…<br />This is an old concern in economics; it’s “capital-biased technological change”, which tends to shift the distribution of income away from workers to the owners of capital.<br />Twenty years ago, when I was writing about globalization and inequality, capital bias didn’t look like a big issue; the major changes in income distribution had been among workers (when you include hedge fund managers and CEOs among the workers), rather than between labor and capital. So the academic literature focused almost exclusively on “skill bias”, supposedly explaining the rising college premium.<br />…</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>If this is the wave of the future, it makes nonsense of just about all the conventional wisdom on reducing inequality. Better education won’t do much to reduce inequality if the big rewards simply go to those with the most assets. Creating an “opportunity society”, or whatever it is the likes of Paul Ryan etc. are selling this week, won’t do much if the most important asset you can have in life is, well, lots of assets inherited from your parents. And so on.<br />I think our eyes have been averted from the capital/labor dimension of inequality, for several reasons. It didn’t seem crucial back in the 1990s, and not enough people (me included!) have looked up to notice that things have changed. It has echoes of old-fashioned Marxism — which shouldn’t be a reason to ignore facts, but too often is. And it has really uncomfortable implications. </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>But I think we’d better start paying attention to those implications.</p></blockquote>
<p>Hat tip Martin Ford at Econfuture:<br />
<blockquote>The really big deal in the U.S. will be when automation hits the service sector/white collar jobs. Impact on :<a href="http://econfuture.wordpress.com/2012/08/20/china-robotsautomation-and-unemployment/" target="_blank">manufacturing in China might also be very significant</a>.</p></blockquote>
<p>(Lifted from an e-mail from Martin Ford and pointing to Paul Krugman&#8217;s article).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/paul-krugman-changes-his-mind-on-impacts-of-automation.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Reality going to the Dogs</title>
		<link>./../../2008/04/reality-going-to-the-dogs.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/04/reality-going-to-the-dogs.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2008 17:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Military expenditures]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[robotics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/04/reality-going-to-the-dogs.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This one is for those concerned about how we spend our tax dollars. It is a robotics project funded by the pentagon performed by Boston Dynamics called the BigDog. I&#8217;m not going to comment because I can think of many positives as in the moon shot program and transitors and I can think of many [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://gizmodo.com/368651/new-video-of-bigdog-quadruped-robot-is-so">This one</a> is for those concerned about how we spend our tax dollars.  It is a robotics project funded by the pentagon performed by Boston Dynamics called the BigDog.</p>
<p>I&#8217;m not going to comment because I can think of many positives as in the moon shot program and transitors and I can think of many negatives, as in militarizing space.  What do you think?</p>
<p>Enjoy.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/04/reality-going-to-the-dogs.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
