<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>patents &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Patents, innovation, asset class, and weapon</title>
		<link>./../../2012/09/patents-innovation-asset-class-and-weapon.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/09/patents-innovation-asset-class-and-weapon.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2012 14:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[courts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[patents]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[trade policy]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/09/patents-innovation-asset-class-and-weapon.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[While the issues involved are complex and also involve the use of government force to make it stick, and drug patents have a long and debated history, New asset class and much more at Dealbook points to a growing phenomenon for the global economy as well. Patents and innovation deserve a separate post, but the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>While the issues involved are complex and also involve the use of government force to make it stick, and drug patents have a long and debated history, <a href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2012/09/24/with-smartphone-deals-patents-become-a-new-asset-class/?nl=business&#038;emc=edit_dlbkpm_20120924" target="_blank">New asset class and much more</a> at Dealbook points to a growing phenomenon for the global economy as well.  Patents and innovation deserve a separate post, but the weapons of choice is heating up and involves much more than &#8216;competition&#8217;:</p>
<p>
<blockquote>
<div>“Patents are a volatile, spot market,” he said. “This is a market, but a market that is more like art than stocks or oil.”</div>
<div>Ron Epstein, chief executive of Epicenter IP Group, agreed that pricing patents, especially large portfolios, was difficult. But he said he thought corporate trading in patents would become more commonplace, and pricing more routine. Someday, he predicted, patent acquisition costs may be a standard line item in corporate earnings statements.</div>
<div>“By fits and starts, we are moving to a more efficient marketplace for innovation,” Mr. Epstein said.</div>
<div>Calling patents an asset class is shortsighted, said Kevin Rivette, a founder of 3LP Advisors. The larger value of a portfolio, he said, can be as a strategic tool to negotiate lower costs from a supplier or to alter a rival’s product plans.</div>
<div>“You can use patents to change the competitive landscape,” he said.</div>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/09/patents-innovation-asset-class-and-weapon.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Courts and intellectual property rights</title>
		<link>./../../2012/08/courts-and-intellectual-property-rights.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/08/courts-and-intellectual-property-rights.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 31 Aug 2012 18:09:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[intellectual property]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[patents]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[trade agreements]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[trade policy]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/08/courts-and-intellectual-property-rights.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Caught from the Washington Post&#8230;and also interesting knowing theTrans Pacific agreements allowing multinational CEOs and firms to sue in domestic courts: Apple patents were violated by Samsung, jury rulesApple won a sweeping victory in its landmark patent dispute against Samsung when a Silicon Valley jury ruled Friday that a series of popular smartphone and tablet [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Caught from the Washington Post&#8230;and also interesting knowing the<a target="_blank" href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2012/aug/27/pacific-free-trade-deal?CMP=twt_gu">Trans Pacific agreements</a> allowing multinational CEOs and firms to sue in domestic courts:
<div><a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/business/economy/apple-patents-were-violated-by-samsung-jury-rules/2012/08/24/d4e44b2a-ee3b-11e1-afd8-097e90f99d05_story.html">Apple patents were violated by Samsung, jury rules</a><br />Apple won a sweeping victory in its <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/business/technology/apple-samsung-have-their-final-say-in-court/2012/08/22/58918786-ec56-11e1-9ddc-340d5efb1e9c_story.html">landmark patent dispute</a> against Samsung when a Silicon Valley jury ruled Friday that a series of popular smartphone and tablet features — from the rounded rectangle shape to the way screens slide and bounce to the touch — are proprietary Apple innovations.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/tokyo-court-finds-no-samsung-infringement-on-apple-patent-in-latest-in-global-battle/2012/08/31/49b14bf4-f348-11e1-adc6-87dfa8eff430_story.html%20Chinese">Tokyo court finds no Samsung infringement on Apple patent in latest in global battle </a><br />A Japanese court on Friday dismissed Apple’s patent infringement claim against Samsung, a significant legal bounceback for the South Korean tech giant as the rivals wage a global battle over intellectual property. A Tokyo District Court ruled in a preliminary session that Samsung didn’t violate patents with its technology for synchronizing music and video between computers and smartphones or tablets. The ruling, the latest in a series of lawsuits and counter-lawsuits spanning at least nine countries and four continents, comes one week after a <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766">U.S. court dealt Samsung a costly defeat </a>that could lead to an injunction against some of its devices. Samsung shares rose after the Friday verdict, helping the company recover from sharp losses earlier in the week, reports <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766">Chico Harlan</a>:</p>
<p><a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/business/economy/chinese-firms-put-intellectual-property-lawsuits-to-work/2012/08/30/12d9a418-f1c3-11e1-adc6-87dfa8eff430_story.html">Chinese firms put intellectual property lawsuits to work</a><br />U.S. companies have long accused the Chinese of stealing their intellectual property. But now some in China are pointing the finger back. In recent months, Apple has been slapped with <a href="http://wapo.st/A3y291">lawsuits in China </a>alleging that the <a href="http://wapo.st/Snddk4">most valuable company in U.S. history</a> is infringing on patents and trademarks with a range of its products, from the iPhone voice assistant Siri to the Snow Leopard operating system. Many U.S. firms are used to accusing the Chinese of mimicking their products. But the lawsuits being filed in Chinese courts are evidence of a growing awareness in this country that intellectual property can be a valuable tool — for protecting your ideas and for squeezing money out of other companies, too, reports <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/jia-lynn-yang/2011/03/03/ABnOHIQ_page.html">Jia Lynn Yang</a>:</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/08/courts-and-intellectual-property-rights.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
