<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>BATNA &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>And the Wrong Words Make You Listen in this Criminal World</title>
		<link>./../../2011/07/and-the-wrong-words-make-you-listen-in-this-criminal-world.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/07/and-the-wrong-words-make-you-listen-in-this-criminal-world.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2011 01:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[BATNA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Idiocy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obama Administration]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/07/and-the-wrong-words-make-you-listen-in-this-criminal-world.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Mark Thoma, who supported (and probably voted for) the man during the primaries, is dumuch more gracious than I am: A vague promise from Democrats about the future is all but worthless right now, we&#8217;ve had too many promises broken already. Obama&#8217;s promises in particular mean nothing. The nicest thing I can do is describe [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Mark Thoma, who supported (and probably voted for) the man during the primaries, is du<a href="http://economistsview.typepad.com/economistsview/2011/07/sanctioning-blackmail.html">much more gracious than I am</a>:<br />
<blockquote>A vague promise from Democrats about the future is all but worthless right now, we&#8217;ve had too many promises broken already. Obama&#8217;s promises in particular mean nothing.</p></blockquote>
<p>The nicest thing I can do is describe this as BarryO&#8217;s &#8220;Only Nixon could go to China moment.&#8221;  But that&#8217;s because that slimy cocksucker was willing to sell out two countries—Formosa and Tibet—so he could discuss panda sex with Margaret Trudeau.</p>
<p>Obama&#8217;s version is selling out Democrats and Middle-Class and Aspiring Middle-Class Americans. When the best hope is that Stan Collender is right <a href="http://capitalgainsandgames.com/blog/stan-collender/2334/debt-ceiling-deal-may-be-serious-trouble-house">that bending over and sucking off isn&#8217;t going to be good enough for House Republicans</a>, it&#8217;s time for all you idiots who said no one should run against BarryO &#8220;from the left&#8221; to do the honorable thing and find your wakizashi and prepare four cups of sake. (I&#8217;m certain there will be plenty of kaishkunin volunteers to aid you in Doing the Right Thing.)</p>
<p>Democrats may still run someone against Obama from the left, though Timothy McVeigh is unavailable. But the attempt to destroy their political viability has been executed perfectly.  Glad BarryO &#8220;plays eleven-dimensional chess&#8221; now?
<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/07/and-the-wrong-words-make-you-listen-in-this-criminal-world.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
