<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>calculator &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Arms races and sales and Sunday reading&#8230;</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/arms-races-and-sales-and-sunday-reading.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/arms-races-and-sales-and-sunday-reading.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 Jan 2013 07:07:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[arms sales]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[calculator]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sunday reading]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/arms-races-and-sales-and-sunday-reading.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[From Reuters comes this piece on arms spending: Demand for big-ticket U.S. weapons is expected to stay strong for at least the next few years, the trade group said in a 2012 year-end review and forecast released in December.Fears resulting from China&#8217;s growing military spending (bolding mine&#8230;the US has about 4.8% spending to GDP ratio) [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>From <a href="http://www.reuters.com/article/2013/01/01/us-usa-asia-arms-sales-idUSBRE90005D20130101?article" target="_blank">Reuters</a> comes this piece on arms spending:</p>
<blockquote><p>Demand for big-ticket U.S. weapons is expected to stay strong for at least the next few years, the trade group said in a 2012 year-end review and forecast released in December.<br />Fears resulting from China&#8217;s growing military spending (bolding mine&#8230;the US has about <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/08/27/us-arms-sales-2011_n_1833602.html#slide=504167US...4.8%25">4.8% spending to GDP ratio</a>) should lead to enough U.S. sales in South and East Asia to more than offset a slowdown in European arms-buying, according to the forecast.</p></blockquote>
<p>(Dan here:) The graph offers a year to year estimate of China&#8217;s spending to GDP ratio.  What am I  missing?</p>
<div><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-JxKgFLlY6GU/UO7atuiz5RI/AAAAAAAABW0/MD74AmaOmTo/s1600/chinaarms.PNG" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="320" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-JxKgFLlY6GU/UO7atuiz5RI/AAAAAAAABW0/MD74AmaOmTo/s640/chinaarms.PNG" width="640"></a></div>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />The article continues&#8230;<br />
<blockquote>The trade group, whose members include Pentagon suppliers Lockheed Martin Corp, Boeing Co and Northrop Grumman Corp, did not put numbers to its 2013 forecast. Nor did the Pentagon&#8217;s Defense Security Cooperation Agency, which has overseen a boom in worldwide deals under President Barack Obama.</p>
<p>The security agency, in response to a Reuters request, said sales agreements with countries in the U.S. Pacific Command&#8217;s area of activity rose to $13.7 billion in fiscal 2012, up 5.4 percent from a year before. Such pacts represent orders for future delivery.</p>
<p>In 2012 there were about 65 notifications to Congress of proposed government-brokered foreign military sales with a combined potential value of more than $63 billion. In addition, the State Department office that regulates direct commercial sales was on track to receive more than 85,000 license requests in 2012, a new record.</p>
<p>Overall, the United States reached arms transfer agreements in 2011 totaling $66.3 billion, or nearly 78 percent of all such worldwide pacts, according to the nonpartisan Congressional Research Service. The 2011 total was swollen by a record $33.4 billion deal with Saudi Arabia. India ranked second with $6.9 billion in such agreements.</p>
<p><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-AGiYRSvHvX0/UO7auBYwieI/AAAAAAAABXA/Gfm7qQcG8yI/s1600/chinaarms2.PNG" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="232" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-AGiYRSvHvX0/UO7auBYwieI/AAAAAAAABXA/Gfm7qQcG8yI/s320/chinaarms2.PNG" width="320"></a>Rupert Hammond-Chambers, who consults for U.S. arms makers through BowerGroupAsia, an advisory with 10 offices in the region, predicted Southeast Asian defense budgets would expand steadily as a hedge against Chinese assertiveness in disputes in the South China and East China seas.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/arms-races-and-sales-and-sunday-reading.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
