<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>economic policies &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Elites Demanding Austerity Also Ignored Housing Bubble</title>
		<link>./../../2012/11/elites-demanding-austerity-also-ignored-housing-bubble.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/11/elites-demanding-austerity-also-ignored-housing-bubble.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Nov 2012 13:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[economic policies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fiscal cliff]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fiscal commission]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[housing bubble]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/11/elites-demanding-austerity-also-ignored-housing-bubble.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Dean Baker writes to the question of who is pushing the fiscal cliff idea: Elites Demanding Austerity Also Ignored Housing Bubble … it was somewhat shocking to see a book review in The New York Times by Noam Scheiber, an editor at The New Republic, that longed for the day when we will have people [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>Dean Baker writes to the question of who is pushing the fiscal cliff idea:</div>
<p>Elites Demanding Austerity Also Ignored Housing Bubble</p>
<p>
<blockquote><strong>… </strong>it was somewhat <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/11/04/books/review/the-signal-and-the-noise-by-nate-silver.html">shocking to see a book review in The New York Times by Noam Scheiber, an editor at The New Republic</a>, that longed for the day when we will have people who can use data to identify housing bubbles before they grow so large as to pose a serious danger to the economy.
<p>The personal slight is beside the point; the issue is that our elites are being allowed to construct an alternative reality that absolves them of responsibility for the ruined lives all around us. The reality is that people in positions of authority chose to ignore the evidence of a rapidly growing bubble and those trying to call attention to the dangers it posed. Instead, we have Scheiber giving us the &#8220;Who could have known?&#8221; story. His case is that the dynamics of the bubble were just too complicated for people to grasp given the tools available at the time. The people who clearly warned of the bubble, using data, simply did not exist in Scheiber&#8217;s universe.</p>
<p>If it were just Scheiber saying this on a rant somewhere, he could be easily dismissed as a crank. While he is a prominent writer on policy and politics, prominent writers say ridiculous things all the times.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />
<blockquote>But this was not just a random rant. It was a book review in The New York Times, by far the nation&#8217;s most prestigious newspaper. It is a paper that employs fact checkers and prides itself on accuracy. Would The New York Times allow a book reviewer to bemoan the fact that no one had questioned the existence of weapons of mass destruction in Iraq prior to the war?
<p>And the bubble warners were not entirely below The New York Times&#8217; radar screen. In fact, <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/25/weekinreview/the-nation-the-perils-of-predicting-financial-bubbles.html">several Times reporters</a> had <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/11/business/business-in-debate-over-housing-bubble-a-winner-also-loses.html">picked up</a> on <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/05/28/business/28home.html?pagewanted=all">warnings</a> of the housing bubble. In fact, <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/16/opinion/mind-the-gap.html">Paul Krugman,</a> perhaps the most famous economist in the world, used his New York Times column in 2002 to warn of the dangers posed by the housing bubble.<br />Given this history, how can an ill-informed book reviewer get away with making what is obviously an untrue assertion in a New York Times book review? The simple answer is that Scheiber&#8217;s &#8220;Who could have known?&#8221; story is quite comforting to people with power in this country.</p>
<p></p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/11/elites-demanding-austerity-also-ignored-housing-bubble.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
