<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>weather &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Snow today and tomorrow</title>
		<link>./../../2011/02/snow-today-and-tomorrow.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/02/snow-today-and-tomorrow.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2011 01:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[snow]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[weather]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/02/snow-today-and-tomorrow.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Snow today and tomorrow Reporting in so far from Mass., Rhode Island, Ohio, New York, Michigan, Illinois, on the snow storm surging across a third of the US. No pictures yet. Dan B. says: I&#8217;ve had enough. Between plowing my office, the shop, the home and mom&#8217;s. Then snow blowing the piles to make room [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>Snow today and tomorrow</strong></p>
<p>Reporting in so far from Mass., Rhode Island, Ohio, New York, Michigan, Illinois, on the snow storm surging across a third of the US.  No pictures yet. </p>
<p><strong>Dan B</strong>. says:</p>
<p>I&#8217;ve had enough.  Between plowing my office, the shop, the home and mom&#8217;s.  Then snow blowing the piles to make room for more.  Being, literally up to my hips in snow cleaning off the greenhouses and cancelling my office because I can not keep the hill of the driveway clean&#8230;<br />I&#8217;ve had enough.</p>
<p>After this current storm, I have a friend coming to the office with his Bobcat to clean out the 8 to 10&#8242; high mounds on both sides of the driveway at the bottom.  I have a unique situation such that the highway plows unload 2.5 lanes of snow that has been pushed for 200&#8242; the minute they hit my driveway.</p>
<p><strong>Spencer England</strong> says:</p>
<p>I’ve been in New England since 1974 and this is the first time I’ve ever hired anyone to do my driveway. Although after the blizzard of 1978 I did hire a crew to shovel<br />the snow off my roof. That one storm dropped five feet of snow. In the Boston area we are seeing building collapse already from the heavy snow on flat roofs even before this storm hits.  In one parking garage two guys were trapped in their car when the  roof collapsed on them. We already have five feet of snow and I am running out of room to but more.</p>
<p>Just did my deck shoveled before this storm for the first time this season. It was still relatively light snow, not ice and I could slide most of it under the railing rather than lifting it.. They expect the second snow this week to be a heavy wet one with freezing rain, etc<br /><a name="more"></a><br /><strong>Mike</strong> says:</p>
<p>I live sox blocks from the office and walk to work every day.  It was a very slow trudge today.  I suspect it will be worse tomorrow.  We also feed some feral cats and one dog which requires a drive.  It sucks in this weather but they gotta eat.</p>
<p><strong>Rebecca</strong> says:</p>
<p>I have to shovel a 2&#8242; by 10&#8242; sidewalk.</p>
<p><strong>Dan C.</strong> says:</p>
<p>Back in the day the private contractor who plows for the town had his young daughter with him, and Linda provided hot chocolate and coffee for the two (or me some other times) the next couple winters.  His daughter is in high school now, but he plows the area which includes our driveway and walk area.  At this point I am estatic for the favor.  I had to shovel a section of the roof for ice dams.</p>
<p>Of course the snow piles are over 8 feet by tonite.</p>
<p>No word from Linda or Ken, but my Chicago son says lots of snow for that city. I can hear Rusty grumbling from here!  As people check in I will add comments.  I expect Robert is doing fine with the weather in Italy.  Noni Mausa has the dogs out and sleds ready. </p>
<p><strong>Run75441</strong> says:</p>
<p> &#8230;work in Upstate New York in the snow belt and we are over 110 inches since December. We get plenty of snow. If you don&#8217;t like cross country skiing, downhill, or snowshoe-ing; you go dormant. Got snowshoes for Christmas as my oldest son kept my cross country skiis.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/02/snow-today-and-tomorrow.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
