<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Mish Shedlock &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>How To Debate Paul Krugman</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/how-to-debate-paul-krugman.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/how-to-debate-paul-krugman.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2013 21:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[austerity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Austrian economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jazzbumpa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mish Shedlock]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Krugman]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/how-to-debate-paul-krugman.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[On Saturday Mish wrote a really awful article with those words in it&#8217;s title. The article borrows these words and includes a quote from an even more awful article by Austrian school economist and author Detlev Schlichter.  Part of that quote is presented here. What makes him [PK] so annoying is his unquestioning, reflexive and [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>On Saturday Mish wrote a <a href="http://globaleconomicanalysis.blogspot.com/2013/01/how-to-debate-paul-krugman-ask.html">really awful article</a> with those words in it&#8217;s title.</p>
<p>The article borrows these words and includes a quote from <a href="http://detlevschlichter.com/2012/05/how-to-debate-paul-krugman/">an even more awful article</a> by Austrian school economist and author <a href="http://detlevschlichter.com/about/">Detlev Schlichter</a>.  Part of that quote is presented here.<br />
<blockquote>What makes him [PK] so annoying is his unquestioning, reflexive and almost  childlike enthusiasm for state intervention, even in the face of its  obvious failure, and his apparent unwillingness to probe any deeper into  the real causes of our present economic problems or to show any  willingness to investigate the effectiveness or ineffectiveness of his  particular medicine.</p></blockquote>
<p>I want to  make something perfectly clear before we go any further.  It is fine to  disagree with Krugman, or me, or the Pope, or anyone else, as long as  you bring facts, data, and some basic skill in rational discourse.  What  is not fine is misrepresenting someone&#8217;s position and then holding the  misrepresentation up to ridicule.  That is both vile and stupid.</p>
<p>Back to the quote: does that sound anything like the Paul Krugman who puts his ideas <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/">out there for the world to see</a> on a daily basis?  What I see in Krugman is thoughtful analysis, and  deep probing into both the causes of our problems and the consequences  of economic policy decisions.  You don&#8217;t have to agree with his  assesments, but you cannot validly deny that he is making them.</p>
<p>When the opportunities smack me in the face like  this, I put on my <a href="http://jazzbumpa.blogspot.com/2010/01/deep-stupid-14.html"><u><i>Krugman Truth Squad</i> </u></a>hat.   Schlichter offers us a standard issue stale Austrian anti-Krugman  diatribe. You have to wonder if he has ever bothered to read anything  that Krugman has written.   His wordy, repetitive, rambling, semi-coherent, desperate-sounding  article &#8211; which I cannot recommend highly enough &#8211; is an impressive  exercise in partial-truths, distortions, make believe, and straw man  stuffing.  He then hints that we should go back to the gold standard and  totally unfettered free markets.</p>
<p>Schlichter lists Krugman&#8217;s alleged assumptions, condensed here:</p>
<blockquote><p>1)   Recessions, depressions and crises are the result of the unhampered market. <br />2)   The Great Depression was caused by uncontrolled markets.<br />3)    Recessions, depressions and crises are practically the result of one  problem: a lack of aggregate demand.  .  .  .   It is the role of  government to get people spending again. This is done  by printing money and causing inflation so that people spend. <br /> 4)   The Great Depression was solved by the government spending lots of money and the central bank printing lots of money.</p></blockquote>
<p>Let&#8217;s  pause here for a moment and set aside the redundancy.  I&#8217;m not sure  points 1 and 2 represent PK&#8217;s view with any degree of accuracy.   Certainly they are gross oversimplifications and neglect other factors.   But if they are true, then point 3 can&#8217;t be.  Let&#8217;s set that aside, as  well.  Points 3 and 4 are reasonably close to the truth, though if you  read the original, point 3 runs off the rails as it continues.  </p>
<p>From there it only gets worse.</p>
<blockquote><p>5)   This explains ALL economic problems.</p></blockquote>
<p>So,  according to Schlechter, Keynes taught, Krugman believes &#8211; and would  have us believe &#8211; that loose money policies and causing inflation are  the right policy measures not only for recessions, but for boom times,  and periods of inflation, hyper-inflation, stag-flation, or any other  problem you can think of.  Even I <a href="http://jazzbumpa.blogspot.com/2011/02/accidental-keynesians.html">know enough about Keynes</a> to call that out as false. </p>
<p>The  redundency continues to pile up.  I&#8217;ll extract one more point. [#&#8217;s  6,7, and 8 are repetitions of #4 with various degrees of elaboration and  snark.]</p>
<blockquote><p>7)   If after many rounds of money printing and deficit spending, there  is still a recession, then only one conclusion is permissible: There was  obviously not enough money printing and deficit spending. We need more  of it.</p></blockquote>
<p>I don&#8217;t claim to  know everything, but I&#8217;m not aware of any situation in recent history  that has played out like this, so it looks like a Schlichterian  fantasy.  In the post WW II era, the combination of loose money and  fiscal expansion has generally kept recessions rather short, leading to  V-shaped recoveries, and putting the brakes on too quickly has  occasionally led to a double dip.  England has recently experienced an <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/business/2012/apr/25/uk-sinks-double-dip-recession-gdp">austerity-induced double dip recession</a>.   In the current U. S. doldrums, Krugman tells us fiscal frugality has  led to a slow and limping recovery.  This is credible since spending is  flat and GDP growth is anemic. [Graph 1]</p>
<p>
<div><a href="http://research.stlouisfed.org/fredgraph.png?g=f65"><img border="0" height="240" src="http://research.stlouisfed.org/fredgraph.png?g=f65" width="400"></a></div>
<div>Graph 1, Current Expenditures and GDP (log scale)</div>
<p>Has any modern major economy had a recession persist after &#8220;many rounds of money printing and deficit spending&#8221;?  Even in the Great Depression things <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/10/19/1933-and-all-that/">turned around pretty quickly</a> once New Deal policies were implemented.  But, as PK also tells us, recessions brought on by a financial crisis are <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/10/08/fact-checking-financial-recessions/">different from the typical post WW II recession</a>.</p>
<p>Schlichter doesn&#8217;t let up. Though this statement [emphasis added], &#8220;Krugman is the one who should be made to explain his policy  recommendations and who has to answer the criticism that <u><i>policies like  the ones he is recommending got us into this mess in the first place</i> </u>and  that <i><u>his policy ideas have been implemented for years to no effect</u></i>, at  least no positive effect.&#8221;  is hard to beat for sheer negation of reality [and for channeling Ron Paul],  the real capper is this: &#8220;Krugman is practicing Keynesianism as a religion.&#8221;</p>
<p>It is because of statements like this that I lose patience with people who use words like &#8220;<i>disingenuous</i>.&#8221; You can supply your own alternative vocabulary   Check Krugman&#8217;s Op-Eds and blog  posts, where he repeatedly demonstrates reality with <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/01/23/martin-wolf-hippie/">graphs and tables</a>, shows how <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/12/11/bleeding-europe/">austerity is failing right now</a> with real-world examples, and <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/12/30/is-our-austerians-learning/">admits it when he gets something wrong</a>.  When is the last time you saw a Krugman-hater do that?</p>
<p>Mish, to his eternal discredit, says of this nonsense: &#8221; Moreover, it appears to be 100% accurate.&#8221;</p>
<div>But, Mish continues, the real way to debate Krugman is demonstrated by Economist Hans Hermann-Hoppe in this one minute video.</div>
<p>This is genuinely awesome.   That an economist can be so thoroughly  wrong &#8211; wrong in general and wrong in every particular &#8211; about what  Keynesianism is and does, leaves me speechless, and that&#8217;s saying  something.</p>
<p>OK &#8211; almost speechless.  Any child can see  that the earth is flat and the sun revolves around it.  So let&#8217;s forget  the trivially unimportant technical  details and ask simple-minded, allegedly probing questions that in this  case are  totally unrelated not only to the policies Keynes and Krugman propose,  but to anything else in the real world, and then point and stare when  these questions cannot be answered &#8211; by anyone, while your minions nod  approvingly.</p>
<p>But would it work?  Mish concludes this way:</p>
<blockquote><p>Krugman would respond with incomprehensible gibberish &#8220;for wonks only&#8221;  as well as typical Keynesian nonsense about how paying people to dig  holes and other people to fill them up would start a chain reaction of  growth.</p></blockquote>
<p>
<blockquote>A child would see the answer was preposterous, but not a trained  economist, politician, or brainwashed academic. Paul Krugman, keynesian  economists in general, politicians wanting a free lunch, and most  academics are all incurable.</p></blockquote>
<p>
<blockquote>Nonetheless, Hans Hermann-Hoppe&#8217;s answer is indeed the correct one. By  asking questions a child will understand, some non-brainwashed people  will see Keynesian and Monetary stimulus for what they really are:  economic stupidity.</p></blockquote>
<p>In <a href="http://globaleconomicanalysis.blogspot.com/2013/01/libertarian-turned-keynesian-responds.html">a follow up article</a> [with a 5 point list that includes 2 naked assertion and 3  irrelevancies {seriously &#8211; Zimbabwe?!?}] Mish makes it clear that in his view monetary  and fiscal stimulus are BOTH stupid.   So, at this point it looks as if he &#8211;  with his straw man army and blatant intellectual nihilism &#8211;  and I have  devolved into a schoolyard game of calling each other <i>stupid</i>.</p>
<p>But I&#8217;m quite sure Mish is not stupid, and I&#8217;m fairly certain I&#8217;m not  either.  The real questions are these: who is paying attention to  reality, whose policies make things better or worse <i>in a given situation</i> [absolutism, anyone?] and whose concepts have had some predictive power  over the last several years.  [Here&#8217;s a hint:<a href="http://delong.typepad.com/sdj/2012/12/when-will-robert-murphy-conclude-that-he-just-does-not-know-what-he-is-doing.html"> it&#8217;s not the Austerians</a>.]</p>
<p>So, maybe a better way to phrase it is, &#8220;<a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/01/28/failures/"><u><i>Who is practicing their economics as a religion</i></u></a>?&#8221;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/how-to-debate-paul-krugman.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Shedlock on automation</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/shedlock-on-automation.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/shedlock-on-automation.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Dec 2012 07:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[automation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mish Shedlock]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[robotics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/shedlock-on-automation.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Mish Shedlock points to this video of an automated Greek slaughter house, and opines: Automation Rules What can be automated, will. The number of things that can be automated increases every month]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://globaleconomicanalysis.blogspot.com/2012/12/what-can-be-automated-will-be-automated.html">Mish Shedlock</a> points to this video of an automated Greek slaughter house, and opines:<br />
<blockquote>Automation Rules</p>
<p>What can be automated, will.</p>
<p>The number of things that can be automated increases every month</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/shedlock-on-automation.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
