<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>water &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Water, human rights and government failure</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/water-human-rights-and-government-failure.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/water-human-rights-and-government-failure.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 05 Dec 2012 05:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[David Zetland]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[government intervention]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[human rights]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[water]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/water-human-rights-and-government-failure.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by David Zetland Water, human rights and government failure I wrote a paper on a human right to water several years ago,* in which I made the point (using data!) that laws supporting a human right to water are unlikely to work in countries where the rule of law is weak.** But what about places [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by David Zetland</p>
<p>Water, human rights and government failure</p>
<p>I wrote <a href="http://ssrn.com/abstract=1549570">a paper</a> on a human right to water several years ago,* in which I made the point (using data!) that laws supporting a human right to water are unlikely to work in countries where the rule of law is weak.**    <br />But what about places where the rule of law means something? What about in California, where Governor Brown <a href="http://www.inlandvalleynews.com/2012/09/26/ca-governor-brown-signs-human-right-to-water/">just signed AB 685</a> into law? AB 685 was drafted into law as a &#8220;do something&#8221; response to the problems to the poor quality water that communities in the southern Central Valley were facing. These communities &#8212; mostly poor, mostly migrant &#8212; are in the middle of California&#8217;s &#8220;industrial ag&#8221; belt, and their groundwater was contaminated by runoff/seepage from cowshit generated at large-scale dairies (Happy cows! California #1!) and from excess pesticide/fertilizer applied at big farms.***<br />     <br />Although AB 685 sounds good, it actually does nothing concrete. It merely espouses a nice idea that will only be implemented if convenient. Here, in fact, is <a href="http://www.leginfo.ca.gov/pub/11-12/bill/asm/ab_0651-0700/ab_685_bill_20120925_chaptered.pdf">the entire addition to the State&#8217;s water code</a> [pdf]:</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<blockquote><p>SECTION 1. Section 106.3 is added to the Water Code, to read:   <br />106.3. (a) It is hereby declared to be the established policy of the state that every human being has the right to safe, clean, affordable, and accessible water adequate for human consumption, cooking, and sanitary purposes.    <br />(b) All relevant state agencies, including the department, the state board, and the State Department of Public Health, shall consider this state policy when revising, adopting, or establishing policies, regulations, and grant criteria when those policies, regulations, and criteria are pertinent to the uses of water described in this section.    <br />(c) This section does not expand any obligation of the state to provide water or to require the expenditure of additional resources to develop water infrastructure beyond the obligations that may exist pursuant to subdivision (b).    <br />(d) This section shall not apply to water supplies for new development.    <br />(e) The implementation of this section shall not infringe on the rights or responsibilities of any public water system.</p></blockquote>
<p>Although sections (a) and (b) sound good, sections (c-e) seem to create giant loopholes (I still cannot understand what &#8220;beyond the obligations that may exist pursuant to subdivision (b)&#8221; means).  <br />So, I see this bill as a non-solution to a problem that needs to be addressed by:  
<ul>
<li>Reducing pollution from agriculture; and </li>
<li>Requiring farmers whose pollution has damaged groundwater to pay for substitute water supplies to communities with &#8220;impaired&#8221; water supplies or pay for the relocation of the people in those communities (polluter pays). </li>
</ul>
<p>Without a doubt, this ridiculous bill is a failure because it shifts the costs of a problem caused by agriculture onto public water agencies, giving us yet another example of how farmers representing less than 3 percent of California&#8217;s population, economy and workforce screw over the other 97 percent of Californians.****   <br />So, that&#8217;s the most recent development in the ongoing, worthless &#8220;discourses&#8221; in water policy &#8212; a human right to water &#8212; and another example of how politicians <strike>totally screw up policy</strike> present empty promises as &#8220;solutions.&#8221;<br />    <br />If you&#8217;re interested in hearing more of my thoughts on this topic, challenging those thoughts, or adding your own ideas and impressions, then tune into tomorrow&#8217;s webinar on Chapter 11 of <a href="http://endofabundance.com/">my book</a> (A human right to water), <a href="http://meet15266574.adobeconnect.com/chapter11/">here</a> at 9am Pacific (<a href="http://www.worldtimeserver.com/convert_time_in_US-CA.aspx?y=2012&#038;mo=10&#038;d=12&#038;h=9&#038;mn=0">get the time in your location</a> and <a href="http://meet15266574.adobeconnect.com/common/help/en/support/meeting_test.htm">test your Flash installation</a>).    <br />Bottom Line: Words are nice, but deeds matter. The easiest way to get deeds is to create an incentive to act, and fine words from activists to politicians are hollow unless those politicians (and their bureaucratic minions) must deliver results.</p>
<hr>* I submitted the paper to <i>Water Resources Management </i>in August 2011, but they failed to find referees for it after one year. I withdrew it last week. FAIL.    <br />** I go on to suggest that a <i>property right</i> in water is more likely to result in water service to the poor, since they will be able to convert their rights into money, and money DOES flow towards those who can pay.     <br />*** I asked a representative of one of those counties about the &#8220;cowshit plume&#8221; in groundwater about eight years ago. She changed the subject to their LEED-certified office building. They were either too afraid of or owned by dairy farmers.    <br />**** This pattern holds in many countries, with the noble exceptions of New Zealand and Australia.</p>
<p>reposted with permission from <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/10/water-human-rights-and-government.html" target="_blank">Aguanomics</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/water-human-rights-and-government-failure.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Hurricane Sandy and choices for the future</title>
		<link>./../../2012/11/hurricane-sandy-and-choices-for-the-future.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/11/hurricane-sandy-and-choices-for-the-future.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 09 Nov 2012 15:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[climate change]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[David Zetland]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[early warning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[water]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/11/hurricane-sandy-and-choices-for-the-future.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by David Zetland   David Zetland is a senior water economist at Wageningen University in the Netherlands and maintains a blog on water issues at Aguanomics Hurricane Sandy and choices for the future I live in the Netherlands, where living below sea level for many years has driven the Dutch to take flooding and storm surges [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by David Zetland   David Zetland is a senior water economist at Wageningen University in the Netherlands and maintains a blog on water issues at <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/11/hurricane-sandy-and-choices-for-future.html">Aguanomics</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/11/hurricane-sandy-and-choices-for-future.html">Hurricane Sandy and choices for the future</a></p>
<p>I live in the Netherlands, where living below sea level for many years has driven the Dutch to take flooding and storm surges very seriously.*<br />    <br />It&#8217;s therefore interesting to compare the damage from the storm to the <a href="http://www.reuters.com/article/2012/11/03/us-storm-sandy-infrastructure-idUSBRE8A203G20121103">early warnings</a> that Americans had from the Dutch and scientists. Were the Americans right to have ignored those warnings? After all&#8230; &#8220;<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/11/03/opinion/our-latest-high-water-mark.html">Hurricane Sandy was a fluke, right?</a> A storm surged from 90-mile-per-hour winds of a hurricane colliding with a northeaster, perfectly timed with a maximum full-moon high tide. The statistical likelihood of this is once in every 500 to 1,000 years.&#8221;<br />    <br />Huh. I guess the 2010 book on my table [pp 51-52 of Book II <a href="http://www.rotterdamclimateinitiative.nl/nl/delta_cities_website/documents">here</a>] is about 497 years early:<br />
<blockquote>Storm surges along the eastern seaboard of the US are associated with either late summer-autumn hurricanes or extra-tropical cyclones in the winter period, so called nor&#8217;easters&#8230; the height of the hurricane surge is amplified if it coincides with the astronomical high time and additionally occurs at the time of new and full moon&#8230; hurricanes have struck the coastal New York area six times in 1900-1990, resulting in severe coastal flooding, damage and destruction of beachfront property, severe beach erosion, downed power lines, power outages and disruption of normal transportation.</p></blockquote>
<p>When I visited with Piet Dircke in Rotterdam (the center of Dutch vulnerability to floods) two years ago, we discussed the problem of flooding, and he gave me his book (<a href="http://www.rotterdamclimateinitiative.nl/nl/delta_cities_website/documents">free to download</a>, by the way). He was also disappointed that New Yorkers were not interested in investing the time and money necessary for protecting their city from surges and floods. How was that possible when the CEO of New York was saying this?  </p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-SP6gT6XXB-E/UJuyoDAJIiI/AAAAAAAAEGg/dKYxGBgkNi8/s1600/Bloom.PNG"><img border="0" height="255" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-SP6gT6XXB-E/UJuyoDAJIiI/AAAAAAAAEGg/dKYxGBgkNi8/s640/Bloom.PNG" width="640"></a><br />Well, it&#8217;s possible because they were trying to avoid relocating people and neighborhoods or paying $20-30 billion for a real (i.e., Dutch-quality) system for protecting the area that would [p. 59]:** <br />
<blockquote>&#8230; stretch across from Sandy Hook, N.J. to Far Rockaway, Long Island&#8230; providing protection to the outer boroughs of Brooklyn and Queens, additional northern NJ communities, Jamaica Bay and JFK Airport.</p></blockquote>
<p>Now it would probably have been impossible for New Yorkers and others in the region to build such a system in time for the (unexpected) arrival of Sandy, but was there any plan in the works? Not that I know of. That&#8217;s unfortunate, as the storm caused <a href="http://www.reuters.com/article/2012/11/03/us-storm-sandy-infrastructure-idUSBRE8A203G20121103">$20 billion in damages</a> to New York alone.***  <br />So what will happen next? The Dutch would engage in a ruthless triage &#8212; moving people away from vulnerable but poor areas while building up 1-in-10,000 year defenses for places that are too valuable to abandon (e.g., Rotterdam).  </p>
<p>Will the People of Sandy engage in the same ruthless triage, or will they make the same mistake as we&#8217;ve seen with the rebuilding of the Ninth Ward in New Orleans? That political decision to rebuild is a costly and populist gesture that is likely to end when the returnees are flooded again in the future.  </p>
<p>Although that mistake is possible, I am hoping the Bloomberg and others take the time to read this book (and all the other warnings and studies) and make the <a href="http://www.env-econ.net/2012/11/oh-sandy-the-aurora-is-risin-behind-us-1.html">right decision</a> to rebuild in safer places while leaving those who want to stay in unsafe places to pay for their own foolishness.   </p>
<p>Bottom Line: Climate change means that the environment is not going to be reliable and business as usual is going to get more costly. We need to learn a few things from the Dutch: (1) Be realistic; (2) Plan seriously; and (3) Spend seriously. Anything less is not just going to be tragic, but criminally incompetent.  <br />
<hr>* You may want to read my posts on the <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/08/dutch-deltaworks.html">Delta Works</a> and <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2011/01/learning-from-dutch.html">Delta Commission</a>, which addressed these dangers in the past and for the future, respectively. Read <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/05/dutch-water-expertise-does-not-apply.html">this post</a> on why it&#8217;s difficult for the Dutch to export their water &#8220;expertise&#8221; &#8212; mostly because the rest of the world faces water shortage rather than water superabundance.  <br />** They were paying more attention to redeveloping New York, since valuable real estate generates property taxes and flood barriers cost money. I just saw <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Urbanized">Urbanized (2011)</a>, which has an extensive narrative on The High Line and other cool projects but nothing about urban defenses.  <br />*** As well as causing vast grief and inconvenience. People unable to use the flooded subways or tunnels <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/video/2012/11/02/nyregion/100000001880180/after-sandy-two-wheeled-commute.html">took to bikes</a> to avoid horrible traffic jams (as well as the need to buy gasoline, which was <a href="http://www.buzzfeed.com/annanorth/13-people-trying-to-trade-sex-for-gas-on-craigslis">available for sex</a>). It&#8217;s a gratuitous tragedy that so many politicians have embraced &#8220;anti-gouging laws&#8221; that prevent prices from rising to balance supply and demand. Some gas stations stayed closed to avoid angry customers (or offer fuel for sex!); others stayed open but had cars waiting for hours to fill up. Read more on how these laws are counter-productive <a href="http://www.env-econ.net/2012/11/this-just-in-new-yorks-attorney-general-prefers-shortages-to-price-rationing.html">here</a> and <a href="http://knowledgeproblem.com/tag/price-gouging/">here</a>.  <br /><i>H/Ts to MR, MS and MV</i>  <br /><a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/11/hurricane-sandy-and-choices-for-future.html" title="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/11/hurricane-sandy-and-choices-for-future.html">http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/11/hurricane-sandy-and-choices-for-future.html</a><br />Labels:<a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/search/label/climate%20change">climate change</a>,<a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/search/label/floods">floods</a>,<a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/search/label/infrastructure">infrastructure</a>,<a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/search/label/institutions">institutions</a>,<a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/search/label/NL">NL</a>,<a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/search/label/oceans">oceans</a>,<a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/search/label/OPM">OPM</a>,<a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/search/label/politics">politics</a>,<a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/search/label/sustainability">sustainability</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/11/hurricane-sandy-and-choices-for-the-future.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>About reporting and water issues…</title>
		<link>./../../2012/11/about-reporting-and-water-issues.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/11/about-reporting-and-water-issues.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2012 10:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[David Zetland]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[water]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[water economics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/11/about-reporting-and-water-issues.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by David Zetland    David Zetland is a senior water economist at Wageningen University in the Netherlands and maintains a blog on water issues at Aguanomics. It&#8217;s not as simple as selling books Many people ask me to comment on statements made by journalists covering the water sector. Most of the time, I am happy [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by David Zetland    <a href="http://www.blogger.com/profile/11677758798533719965">David Zetland</a> is a senior water economist at Wageningen University in the Netherlands and maintains a blog on water issues at <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/10/will-san-diego-make-desalination-mistake.html" title="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/10/will-san-diego-make-desalination-mistake.html">Aguanomics</a>.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/10/its-not-as-simple-as-selling-books.html">It&#8217;s not as simple as selling books</a></p>
<p>Many people ask me to comment on statements made by journalists covering the water sector. Most of the time, I am happy to see journalists covering water issues, since they tend to promote awareness of the need to change our ways, but there are two big exceptions. The first is when a lazy journalist fails to see that water shortages are not caused by a failure to rain as much as a failure (of managers) to keep demand below supply. In those cases, I often leave comments or send emails to correct them, hoping that they look a little deeper in the future.   </p>
<p>The second problem is much more dangerous: a journalist posing as an expert.    </p>
<p>But what does it take to be an &#8220;expert&#8221;? Well, it doesn&#8217;t mean you need a PhD or need to spend years studying the topic. You need a decent framework that explains causes and effects within local institutions that also matches the knowledge and intuition of those who have lived with the situation for many years.     <br />Journalists can certainly explain the causes of a problem, how to resolve it, and why resolution may not be occurring. That&#8217;s why I admire the work of <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/06/when-rivers-run-dry-review.html">Fred Pearce</a> and <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/01/blue-revolution-review.html">Cynthia Barnett</a>, for example.    </p>
<p>But then we run into journalists who turn a few shallow anecdotes into a problem that can be &#8220;solved&#8221; in ways that won&#8217;t work. Although some of these journalists are sloppy (see above), others intentionally over-reach because <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/03/on-journalists-moonlighting-as-big-ticket-speakers-for-financial-firms.html">they are making money</a>.    </p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>I&#8217;m going to name two here (with specific examples) because I want to call attention to <i>their need</i> to do a better job in their jobs as &#8220;experts&#8221; (I&#8217;m not saying anything about their work as journalists) and <i>our need</i> to bring an appropriately critical perspective to their opinions. <br />
<hr>Why is this post important? People with limited attention rely on &#8220;prime time&#8221; outlets rather than study complex problems. That means that mistakes in those outlets can lead to an abundance of bad decisions.  <br />
<hr>So, that&#8217;s a preamble for why we need to care about journalists&#8217; accuracy, but let me also also clarify why I &#8212; as an academic &#8212; feel a need to correct their contributions to public discourse. It turns out to be more complicated than &#8220;that&#8217;s what academics do.&#8221;  </p>
<p>As you know, I&#8217;ve been giving my opinion on water policy for many years, writing on this blog, giving public talks, holding discussions with experts and stakeholders, and so on. In most circumstances, I combine my knowledge of economics, a familiarity with facts, and a sensitivity to other perspectives into an opinion on what I consider the &#8220;right&#8221; thing to do.  </p>
<p>Economists say that I do &#8220;normative economics,&#8221; i.e., the economics of what should be, but most economists practice what&#8217;s called &#8220;positive economics,&#8221; i.e., the economics of what is. These positive economists may carry out research describing the connection between water service and child mortality, or measuring the efficiency of water markets or the impact of new water tariffs on consumption behavior. I go further, using these results to advocate for policy changes.  </p>
<p>In that sense, I am not an academic concerned with the details of reality as much as a pundit* promising to deliver a future to those who follow my advice. I am not alone in that, and thus we arrive at the problem of identifying who&#8217;s right, a problem that is often ignored because people standing on high are more often believed than people standing on firm ground.  </p>
<p>It&#8217;s well-known, for example, that there are two ways to become a famous blogger: be famous or work hard.   <br />This definition will raise a warning signal to those interested in maximizing the quality of debate. There may be, for example, hundreds of people qualified to advise on improving urban water management, but these people may not get as much attention as a single tweet from Madonna (&#8220;OMG, I&#8217;m no virgin, but showering in recycled toilet water? Yuck. Gimme NATURAL water&#8221;).  </p>
<p>That tweet will be heard by many. Most will ignore it, but others will change their opinion about recycled water. In the resulting debate over indirect potable reuse, experts are buried under an onslaught of collective ignorance, the motion to recycle water is denied, and the utility continues to overpump a river full of wastewater into the drinking water system &#8212; to the future regret of everyone.  </p>
<p>The problem of short and clever vs 78 pages and precise is widespread. We see it in political debates, cocktail chatter, and the know-it-all friends with the same solution to every problem (some variation of education, regulation or markets).  </p>
<p>These opinions may be 50, 70 or even 90 percent right, but they tend to leave out caveats, qualifications and limitations that can render the opinion irrelevant or counterproductive. The trouble comes when readers and listeners assume the opinion is 100 percent right &#8212; perhaps more right than even the author would admit, given his attempt to present the essence of a complex idea while still understanding its limitations.   </p>
<p>That&#8217;s why academics can provide a useful service by recognizing the limits to what they know or can claim and explaining how complex systems are neither simple enough to understand nor manipulate. Academics, in short, are trained to be humble with their ideas.**  </p>
<p>So what can we learn from academics?   
<ol>
<li>Take the position of the other side, to understand and address their objections. This process means that you will need to either admit or correct your weaknesses. </li>
<li>Contextualize your idea within the conditions where it is appropriate while acknowledging that those conditions are not universal. </li>
<li>Think very carefully about how your idea will interact with existing policies, taking into account the ways that people have tried to deal with the problem &#8212; or not &#8212; in the past.</li>
</ol>
<p>Now, after all that long introduction and context, let me get to the journalists whose opinions are not expert in a few recent pieces.  </p>
<p>In <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2011/07/big-thirst-review.html">my review</a> of Charles Fishman&#8217;s <i>Big Thirst</i>, I said &#8220;his journalistic style was too breezy.&#8221; Indeed, his op/eds at <a href="http://newswatch.nationalgeographic.com/2012/02/10/ireland-charge-for-water/">National Geographic</a> and the <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/08/17/opinion/dont-waste-this-drought.html">New York Times</a> are oversimplified and misleading. In the former, he omits the facts that Ireland has charged residential users for water in the past and that non-residential users pay for metered water. Besides these omissions, which make his claims sound more significant than they are, he forgets (or does not know) that meters are not always cost-efficient to install and that customers always pay for meters, either up-front or in the long run.</p>
<p>In his NYT piece, Fishman&#8217;s &#8220;obvious&#8221; command and control &#8220;solutions&#8221; have been tried in many places. In some they work, in others they are inefficient from a cost or water perspective. He also omits the more fundamental discussion of why other, more effective actions are not taken (raising water prices in Las Vegas, for example) &#8212; an omission that makes me wonder if he&#8217;s looked any deeper than press releases and speeches by water managers and politicians. Journalists sometimes get a little over-used to dealing with the contents of the box they are given instead of looking outside the box &#8212; a job that academics (and activists) are accustomed to executing. His over-simplified perspective may sell books, but his solutions are more likely to be counterproductive than useful.</p>
<p>Frederick Kaufman expresses a fear of water markets in <a href="http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v490/n7421/full/490469a.html">Nature</a> and <a href="http://www.wired.com/wiredscience/2012/10/water-derivatives/">Wired</a> magazines that is straight out of science fiction: global water markets in which derivatives allow traders to hedge shortage in Kazakstan with grain production in Australia by borrowing against wetlands in Canada. His working hypothesis is weak on many levels. I responded to his Nature piece and Wired interview with several comments, but these will do here:  
<ul>
<li>Water is NOT EVEN CLOSE to fungible. Are you kidding about &#8220;icebergs and aquifers&#8221; as interchangeable? Go get $1 of tap water (about one cubic meter) and then move it to the other side of the room. Hard to do? Sure, since 1,000 liters weighs one ton. Water systems — let alone markets — will NEVER be integrated like oil, gold or computer ship markets because the costs of transactions are so high. </li>
<li>The greatest distortions in the efficient use of water are caused by political interference. In this sense, bad water management is the same as bad financial management, but don&#8217;t blame markets for bailing out &#8220;too big to fail&#8221; fools or failing to get water to efficient farmers or taps in poor countries. Blame politicians. </li>
<li>Water markets have been VERY useful in reducing water waste and directing water from the powerful and rich to the poor and powerless &#8211; because the rich are getting water at a lower price than the poor are willing to pay&#8230; </li>
</ul>
<p>Go read these pieces and ask yourself: Do these guys know what they are talking about? Should politicians and citizens turn their views and ideas into policies for managing our water? More fundamentally, remember that some people put out uneven work (I know I do). These pieces may not represent the norm for these guys (I sure hope not), but they risk damaging reputations built on solid work that combines relevant facts into a plausible narrative to explain how a situation arose and how it might be improved.  <br />No matter your answer, please leave comments here (or there) to tell me and them what we got right or wrong.  </p>
<p>Bottom Line: Journalists can cause a lot of damage when they misdiagnose problems, offer the wrong solution and appeal to fear, uncertainty and dread. What they need to do &#8212; and what I try to do &#8212; is explain the facts and barriers to change before suggesting gradual reforms to improve our water management.   <br />
<hr>* &#8220;Pundit&#8221; comes from &#8220;pandit,&#8221; a Hindi word for a scholar or teacher who has mastered a topic (classically Sanskrit language, vedic scriptures, Hindu law, etc.) under a guru. This definition could be applied to any &#8220;doctor of philosophy,&#8221; since PhD programs are designed to impart mastery over a topic to a student under supervision. I wouldn&#8217;t be surprised if pandits were also supposed to possess wisdom, a characteristic not required of PhDs.  <br />** I may be giving academics too much credit, as many of them disregard their training when it comes to arguing that their opinion is right &#8220;because I have a PhD.&#8221; Academics, OTOH, are routinely absent from debates in which they could make a useful contribution, due to a combination of shyness (PhDs are known for long hours of study not extroversion), professional incentives (professional publication is more important than social impact), and aversion to debate with non-academics who may neither respect their credentials nor engage in &#8220;structured fair play.&#8221;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/11/about-reporting-and-water-issues.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Water economics for beginners</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/water-economics-for-beginners.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/water-economics-for-beginners.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 28 Oct 2012 11:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[water]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/water-economics-for-beginners.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[From David Zetland (Aguanomics) comes this note… Marginal Revolution University [free, online] has released 14 lessons (2-7 min, each) on water economics as part of its development economics unit. They give a decent introduction to several issues. I am going to contribute a few lessons. The series has a point of view about an economic [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>From David Zetland (<i>Aguanomics</i>) comes this note…<br />
<blockquote>Marginal Revolution University [free, online] has released 14 lessons (2-7 min, each) on water economics as part of <a href="http://aguanomics.hosted.phplist.com/lists/lt.php?id=LEUNBUwAVE9QCA%3D%3D">its development economics unit</a>. They give a decent introduction to several issues. I am going to contribute a few lessons.</p></blockquote>
<p>The series has a point of view about an economic approach to the issues, but offers a beginning for those new to thinking about the issues.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/water-economics-for-beginners.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Will San Diego make the desalination mistake?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/will-san-diego-make-the-desalination-mistake.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/will-san-diego-make-the-desalination-mistake.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2012 20:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[David Zetland]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[desalination]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[water]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/will-san-diego-make-the-desalination-mistake.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[(Dan here&#8230;a recent talk I attended on water in Burkina Faso reminded me to look at another important issue even for the US) by David Zetland    David Zetland is a senior water economist at Wageningen University in the Netherlands and maintains a blog on water issues at Aguanomics. Will San Diego make the desalination mistake? [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>(Dan here&#8230;a recent talk I attended on water in Burkina Faso reminded me to look at another important issue even for the US)</p>
<p>by David Zetland    <a href="http://www.blogger.com/profile/11677758798533719965">David Zetland</a> is a senior water economist at Wageningen University in the Netherlands and maintains a blog on water issues at <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/10/will-san-diego-make-desalination-mistake.html" title="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/10/will-san-diego-make-desalination-mistake.html">Aguanomics</a>.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/10/will-san-diego-make-desalination-mistake.html">Will San Diego make the desalination mistake?</a></p>
<p>Poseidon Resources has been lobbying to build a desalination plant in Carlsbad (San Diego County), California for around a decade, and I&#8217;ve been skeptical of that proposal (<a href="https://www.google.com/search?num=50&#038;hl=en&#038;safe=off&#038;q=Poseidon%7Ccarlsbad+site%3Aaguanomics.com">earlier posts</a>) &#8212; mostly because water consumption in San Diego is still quite high (ranging from 100-300 gallons/capita/day; compare that number to Sydney or Melbourne at 50 gcd!).</p>
<p>It makes more economical and environmental sense, in other words, for San Diego to reduce its demand before going for more supply (this <a href="http://www.kysq.org/docs/SDCWA_Supply%20Alternatives.pdf">year-old analysis of their supply alternatives</a> [pdf] lists desalination at $1,600/af but that cost is now up to $2,000+/af). </p>
<p>But San Diego politicians are not thinking in terms of environmental or economic sustainability. <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/03/san-diego-vs-mwd.html">They are at war with the Metropolitan Water District</a> over imported water and in alliance with <a href="http://www.water-alternatives.org/index.php?option=com_content&#038;task=view&#038;id=74&#038;Itemid=1">property developers who want more supply to build more subdivisions</a>. (It&#8217;s ironic, in fact, that SD leaders worry about the burden of <a href="http://www.kysq.org/docs/SDCWA2CNRA.pdf">paying too much for more water imported from Met via the Delta</a> [pdf] when they are prepared to throw caution to the wind for a local &#8220;solution.&#8221;)    </p>
<p>Those are just some preliminary comments and opinions based on my observations over the past 7-8 years, but there are some new developments that make these comments even more relevant.    </p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>First, the San Diego Country Water Authority is thinking of signing a <a href="http://sdcwa.org/issue-desal">30-year water purchase agreement</a> to buy water from Poseidon, an agreement that will make it possible for Poseidon to borrow money from the State of California (!) for constructing the plant.     </p>
<p>Second, that agreement does not specify how much equity (&#8220;skin in the game&#8221;) Poseidon will bring to the table in financing the $900 million project, but it DOES specify how much money Poseidon will receive for &#8220;overseeing&#8221; a project that it will neither design, nor construct, nor operate.     </p>
<p>Third, it appears that SDCWA will pay about $3.2 billion over 30 years for water that will be twice as expensive as its existing water supplies from Met. Given the industry-norm of charging average cost for water, that means that SDCWA will be selling water it buys for $2,000 per af for about $1,200 per af. Try swinging that business model past Wall Street. (The Independent Rate Oversight Committee <a href="http://www.kysq.org/docs/IROC2SDCWA.pdf">sure doesn&#8217;t like it!</a> [pdf])    </p>
<p>Fourth, you should read <a href="https://docs.google.com/file/d/0B_lZtMmwi5SXdnNCNzhLaGVzUlE/edit">my 6-page analysis of the water purchase agreement</a> (all 550 pages of what-the-hell-are-these-lawyers-saying!?!). <a href="http://sandiego.surfrider.org/independent-economist-is-leary-of-the-water-purchase-agreement-between-san-diego-county-water-authority-poseidon-resources">The Surfrider Foundation paid me to prepare it</a>, but &#8212; as usual &#8212; I acted as a consultant with a conscience: I put my original opinions in that report, since I am paid for honesty and accuracy, not groupthink. But read it for yourself.    </p>
<p>Bottom Line: San Diego should not build a desalination plant because it would be an <i>expensive non-solution</i> to water reliability problems that are actually caused by poor management of regional water at Metropolitan and a failure to restrict demand to sustainable levels.</p>
<p>reposted from <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/10/will-san-diego-make-desalination-mistake.html" title="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/10/will-san-diego-make-desalination-mistake.html">Aguanomics</a></p>
<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/will-san-diego-make-the-desalination-mistake.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Miya Water&#8217;s quest to plug leaks</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/miya-waters-quest-to-plug-leaks.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/miya-waters-quest-to-plug-leaks.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 24 Jul 2012 13:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[agriculture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[aguanomics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[David Zetland]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[urban water]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[water]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/miya-waters-quest-to-plug-leaks.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Via David Zetland&#8217;s Aguanomics. I continue to follow David&#8217;s thinking on how to plan, price, and ultimately use water in a 21st century manner. He offers interesting notions on the roles of government/pricing (and markets). There is currently big bucks involved and only to grow in importance and critical decisions to be made. Water is [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Via David Zetland&#8217;s <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2011/07/miya-waters-quest-to-plug-leaks.html" target="_blank">Aguanomics</a>.  I continue to follow David&#8217;s thinking on how to plan, price, and ultimately use water in a 21st century manner.  He offers interesting notions on the roles of government/pricing (and markets).  There is currently big bucks involved and only to grow in importance and critical decisions to be made.  Water is also an intensely watershed based arena (local) except when it is not. Re-posted with permission.</p>
<p>Miya Water&#8217;s quest to plug leaks</p>
<p>While in Jerusalem, I had the opportunity to speak with Tami Gaoni Feldman of <a href="http://www.miya-water.com/">Miya Water</a>.     <br />Her company is in the business of reducing non-revenue water (NRW), or water that goes into pipes but never <strike>reaches a customer&#8217;s meter</strike> gets paid for.<br />    <br />Well-managed water systems might have a NRW rate of 5 percent (due to fire hydrants, flushing the system, minor leaks, etc.). In a poorly-managed and maintained system, NRW rates range from 40 to 90 percent. The most common causes of high NRW rates are theft of water, non-payment of bills, leaking pipes and miscalibrated meters.<br />    <br /><a href="http://www.ib-net.org/">IBNET</a> tracks NRW rates for about 2,000 utilities.<br />    <br />Tami told me that Miya is working with one of two utilities in Manila, where the 300 staffers in the NRW division tackle 100 leaks per day and overall system losses of 300 ML per day (about 240 acre feet per day). Miya has had some success so far in reducing NRW from 67 to 50 percent.     <br />Miya uses three main tools to reduce NRW: monitor and fix leaks, manage system pressure to reduce leaks in low-demand periods (middle of the night), and increase payment for services. As a first step, Miya makes sure there are water meters at big junctions, to make it easier to track down branches with high 24/7 baseline use.<br />  <br /><a name="more"></a>  <br />These technical details were interesting, but Miya faces an additional problem: water managers and politicians facing water shortages prefer to increase supply (via desalination, reclamation, groundwater pumping, etc.) instead of reducing NRW losses.<br />     <br />This behavior does not make sense from a cost-benefit perspective. A decent NRW program will increase revenue per unit of treated water pumped into the system. Those revenues mean that NRW programs &#8220;pay for themselves.&#8221;<br />     <br />I hate to say it, but this feature is even more attractive than my &#8220;raise prices&#8221; recommendation: it&#8217;s an engineering solution (water managers like those) that will not increase prices (politicians like those).     <br />So why is it hard for Miya to sell its services?<br />     <br />I see two main reasons. First, a good NRW program requires up-front financing to pay for staff, software, meters, and so on. For most cash-strapped utilities, additional money is hard to come by. So why not get a loan from a bank or development agency? Because (according to Tami, but within my understanding) bankers are not familiar with NRW programs. They are more comfortable with making loans on physical assets like desalination plants that can be pledged as collateral.<br />     <br />Now stop and think about this for a second. What happens if a water utility fails to repay a loan on a NRW program? There&#8217;s no collateral to grab. What happens if it fails to repay a loan on a plant? Yes, there&#8217;s collateral, but then what? Are the bankers going to drag a plant from Dhaka back to Geneva? So the &#8220;collateral excuse&#8221; is hollow.<br />     <br />That leaves conservatism and one other excuse: managers and politicians <i>like</i> new facilities that they can pose in front of, cut ribbons for, etc. There&#8217;s no photo opportunity at a non-leaking pipe.    <br />We couldn&#8217;t think of any other reasons, but maybe you can.<br />    <br />Until then, I will conclude that NRW reduction programs are an underutilized method of improving utility performance.<br />    <br />Bottom Line: Every water utility should have a program to track, report and reduce its NRW rate &#8212; for its financial stability, environmental stability, and the good of its customers</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/miya-waters-quest-to-plug-leaks.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The water data hub is LIVE!</title>
		<link>./../../2012/03/the-water-data-hub-is-live.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/03/the-water-data-hub-is-live.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2012 15:17:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[agriculture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[aguanomics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[urban water]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[water]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/03/the-water-data-hub-is-live.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Who gets water at what prices in the US still appears to be considered a local issue in the US at its core, and at best regional during droughts that cross borders or as it pertains to agricultural use and &#8216;retail&#8217; (cities and burbs).  The issue of private versus public ownership is not very visible [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Who gets water at what prices in the US still appears to be considered a local issue in the US at its core, and at best regional during droughts that cross borders or as it pertains to agricultural use and &#8216;retail&#8217; (cities and burbs).</p>
<p> The issue of private versus public ownership is <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/search?q=drought+2007" target="_blank">not very visible yet in US news</a>, nor our need to <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2010/12/water.html" target="_blank">repair our infrastructure</a> (see my series on water  <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/search?q=water" target>links to Part 1-5</a>) .  And our friends in Texas haven&#8217;t sent any recent alerts to me on their current problems (have any of us followed any other drought concerns on the national stage?).  Water distribution questions did actually make national news in 2007/2008 droughts along the east coast and southwest but quickly disappeared.  However, the fault lines on who has access to water, news on how we actually obtain fresh water,  and questions on price structures became quite sharp and very legal in a only a year or two.</p>
<p>The question on an international scale remains largely invisible to US and perhaps is time to revisit.  The IMF and World Trade Organization ownership rules are considered arcane and not relevant unless it involves the occasional town water supply and a company like Nestle&#8217;s.</p>
<p>Ian Wren and David Zetland have begun the <a href="http://waterdatahub.org/">Water Data Hub</a> to help centralize primary source material worldwide.  The authors announced the hub to help centralize data at David&#8217;s <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/03/water-data-hub-is-live.html" title="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/03/water-data-hub-is-live.html">Aguanomics</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>I&#8217;ve been looking for a centralized source of water data for over a year, a place where I could go to find data on any kind of water question.</p>
<p>Although that quest led me to <a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=ibnet&#038;sitesearch=aguanomics.com#hl=en&#038;sclient=psy-ab&#038;q=ibnet%7Cib-net+site:aguanomics.com&#038;oq=ibnet%7Cib-net+site:aguanomics.com&#038;aq=f&#038;aqi=&#038;aql=1&#038;gs_sm=3&#038;gs_upl=13081l14906l0l15625l7l7l0l0l0l0l67l364l7l7l0&#038;gs_l=serp.3...13081l14906l0l15625l7l7l0l0l0l0l67l364l7l7l0.efis.1.&#038;pbx=1&#038;bav=on.2,or.r_gc.r_pw.r_cp.r_qf.,cf.osb&#038;fp=c0e94774f9e948be&#038;biw=1480&#038;bih=835">IBNET</a> &#8212; a fantastic resource on water utility data in many countries &#8212; I was unable to find a good centralized index of water data.    <br />Even more depressing, I was unable to get any interest or support out of organizations (USGS, World Bank, OECD, et al.) whose missions might imply support for just such an idea.</p>
<p>So, I decided to set up my own water data hub (WDH) &#8212; a central location that links to water data, no matter where it is, who owns it, or what dimension of water it describes.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Last November, I <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2011/11/bleg-drupal-programmer.html">asked for help</a> on this project, and Ian Wren (from San Francisco) joined me.</p>
<p>It&#8217;s thanks to Ian&#8217;s hard work (weekends and evenings!) that I can now invite you to visit <a href="http://waterdatahub.org/">waterdatahub.org</a>!</p>
<p>So, please go there and <i>add</i> data sources. The WDH, like <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/03/how-networks-grow-and-then-shrink-in.html">any network</a>, gains value with the number of links.</p>
<p>Oh, and don&#8217;t forget that <i>anyone</i> can add a link to the hub. You only need a <a href="http://waterdatahub.org/user/register">WDH account</a> (free and easy to set up). So, go ahead and add your favorite data source from the World Bank, Exxon-Mobile, the Nature Conservancy, et al.</p>
<p>Note by my wording that the WDH does <i>not</i> host, own or control data. It&#8217;s basically an index of data controlled by other organizations.<br />  <br />The big goal <i>now</i> is to make a census of data, so that we know what exists, what&#8217;s missing and what overlaps.<br />Future developments:
<ul>
<li>WDH 1.1: You can add records for data that exist but are not available to the public. This will make it easier to contact data owners to ask for access and &#8212; hopefully &#8212; to pressure them to release it to the public.</li>
<li>WDH 1.2: Anyone can comment on the <i>quality</i> of data sources held elsewhere; this will help everyone understand the uses and limitations of data &#8212; information that is not necessarily available from data owners.</li>
<li>WDH 2.0 (2013): We will start the very difficult process of &#8220;normalizing&#8221; data from many sources (using translation tables) to make it possible to assemble a data table from 2+ sources linked to the WDH.</li>
</ul>
<p>Note that the WDH will make it easier for <i>anyone</i> who analyzes data to do their job; analysis is too difficult to automate.</p>
<p>As you might expect, I am running WDH as a stand-alone, academic, non-profit. At the moment, we do not need money as much as your <i>time</i>.</p>
<p>Bottom Line: Please add new spokes to the WDH (get it?) and tell others about the water data hub.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/03/the-water-data-hub-is-live.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Water, Rights and Privileges, and Global Markets</title>
		<link>./../../2011/09/water-rights-and-privileges-and-global-markets.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/09/water-rights-and-privileges-and-global-markets.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2011 14:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[international aid]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[international trade]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[property rights]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[water]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/09/water-rights-and-privileges-and-global-markets.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[An article about famine in the Horn of Africa by Maude Barlow appeared today. It is worth your consideration. (h/t coberly) My own response is in comments. Following are excerpts: Most Westerners see the crisis in the Horn of Africa as a combination of a large population, chronic poverty, corruption on the part of African [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>An article about famine in the <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.ca/maude-barlow/africa-drought_b_936262.html" target="_blank">Horn of Africa by Maude Barlow</a> appeared today. It is worth your consideration. (h/t coberly)  My own response is in comments.  Following are excerpts:<br />
<br />
<blockquote>
<br />Most Westerners see the crisis in the Horn of Africa as a combination of a large population, chronic poverty, corruption on the part of African government officials, failed states and no rain, and that none of this will ever change so giving money to this self perpetuating crisis is throwing it away. But I offered another narrative that I believe is closer to the truth.</p>
<p>I believe the water and food crises in the Horn of Africa are the direct result of old-fashioned colonial exploitation: land grabs by foreign hedge and investment funds and wealthy countries setting up large foreign-based agribusinesses that are guzzling the lion&#8217;s share of the water resources and using them to grow crops and biofuels for export and drive up speculation.<br />
<br /><a name="more"></a><br />
<br />&#8230;<br />
<br />Foreign acquisitions are forcing small farmers and peasants off the land depriving them of access to food and water. The food and water of the region is being used for export for profit and not being used for local people. As a result, food prices in the region have gone up 200 per cent in less than a year and the price of water has risen 300 per cent. The foreign minister of Ethiopia defends his government&#8217;s actions with the neo-liberal explanation that these foreign &#8220;investments&#8221; will make the country wealthy enough that it can stop producing food and start buying it on the world market.<br />
<br />&#8230;<br />
<br />But exactly the opposite is happening when you drain the land of its water, as is being done by this agribusiness industry, and the rains stop coming. The drought is directly related to both climate change and the resulting desertification of a land stripped of its water sources. Here is what is essential to know: deserts can arise because humans treat land and water badly.<br />
<br />&#8230;<br />
<br />Desertification is taking place in over 100 countries in the world, as we strip the land of land-based water from aquifers and rivers, sending it to thirsty mega-cities (who dump it untreated into oceans), or using it to grow food and other goods for the world market, where it is transported out of local watersheds in the form of &#8220;virtual water exports.&#8221; </p></blockquote>
<p>[end of excerpts. feel free to research the subject yourself. if Barlow is right, she provides a much more reality based understanding of what is going on in the world than the usual politicized and politicized economics analyses we usually see&#8230; coberly]</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/09/water-rights-and-privileges-and-global-markets.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>World Water and ho hum</title>
		<link>./../../2011/03/world-water-and-ho-hum.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/03/world-water-and-ho-hum.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Mar 2011 15:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[agribusiness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[human rights]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[urban water]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[water]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/03/world-water-and-ho-hum.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[David Zetland at Aguanomics suggests that the problems worldwide with water for drinking and as importantly sanitation receives little attention. I like the poll on his site which suggests for the US that floods or droughts are the main driving force getting us to notice, or special interests. World Water WTF Today (March 22) is [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>David Zetland at Aguanomics suggests that the problems worldwide with water for drinking and as importantly sanitation receives little attention.  I like the poll on his site which suggests for the US that floods or droughts are the main driving force getting us to notice, or special interests.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2011/03/world-water-wtf.html">World Water WTF</a><br />
<blockquote>
<p>Today (March 22) is the annual circus of &#8220;look at me&#8221; articles, press releases, conferences and speeches by people and for people with attention-spans of a goldfish.   <br />Not my scene, so I am I&#8217;m giving you a break from the fracas, with BONUS funnies that <a href="http://xkcd.com/871/">put things in context</a>&#8230;</p>
<p><a href="http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/charity.png"><img border="0" src="http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/charity.png" width="400" height="201"></a></p>
<p>and <a href="http://xkcd.com/874/">help with priorities</a>&#8230;</p>
<p><a href="http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/time_management.png"><img border="0" src="http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/time_management.png" width="400" height="177"></a></p>
<ul></ul>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/03/world-water-and-ho-hum.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>King of California</title>
		<link>./../../2011/03/king-of-california.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/03/king-of-california.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2011 13:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[agriculture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[water]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/03/king-of-california.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[David Zetland at Aguanomics offers this review of a topic that gets little national attention &#8211; the use of water between watershed areas, water rights, and how we value water to date at least in this area of the country. Use of water and policy on water use tends to be regionally and locally based, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>David Zetland at <a target="_blank" href="http://www.aguanomics.com/">Aguanomics</a> offers this review of a topic that gets little national attention &#8211; the use of water between watershed areas, water rights, and how we value water to date at least in this area of the country. Use of water and policy on water use tends to be regionally and locally based, making a one size fits all answer to the problems of water use less than useful. </p>
<p><a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2011/03/king-of-california-review.html">King of California &#8212; The Review</a>
<p><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-XaQ74XLJcMY/TWpSHvqWeXI/AAAAAAAAB98/gVZw-2S42dU/s1600/ts.jpg"><img border="0" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-XaQ74XLJcMY/TWpSHvqWeXI/AAAAAAAAB98/gVZw-2S42dU/s320/ts.jpg" width="320" height="278"></a>In <a href="http://www.amazon.com/King-California-Boswell-Making-American/dp/1586482815">this book</a>, Mark Arax and Rick Wartzman illustrate the fascinating details behind a family that combined hard work, farming wisdom and political maneuvering to turn &#8220;lake-bottom land&#8221; into a farming empire, with help from government workers who may have ignored the Public interest and badly-written and ill-enforced government laws. <a name="more"></a>   <br />The book (subtitle: &#8220;JG Boswell and the Making of a Secret American Empire&#8221;) traces the story of the Boswell family, which left Georgia&#8217;s cotton lands for California. The Boswell began marketing cotton in Los Angeles and then moved into production, turning land, abundant water, and very sharp management into one of the largest farming operations in the US and world. I won&#8217;t summarize the fascinating, well-written story, but here are some notes I took on the way:<a name="more"></a></p>
<ul>
<li>During a conflict over flows from the Kings river in the 1880s, Mr. Church raised his dam on the river, reducing water available to downriver farmers. This action &#8212; more akin to &#8220;possession is ownership&#8221; than riparian rights or prior appropriation &#8212; invoked a similar response: the farmers downstream blew up the dam and got &#8220;their&#8221; water. See <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2011/02/irrigation-100-years-ago.html">this post</a> on irrigation in the West 100 years ago, including how the government has to subsidize projects too risky and unprofitable for private companies.</li>
<li>Huge land grants from the Spanish and Mexican eras were mostly along the coast of California, not in the Central Valley. The Mexicans allocated huge tracts in the Valley just before California was annexed by the US in 1850. These tracts were reaffirmed by the US Land Commission for California. In 1871, 516 men owned 9 million acres of California land. Those who later abused the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Newlands_Reclamation_Act">Reclamation Act of 1902</a> &#8212; including Southern Pacific &#8212; had lots of practice. </li>
<li>Miller &#038; Lux, two German migrants based in San Francisco, owned 1.3 million acres in the Central and Santa Clara Valleys. Some of their land was irrigated by the San Joaquin River, but farmers upstream were taking enough water by prior appropriation (&#8220;first in time, first in right&#8221;) to reduce flows next to M&#038;L properties with riparian rights (&#8220;take what you want as long as you do not damage your neighbors&#8221;). In resulting disputes, California &#8220;found a way to blend both riparian and prior appropriation rights under a formula of `beneficial and reasonable&#8217; uses. What this meant on the ground was that the water generally went to those with the most creative lawyers and engineers.&#8221; [p. 80]</li>
<li>The abuses of the Federal laws took place when individuals/families/corporations acquired multiple 80- or 160-acre parcels from programs dedicated to assisting small farmers and assembled them into illegally-large parcels. Abuses of water-related programs occurred when farmers with large farms took water that was supposed to go to small farms or paid subsidized prices for that water. Subsidies were (and still are) huge: Farmers only paid a portion of the cost of delivering water, without paying the capital costs of the projects that constructed them, the interest on those costs, and so on.     <br />The worst part of these abuses was not that the Federal Agencies (Bureau of Reclamation or US Army Corps of Engineers) willingly helped big farmers abuse and avoid the rules. It wasn&#8217;t that politicians exempted abuses via special amendments in unrelated laws. It was that these very talented and rich farmers took the subsidized land and water instead of paying the market rate. That&#8217;s like Bill Gates paying $0.85 for his $2.00 Big Mac.       <br />Of course, this kind of corruption, of the rich and powerful working with government to become more rich and powerful, has a long and infamous role in US policies, <a href="http://www.rollingstone.com/politics/news/why-isnt-wall-street-in-jail-20110216?print=true">including the recent financial crisis that bailed out Wall Street and left taxpayers with the tab</a>.      <br />So these were crony capitalists, not free marketeers. (There&#8217;s one point in the book where Boswell says he &#8220;sent back&#8221; his cotton subsidy check. Yes, he did that once, but cashed the other ones.) </li>
<li>Harry Chandler (1864-1944) ran the Los Angeles Times for &#8220;what is good for real estate&#8221; [p. 214]. That&#8217;s because he owned large tracts in the San Fernando Valley (his maneuvers to add water to them are portrayed in the movie <i>Chinatown</i>), Tejon Ranch, and other places. He was perhaps a central character in the story that I traced in <a href="http://ssrn.com/abstract=1129046">my dissertation</a>, and more directly in &#8220;<a href="http://www.water-alternatives.org/index.php?option=com_content&#038;task=view&#038;id=74&#038;Itemid=1">The end of abundance: How water bureaucrats created and destroyed the southern California oasis</a>&#8220;</li>
<li>In the late 1970s, the government looked set to break up Boswell&#8217;s empire, based on its use of water reserved for 160 acre holdings. Boswell and Salyer (another big land holder) spent big money to &#8220;get access&#8221; to politicians and staffers, to present their views. In the end, they won an exemption from the limit, based on the idea that their private water rights were not affected by laws dictating that access to infrastructure <i>and</i> water was reserved for smallholders. Boswell et al. stayed in the business of collecting subsidies. (The weirdest case [p. 379] was when they got money for flood damage on land that they claimed was going to be used for wheat but were paid (in-kind) to not plant in wheat. When the government ran out of wheat for &#8220;payment in kind&#8221; for fallowed land, it bought wheat from Boswell&#8217;s other operations, to give it to Boswell, who sold it again. Without any of these programs, the land would have been flooded. With them, Boswell&#8217;s triple was worth millions of dollars.)</li>
<li>We know that big farms are good for individual farmers who can make more money from their management expertise. But small farms allow more people to make a living off of farming. Is that more productive? Maybe. Is it more profitable? Maybe (especially if subsidies are removed; they tend to go to bigger farms*).      <br />But are small farms better than big farms for the community? In a 1946 study that compared the company town of Arvin (dominated by the DiGiorgo family) to Dinuba, a similar-sized town in the area with many small farms, social scientist Walter Goldschmidt found Dinuba to be better in every way.** This result indicated that the logic behind the Reclamation Act was sound, even as it pointed out how Reclamation (and most other subsidy programs for farmers) had undermined the existence of towns like Dinuba.      <br />I&#8217;m not worried so much about reducing the number of people working in farming (currently <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agriculture_in_the_United_States#Employment">less than one percent of workers</a>) as much as the jobs those people have: 85 percent of them are hourly laborers making $8/hour. Why does that bother me? Because it&#8217;s the result of government subsidies, not free market dynamics.</li>
<li>Arax and Wartzman ask an important question near the end of their book: big farmers like Boswell used federal subsidies to build huge farms on the bottom of a lake. They got rich and their crops were part of a vast system chasing yield. What were the costs? The Tulare Lake &#8212; the largest lake west of the Mississippi &#8212; was turned into farm land with troublesome runoff and little environmental value. Taxpayers sent huge checks to &#8220;welfare farmers.&#8221; Their workers were more like wage slaves than farmers. Communities (as <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2009/11/subsidies-and-poverty-go-together.html">Lloyd Carter has documented</a>) were weak and troubled.</li>
</ul>
<p> I will soon post more on government failure in agricultural policy (Westlands).  <br />Bottom Line: I give this book FIVE STARS as a fascinating history of a family that was good at farming and even better at working with bureaucrats and politicians to destroy the environment, local communities and small farmers for the sake of more subsidies, cheaper land, and free water.<br />
<hr> * <a href="http://www.ncifap.org/_images/Big_Farms_USDA_report.pdf">According to the USDA</a>  [pdf], production and subsidies are shifting to larger farms that are run by wealthier people &#8212; and that&#8217;s only between 1989 and 2003!  <br />** There is some debate over whether Goldschmidt was right to conclude that &#8220;similar&#8221; areas ended up having such big differences in farm size and quality of life. Hayes and Olmstead review them in <a href="http://www.kysq.org/docs/Hayes-Olmstead_Arvin-Dinuba.pdf">this paper</a> [pdf] with useful notes on the size of oil revenues and cost of water pumping on farm size and crop mix. They claim that small farms would pay almost double the cost of water in Arvin without considering shared pumping facilities. But even without such quibbled, they also agree that the larger farms &#8212; however they got there &#8212; were not contributing to community life. (In other words, Las Vegas differs from San Francisco for many reasons, but do you want government programs to encourage more cities like Las Vegas?)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/03/king-of-california.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
