<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>capital adequacy &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Weekend Reflection Points</title>
		<link>./../../2011/09/weekend-reflection-points.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/09/weekend-reflection-points.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2011 19:49:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[alternative energy investment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Banks and Financial Institutions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[capital adequacy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[employer-provided health insurance]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[environment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[risk management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[TARP]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/09/weekend-reflection-points.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The lead article in the current AER is available here (gated, apparently, though the link isn&#8217;t working; h/t Tom Bozzo [on FB] and Brad DeLong; I was using the paper copy). The most interesting part so far: the authors only considered the documented costs of air pollution—not land, not water—in deriving the (embarrassingly negative) ROI [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The lead article in the current AER is <a href="http://www.aeaweb.org/articles.php?doi=10.1257/aer.101.5.1649">available here</a> (gated, apparently, though the link isn&#8217;t working; h/t Tom Bozzo [on FB] and <a href="http://delong.typepad.com/sdj/2011/09/coal-fueled-power-as-a-value-subtracting-industry.html">Brad DeLong</a>; I was using the paper copy). The most interesting part so far: the authors only considered the documented costs of <em>air</em> pollution—<strong>not</strong> land, <strong>not</strong> water—in deriving the (embarrassingly negative) ROI figures for coal and oil.</p>
<p>As Cousin Lucia and Tom Zeller, Jr., note today, <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/09/30/keystone-pipeline-meetings-nebraska_n_988203.html">the cost of water pollution makes oil power plants an even worse option</a>.</p>
<p>In such a context, Europe in general and Germany (the top maker of solar panels until China recently passed them) in particular <a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2011-09-29/utilities-giving-away-power-as-wind-sun-flood-european-grid.html">rubs in our faces that they&#8217;re winning on the alternative-energy sources front</a> (h/t Barry Ritholtz):</p>
<blockquote><p>The 15 mile-per-hour winds that buffeted northern Germany on July 24 caused the nation’s 21,600 windmills to generate so much power that utilities such as EON AG and RWE AG (RWE) had to pay consumers to take it off the grid. </p>
<p>Rather than an anomaly, the event marked the 31st hour this year when power companies lost money on their electricity in the intraday market because of a torrent of supply from wind and solar parks. The phenomenon was unheard of five years ago.</p></blockquote>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />Meanwhile, back in the U.S., it is no secret that Brad and Robert Waldmann are on one (affirmative) side of the TARP-was-a-success argument, and I&#8217;m on the other.* But even the Success crowd may pause to wonder <a href="http://uk.reuters.com/article/2011/09/30/business-us-usa-bailout-banks-idUKTRE78T0GR20110930">if the short-term &#8220;profit&#8221; was a good long-term strategy</a>:<br />
<blockquote>Some large U.S. banks would have stronger capital bases to better deal with today&#8217;s market stresses had regulators not relaxed bailout repayment criteria in late 2009, a new government audit showed on Friday.</p>
<p>Bank of America (BAC.N) Citigroup (C.N), Wells Fargo (WFC.N) and PNC Financial (PNC.N) were allowed exit the Troubled Asset Relief Program without raising as much equity capital as initially prescribed by the Federal Reserve, the TARP Special Inspector General said in the report.</p>
<p>Following bank stress tests earlier in 2009, the Fed gave several banks guidance that they must raise $1 in common equity for every $2 in TARP bailout funds repaid &#8212; a formula meant to enable them to withstand future stresses.</p>
<p>But this standard &#8212; which was never previously made public &#8212; was quickly relaxed, allowing Bank of America, Citi and Wells Fargo to repay taxpayers nearly simultaneously in <strong>December 2009</strong>,** raising a combined $49.1 billion in equity capital.</p>
<p>Enforcement of the $1 in equity for every $2 repaid guidance would have required $57.5 billion in equity capital to be raised by the three institutions. PNC was later allowed to exit TARP under similar relaxed guidance. [emphasis mine]</p></blockquote>
<p>The most <a href="http://www.sigtarp.gov/reports.shtml">recent SIGTARP report</a> (28 July 2011), uses the word &#8220;Bailout&#8221; only once in its 304 pages—and that&#8217;s in the title of testimony by Sheila Bair, &#8220;“Statement of Sheila C. Bair, Chairman, Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation on The Changing Role of the FDIC before the Subcommittee on TARP, Financial Services, and Bailouts of Public and Private Programs; Committee on Oversight and Government Reform, U.S. House Of Representatives.”</p>
<p>Noted for the record: Patch uses the <a href="http://maplewood.patch.com/articles/charter-schools-its-decision-time-c2a7f366">same</a> <a href="http://montclair.patch.com/articles/charter-schools-its-decision-time-360d31d0">article</a> (with minor customization) in multiple locales, highlighting it as a &#8220;local&#8221; piece. I defer to <a href="http://blogs.reuters.com/felix-salmon">Felix</a> as to whether this is in keeping with the rest of their &#8220;business model.&#8221;</p>
<p>As <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2008/12/real-world-business-for-economic-buffs.html">Dan</a> <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2009/07/update-real-world-business.html">Becker</a> <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2010/01/i-got-your-real-state-of-union-right.html">can</a> <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2011/07/once-more-i-want-more-spending.html">tell</a> <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2011/09/this-is-reality-of-real-small-business.html">you</a>, the small business &#8220;ownership society&#8221; is not for the faint of heart. Nor, as anyone who thinks about it for more than three seconds can tell you, is it <a href="http://www.businessweek.com/printer/magazine/rethinking-the-boosterism-about-small-business-09282011.html">a primary driver of employment growth</a>. Yet when the most visible and successful Management Consultancy in the United States thinks about growth, its <a href="http://www.mckinsey.com/en/Features/Growth/What_business_can_do_to_restart_growth.aspx">two primary points </a>are &#8220;take monies from the government&#8221; and &#8220;expand small businesses.&#8221; But give them credit for recognizing a point that is often obscured by <s>H1-B trolls</s> technology firm leaders such as Meg Whitman:<br />
<blockquote>[I]t’s not just the young who can help fill the skills gap; older, experienced workers can play a part, too. In the US aerospace sector, 60 percent of the workforce is over 45. A practical response would be for governments to remove barriers—<strong>particularly those related to the provision of health care and to benefits rules</strong>—that prevent older workers from staying in the workforce longer. Germany and the Netherlands raised the participation rate of the 55-to-64 age group by 21 and 24 percentage points, respectively, between 1990 and 2009. In the Netherlands, there were significant changes to pensions and welfare benefits to improve incentives to work longer, coupled with initiatives to change public perceptions, improve employability, and reduce discrimination against older workers. [emphasis mine]</p></blockquote>
<p>It&#8217;s nice to see McKinsey endorsing Medicare For All.</p>
<p>*As a general rule, the Econ-first analysts are affirmatives, the finance-grounded ones are negative. If you have to think about why that would be: one group makes its living finding $100 bills on the sidewalk that the other one swears cannot exist.  As the Mark Thomas of the world would note, the issue of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prior_probability">priors</a> might need to be addressed.</p>
<p>**The reason December 2009 is important is that it meant that monies that otherwise would have to have been used to shore up capital were instead paid out as bonuses by the now-uncontrolled banks, or, in Reuterspeak, &#8220;keen to escape executive compensation restrictions associated with the bailout funds.&#8221;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/09/weekend-reflection-points.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interlude</title>
		<link>./../../2009/02/interlude.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/02/interlude.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2009 19:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Bank Crisis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bank failure]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[capital adequacy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[humor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[risk management]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/02/interlude.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[What my brain wants to do: Bank capitalisation, stress testing, book value, and discussion of other data that clearly indicates the need for the nationalisation of several LARGE banks. What my brain is currently capable of doing: The cheerleader who saves the world? Hayden Pantierre (Heroes) George W. Bush (ex-President of the USA) Christy Carlin [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>What my brain wants to do:</p>
<p>Bank capitalisation, stress testing, book value, and discussion of other data that clearly indicates the need for the nationalisation of several LARGE banks.</p>
<p>What my brain is currently capable of doing:
<p></p>
<div>
<p>The cheerleader who saves the world?</p>
<ul>
<li><label for="4893727">Hayden Pantierre (Heroes)</label></li>
<li><label for="4893728">George W. Bush (ex-President of the USA)</label></li>
<li><label for="4893729">Christy Carlin Romano (Kim Possible)</label></li>
</ul>
<p><a href="http://www.acepolls.com/polls/842570-the-cheerleader-who-saves-the-world/results">View Results</a><br /><a href="http://www.acepolls.com/create">Create a Blog Poll</a></p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/02/interlude.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
