<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>contraception &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Real information on &#034;contraceptive pills&#034; and health insurance</title>
		<link>./../../2012/03/real-information-on-contraceptive-pills-and-health-insurance.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/03/real-information-on-contraceptive-pills-and-health-insurance.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Mar 2012 22:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[contraception]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health Insurance]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jon Hammond]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/03/real-information-on-contraceptive-pills-and-health-insurance.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Jon Hammond from econographia reseached the topic of contraceptive pills on the cost aspects involved with health insurance at my request. Instead of losing real data in the comments sections on previous posts, I am posting his findings here: Here are some of the empirical findings dealing with the insurance costs and cost-savings of coverage [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Jon Hammond from <i>econographia</i> reseached the topic of contraceptive pills on the cost aspects involved with health insurance at my request.  Instead of losing real data in the comments sections on previous posts, I am posting his findings here:</p>
<p>  Here are some of the empirical findings dealing with the insurance costs and cost-savings of coverage for contraceptive services.     The direct costs of providing contraception as part of a health insurance plan are very low and do not add more than approximately 0.5% to the premium costs per adult enrollee (see Daroch, J. E.). In 1998, Buck Consultants estimated that the direct cost of providing contraceptive benefits averaged $21 per enrollee per year (see Daroch, J. E.). The most recent actuarial analysis, completed by the Actuarial Research Corporation in July 2011, using data from 2010, estimated a cost of about $26 per year per enrolled female (see Callahan, C.)</p>
<p>However, with respect to the effect on insurance premiums when medical costs associated with unintended pregnancies are taken into account … including costs of prenatal care, pregnancy complications, and deliveries … the net effect on premiums is close to zero (see Washington Business Group on Health, Sept 2000). And when time away from work and lost productivity are considered (<i>factors salient to employers</i>) . . the total costs to employers are reduced.</p>
<p>PriceWaterhouseCoopers issued a report in 2007 which found that providing contraceptive services yields a net cost-savings (see Campbell, K.P.).     </p>
<p>The cost-savings impact of contraceptive services has also been demonstrated via the Medicaid Section 1115 Family Planning Demonstrations conducted in six states in the 1990s.     Please refer to Tthe February 2012 U.S. DHHS brief on this subject .. it contains both the content and full citations noted in abbreviated form above .. see here:</p>
<p><a href="http://aspe.hhs.gov/health/reports/2012/contraceptives/ib.shtml#_ftn17">http://aspe.hhs.gov/health/reports/2012/contraceptives/ib.shtml#_ftn17</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/03/real-information-on-contraceptive-pills-and-health-insurance.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Insurance and Birth Control</title>
		<link>./../../2012/03/insurance-and-birth-control.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/03/insurance-and-birth-control.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 04 Mar 2012 16:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[contraception]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health care costs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[healthcare insurance costs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jazzbumpa]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/03/insurance-and-birth-control.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In this Forbes article, Tim Worstall says he agrees with generally available birth control, but questions why health insurance should pay for it.    Specifically he says:  &#8220;But I really cannot see the point of trying to have health care insurance which then covers a multitude of treatments that aren’t really insurable matters, contraception being just [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/timworstall/2012/03/03/rush-limbaugh-sandra-fluke-and-why-is-contraception-part-of-health-insurance-anyway/">this Forbes article</a>,  Tim Worstall says he agrees with generally available birth control, but  questions why health insurance should pay for it.    Specifically he  says:  &#8220;<i>But I really cannot see the point of trying to have health care  insurance which then covers a multitude of treatments that aren’t really  insurable matters, contraception being just one of these (regular  shots, ‘flu vaccines, general everyday low level treatments in fact).</i>&#8221;  This is after he points out that, per Wikipedia, &#8220;<i>Insurance is a form of risk management primarily used to hedge against the risk of a contingent, uncertain loss.</i>&#8220;</p>
<p>The  first question this prompts in my mind regarding insuring against  (unwanted) pregnancy is what loss does that pregnancy entail?  The  answer is large measures of personal freedom, hundreds of thousands of  dollars in unplanned child-rearing expenses, and quality of life for the  potential child resulting from the pregnancy.  These are significant  risks, with <a href="http://www.prochoiceforum.org.uk/psy_ocr2.php">ramifications for society at large</a>,  involving the employability and  productivity (in a purely economic  sense) of the involved woman, and her uses of discretionary income.   Furthermore, unwanted children, particularly if the mother is single,  are more liable to live in poverty and neglect, suffer from illness and  abuse, become delinquent, and develop into adults that are  psychologically disturbed, draw welfare, and commit crimes.</p>
<p>So, there are significant personal hardships and costly negative externalities that result form unwanted pregnancies.  </p>
<p>Is it ironic that in the past right-wingers have proposed the <a href="http://mississippiappendectomy.wordpress.com/2007/11/19/black-women-in-the-1960s-and-1970s/">forced sterilization of welfare mothers</a>?  </p>
<p>Also, the hormone therapy we call &#8220;birth control&#8221; has many other preventive medial uses, including controlling <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmedhealth/PMH0001913/">endometriosis</a>.  So a focus in the merely contraceptive attributes is misplaced.</p>
<p>Currently,  more than half the states mandate that hormonal birth control be  included in prescription coverage, and since 1998, this coverage has  been included for all federal employees.  There is ample precedent for  this coverage, and insurance companies are well equipped to handle it.</p>
<p>Worstall conducts this thought experiment.</p>
<blockquote><p> Just to make up some numbers, say that the preferred method costs $30 a  month. But that having the contraception covered by insurance will raise  the premium by $50 a month. The insurance company does, after all, have  certain costs associated with taking the premium then paying it  straight back out again to buy the pill. Why would anyone do this? Why  not purchase the pill for $30, stiff the insurance company bureaucrats  the $20 and spend it on a couple of cocktails at a place where you might  meet someone who thinks that your being a contraceptive user is a good  idea?</p></blockquote>
<p>Of course, when you&#8217;re  just making up numbers, its easy to have them suit whatever fell purpose  you have in mind.  Suppose a much more realistic <a href="http://www.healthinsurancerates.com/56-birth-control-and-health-insurance.html">$16 per month</a>, and the whole make-believe argument  collapses.</p>
<p>Besides,  in terms of brute economics, the insurance company is better off paying  for decades of contraception in $30 increments than one avoidable  pregnancy at many thousands of dollars, if everything goes smoothly.    Let&#8217;s just say you can&#8217;t count on that.  </p>
<p>So far, this has been a basically economic argument.  Now let&#8217;s look at an issue of fairness and parity.  <a href="http://www.healthinsurancerates.com/56-birth-control-and-health-insurance.html">More than half of the prescription programs cover Viagra</a>.   Need I say more?</p>
<p>Worstall&#8217;s  argument has some logical consistency &#8211; he seems opposed to insurance  coverage of other types of preventive care.  But this is ignorant and  short-sighted.  A flu-shot is less than $25.  An office call is $90 and  up.  Prevention, in general,  is cheap, and treatment is expensive.  If  cost minimization is your goal, then the clear focus should be on  prevention.</p>
<p>Worstall&#8217;s problem, I think, is in relating  contraception to a free-market business model, though, as I have  indicated, he isn&#8217;t even understanding that properly.  The proper focus  also includes the high costs of the externalities that he conveniently  ignores.</p>
<p>The real root problem though, is in trying to  force-fit any health insurance system into a for-profit model.  There is  simply no way to reconcile the conflicting goals of profit maximization  and providing the needed services.  In fact, there are only three  avenues to profit maximization: raise premiums, deny coverage, or  emphasize prevention.</p>
<p>Whether this leads to the  conclusion that a single payer, government mandated program is the best  overall approach is left as an exercise for the interested reader.</p>
<p>UPDATE: I forgot the great positive externality of contraception &#8211; it prevents hundreds of thousands of abortions every year.</p>
<p>Cross posed at <a href="http://jazzbumpa.blogspot.com/2012/03/insurance-and-birth-control.html">Retirement Blues</a>. </p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/03/insurance-and-birth-control.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Will “We” Really Be Paying Sandra Fluke’s Healthcare Insurance Premiums?*</title>
		<link>./../../2012/03/will-we-really-be-paying-sandra-flukes-healthcare-insurance-premiums.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/03/will-we-really-be-paying-sandra-flukes-healthcare-insurance-premiums.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 03 Mar 2012 04:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Beverly Mann]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[contraception]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rush Limbaugh]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sandra Fluke]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the ACA]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/03/will-we-really-be-paying-sandra-flukes-healthcare-insurance-premiums.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Highlights from the transcript of Rush Limbaugh’s uber-viral Wednesday diatribe against Sandra Fluke (in case y’all missed it): What does it say about the college co-ed Sandra Fluke, who goes before a congressional committee and essentially says that she must be paid to have sex, what does that make her? It makes her a slut, right? It makes her a [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>Highlights <a href="http://www.rushlimbaugh.com/daily/2012/02/29/butt_sisters_are_safe_from_newt_and_rick">from the transcript </a>of Rush Limbaugh’s <i>uber</i>-viral Wednesday diatribe against <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/ezra-klein/post/meet-sandra-fluke-the-woman-you-didnt-hear-at-congress-contraceptives-hearing/2012/02/16/gIQAJh57HR_blog.html">Sandra Fluke</a> (in case y’all missed it):
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>What does it say about the college co-ed Sandra Fluke, who goes before a congressional committee and essentially says that she must be paid to have sex, what does that make her? It makes her a slut, right? It makes her a prostitute. She wants to be paid to have sex. She&#8217;s having so much sex she can&#8217;t afford the contraception. She wants you and me and the taxpayers to pay her to have sex. What does that make us? We&#8217;re the pimps. (interruption) The johns? We would be the johns? No! We&#8217;re not the johns. (interruption) Yeah, that&#8217;s right. Pimp&#8217;s not the right word. Okay, so she&#8217;s not a slut. She&#8217;s &#8220;round heeled.&#8221; I take it back.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And:
</p>
</div>
<div>Well, I guess now we know why Bill Clinton went to Georgetown and why Hillary went to Wellesley. Well, all the sex going on at Georgetown. Sandra Fluke. So much sex going on, they can&#8217;t afford birth control pills. She said that to Nancy Pelosi yesterday. Pelosi probably said, &#8220;Have you heard what Botox costs? I can relate!&#8221; 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div><a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/rush-limbaugh-should-apologize-to-sandra-fluke/2012/03/02/gIQAo9gqmR_story.html">And</a>:
</p>
</div>
<div>So, Miss Fluke, and the rest of you feminazis, here’s the deal. If we are going to pay for your contraceptives . . . we want something for it. We want you to post the videos online so we can all watch.”
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>Expressions of disgust by, well, everyone have flooded the news media and the general web.  But, to my knowledge, no one’s asked why Limbaugh thinks “we” will be paying for Fluke’s, or other Catholic university students’, contraceptives.  Or (presumably) why he thinks “we” will be paying for the contraceptives of employees covered under employer-provided healthcare insurance, whether at Catholic universities, hospitals and charities, or elsewhere. </p>
<p><a name="more"></a></div>
<div>The government doesn’t pay student medical insurance premiums; the students do.  Nor does the government pay the medical insurance premiums of employees at any of the other employers who will be obligated under the ACA to provide minimum healthcare benefits; the employer and the employee together do.  <i>That</i>, of course, is what’s caused all the controversy about whether it violates freedom-of-religion guarantees of the government to require that the healthcare insurance that Catholic universities hospitals and charities provide their employees include contraception.  If the government were paying these premiums, this controversy wouldn’t exist.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<p>So Limbaugh’s statement directed at Sandra Fluke was vile, but it wasn’t just about Fluke and other students at Catholic colleges.  It targeted <i>all</i> women whose healthcare insurance, via premiums, covers contraception.  Limbaugh called them all sluts and prostitutes, and wants them to post videotapes of the sex lives in exchange for their school’s or employer’s, and their own, payments of premiums.</p>
<p>&#8212;&#8211;</p>
<p>*UPDATE: Limbaugh has now issued what he characterizes as an apology to Fluke for calling her a “slut” and a “prostate,” saying that the words were ill-advised and that he didn’t intend them as directed personally at her.  Earlier today, Fluke had said she’s considering suing him for libel.
<div>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/limbaugh-apologizes-to-law-student-for-insult-says-he-intended-no-personal-attack/2012/03/03/gIQAz53LpR_print.html">Washington Post article</a> about Limbaugh’s statement quotes him as saying, yesterday:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Amazingly, when there is the slightest bit of opposition to this new welfare entitlement being created, then all of a sudden we hate women. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>According to the Post, his statement today, a rambling press release, says:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I personally do not agree that American citizens should pay for these social activities.  What happened to personal responsibility and accountability? Where do we draw the line? If this is accepted as the norm, what will follow? Will we be debating if taxpayers should pay for new sneakers for all students that are interested in running to keep fit?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>So even as late as this evening when he released the statement, he’s claiming that <i>taxpayers</i>would be paying the part of employee and student healthcare premiums that cover contraceptives.  And that taxpayers pay for running pants, shorts and tank tops for employees and students who jog, but don’t pay for the Nikes and Reeboks. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Weird. 
</p>
<p>&#8212;&#8211;</p>
<p>
<div>ALSO SEE:  “Insurance and Birth Control” and “Rush Limbaugh Says Tax Money Pays For Students’ and Employees’ Jogging Pants As A Welfare Entitlement,” above, posted today respectively by Jazzbumpa and me.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/03/will-we-really-be-paying-sandra-flukes-healthcare-insurance-premiums.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
