<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>bias &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>I resemble those remarks!</title>
		<link>./../../2010/05/i-resemble-those-remarks.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/05/i-resemble-those-remarks.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 08 May 2010 06:43:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[bad economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Behavioral Economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bias]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Class war]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/05/i-resemble-those-remarks.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[By Daniel Becker (DOLB) Following up on Robert&#8217;s post which at it&#8217;s core is discussing the article: Economic Enlightenment in Relations to College-going&#8230;. I find it interesting (not alarming at all, at least not regarding the data) that the following combination is the ultimate economically enlightened member of society if you are: very likely to [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By Daniel Becker (DOLB)</p>
<p>Following up on <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2010/05/progressives-views-on-supply.html">Robert&#8217;s post</a> which at it&#8217;s core is discussing the article: <a href="http://econjwatch.org/articles/economic-enlightenment-in-relation-to-college-going-ideology-and-other-variables-a-zogby-survey-of-americans">Economic Enlightenment in Relations to College-going&#8230;.</a></p>
<p>I find it interesting (not alarming at all, at least not regarding the data) that the following combination is the ultimate economically enlightened member of society if you are: </p>
<blockquote><p>very likely to vote next time, voted for McCain, libertarian, white, not Hispanic/Latino, a suburbanite, atheist/realist/humanist, born again, attend church multi times/ week, non union, married, consider America you residence, are military (or family in military), NASCAR fan, think your in the investor class, shop every week at Walmart, earn over $100K/yr, male.</p></blockquote>
<p>One more thing based on their figure 2 chart: high school education or less. That group of educated had the highest economic enlightenment score.  That group of educated had the highest economic enlightenment score. There is a bit of concern with this data piece considering two of their sited points:</p>
<blockquote><p>The caveat that we see as most significant as pertains to the education variable is that the survey procedure likely tended to discourage low-IQ individuals from participation, thus artificially raising the observed economic enlightenment scores of the less educated groups&#8230; </p></blockquote>
<p>And: <br />
<blockquote>Meanwhile, Caplan and Miller (2006)&#8230;find that “the estimated effect of education sharply falls after controlling for IQ. In fact, education is driven down to second place, and IQ replaces it at the top of the list of variables that make people ‘think like economists.’”</p></blockquote>
<p>Do I dare suggest that they are finding that the most economically enlightened are the smartest people who never finished high school? You know, when I asked 2 years ago if we could try a different school of economic&#8217;s I did not realize the one we needed was the non-schooled school. </p>
<p>Interestingly enough, you are most unenlightened if you are </p>
<blockquote><p>progressive and college educated along with being: not likely to vote, voted green party, identify Green, African American, Hispanic/Latino, large city dweller, no religious affiliation, not born again and never attend church, union, civil union/domestic partner, consider your home the planet earth (no other planet offered), not military, not a fan of NASCAR (should have asked about horse racing), not of the investor class, never shop at Walmart (guess the other big boxes don&#8217;t count), $25K or less/yr (and they don&#8217;t shop at Walmart?), female.</p></blockquote>
<p>This is an amazing study. It managed to show that there are two groups of people in this nation whose thinking regarding money is totally reflective of the common cliche&#8217;s heard during the political season (which is a season with no ends) and are often applied slanderously. They have proven that the cliche&#8217;s are true!  But, then why would I expect anything else from this considering the following commentary from their “scholarly” piece of work: </p>
<blockquote><p>At least since the days of Frédéric Bastiat, many have said that people of the left often trail behind in incorporating basic economic insight into their aesthetics, morals, and politics. We put much stock in Hayek’s theory (Hayek 1978, 1979, 1988) that the social-democratic ethos is an atavistic reassertion of the ethos and mentality of the primordial paleolithic band, a mentality resistant to ideas of spontaneous order and disjointed knowledge. Our findings support such a claim,</p></blockquote>
<p>Ok, this economic ignoramus needs to go to his flower shop now. God help me if it goes under. I should have never gone to college. It&#8217;s my mom&#8217;s fault too.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/05/i-resemble-those-remarks.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Look at the Liberal Media: Media Bias?</title>
		<link>./../../2008/03/a-look-at-the-liberal-media-media-bias.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/03/a-look-at-the-liberal-media-media-bias.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2008 14:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[bias]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[media]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/03/a-look-at-the-liberal-media-media-bias.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[We&#8217;ve all heard that the media is biased. Those who make that argument typically point out (as proof) to the high percentage of reporters are registered Democrats. I&#8217;d like to argue that the high percentage of reporters that are registered Democrats is not a sign of bias, and might be just the opposite, in fact. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We&#8217;ve all heard that the media is biased.  Those who make that argument typically point out (as proof) to the high percentage of reporters are registered Democrats.  I&#8217;d like to argue that the high percentage of reporters that are registered Democrats is not a sign of bias, and might be just the opposite, in fact. </p>
<p>Here&#8217;s the annual growth in real GDP per capita over the length of each administration beginning with Ike.</p>
<p><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_yBU2IH33oeM/R86gbmi5efI/AAAAAAAABA8/xrJk7JF2Ops/s1600-h/real+GDP+per+capita,+Ike+to+GW.jpg"><img src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_yBU2IH33oeM/R86gbmi5efI/AAAAAAAABA8/xrJk7JF2Ops/s320/real+GDP+per+capita,+Ike+to+GW.jpg" border="0" alt=""></a></p>
<p>(Data from the BEA&#8217;s <a href="http://www.bea.gov/national/nipaweb/SelectTable.asp?Selected=N#S7">NIPA Table 7.1</a>.  Note&#8230;  growth rates calculated from the year before a President took office to his last full year in office.  Thus, for Ike, growth rates were calculated from 1952 to 1960.  Exceptions were made for incomplete terms&#8230; thus growth rates for JFK were calculated from 1960 to 1963, for LBJ from 1963 to 1968, for Nixon from 1968 to 1974, and for Ford from 1974 to 1976.  The data and calculations have been uploaded into <a href="http://spreadsheets.google.com/pub?key=p_ax_fywYILh6fYIqgogvcw">Google Docs</a>.) </p>
<p>Now, if you think I&#8217;m cherrypicking, NIPA table 7.1 has data going back to 1929.  Here&#8217;s the same graph extended that far.  (Note&#8230; because the folks who argue media has a liberal bias also like to say that the economy only recovered from the Great Depression as a result of WW2, I&#8217;ve broken FDR&#8217;s term into two:  FDR 1  is the term from 1933 to 1940, and FDR 2 is the term from 1941 to 1945.)</p>
<p><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_yBU2IH33oeM/R86gh2i5egI/AAAAAAAABBE/Uw_xvFAnl2o/s1600-h/real+GDP+per+capita,+Hoover+to+GW.jpg"><img src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_yBU2IH33oeM/R86gh2i5egI/AAAAAAAABBE/Uw_xvFAnl2o/s320/real+GDP+per+capita,+Hoover+to+GW.jpg" border="0" alt=""></a></p>
<p>Let&#8217;s say these weren&#8217;t graphs showing the annualized real GDP per capita growth rates over the length of each President.  Let&#8217;s tell a different story.  When cancer patients are treated with chemotherapy, it kills off production of their white blood cells, and because these cells are used to fight off infection, chemotherapy drains patients and makes them more likely to get infections.  Now, say there are two schools of thought for how to deal with this problem, the &#8220;red&#8221; school of thought and the &#8220;blue&#8221; school of thought.  If the graphs above showed the average change in the number of white blood cells of patients who had undergone either the red or blue program, would your first assumption, on looking at those graphs be:  &#8220;gee, any reporter who specializes in medical issues who gets cancer and asks his doctor to put him through the blue program must be biased&#8221;?   Sure, there could be mitigating circumstances, but unless there was some funny business with how the tests were designed or conducted or the data was collected in some odd way, most of us would be more likely to assume if there was something wrong, it would be among those reporters who developed cancer and nevertheless requested the red program to supplement their chemotherapy.</p>
<p>My point&#8230;  maybe most reporters are not familiar with the numbers.  They haven&#8217;t seen these graphs.  But they are still somewhat close to the action.  And they&#8217;re better educated about what is going on than the average person.  Perhaps if there are more of them that are registered Democrats than registered Republicans, there is a good reason for it.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/03/a-look-at-the-liberal-media-media-bias.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
