<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>protest &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Blanket the Earth</title>
		<link>./../../2011/10/blanket-the-earth.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/10/blanket-the-earth.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2011 20:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[income inequality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[OWS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[protest]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/10/blanket-the-earth.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The Rude Pundit Has a Brilliant Suggestion. OWS didn&#8217;t expect to be in Zucotti Park for more than two months. It looks as if they&#8217;ll be there a lot longer. UPDATE: Michael Swanwick shows how easy it can be: It&#8217;s Halloween! So Marianne and I went down to City Hall to donate a case of [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Rude Pundit Has a Brilliant Suggestion. OWS didn&#8217;t expect to be in Zucotti Park for more than two months.  It looks as if they&#8217;ll be there a lot longer.</p>
<blockquote><p>UPDATE: Michael Swanwick <a href="http://floggingbabel.blogspot.com/2011/10/boo.html">shows how easy it can be</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>It&#8217;s Halloween!  So Marianne and I went down to City Hall to donate  a case of water, a box of granola bars, and some M&#038;Ms (for the seasonality) to the Occupy Philadelphia people.</p></blockquote>
</blockquote>
<p>This presents some issues; that summer sleeping bag <a href="http://rudepundit.blogspot.com/2011/10/lets-actually-do-something-blanket.html">isn&#8217;t really adequate for NYC winters</a>:<br /><a name="more"></a><br />
<blockquote>[W]inter&#8217;s coming, fast up here in the Northeast. And while the Rude Pundit is convinced that the true flourishing of the Occupy movement will occur next spring (and into the awful summer and awfuller fall of an election year), there&#8217;s a core of the protesters who are gonna stay, no matter what.</p>
<p>Here&#8217;s what the Rude Pundit proposes, an action in the spirit of OWS:</p>
<p>On Friday, November 25, the day after Thanksgiving, Black Friday, the biggest shopping day of the year, as marketers force us to know, let&#8217;s give to our local Occupy encampments what they need to stay warm for the winter.</p>
<p>The deal: check out your local Occupy website. There&#8217;s <a href="http://occupywallst.org/article/urgent-winter-donation-needs/">a list</a> of all the <a href="http://www.occupybuffalo.org/donate/">things</a> they <a href="http://occupychi.org/supplies-needed">need</a> in <a href="http://occupynashville.org/">order</a> to flat out survive into the <a href="http://occupysf.com/get-involved/donate/donation-list-up-to-date">Spring</a>. [links to NY, Buffalo, Chicago, Nashville, and SF lists in original]</p></blockquote>
<p>Having shoveled snow this weekend—and knowing people in NJ, MA, and CT who are without power, and (especially in MA) don&#8217;t expect to have it back until the weekend at least—my only concern with this plan is that 25 November may be late.
<p></p>
<blockquote><p>Speaking of marketing, we could call this &#8220;Blanket the Earth.&#8221; We could organize this on, say, a <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Blanket-the-Earth/222529267813542?skip_nax_wizard=true#%21/pages/Blanket-the-Earth/222529267813542?sk=wall">Facebook</a> page or perhaps a <a href="http://twitter.com/#%21/blankettheearth">Twitter</a> feed or a hastag.</p></blockquote>
<p>
<p>Blanket the Earth it is.  Just make certain there are no <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/13/science/13mqa.html?adxnnl=1&#038;adxnnlx=1320092603-jAODVT6lYH4IoPmltq6f7g">smallpox virus cultures</a> in them this time.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/10/blanket-the-earth.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>A little OWS, a little 99%, a little history</title>
		<link>./../../2011/10/a-little-ows-a-little-99-a-little-history.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/10/a-little-ows-a-little-99-a-little-history.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2011 22:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[99%]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[deregulation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Job creation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jobs program]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[occupy wall street]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[privatization]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[protest]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[recession]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/10/a-little-ows-a-little-99-a-little-history.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[So today I read at the Yahoo Finance (it&#8217;s my home page because I can look at the stock numbers on the left and read the headline on the right for a guaranteed laugh) that  John Mauldin thinks the OWS would be better off if they occupiedCongress: Mauldin believes America still has time to figure [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div></div>
<div>So today I read at the Yahoo Finance (it&#8217;s my home page because I can look at the stock numbers on the left and read the headline on the right for a guaranteed laugh) that  <a href="http://finance.yahoo.com/blogs/daily-ticker/forget-wall-street-protestors-occupy-congress-mauldin-says-121137354.html?sec=topStories&#038;pos=main&#038;asset=&#038;ccode=">John Mauldin thinks the OWS</a> would be better off if they occupiedCongress:</div>
<div></div>
<blockquote><div>Mauldin believes America still has time to figure out a path out of what he says is the big problem worldwide: &#8220;We&#8217;ve over committed public monies and we don&#8217;t have them.&#8221; While some what sympathetic to the protestors&#8217; frustrations, Mauldin says their anger is misdirected.</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8220;My message to the &#8216;Occupy Wall Street&#8217; guys: if they really want to If  they really want to go after the source of the problem, they should go occupy Congress,&#8221; </div>
<div></div>
<div>Instead of focusing on Wall Street,Washington and the protests should be focusing on reducing regulation and making it easier for new businesses to start, Mauldin says. To that end, he offers a new slogan I somehow doubt will showup at any Occupy Wall Street protest anytime soon: &#8220;Up with Entrepreneurs&#8221;</div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div>As I understand it, OWS is about economic equality. President Roosevelt referred to it as the economic royalty. I just don&#8217;t see how one can stop, look and listen to OWS and think &#8220;go tell congress to further deregulation&#8221;. John Boy can&#8217;t be this much of an idiot, can he?</div>
<div></div>
<div>My sweetheart gets home from the dentist. $4000 dollars worth of bridge work is down the drain because a tooth of the bridge went bad. </div>
<div></div>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<div>For those who don&#8217;t know, we are the &#8220;Entrepreneurs&#8221; John Boy is referring to, thus we are paying for our health insurance, no dental. But, she was offered a payment plan. Has a nice dental name at 14.5% interest! This bit of private market solution to paying for health care is brought to you by GE Financial. Yes, the GE of Jeffrey Immelt, Obama&#8217;s job creating adviser. Hey Obama? Did you read my <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2010/01/i-got-your-real-state-of-union-right.html">state of the union</a>?  Obviously not or Jeffrey baby would not be your man.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Did you hear that <a href="http://real-economics.blogspot.com/2011/10/end-of-economically-progressive-left.html">JP Morgan was all blowed up</a>? Yes, I&#8217;m not lying. People got pissed at Wall Street and blew up JP: </div>
<div></div>
<blockquote><div>&#8220;During this period anarchists and socialists held protests on Wall Street out of a similar sense of frustration and rage at the banking system. The movement culminated in what was known as the greatest act of terrorism on American soil: the 1920 bombing outside J.P. Morgan and Company</div>
<div>Thirty eight people were killed when the horse and wagon bomb went off at noon on Sept 16, 1920. The perpetrators, thought to be anarchists, were never caught, but their exploits and the aftermath were captured by photographers.&#8221;</div>
</blockquote>
<div>Check out <a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/wall-street-bombing-anarchist-1920-2011-10?op=1">the pictures</a> here. </div>
<div></div>
<div>Why do we not hear about this history considering the present times? I know, stupid question. To ask it is to give purpose to OWS. Though one sector of this nation seems to remember a portions of this history or we would not be hearing the pejoratives being slung a the 99%&#8217;ers. You know Anarchists, socialists, communists out to destroy the American Way (A catchy phrase brought to you by the National Association of Manufacturers via General Food&#8217;s CEO, the US Chamber of Commerce and AT &#038; T&#8217;s monopoly is good all via Madison Ave,<a href="http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,756746,00.html"> Time Magazine 9/28/1936</a>) .</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>Which brings me to <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2008/09/can-we-please-broaden-our-thinking-in.html">my original question</a> since the shit hit the fan: HOW MANY TIMES DO WE HAVE TO DO THIS? HOW MANY FREAKIN&#8217; TIMES DO WE HAVE TO LEARN THE LESSON? </div>
<div></div>
<div>Obviously from the above 3 subtopics, quite a few more times as we seem to have not learned the definition of <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2009/05/define-rich-part-ii-rat-race-and.html">Rat Race</a> yet: A rat race is a term used for an endless, self-defeating or pointless pursuit&#8230;</div>
<div></div>
<div>I think I know what is wrong with US today. When I typed in Deja Vu at youtube,  amazingly <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HiDOMuhpqUo">this tune</a> did not even come up in the suggestion list. </div>
<p>No, I had to actually know that CSNY wrote what I consider the true musical capture of the concept of deja vu&#8230;the song that is most appropriate for the application of the concept today. I say this because they intentionally wrote the song so that it <i><u>does not</u></i> <i><u>repeat</u> </i>any one section (heard years ago in an interview). 
<div></div>
<div>Get it?</div>
<div></div>
<div>(I haven&#8217;t forgotten the tax tables. It&#8217;s a coming.)</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/10/a-little-ows-a-little-99-a-little-history.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
