<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>taxes &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>If I were writing that piece</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/if-i-were-writing-that-piece.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/if-i-were-writing-that-piece.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2013 15:43:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[recession]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wages]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/if-i-were-writing-that-piece.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Here is an interesting way to deal numbers, with the complete post to be read from the link: Obama taxes us into recession  (Mish&#8217;s musings) Withheld income and employment taxes have been running about 8.3% higher year over year, comparing the same 33 business days between Tuesday, January 8 and Monday, February 25.&#8230;Regardless, there is [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Here is an interesting way to deal numbers, with the complete post to be read from the link:</p>
<p><a href="http://globaleconomicanalysis.blogspot.com/2013/02/did-obama-tax-us-into-recession.html">Obama taxes us into recession</a>  (Mish&#8217;s musings)<br />
<blockquote>Withheld income and employment taxes have been running about 8.3% higher year over year, comparing the same 33 business days between Tuesday, January 8 and Monday, February 25.<br />&#8230;<br />Regardless, there is no doubt that the Obama Administration has taxed us into a recession. Congratulations.</p></blockquote>
<p>Lifted from several e-mails in response to the link being sent:</p>
<p>Ken Houghton:    If I were writing that piece, it would be about how the cuts in taxes last year are the only thing that allowed people to pretend we were in a recovery, which has otherwise been jobless. (Check out YoY for 2009 to 2010 or 2010 to 2011.) Krugman is probably right not to dismiss out of hand the idea that you can sustain economic growth with a plutocracy, but it&#8217;s not at all an even odds bet.<br />&#8230;</p>
<p>Personal income was just released; down 3%.</p>
<p>The game with numbers was to treat the employer side of SocSec tax as if it would otherwise be circulating. It&#8217;s more accurate to think of that as I than C. (I would argue all of SocSec payments are I&#8211;a &#8220;forced savings&#8221; program, as it were&#8211;but that&#8217;s a sidebar.)</p>
<p>And we know that those monies were not being reinvested last year. (See <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/02/does-saving-fund-investment.html">Steve Roth&#8217;s post a couple of days ago</a>.). Will be interesting if we see Excess Reserves start to fall when those tax payments all come due.</p>
<p>And a sad thank you, Mike. You and I may have improved our lot last year, but that was the exception, not the rule, and not without painful transition.</p>
<p>How we call extended joblessness and growth based on consuming savings a &#8220;recovery&#8221; befuddles me.</p>
<p>Dale Coberly:  As I may have tediously tried to point out elsewhere, rescinding the tax holiday is not a tax raise.. it is the end of a government &#8220;stimulus&#8221; funded by borrowing, unnecessarily attached to the payroll tax for devious political purposes.  the SS &#8220;tax&#8221;  is always circulating&#8230; it goes to benefits to the otherwise poor elderly who spend it right away.  unless you are going to fund those benefits by borrowing or taxing the rich,  reducing the payroll tax would reduce &#8220;circulating&#8221;  by the extent to which people &#8220;saved&#8221; that money for their eventual retirement&#8230; assuming they could find a way to &#8220;save&#8221; it, given the fact that no one is &#8220;investing.&#8221;  i guess we could go back to gold coins buried in jars in the backyard.  that should be good for the economy.</p>
<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/if-i-were-writing-that-piece.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Negative externality or just raising money</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/negative-externality-or-just-raising-money.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/negative-externality-or-just-raising-money.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Feb 2013 03:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[David Zetland]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[water economics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/negative-externality-or-just-raising-money.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Lifted from one of David Zetland&#8217;s Aguanomics musings on how our conversations mix things up: Gasoline taxes are often justified as the response to a &#8220;negative externality&#8221; of pollution from cars, but the money from those taxes rarely (never?) goes to people who suffer from pollution. So is it really a tax on an externality [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Lifted from one of <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2013/02/mias-review.html">David Zetland&#8217;s</a> Aguanomics musings on how our conversations mix things up:</p>
<blockquote><p>Gasoline taxes are often justified as the response to a &#8220;negative externality&#8221; of pollution from cars, but the money from those taxes rarely (never?) goes to people who suffer from pollution. <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2013/01/pigouvian-taxes-do-not-produce.html">So is it really a tax on an externality or is it just a way of raising money?</a></p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/negative-externality-or-just-raising-money.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Free market adjusts to taxes&#8230;like any other &#034;scarcity&#034;</title>
		<link>./../../2012/11/free-market-adjusts-to-taxes-like-any-other-scarcity.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/11/free-market-adjusts-to-taxes-like-any-other-scarcity.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 03 Nov 2012 09:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[free market]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[taxes]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/11/free-market-adjusts-to-taxes-like-any-other-scarcity.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Stolen from an e-mail from coberly and worth a comment or two I think: &#8230;&#8221;the free market&#8221; adjusts&#8230; freely&#8230; to taxes the way it adjusts to any other &#8220;scarcity.&#8221; but apparently economics has not discovered this fact.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Stolen from an e-mail from coberly and worth a comment or two I think:</p>
<blockquote><p>&#8230;&#8221;the free market&#8221; adjusts&#8230; freely&#8230; to taxes the way it adjusts to any other &#8220;scarcity.&#8221;   but apparently economics has not discovered this fact.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/11/free-market-adjusts-to-taxes-like-any-other-scarcity.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Romney Says He’ll Shoot Farm Price Supports, Draught Relief and Veterans’ Benefits, Right Along With Big Bird!</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/romney-says-hell-shoot-farm-price-supports-draught-relief-and-veterans-benefits-right-along-with-big-bird.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/romney-says-hell-shoot-farm-price-supports-draught-relief-and-veterans-benefits-right-along-with-big-bird.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 05 Oct 2012 17:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Federal budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[William Saletan]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/romney-says-hell-shoot-farm-price-supports-draught-relief-and-veterans-benefits-right-along-with-big-bird.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Slate’s William Saletan has a terrific article there today, with a terrific title: Tax Evasion: Romney’s preposterous arguments for not telling you which tax breaks he’d abolish.  And, yes, elsewhere, too, mainstream-media folks are showing some morning-after queasiness about their debate verdict, by getting into the “um … huh?” stuff now. But in pointing out that [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>Slate’s William Saletan has a terrific article there today, with a terrific title: <i><a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/politics/2012/10/romney_s_tax_deduction_plan_why_won_t_he_tell_you_which_loopholes_he_d_close_.html#comments">Tax Evasion:</a> </i><i><a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/politics/2012/10/romney_s_tax_deduction_plan_why_won_t_he_tell_you_which_loopholes_he_d_close_.html#comments">Romney’s preposterous arguments for not telling you which tax breaks he’d abolish</a>.</i>  And, yes, elsewhere, too, mainstream-media folks are showing some morning-after queasiness about their debate verdict, by getting into the “um … huh?” stuff now.</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>But in pointing out that Nixon really doesn’t have a plan to end the Vietnam War—er, I mean, that Romney doesn’t really have a plan to balance the budget—they’ve been talking mostly about Romney’s refusal to identify the tax loopholes and deductions he’ll end. They haven’t mentioned much Romney’s other demonstration of, um, willingness to be specific about extremely important budget matters: His statement that he’ll end all programs that, in his opinion, aren’t worth borrowing money from China for. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Which include Medicaid and Sesame Street.  But what <i>other </i>programs?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The effective end of federally supported Medicaid is obviously too serious a subject to joke about, and it needs much more attention from the news media than it’s getting—as well as from the Obama campaign, which should put up ads featuring nursing home residents and nursing home <i>owners</i>; i.e., small-business owners who are jobs creators, to explain the issue.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>But Obama also should say—yes, <i>say</i>—when he’s campaign in, maybe, Iowa, eastern Colorado, Wisconsin and North Carolina that Romney doesn’t think farm subsidies, flood insurance, hurricane and tornado disaster relief are worth borrowing money from China from. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And when campaigning in North Carolina, Virginia, Ohio and, well, everywhere else, he should say that Romney doesn’t think veterans’ benefits are worth borrowing money for China for.  And that that might make it harder to recruit those additional 100,000 people into the armed services that he says he wants to add, although of course he might just have a military draft in mind.  You never know; he’s not all that keen on revealing specifics, after all.  (Does Romney <i>ever</i> think beyond the end of whatever sentence he’s mouthing at the  moment?)
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Seriously. The only way to start to nail down Romney’s plans is to start actually filling in his blanks.  Say, outright, that Romney plans to end farm price supports, drought relief, disaster relief and veteran’s benefits.  Romney then will have to say that he has no such plans.  Great! Then say that Romney plans to shut down the FDA and the National Transportation Safety Board; a few hundred deaths from dangerous medications and airplane crashes each year aren’t worth borrowing money from China to prevent.  Not when you have more important needs, such as incessantly spiraling tax cuts for the wealthy. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Which, despite his Wednesday protestations, he does think are worth borrowing money from China for.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Or here’s another idea: Let’s develop a contest in which the winner accurately predicts Romney’s selections for Programs Worth Borrowing From China For.  And a bonus contest in which the winner correctly calls the tax loopholes and deductions eliminated in Romney’s tax-code revision plan.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The winners will be announced on the same day as the announcement of the Publishers Clearinghouse winner for 2015. The prize?  We can have another contest to guess that.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/romney-says-hell-shoot-farm-price-supports-draught-relief-and-veterans-benefits-right-along-with-big-bird.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Spain. Please, Mr. Obama, talk about Spain. Please.</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/spain-please-mr-obama-talk-about-spain-please.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/spain-please-mr-obama-talk-about-spain-please.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 04 Oct 2012 14:49:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dodd-Frank]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jim Lehrer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Krugman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spain]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[taxes]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/spain-please-mr-obama-talk-about-spain-please.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[ROMNEY: Look, the revenue I get is by more people working, getting higher pay, paying more taxes. That’s how we get growth and how we balance the budget. But the idea of taxing people more, putting more people out of work, you’ll never get there. You’ll never balance the budget by raising taxes. Spain &#8212; [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div></div>
<div>ROMNEY: Look, the revenue I get is by more people working, getting higher pay, paying more taxes. That’s how we get growth and how we balance the budget. But the idea of taxing people more, putting more people out of work, you’ll never get there. You’ll never balance the budget by raising taxes.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Spain &#8212; Spain spends 42 percent of their total economy on government. We’re now spending 42 percent of our economy on government. I don’t want to go down the path to Spain. I want to go down the path of growth that puts Americans to work with more money coming in because they’re working.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>LEHRER: But &#8212; but Mr. President, you’re saying in order to &#8212; to get the job done, it’s got to be balanced. You’ve got to have&#8230;
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>(CROSSTALK)
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212; <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/decision2012/2012-presidential-debate-president-obama-and-mitt-romneys-remarks-in-denver-on-oct-3-running-transcript/2012/10/03/24d6eb6e-0d91-11e2-bd1a-b868e65d57eb_print.html">Last night</a>
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Romney doesn’t want to go down the path to Spain?  Oh?  Well, since, actually, the percent of Spain’s total economy that they spend on government has nothing at all to do with Spain’s situation now, and instead has <i>everything</i>to do with the fact that they had a huge, huge housing bubble, worse even than ours, and since their housing bubble is—like ours—the main cause of their economic problems, and since Romney wants to repeal the Dodd-Frank Wall Street and Mortgage-lending regulations and replace them with regulations that favor Wall Street … then, yes, Romney does want to go down the path of Spain. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Or at least down the path we took during our deregulation juggernaut.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>OK, here’s the thing: Romney and his campaign aides recognized that that debate forum would present a <i>perfect</i> opportunity for him to just rattle off statements without any challenge.  Just a steady stream of nonsense, without any real risk of being confronted with actual challenges to any of it.  They knew, as I did, that Lehrer—I still remember his nauseating role in the first Bush/Gore debate in 2000—does nothing but ask the candidates to state their positions on whatever.  Open-ended questions in which each one is supposed to state his policy proposal on, say, taxes, or “jobs.” There’s no actual questioning <i>about</i> the proposal.  None.  None.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>So, Romney gets to state, <i>free and clear</i>, a completely false inference of fact about the cause of Spain’s economic problems.  And he gets to say, <i>free and clear</i>:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Look, the revenue I get is by more people working, getting higher pay, paying more taxes. That’s how we get growth and how we balance the budget. But the idea of taxing people more, putting more people out of work, you’ll never get there. You’ll never balance the budget by raising taxes.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Really?  You’ll never balance the budget by raising taxes?  Oh? Didn’t we do exactly that during the Clinton administration?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And, the revenue he gets is by more people working, getting higher pay, paying more taxes?  Oh? Through the same policies as George W. Bush did?  Really?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And so forth. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Like, that Romney is going to cut tax rates <i>across the board</i> by 20%.  But he’s not going to lower tax revenue from the wealthy at all.  And so forth.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>What Obama needs to do—really, really <i>needs</i> to do—is put up a series of ads juxtaposing Romney’s earlier statements with his gibberish from last night. (I strongly urge using a clip from Romney’s speech to the Detroit Economic Club in February, and a similar speech that same week in Arizona; Michigan and Arizona had their primaries on the same Tuesday.)  But rather than just suggesting that Romney is a slippery liar who’s trying to trick voters into putting into office a team that would put in place drastic, basic changes that he knows a substantial majority of the public <i>doesn’t want</i>, Obama should pretend that Romney just doesn’t know the facts and can’t do simple math.  He is, in other words, not very smart, or at least not very well-informed. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The public, of course, will recognize that Romney’s a sleaze bucket. But Obama can just say, for example, that if Romney doesn’t know that during the Clinton years, we had a balanced budget, he’s too ill-informed to be president.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And, about that Spain thing: The final debate will be about foreign policy.  Which, Obama should point out, requires some knowledge of such things as what <i>actually</i>caused Spain’s economy to crash. And then he should educate the public about it.  He can do that in two or three sentences of medium length.  If he wants to see how it&#8217;s done, he can read any one of several Paul Krugman columns in which Krugman did exactly that.  It’s not rocket science.  It’s not even economic science.  It’s simple, established fact.  Of exactly the sort that not long ago Romney’s pollster said the Romney campaign wouldn’t trouble itself about, and that it would instead continue to make up its own facts.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Speaking of good way for the Obama campaign to get a message across in an ad ….
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The bottom line: Obama can easily turn Romney’s performance last night into a plus. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Easily.  Really.
</p>
<p>&#8212;-<br /><i>Typo-corrected 10/5.</i></div>
<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/spain-please-mr-obama-talk-about-spain-please.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Romney says he never paid less than 13% in taxes for any of the last 10 years. But how much would he pay each year once the Ryan plan is passed?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/08/romney-says-he-never-paid-less-than-13-in-taxes-for-any-of-the-last-10-years-but-how-much-would-he-pay-each-year-once-the-ryan-plan-is-passed.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/08/romney-says-he-never-paid-less-than-13-in-taxes-for-any-of-the-last-10-years-but-how-much-would-he-pay-each-year-once-the-ryan-plan-is-passed.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Aug 2012 22:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[budget and tax proposal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[IRS amnesty program]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[taxes]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/08/romney-says-he-never-paid-less-than-13-in-taxes-for-any-of-the-last-10-years-but-how-much-would-he-pay-each-year-once-the-ryan-plan-is-passed.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[&#8230; And when, exactly, did he pay that at-least-13% per year?  Might some of it have been paid under the 2009 IRS amnesty plan for people who’d been hiding money in secret overseas bank accounts, after the Swiss banks suddenly agreed to reveal to the IRS the identities of American account holders? Just wondering. ]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>&#8230; And when, exactly, <i>did </i>he pay that at-least-13% per year?  Might some of it have been paid under the 2009 IRS amnesty plan for people who’d been hiding money in secret overseas bank accounts, after the Swiss banks suddenly agreed to reveal to the IRS the identities of American account holders?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Just wondering. 
</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/08/romney-says-he-never-paid-less-than-13-in-taxes-for-any-of-the-last-10-years-but-how-much-would-he-pay-each-year-once-the-ryan-plan-is-passed.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Romney says he likes straight talk. Just not from him.</title>
		<link>./../../2012/08/romney-says-he-likes-straight-talk-just-not-from-him.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/08/romney-says-he-likes-straight-talk-just-not-from-him.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Aug 2012 19:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[straight talk]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[taxes]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/08/romney-says-he-likes-straight-talk-just-not-from-him.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Washington may not like straight talk, but I do. &#8212; Mitt Romney, yesterday Sooo, Governor, about those massive tax cuts for the wealthy ….  You know, including the elimination of all incomes taxes on capital gains and stock dividends, which your running mate’s budget proposal includes?  How, exactly, do you plan to balance the budget [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div></div>
<div>Washington may not like straight talk, but I do.
</p>
</div>
<div>&#8212; Mitt Romney, yesterday
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Sooo, Governor, about those <i>massive</i> tax cuts for the wealthy ….  You know, including the elimination of all incomes taxes on capital gains and stock dividends, which your running mate’s budget proposal includes?  <i>How</i>, exactly, do you plan to balance the budget despite that loss of revenue?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>No, no, no.  I mean, how, <i>exactly</i>, do you plan to do that?
</p>
</div>
<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/08/romney-says-he-likes-straight-talk-just-not-from-him.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Kevin Drum on Reid’s gambit on Romney’s taxes</title>
		<link>./../../2012/08/kevin-drum-on-reids-gambit-on-romneys-taxes.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/08/kevin-drum-on-reids-gambit-on-romneys-taxes.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Aug 2012 12:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2012 Presidential elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[taxes]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/08/kevin-drum-on-reids-gambit-on-romneys-taxes.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Kevin Drum has an opinion on election tactics: Come on, folks. Reid didn&#8217;t say I&#8217;ll bet Romney didn&#8217;t pay any taxes. He didn&#8217;t say he talked to someone familiar with high earners who told him Maybe Romney won&#8217;t release his returns because he didn&#8217;t pay any taxes. He made a flat statement of fact. He [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.motherjones.com/kevin-drum/2012/08/its-time-stop-celebrating-harry-reid#disqus_thread">Kevin Drum</a> has an opinion on election tactics:</p>
<blockquote><p>Come on, folks. Reid didn&#8217;t say <em>I&#8217;ll bet Romney didn&#8217;t pay any taxes</em>. He didn&#8217;t say he talked to someone familiar with high earners who told him <em>Maybe Romney won&#8217;t release his returns because he didn&#8217;t pay any taxes</em>. He made a flat statement of fact. He said he has an &#8220;extremely credible source,&#8221; which in this context means someone with direct knowledge of Romney&#8217;s taxes who decided to pick up the phone and dish about it to Harry Reid. Does anyone really believe this? Really? Then, as if that weren&#8217;t enough, Reid made his little bluff even less plausible by deciding that Romney didn&#8217;t just avoid all taxes for one year, he avoided them for <em>ten years</em>. Yeah, baby, that&#8217;s the ticket! Put these two things together with the fact that Reid hasn&#8217;t even tried to make his fairy tale sound believable (it&#8217;s just some guy he talked to) and this is not a story that a five-year-old would credit. It&#8217;s just Reid making stuff up in order to put pressure on Romney, and I think we all know it.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Can I prove this? Of course not. Given the epistemological limits of proof, I can&#8217;t prove Barack Obama was born in the United States either. Nevertheless, I feel safe saying that anyone who claims to have an &#8220;extremely credible source&#8221; that Obama was born elsewhere is either crazy or lying. The same is true for Reid, and Reid isn&#8217;t crazy. It&#8217;s simply vanishingly unlikely that he&#8217;s telling the truth, and no one — not liberal or conservative — would spend even ten seconds on a story so patently far-fetched if it were anybody but Reid and the background were anything but the frenzy of a presidential campaign.</p>
<p>Politically, of course, Reid&#8217;s ploy has worked like a charm. Romney&#8217;s taxes are back in the news and Romney&#8217;s ham-handed handling of the whole affair has kept it there. And that gives everyone a fifth reason to cheer on Reid: the end justifies the means.</p>
<p>Take a deep breath, folks. This is contemptible stuff and it&#8217;s not just business as usual. We&#8217;ve spent too many years berating the tea partiers for getting on bandwagons like this to get sucked into it ourselves the first time it&#8217;s convenient. It&#8217;s time to quit cheering on Reid and get off this particular bus.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/08/kevin-drum-on-reids-gambit-on-romneys-taxes.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Kleinbard: Tax Fairness and Fairness in Tax Data Reporting</title>
		<link>./../../2012/08/kleinbard-tax-fairness-and-fairness-in-tax-data-reporting.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/08/kleinbard-tax-fairness-and-fairness-in-tax-data-reporting.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 07 Aug 2012 23:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[fairness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[taxes]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/08/kleinbard-tax-fairness-and-fairness-in-tax-data-reporting.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[From TaxProf blog: Kleinbard: Tax Fairness and Fairness in Tax Data Reporting Following up on yesterday&#8217;s post, WSJ: Taxing the Rich &#8212; The Facts:  Huffington Post:  Tax Fairness and Fairness in Tax Data Reporting, by Edward D. Kleinbard(USC):  The impetus for this little paper was an op-ed by Ari Fleischer in the Wall Street Journal [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://taxprof.typepad.com/taxprof_blog/2012/08/kleinbard-.html">From TaxProf blog</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>Kleinbard: <em>Tax Fairness and Fairness in Tax Data Reporting</em></p>
<p>Following up on yesterday&#8217;s post, <a href="http://taxprof.typepad.com/taxprof_blog/2012/08/wsj-taxing-the-.html">WSJ: Taxing the Rich &#8212; The Facts</a>:  Huffington Post:  <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/edward-d-kleinbard/tax-fairness-and-fairness_b_1733059.html">Tax Fairness and Fairness in Tax Data Reporting</a>, by <a href="http://lawweb.usc.edu/contact/contactInfo.cfm?detailID=68912">Edward D. Kleinbard</a>(USC): </p>
<blockquote><p>The impetus for this little paper was an op-ed by Ari Fleischer in the Wall Street Journal a couple of weeks ago [<a href="http://taxprof.typepad.com/taxprof_blog/2012/07/president-obama.html">The Latest News on Tax Fairness</a>] that unfairly claimed that the <a href="http://taxprof.typepad.com/taxprof_blog/2012/07/cbo-the-.html">Congressional Budget Office had demonstrated</a> that the most affluent Americans were &#8220;overtaxed.&#8221; That op-ed contained  many rhetorical tricks and incomplete statements that are a staple of the current political right, and I felt it important both to defend the honor of the CBO and to offer readers a more balanced presentation of the underlying issues. Editorials like Fleischer&#8217;s simply polarize discussion and distract from the real questions of fiscal policy, which are the appropriate role of government in contemporary society and the best modes of financing it, and as to which reasonable people can come to somewhat different conclusions.</p></blockquote>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/08/kleinbard-tax-fairness-and-fairness-in-tax-data-reporting.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>What is Mitt Romney Hiding?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/what-is-mitt-romney-hiding.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/what-is-mitt-romney-hiding.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 05 Jul 2012 22:54:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2012 Presidential elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kenneth Thomas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[taxes]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/what-is-mitt-romney-hiding.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Kenneth Thomas What is Mitt Romney Hiding? Mitt Romney has so far released only one year of tax returns (2010), plus an estimate for 2011. This stands in stark contrast to his father, Michigan Governor George Romney, who released 12 years of tax returns when he began running for President in 1967. As his [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Kenneth Thomas</p>
<p>What is Mitt Romney Hiding? </p>
<p>Mitt Romney has so far released <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2012/01/jon-stewart-delivers-goods-on-mitt.html">only one year</a> of tax returns (2010), plus an estimate for 2011. This stands in stark contrast to his father, Michigan Governor George Romney, who released 12 years of tax returns when he began running for President in 1967. As his father said at the time, &#8220;One year could be a fluke.&#8221; So the questions remain about what is in Romney&#8217;s older returns.<br />    <br />Two stories this week and last have ratcheted up the pressure. One is a recent web exclusive for &#8220;The Last Word with Laurence O&#8217;Donnell&#8221; where <a href="http://thelastword.msnbc.msn.com/_news/2012/06/27/12444118-questions-linger-over-romneys-tax-history">David Cay Johnston</a> has five questions for Romney that can only be answered with his tax returns. The other is a <a href="http://www.vanityfair.com/politics/2012/08/investigating-mitt-romney-offshore-accounts">blockbuster story</a> by Nicholas Shaxson (h/t <a href="http://livewire.talkingpointsmemo.com/entries/vanity-fair-looks-into-romneys-offshore-finances">TPM</a>) in the new <i>Vanity Fair</i> on the shadowy world of Romney&#8217;s tax havens. Together, they put a laser-like focus on the finances of the man who could become our 45th President.<br />    <br />Johnston is a well-known former <i>New York Times</i> reporter, Pulitzer Prize winner, and the author of the major books <i>Perfectly Legal</i> and <i>Free Lunch</i>. If you don&#8217;t have time to watch his 3:45 video, here are the five questions:<br />    <br />&#8220;1. Did you buy any illegal or gray area tax shelters?    <br />&#8220;2. Did an IRS audit ever uncover serious problems with any of your tax returns?    <br />&#8220;3. Did you make use of offshore vehicles to defer, or avoid paying, federal income taxes?    <br />&#8220;4. Did you take advantage of any tax strategies that the IRS did not uncover in audits?    <br />&#8220;5. Did you fully tithe to the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints every year and take a deduction on your tax return that shows that?&#8221;    </p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>These are important questions. We know that Governor Romney has had a Swiss bank account, as well as money in <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2012/05/obama-campaign-maps-romneys-tax-havens.html">other tax havens</a> like the Cayman Islands, Luxembourg, Bermuda, and Ireland. Romney&#8217;s answer to any question about his taxes has basically been, &#8220;Trust me.&#8221; But the guy&#8217;s running for President, <a href="http://blogs.villagevoice.com/runninscared/2011/10/mitt_romney_im_running_for_office_for_petes_sake_i_cant_have_illegals.php">for Pete&#8217;s sake</a>. He owes us more than that.<br />    <br />Shaxson, a researcher for the <a href="http://www.taxjustice.net/cms/front_content.php?idcatart=2&#038;lang=1">Tax Justice Network</a> and author of the book <a href="http://treasureislands.org/"><i>Treasure Islands</i></a>, asks us to consider the possibility that maybe not everything Romney has done tax-wise has been legal. He opens with a story told by a former Bain employee about how Romney encouraged him to lie to get secret information on competitors. There is, of course, the fact that Romney has funds parked in numerous tax havens and the fact that his supposedly &#8220;blind&#8221; trust invested in a business started by Romney&#8217;s son Tagg, and the fact that he has $102 million in his IRA despite a contribution limit of $2000 per year for the entire 15 years Romney ran Bain. Obviously nothing to see here&#8230;<br />    <br />The standard answer of the Romney campaign to all this is that he always followed the law. As <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2012/01/jon-stewart-delivers-goods-on-mitt.html">Jon Stewart</a> had to point out since the major media did not, Romney did plenty to affect the law he was supposedly &#8220;just following,&#8221; including his defense of the &#8220;covered interest&#8221; tax loophole that let him treat his fees at Bain as if they were capital gains (15% tax) rather than wages (35% tax). All perfectly legal and as Johnston points out in his book by that name, that is the real scandal.<br />    <br />Further, Shaxson reveals that an early filing of the original Bain Capital fund in 1984 showed that many of its foreign investors were routed through tax havens and that at least one was a notorious financial criminal, Robert Maxwell. Thus, Bain helped foreigners take advantage of the fact that the United States has set itself up as a tax haven for non-citizens (see also <a href="http://www.relooney.info/0_New_8887.pdf">Jason Sharman&#8217;s paper</a> on setting up anonymous companies in the U.S. and elsewhere; h/t <a href="http://taxprof.typepad.com/files/67ti0069.pdf">Robert Kudrle</a>). Shaxson quotes Rebecca Wilkins of Citizens for Tax Justice, “It is shocking that a presidential candidate should think that is O.K.” for Bain to service the likes of Robert Maxwell.<br />    <br />The bottom line is that there is a lot of unsettling information in what investigators have so far been able to piece together about Romney&#8217;s finances. The easiest way for Governor Romney to put to rest what his campaign described to Shaxson as &#8220;unfounded allegations and insinuations&#8221; would be to release his tax returns. Yet he has not done so and shows no sign of changing his mind. <a href="http://talkingpointsmemo.com/archives/2012/07/ill_just_say_it_i.php?ref=fpblg">Josh Marshall</a> calls the questions &#8220;kryptonite&#8221; and thinks Romney will come under a lot of pressure to release more tax returns. Let&#8217;s hope so. The guy&#8217;s running for President, for Pete&#8217;s sake. </p>
<p><a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2012/07/what-is-mitt-romney-hiding.html">Middle Class Political Economist</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/what-is-mitt-romney-hiding.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
