<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Kennth Thomas &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Minimum wage&#8230;who and how much??</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/minimum-wage-who-and-how-much.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/minimum-wage-who-and-how-much.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 24 Feb 2013 17:23:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Kennth Thomas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[minimum wage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Robert Pollin]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/minimum-wage-who-and-how-much.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Spencer England has written about minimum wages and employment, and Minimum wage and employment from 2008 and Teen unemployment and the minimum wage What the fiscal cliff means for the middle class and state and local taxes Economist Robert Pollin, Professor of Economics at the University of Massachusetts in Amherst and founding co-Director of the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Spencer England has written about minimum wages and employment, </p>
<p>and <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2008/06/minimum-wage-employmnet.html" target="_blank">Minimum wage and employment</a> from 2008  and <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2010/03/teen-unemployment-and-minimum-wage.html" target="_blank">Teen unemployment and the minimum wage</a></p>
<p><a href="https://www.blogger.com/://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/11/what-fiscal-cliff-means-for-middle-class.html" target="_blank">What the fiscal cliff means for the middle class</a> and    <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/09/every-state-statelocal-tax-system-taxes.html" target="_blank">state and local taxes</a></p>
<p>Economist <a href="http://therealnews.com/t2/index.php?option=com_content&#038;task=view&#038;id=31&#038;Itemid=74&#038;jumival=9721" target="_blank">Robert Pollin</a>, Professor of Economics at the University of Massachusetts in Amherst and founding co-Director of the Political Economy Research Institute <a href="http://www.peri.umass.edu/" target="_blank">(PERI)</a>, has a series on wages/employment and the minimum wage via Real News Network (they provide transcripts) <a target="_blank" href="http://therealnews.com/t2/index.php?option=com_content&#038;task=view&#038;id=33&#038;Itemid=74&#038;jumival=623">here</a></p>
<p>Professor Richard Burkhauser has commented on President Obama&#8217;s call to raise the minimum wage to $9 an hour. And here&#8217;s what Burkhauser had to say:</p>
<p>President Obama&#8217;s call for an increase in the minimum wage to reduce poverty flies in the face of 30 years of evidence from Card and Krueger to Newmark and Washer that increases in the minimum wage have no effect on poverty rates.<br />Bob, the argument that Burkhauser gives is that most people working at minimum-wage jobs are not heads of families, they&#8217;re younger people in families that already have income earners, and that if you raise the minimum wage, it&#8217;s going to reduce the number of jobs available for young people who are mostly in these minimum-wage jobs and really do nothing about poverty levels, because the main bread-earners are already earning more than the minimum wage, he argues. He says that&#8217;s the evidence for 30 years. What do you make of that?</p>
<p>POLLIN: Well, that&#8217;s not the evidence that I&#8217;m familiar with. The evidence that I&#8217;m familiar with, having studied living-wage proposals, minimum-wage proposals around the country at state levels, at municipal levels, and national levels, the evidence is the overwhelming majority of people who are at or near minimum-wage levels of wages are not teenagers—let&#8217;s put it that way. They&#8217;re—the median age is roughly in the 30s. Most of the people have been at their job or at similar jobs for over a decade. They are on their long-term employment trajectory; they&#8217;re not about to jump up to some middle-income job as soon as they get out of college.<br />That doesn&#8217;t mean that there aren&#8217;t teenagers. The number of teenagers in the labor force are disproportionately at or near minimum-wage jobs. But the majority of people at or near minimum wages are not teenagers.</p>
<p>Now, there is another point. There are many cases in which teenagers or young people who are working at or near minimum-wage jobs are part of families that are above the poverty line, and some of my own research has shown that in fact the contribution of the teenager is what significantly helps to bring the family above the poverty line&#8230;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/minimum-wage-who-and-how-much.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
