<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>temp workers &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Wages, prices, &#034;profit&#034;, and productivity&#8230;and Black Friday too</title>
		<link>./../../2012/11/wages-prices-profit-and-productivity-and-black-friday-too.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/11/wages-prices-profit-and-productivity-and-black-friday-too.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 23 Nov 2012 03:59:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[benefits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[market wages]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[minimum wage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[productivity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[temp workers]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/11/wages-prices-profit-and-productivity-and-black-friday-too.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Black Friday around here in New England begins to night in stores about 8 P.M. On the internet Black Friday&#8217;s discounts began last week as the competition heats up between companies with stores and internet based sales. Stores have responded with aggressive discounts, especially visible is Walmart. This post is relevant to the issue of [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Black Friday around here in New England begins to night in stores about 8 P.M.  On the internet Black Friday&#8217;s discounts began last week as the competition heats up between companies with stores and internet based sales. Stores have responded with aggressive discounts, especially visible is Walmart.</p>
<p>This post is relevant to the issue of wages at Walmart, and points to deeper economic issues one has to keep in mind when reading about the economics overall versus a company policy.  This becomes especially poignant as some Walmart workers attempt to draw attention to wages, benefits, and hours the company paints as necessary.</p>
<p>Demos has some figures for thought in <a href="http://www.demos.org/publication/retails-hidden-potential-how-raising-wages-would-benefit-workers-industry-and-overall-ec" target="_blank">How Raising Wages Would Benefit Workers, the Industry and the Overall Economy</a>.   Here&#8217;s a summary of the study from <i>Demos</i>:</p>
<blockquote><p>This study assumes a new wage floor for the lowest-paid retail workers equivalent to $25,000 per year for a full-time, year-round retail worker at the nation&#8217;s largest retail companies, those employing at least 1,000 workers.  For the typical worker earning less than this threshold, the new floor would mean a 27 percent pay raise.  Including both the direct effects of the wage raise and spillover effects, the new floor will impact more than 5 million retail workers and their families. This study examines the impact of the new wage floor on economic growth and job creation, on consumers in terms of prices, on companies in terms of profit and sales, and for retail workers in terms of their purchasing power and poverty status.</p>
<p>“There is a flaw in the conventional thinking that profits, low prices and decent wages cannot co-exist,” says Catherine Ruetschlin, study author and Demos Policy Analyst. “The findings in the study prove the country’s largest retailers are in an ideal position to launch a private sector stimulus, leading the way towards a new model for American prosperity.”</p></blockquote>
<p><a href="http://robertreich.org/post/36219730368" target="_blank">Robert Reich</a> offers his viewpoint below the fold:</p>
<blockquote><p>Most new jobs in America are in personal services like retail, with low pay and bad hours. According to the Bureau of Labor and Statistics, the average full-time retail worker earns between $18,000 and $21,000 per year.</p>
<p>But if retail workers got a raise, would consumers have to pay higher prices to make up for it? A new study by the think tank Demos reports that raising the salary of all full-time workers at large retailers to $25,000 per year would lift more than 700,000 people out of poverty, at a cost of only a 1 percent price increase for customers.</p>
<p>And, in the end, retailers would benefit. According to the study, the cost of the wage increases to major retailers would be $20.8 billion — about one percent of the sector’s $2.17 trillion in total annual sales. But the study also estimates the increased purchasing power of lower-wage workers as a result of the pay raises would generate $4 billion to $5 billion in additional retail sales.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/11/wages-prices-profit-and-productivity-and-black-friday-too.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
