<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>populism &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Why Are You Out There?</title>
		<link>./../../2011/10/why-are-you-out-there.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/10/why-are-you-out-there.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2011 17:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[fraud]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jobless recovery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[populism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[risk management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[solvency crisis]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/10/why-are-you-out-there.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[When someone attempts to impede democracy actions are good things: Writer and naturalist Henry David Thoreau was once locked up for refusing to pay a poll tax. He opposed the tax on moral grounds – in a democracy, he argued, a man shouldn’t have to pay to vote&#8230;. That night, so the story goes, Thoreau [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When someone attempts to impede democracy <a href="http://bentleyvillepresbyterian.com/2011/03/27/march-27-2011-john-831-47-the-truth/">actions are good things</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>Writer and naturalist Henry David Thoreau was once locked up for refusing to pay a poll tax.  He opposed the tax on moral grounds – in a democracy, he argued, a man shouldn’t have to pay to vote&#8230;.</p>
<p>That night, so the story goes, Thoreau looked up from his jail cell to see Ralph Waldo Emerson&#8230;standing outside.  Emerson looked at him and asked, &#8220;Henry, why are you in there?&#8221;  Thoreau fired right back: &#8220;Ralph, why are you out there?&#8221;&#8230;</p>
<p>The man outside the bars may be every bit as much a prisoner as the one inside.  Or even more so, if his so-called freedom is built on a foundation of denial and lies.</p>
<p>Now, Thoreau was anything but a Christian.  That particular idea, though, was downright Biblical.  It’s more or less what Jesus is getting at [in John 8:31-47].  Jesus is comparing two kinds of freedom: the outward kind, built on a foundation of happy lies and outright denial, which in the end turns out to be just another kind of slavery; and the inward kind, which comes from a clean conscience before God, and can never be taken away.</p></blockquote>
<p>Far be it for me to cite The Sequel; I&#8217;ll take Bentleyville&#8217;s current Presbyterian minister* at his word. And tell anyone who happens to be <a href="http://occupywallst.org/">in the area of One Liberty Plaza</a> this afternoon to say &#8220;hello.&#8221;</p>
<p>*Full disclosure: one of the previous Ministers is an ex-roommate of mine.  That said, the above was found from a Google search, purely a fortuitous coincidence. At least as far as I know.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/10/why-are-you-out-there.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
