<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>football &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The Jets upset the New England Patriots</title>
		<link>./../../2011/01/the-jets-upset-the-new-england-patriots.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/01/the-jets-upset-the-new-england-patriots.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 17 Jan 2011 02:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[football]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/01/the-jets-upset-the-new-england-patriots.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Jets Beat Patriots, 28-21, to Reach A.F.C. Title Game The Jets upset the New England Patriots on their home turf onSunday with a 28-21 victory that set up a matchup with thePittsburgh Steelers in the A.F.C. championship game. A sad day today for this fan. Dan]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Jets Beat Patriots, 28-21, to Reach A.F.C. Title Game</p>
<p>The Jets upset the New England Patriots on their home turf on<br />Sunday with a 28-21 victory that set up a matchup with the<br />Pittsburgh Steelers in the A.F.C. championship game.</p>
<p>A sad day today for this fan.</p>
<p>Dan</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/01/the-jets-upset-the-new-england-patriots.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Eagles Update</title>
		<link>./../../2010/02/eagles-update.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/02/eagles-update.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2010 22:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[football]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[incentives]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[management]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/02/eagles-update.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[For those who missed it yesterday, Palace defeated the Wolves at Selhurst Park last night, 3-1 (only a goal in the 90th minute breaking the shutout) behind a hat trick from defenseman-moved-forward Danny Butterfield, who played a similar role in Saturday&#8217;s 2-0 win over Peterborough. Most interesting is this observation from Palace manager Neil Warnock: [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For those who missed it yesterday, Palace defeated the Wolves at Selhurst Park last night, 3-1 (only a goal in the 90th minute breaking the shutout) behind a hat trick from defenseman-moved-forward Danny Butterfield, who played a similar role in Saturday&#8217;s 2-0 win over Peterborough.</p>
<p>Most interesting is <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/football/2010/feb/03/fa-cup-crystal-palace-notts-county">this observation from Palace manager Neil Warnock</a>:<br />
<blockquote>&#8220;Transfer deadline day was a long day for me. I think Fulham offered £30,000 for three of our academy players, and Chelsea came in for some too. That&#8217;s disgusting. And everybody knows that [the full-back Nathaniel] Clyne almost went to Wolves yesterday, and I was disappointed with the offer we accepted for him. But he turned them down and the money we would have got for him we&#8217;ll get from this Cup run now.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>Fire sales rarely make economic sense if you&#8217;re caretaking a Going Concern and willing to provide bridge financing.  That <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/football/2010/feb/02/crystal-palace-loan-players-wages-agilo">the latter was secured</a> the day after the Transfer Deadline may not be coincident.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/02/eagles-update.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Transfer Deadline Day and Poor Incentive Alignment</title>
		<link>./../../2010/02/transfer-deadline-day-and-poor-incentive-alignment.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/02/transfer-deadline-day-and-poor-incentive-alignment.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2010 23:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[football]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[incentives]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[management]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/02/transfer-deadline-day-and-poor-incentive-alignment.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The big news of Transfer Deadline Day was that Nathaniel Clyne turned down a move from The Eagles to The Wolves.*  As The Guardian noted: [This] will please everyone at Crystal Palace who isn&#8217;t an administrator. Let’s look at the timeline and the reality. Palace was ninth in the Premier Championship [thanks to Tim in [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The big news of <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/football/2010/feb/01/transfer-deadline-day-live" target="_blank">Transfer Deadline Day</a> was that Nathaniel Clyne turned down a move from The Eagles to The Wolves.*  As The Guardian noted:<br />
<blockquote>
<p>[This] will please everyone at Crystal Palace who isn&#8217;t an administrator.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Let’s look at the timeline and the reality.
<ol>
<li>Palace was ninth in the <s>Premier</s> Championship [thanks to Tim in comments] League at the time they were put into Administration. (Owners could not pay bills.)</li>
<li>Being put into Administration carries with it a <strong>10-point</strong> penalty <em>on the team.</em> This moved them from ninth to twentieth—from in contention for <s>the FA Cup</s> Coca Cola Championship playoffs [ibid. to Tim] and possible Promotion to the borderline of Relegation.
<p>UPDATE 2: The Eagles&#8217;s current FA Cup matchup—being one of five remaining Championship League teams in the Round of 16—is a replay today (3:00pm EST) with&#8230;the Wolves.  Yes, the same team to which Clyne declined a transfer. Looking at <a href="http://www.thisislondon.co.uk/standard-sport/football/article-23801512-neil-warnock-is-banking-on-fa-cup-cash-to-keep-crystal-palace-afloat.do">the economics of today&#8217;s game</a> (h/t My Loyal Reader), there is 90,000 quid to get through to the next round, and an expectation of 247,500 in additional revenues from that round. So the proposed 1.5MM transfer fee for Clyne and Moses has to be adjusted by the decrease in probability (from positive to virtually zero) of receiving that 337,500.  Even if you assume only a 40% chance of winning at home, that&#8217;s an immediate 135,000 quid—9%—decline in the value of the sale.</p>
</li>
<li>Note that the team itself did not change in the least at that point.</li>
<li>This puts two factors into play: a relegated Eagles squad would be worth less, but the Administrators are looking for short-term cash flow that can best be achieved by selling top players. (We should call this a “borrowing constraint,” perhaps, save that it was the lack of an initial borrowing constraint and the resultant overextension that led to the situation in the first place, so perhaps it is a resource allocation issue.) </li>
</ol>
<p>The strange thing is that, without the penalty, the incentives of the Administrators would be better-aligned with the long-term goals of the team: putting the best possible product on the field and selling an attractive commodity.**
<p>Note, however, that the previous owners suffer no incremental reputational risk as the team is sold, even though they failed to prepare the <strike>firm</strike> team for those next steps. (Think Sandy Weill and The Big C or Neutron Jack and the DoD-subsid[iar]y/mortgage lender.) The damage after their departure is borne solely by the players.  In this particular case, Nathaniel Clyne’s move of support for the Eagles should be a stronger symbol for potential acquirers of the F.C. than the 1.5 million quid would have been.</p>
<p>*Dissent on this point from <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robbie_Keane" target="_blank">Tottenham</a> supporters is understandable, if wrong.  Yes, it was a boring day on the transfer front.</p>
<p>**This doesn’t mean that they might not still be trying to sell players, just that there wouldn’t be a “Fire Sale” sign on their foreheads, which should produce marginally better deals, i.e., those that are <em>more closely</em> aligned with the longer-term interests of the team.</p>
<p>UPDATE 1: Tim in comments notes, correctly, that Administration does, at least, pay the players, leaving transfer fees a possibility. The purpose of Administration remains, however, (1) keeping the League orderly and (2) being able to sell the franchise to other buyers for as much as possible.  Since transfer fees are based on negotiation, and Administration (&#8220;fire sale&#8221;) prices seem by definition to be below those that would be negotiated if it were One&#8217;s Own Money.</p>
<p>So assuming one expects the Eagles to remain a Going Concern—that is, that Selhurst Park next season won&#8217;t be being developed into a Harrod&#8217;s—taking the transfer fee upfront is at best a wash, and more likely a reduction in the franchise&#8217;s value. Especially in a case where there is risk of Relegation.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/02/transfer-deadline-day-and-poor-incentive-alignment.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>I&#8217;ve Got the Under on S/h/e/a/ C/i/t/i/ Taxpayer Field</title>
		<link>./../../2009/04/ive-got-the-under-on-shea-citi-taxpayer-field.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/04/ive-got-the-under-on-shea-citi-taxpayer-field.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2009 23:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[football]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jourmalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[just life]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/04/ive-got-the-under-on-shea-citi-taxpayer-field.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[So the brilliant NFL has &#8220;solved&#8221; the Yom Kippur problem, moving the starting time for the Jets-Titans game to 1:00p.m. Which means that, with luck, the game ends around 4:00—probably closer to 4:15.* It appears that sundown on 27 September 2009—from which time one is expected to fast for 24 hours, so any eating better [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>So the brilliant NFL has &#8220;solved&#8221; the Yom Kippur problem, moving the starting time for the Jets-Titans game <a target="_blank" href="http://sports.espn.go.com/nfl/news/story?id=4078103">to 1:00p.m</a>.</p>
<p>Which means that, with luck, the game ends around 4:00—probably closer to 4:15.*</p>
<p>It appears that sundown on 27 September 2009—from which time one is expected to fast for 24 hours, so any eating better be done well before that—is going to be <a target="_blank" href="http://aa.usno.navy.mil/cgi-bin/aa_rstablew.pl">just about 6:45pm (assuming EDT)</a>.</p>
<p>I&#8217;ve driven around the Meadowlands around the time of football games before (mostly by accident; not something anyone wants to do).  No one who has done so would agree with Representative Anthony Weiner:<br />
<blockquote>&#8220;This commonsense solution is a win for everyone involved,&#8221; Weiner said, praising the league&#8217;s decision. &#8220;The NFL can maximize the greatest audience while Jewish New York Jets fans can support their team and respect their religion.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>In comments, please estimate where a car of fans with midlevel seats, who pack up at the final whistle of a non-Overtime game and are heading East, will be at 6:45p.m. My admittedly-optimistic assumption is the in the title of this post.**</p>
<p>*For analysis, I am going to assume that the game is close and interesting.  Perhaps the NFL does not make that assumption?</p>
<p>**Feel free to assume driving up to the GWB and taking the Triborough Bridge: maximum tolls and possibly minimum traffic.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/04/ive-got-the-under-on-shea-citi-taxpayer-field.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Obligatory Superbowl Post</title>
		<link>./../../2007/02/obligatory-superbowl-post.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2007/02/obligatory-superbowl-post.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Feb 2007 01:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[football]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2007/02/obligatory-superbowl-post.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I used to watch a lot of soccer &#8211; now I still watch around World Cup time, but my sports watching now seems limited to a once every four year extavaganza limited to however long it takes the South American teams to be eliminated, or, if there&#8217;s an interesting European player like Bergkamp out there, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I used to watch a lot of soccer &#8211; now I still watch around World Cup time, but my sports watching now seems limited to a once every four year extavaganza limited to however long it takes the South American teams to be eliminated, or, if there&#8217;s an interesting European player like Bergkamp out there, however long it takes for his team to drop out.</p>
<p>The Superbowl is on now.  I&#8217;m not watching.  I don&#8217;t have much interest in football.  But I have some thoughts about football.  They&#8217;ve been kicking around my head for a long time &#8211; so long, in fact, that it may be they&#8217;re not original and I actually read them somewhere.  So if I&#8217;m plagiarizing someone&#8217;s idea, my apologies &#8211; its inadvertent.  My thoughts center around the idea that football is the quintessential American sport.  A few features of football that make it the quintessential American sport:</p>
<p>1.  Everyone on the team is a specialist<br />2.  The people on the field don&#8217;t resemble people you see in normal life<br />3.  The action lasts only a few seconds at a time<br />4.  The action is repeated over and over, from a zillion angles<br />5.  Marketing is more important what actually happens on the field<br />6.  There is an insane number of rules, some quite technical<br />7.  In the end, the call made by the referees is often the most important thing in deciding who wins<br />8.  Somone gets sued for something silly.  This year (I&#8217;m too lazy to hunt for links right now), some megachurches were told to cancel their Superbowl parties by the NFL, which was concerned that it would drive down Nielsen ratings<br />9.  There&#8217;s a lot of beer drinking involved</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2007/02/obligatory-superbowl-post.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
