<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>public option &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>More on the Public Option in the current house bill HR 3962</title>
		<link>./../../2009/11/more-on-the-public-option-in-the-current-house-bill-hr-3962.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/11/more-on-the-public-option-in-the-current-house-bill-hr-3962.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 06 Nov 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[health care reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hr3962]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[public option]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/11/more-on-the-public-option-in-the-current-house-bill-hr-3962.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Divorced one like Bush Bruce Webb put up a post titled &#8220;Health Care Exchange: Eligibility vs. Enrollment&#8220;. I have gained some clarification on the subject and have shared it with Bruce. I have asked him to comment also. There is a concern as to whether access to the Public Option (PO) was limited. Bruce&#8217;s [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Divorced one like Bush</p>
<p>Bruce Webb put up a post titled &#8220;<a href="http://angrybear.blogspot.com/2009/10/health-care-exchange-eligibility-vs.html">Health Care Exchange: Eligibility vs. Enrollment</a>&#8220;.  I have gained some clarification on the subject and have shared it with Bruce.  I have asked him to comment also.</p>
<p>There is a concern as to whether access to the Public Option (PO) was limited.  Bruce&#8217;s reading of the bill was that everyone has access to the PO based on section 411(3) which reads:<br />
<blockquote>3) CONTRIBUTION IN LIEU OF COVERAGE.— <br />Beginning with Y2, if an employee declines such offer but otherwise obtains coverage in an Exchange- participating health benefits plan (other than by reason of being covered by family coverage as a spouse or dependent of the primary insured), the employer shall make a timely contribution to the Health Insurance Exchange with respect to each such employee in accordance with section 413.</p></blockquote>
<p>Thus, the PO is not as restricted as people thought and in the future the possibility is that it could grow and be what people are saying it would be; a force for controlling costs, especially regarding insurance premiums.  Sounds good, no?</p>
<p>My reading was that section 411(3) was tied in some way to whether your employer was &#8220;exchange eligible&#8221; or not.  There are provisions that would allow all employers in the future to be exchange eligible but it is dependent on a report or two being produced and then the &#8220;commissioner&#8221; acting on the report or congress acting on the report.  To me, this leaves too much political wiggle room.  </p>
<p>I think we both assumed that exchange eligible or not, if the employee chose the PO, the employer would have to pay for the choice by paying into the exchange, the result being that the cost to the employee would be the same regardless of what decision said employee makes.</p>
<p>Well, Bruce was correct.  Everyone has the option to choose the PO.  Though there is a financial barrier.  A big financial barrier that in my opinion makes this bill crap.  I&#8217;ll post my thoughts more on this later.</p>
<p>I contacted my congress person&#8217;s office.  They put me in touch with their legislative person.  I asked this person (via email) which of us were correct.  </p>
<p>Turns out, as noted, Bruce is correct that everyone has the option for the PO.  However, if you make this choice in lieu of  accepting one of the employer provided options you, my friend are on your own.  You are on your own and will have to accept the total cost of the PO plan because the payment your employer makes into the exchange does not follow you.</p>
<p>The reason given for such a set up in the house bill is that there is concern that the employers would push their employees into the exchange.  The legislative person noted that HR 3962 specifically is attempting to discourage this.  </p>
<p>This is the essential two responses by the legislative person:<br />
<blockquote>Any individual (but not any employer) can participate in the Exchange and therefore could sign up for the public option.  BUT, to do so, they would have to dis-enroll in their qualifying coverage and meet the other requirements necessary to participate in the Exchange.  However, there is zero incentive for anyone to do this since they’d be responsible for 100% of the cost of the care they chose in the Exchange.  If they stuck with their employer sponsored or other qualifying care, the vast majority of the cost of coverage is picked up by someone other than the individual.  That’s why so few people are projected to enter into the public option.  Additionally, access to the Exchange, and the public option, IS restricted for employers.  Only the smallest businesses can use it at first, and later slightly larger businesses.  The Secretary can then choose to open it up to all employers if she feels the Exchange has the capacity to handle that.  The goal is to do so.  </p></blockquote>
<p>I then asked: <em>411(3) notes that the employer has to make a contribution to the exchange following the rules of section 413 if the employee chooses to get health care via such.  How does this square with your statement that the employee would be 100% responsible for the cost of the exchange coverage?  Is the employer contribution not tied to their employee&#8217;s choice?  That is, the employer is just simply being charged as a participate in the over all exchange pool to provide the exchange money and thus the payment is not an offset of the cost incurred by the employee to purchase coverage from the exchange?</em><br />There response:<br />
<blockquote> Exactly—money does not follow the person in the House bill.  The Senate Finance bill does attempt to have the money the money follow the person I believe, but that gets complicated and provides a potential incentive for employers to try and push employees into the Exchange, which is expressly discouraged in HR 3269.  </p></blockquote>
<p>This is a link to a section by <a href="http://energycommerce.house.gov/Press_111/health_care/hr3962_Section_by_Section.pdf">section synopsis </a>of the bill.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/11/more-on-the-public-option-in-the-current-house-bill-hr-3962.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Real Public Option</title>
		<link>./../../2009/10/a-real-public-option.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/10/a-real-public-option.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Oct 2009 14:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Canada]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health care costs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health care reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[public option]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/10/a-real-public-option.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[One of the most notable things about ski trips to the States from Canada was that they offered &#8220;U.S. medical insurance&#8221;—a buy-in that cost around the same as a lift ticket if you wanted to ski Stowe instead of Tremblant. One of the scariest moments in Sicko is when the Canadian relatives note that they [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>One of the most notable things about ski trips to the States from Canada was that they offered &#8220;U.S. medical insurance&#8221;—a buy-in that cost around the same as a lift ticket if you wanted to ski Stowe instead of Tremblant.</p>
<p>One of the scariest moments in <em>Sicko</em> is when the Canadian relatives note that they don&#8217;t dare go to the States, telling about a friend whose injury while golfing in Florida ended up costing him about US$60,000 out of pocket.</p>
<p>U.S. native Tina Fetner at Scatterplot recapitulates those feelings <a target="_blank" href="http://scatter.wordpress.com/2009/10/27/they-paid-the-whole-bill/">in relating her ASA experience</a>. Fortuantely, her experience has a cheerful happy ending.  And her closing line summarizes why there is such a push among people for a &#8220;public option,&#8221;; the current U.S. system doesn&#8217;t work:<br />
<blockquote>The idea that the insurance payouts are an unproblematic obligation that the insurance company just lives up to without question had become so foreign to me that this feels like bonus cash. This is what insurance should be.</p></blockquote>
<p>The Devil will still be in the details, but at least there might be details, instead of a 300% increase in non-treatment insurance payments.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/10/a-real-public-option.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Public Option Opt Out and the Commerce Clause</title>
		<link>./../../2009/10/public-option-opt-out-and-the-commerce-clause.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/10/public-option-opt-out-and-the-commerce-clause.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 26 Oct 2009 15:17:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[employer-provided health insurance]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[public option]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/10/public-option-opt-out-and-the-commerce-clause.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Bruce Webb Well it looks like Harry Reid is going to introduce a bill that includes a Public Option with a state opt-out provision. Which I guess means the Tenthers won&#8217;t have to secede from the Union after all. But it raises some questions. Let&#8217;s say I am from Washington State and have an [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Bruce Webb</p>
<p>Well it looks like Harry Reid is going to introduce a bill that includes a Public Option with a state opt-out provision. Which I guess means the Tenthers won&#8217;t have to secede from the Union after all. But it raises some questions.</p>
<p>Let&#8217;s say I am from Washington State and have an individual plan through the Public Option and am visiting relatives in Indiana, an opt out state. And I fall down on the ice and break a bone. Under those circumstances I would think they would have to accept my insurance, opt out can&#8217;t mean that you just become uncovered every time you fly over Mississippi. That&#8217;s scenario one.</p>
<p>Scenario two. I move to Indiana temporarily for a contract job lasting more than a year. Surely I can maintain my coverage?</p>
<p>Scenario two A. I move to Indiana on that temporary contract and get engaged and marry my High School crush. (Hi LT!). Am I prevented from adding her to my plan?</p>
<p>Scenario three. I am an executive in Seattle for a company that buys insurance from the PO but maintain my full time residence in Coeur d&#8217;Alene Idaho (which as a live free or die red state opted out) and commute by plane. Is my Public Option plan affected?</p>
<p>Scenario four. I am a self-employed consultant based out of my lake front house in Coeur d&#8217;Alene but spend much of my time working for clients in Portland and Seattle. Whether or not I maintain a residence in either city what prevents me from stopping by the insurance office and signing up for the PO through the Exchange? Can one state actually prevent you from buying a perfectly legal product in another state and having your local doctor accept that product? What use then is the Commerce Clause?</p>
<p>Scenario five. I run a consulting shop incorporated in Idaho but with a small office in Portland and Billings and a larger one in Seattle. If Idaho has opted out I am actually prevented from buying a group plan on the Washington Exchange and including myself and my small Oregon and Montana staffs in it along with my larger Seattle group?</p>
<p>I could multiply scenarios endlessly but the question remains: how do individual states enforce an opt-out and under what circumstances? How much presence do you have to maintain in a state that offers the public option to be able to buy through their exchange?</p>
<p>Under our system states have a certain amount of freedom to decide what gets bought and sold within their state boundaries plus some rights to regulate what crosses those borders (for example fireworks). But I just don&#8217;t see how they can block medical providers from accepting health insurance policies written in another state or realistically how they can block their own citizens from purchasing such insurance. And certainly I can&#8217;t see setting up a system where tourists and part-time residents have their insurance honored but full time residents don&#8217;t.</p>
<p>Unless states can mandate that all individuals and employers purchase insurance in-state in addition to whatever coverage they may have through another state I just don&#8217;t see how opt-out does anything but prevent insurance sales on your own state exchange.</p>
<p>Which is why I don&#8217;t think supporters of the PO have much to worry about as concerns Opt-Out. It seems to just be a sop thrown to more conservative states who don&#8217;t want to get tinged with accusations of collaboration with socialism (or something). From a mechanical standpoint I just don&#8217;t see how you enforce this. Any ideas?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/10/public-option-opt-out-and-the-commerce-clause.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Maine Chance</title>
		<link>./../../2009/10/the-maine-chance.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/10/the-maine-chance.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2009 13:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[constitution]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Healthcare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Maine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Olympia Snowe]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[public option]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/10/the-maine-chance.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Robert Waldmann One strange thing about the health care reform debate is that insurance companies claim to support reform. I have tended to suspect that they are just playing possum. Now I find positive proof that WellPoint is willing to do what it takes to make sure health care reform passes &#8212; they sued the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Robert Waldmann</p>
<p>One strange thing about the health care reform debate is that insurance companies claim to support reform.  I have tended to suspect that they are just playing possum.  </p>
<p>Now I find positive proof that WellPoint is willing to do what it takes to make sure health care reform passes &#8212; <a href="http://digbysblog.blogspot.com/2009/10/socialized-profits-by-dday-wild-story.html">they sued the state of Maine claiming they have a constitutional right to make a profit !?!<br /></a><br />In fact they seem to support a public option.  It will be a bit hard for Sens Snowe and Collins to explain why they think no public option is needed after this.</p>
<p>I have a challenge.  Can anyone think of anything anyone could do which is better for the public option that this ?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/10/the-maine-chance.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Quote of the Day</title>
		<link>./../../2009/09/quote-of-the-day-2.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/09/quote-of-the-day-2.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Sep 2009 17:36:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[health care reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Healthcare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[public option]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/09/quote-of-the-day-2.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Health Affairs tells the truth and shames&#8230;well&#8230; Unlike for-profit firms, a public plan has no incentive to cut corners and prevent providers from giving their patients quality evidence-based care, because its ultimate goal is public health, not private profit. Nor does it have any interest in sideswiping regulations and shortchanging consumers. Free market proponents argue [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Health Affairs <a target="_blank" href="http://healthaffairs.org/blog/2009/09/17/why-a-public-health-insurance-option-is-essential/">tells the truth and shames&#8230;well</a>&#8230;<br />
<blockquote>Unlike for-profit firms, a public plan has no incentive to cut corners and prevent providers from giving their patients quality evidence-based care, because its ultimate goal is public health, not private profit. Nor does it have any interest in sideswiping regulations and shortchanging consumers.  Free market proponents argue that private health insurers should be lightly regulated to give Americans the best value. We have seen the results of that sort of regulatory neglect in many industries in the past eight years; the harm to all Americans, businesses and the overall economy could not be more profound.</p></blockquote>
<p>Read <a target="_blank" href="http://healthaffairs.org/blog/2009/09/17/why-a-public-health-insurance-option-is-essential/">the Whole Thing</a>, since you probably won&#8217;t find it being cited at <em>The Atlantic</em>.</p>
<p>UPDATE:  Bonus quote, since it gets to the core of the matter:<br />
<blockquote>[Health insurance is an] oligopoly [market] with high entry barriers in which prices and profits have escalated rapidly.</p></blockquote>
<p>Traditional economic theory holds that there are no economic profits in a true market.* That the Health Insurance industry has realised higher profits while spending a lower portion of each dollar received on claims over the past twenty years is, economics tells us, an indication of market failure.  Strangely, the mass of economists don&#8217;t seem to be saying this.  Which is a market failure of another type.</p>
<p>*There is, of course, a fair Return on Investment embedded in the equation, but that is assumed to be the stable risk-adjusted return, not increasing in an equilibrium state.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/09/quote-of-the-day-2.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Cost Controls and the Public Option: Why Losing the PO Would be Terrible-but Not Fatal</title>
		<link>./../../2009/08/cost-controls-and-the-public-option-why-losing-the-po-would-be-terrible-but-not-fatal.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/08/cost-controls-and-the-public-option-why-losing-the-po-would-be-terrible-but-not-fatal.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 22 Aug 2009 17:36:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[hr3200]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[public option]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/08/cost-controls-and-the-public-option-why-losing-the-po-would-be-terrible-but-not-fatal.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Bruce Webb The part of the blogosphere that caters to the Progressive Left is hardening its position around the Public Option, it has become a non-negotiable point, the line in the sand, the &#8220;are you with us? or against us?&#8221; line. And I don&#8217;t have any problems with that position as a matter of [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Bruce Webb</p>
<p>The part of the blogosphere that caters to the Progressive Left is hardening its position around the Public Option, it has become a non-negotiable point, the line in the sand, the &#8220;are you with us? or against us?&#8221; line. And I don&#8217;t have any problems with that position as a matter of strategy and tactics, the Public Option is much better policy than any proposal that would leave it out, and I don&#8217;t think it has the political risks that the appeasers believe it does. So &#8216;Fight, Fight, Fight for Old PO!&#8217; can be our fight song.</p>
<p>But this does not mean that everyone who argues that life would be worth living even without a Public Option is some treasonous Quisling intent on selling us all out to the insurance companies, as the risk of introducting French into the discussion I suggest the situation is more nuanced than that.</p>
<p>Ultimately I don&#8217;t think we will ever get overall cost-controls in Health Care in place without the PO because only it allows you to attack both of the cost centers, that which comes from the providers and that which comes from the insurers. Now these two sectors of health care are both natural allies and mortal enemies. They are allies in that insurers would be glad to sell coverage to everyone, and providers would be happy to charge for giving care to everyone, meaning each has a lot to gain from mandated insurance coverage. But at that point their interests diverge, under current business models doctors and hospitals gain most when they can supply ever more and ever more expensive treatment, while the financial incentives of insurance companies work in exactly the opposite direction.</p>
<p>Which largely explains the current state of confusion with insurers and providers sometimes pulling in unison, as often in opposition and sometimes at cross purposes. What the Public Option provides is a place to pull from against the providers or from the insurers, and from time to time with one or the other.</p>
<p>Ultimately the Public Option will be bargaining with providers either directly or by accepting some sort of industry wide average itself decided by a bargaining process. too much is at stake to simply allow providers to declare a unilateral pricing monopoly. however large or small its market share may get and no matter how much latitude it is given to bargain as an independent agent the PO will add some pull against providers. On the other hand depending on that latitude it will equally have a smaller or greater pull against the other insurers on the basis of price of insurance.</p>
<p>So depending on how much freedom it is given the Public Option has the potential to help control cost growth in both sectors that of providing health care and that of insuring that families can pay for that care as needed. Without it the situation is a lot more dicey. But as my title suggests not fatal. And the reason why is something I blogged back on July 28th under the title <a target="_blank" href="http://angrybear.blogspot.com/2009/07/hr3200-sec-116-golden-bullet-or-smoking.html">HR3200 Sed 116: Golden Bullet? or Smoking Gun?</a></p>
<p>In the bluntest terms Sec 116 imposes profit controls on the insurance companies and would do so even in the absence of the Public Option. Its existence explains why Republican leadership are signalling, nay shouting, that they will not accept Health Care reform period even if reformers surrendered the Public Option, even if they abandoned the very weak beer that is Co-Ops. The Left by and large is convinced that giving up the PO simply hands the keys to the castle over to the insurance companies with the rest of us tied up in chains at their mercy, that they can just merrily raise rates at their whim. Well no and that control is hidden in plain view in the first two sentences of the Section.<br />
<blockquote>SEC. 116. ENSURING VALUE AND LOWER PREMIUMS. </p>
<p>(a) IN GENERAL.—A qualified health benefits plan shall meet a medical loss ratio as defined by the Commissioner. For any plan year in which the qualified health benefits plan does not meet such medical loss ratio, QHBP offering entity shall provide in a manner specified by the Commissioner for rebates to enrollees of payment sufficient to meet such loss ratio. </p>
<p>(b) BUILDING ON INTERIM RULES.—In implementing subsection (a), the Commissioner shall build on the definition and methodology developed by the Secretary of Health and Human Services under the amendments made by section 161 for determining how to calculate the medical loss ratio. Such methodology shall be set at the highest level medical loss ratio possible that is designed to ensure adequate participation by QHBP offering entities, competition in the health insurance market in and out of the Health Insurance Exchange, and value for consumers so that their premiums are used for services.</p></blockquote>
<p>Insurance companies and their allies/lackies in Congress insist that the House Bill is simply designed to force private health care insurers out of business. Well this claim is not the truth, the whole truth and nothing but the truth, but there is no question that it has some truthiness floating around it. Sec 116 guts the old business model which was based on insuring care to people who may not ever need it and denying it to those who had a proven need for it. Instead under this rule no care provision means no profits instead you have to rebate them to the insurees.</p>
<p>The CBO analysis of HR3200 that showed that it would only cover 10 million people by 2019 implicitly assumed that insurance companies would play fair and just go along with these profit controls. I am not so convinced on this point, and figure that many companies will just abandon those market components that become this profit constrained. Which is why we will need a Public Option to pick up those abandoned market sectors. And sooner is better than later. But ultimately a bill WITHOUT a PO but WITH Sec 116 and the other protections of Sec 111-115 puts us on a path that starts by controlling profits.</p>
<p>So by all means &#8220;Fight, fight, fight for Old PO!&#8221;, that doesn&#8217;t mean that people who suggest losing a battle means losing the war are traitors to their Alma Mater.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/08/cost-controls-and-the-public-option-why-losing-the-po-would-be-terrible-but-not-fatal.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
