<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>defense contractors &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Letter to commission on defense spending</title>
		<link>./../../2011/02/letter-to-commission-on-defense-spending.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/02/letter-to-commission-on-defense-spending.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 19 Feb 2011 14:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[defense contractors]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[defense spending]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/02/letter-to-commission-on-defense-spending.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This letter via Counterpunch to the Deficit Commission makes a clear statement on broad issues of accountability for the DoD, our contracting system, and the huge drain on our resources. Reading the whole letter points to examples of problems, and how the current system has reached and will reach unsustainable levels of spending. We are [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a target="_blank" href="http://www.counterpunch.org/christie11192010.html">This letter</a> via Counterpunch to the Deficit Commission makes a clear statement on broad issues of accountability for the DoD, our contracting system, and the huge drain on our resources.  Reading the whole letter points to examples of problems, and how the current system has reached and will reach unsustainable levels of spending. </p>
<blockquote><p>We are writing to you and other members of the President&#8217;s National Commission on Fiscal Responsibility and Reform as individuals who have worked in national security affairs for decades for the Department of Defense, in the Armed Forces and for Democrats and Republicans in Congress. Our concern is the defense budget.</p>
<p>Similar to what your &#8220;Co-Chairs&#8217; Proposal&#8221; said last week regarding Social Security and other issues, we do not believe that defense spending should be reduced to a bargaining chip in budget negotiations at the Deficit Commission. On the other hand, we do believe that the defense budget is dangerously bloated, giving rise to serious decay in our armed forces.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p><strong>&#8230;</strong><br />Despite Secretary of Defense Robert Gates&#8217; efforts to cancel or redo several weapon programs that were over cost and under-performing, the number of major defense acquisition programs has changed from 91 programs costing $1.6 trillion to 87 programs costing $1.6 trillion. As you know, Secretary Gates has also imposed a plan on the DOD bureaucracy to transfer internally $102 billion dollars over 5 years, but there is no net savings to help the deficit. </p>
<p>Instead, Secretary Gates wants the DOD budget to grow one percent per year plus inflation for the next 10 years. That would increase the base DOD budget from $554 in 2010 to $735 billion in 2020 &#8211; a 33 percent increase, not including any spending for the wars against terrorism. While the Co-Chairs&#8217; Proposal seeks a number of terminations, reductions, and efficiencies beyond the Gates&#8217; plan (many of them welcome and overdue, but some that we believe require major modification), both the Co-Chairs Proposal and the Gates&#8217; plan project into the future a defense program that is essentially the same as that we have today, simply at different spending levels. Under either plan, the size and modernity of our forces will continue to shrink and age, even if all remaining programs are implemented without any cost increases or schedule delays.</p>
<p><strong>&#8230;</strong></p>
<p>Without a jolt, without radically altered incentives, the bureaucratic system that thrives on corrupted, unaudited accounts cannot and will not change. A colleague of yours on the Deficit Commission, Senator Tom Coburn, R-OK, has written to you recommending the urgently required accounting changes, together with a new and strong incentive: the DOD budget should be frozen at current (2010) spending levels until it can pass comprehensive audits of all of its programs, agencies, and contractors. </p>
<p><strong>&#8230;</strong></p>
<p>All this is inextricably interwoven with our present wars. If &#8211; after our withdrawal from Iraq, Afghanistan and similar adventures, an increasingly inevitable consequence of impending bankruptcy &#8211; we simply default to the Pentagon&#8217;s military and civilian bureaucracies, allowing them to continue business as usual by just shrinking presently planned forces, it would be an enormous tragedy for the American people and for all those in uniform. Your support of constructive, thoughtful use of reduced budget levels and audited spending figures can make possible truly fundamental reform, reform that reorients our national military strategy to more prudently balance national ends against national means.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/02/letter-to-commission-on-defense-spending.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>ILSM: Whittle a Break</title>
		<link>./../../2008/04/ilsm-whittle-a-break.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/04/ilsm-whittle-a-break.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2008 11:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[defense contractors]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[defense spending]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Whittle a Beak]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/04/ilsm-whittle-a-break.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This one is by ILSM&#8230; &#8212; I&#8217;d like to comment on this front page story in the Washington Post, published on April 1, 2008 by Dana Hedgpeth, a Washington Post Staff Writer. GAO Blasts Weapons BudgetCost Overruns Hit $295 Billion Government auditors issued a scathing review yesterday of dozens of the Pentagon&#8217;s biggest weapons systems, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This one is by ILSM&#8230;</p>
<p>&#8212;</p>
<p>I&#8217;d like to comment on <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/03/31/AR2008033102789.html?hpid=topnews">this front page story</a> in the Washington Post, published on April 1, 2008 by Dana Hedgpeth, a Washington Post Staff Writer.</p>
<blockquote><p>GAO Blasts Weapons Budget<br />Cost Overruns Hit $295 Billion</p>
<p>Government auditors issued a scathing review yesterday of dozens of the Pentagon&#8217;s biggest weapons systems, saying ships, aircraft and satellites are billions of dollars over budget and years behind schedule.</p>
<p>Auditors said the Defense Department showed few signs of improvement since the GAO began issuing its annual assessments of selected weapons systems six years ago. &#8220;It&#8217;s not getting any better by any means,&#8221; said Michael Sullivan, director of GAO&#8217;s acquisition and sourcing team. &#8220;It&#8217;s taking longer and costing more.&#8221;</p>
<p>&#8220;In most cases, programs also failed to deliver capabilities when promised &#8212; often forcing war fighters to spend additional funds on maintaining&#8221; existing weapons systems, the report says.</p></blockquote>
<p>This is somewhat misleading. In almost every case the reliability of new systems is poor, requires more people to repair it, resulting in lost utility, more maintenance equipment, parts and costing more than keeping the old system running. This will be the case with the Airbus tanker. The KC-135 even with more depot stays will be more useful and cheaper to operate than the Airbus.</p>
<blockquote><p>The GAO chose 72 systems to examine, based on high-dollar value and congressional interest. The various systems were at different stages of the acquisition process over the last year.</p>
<p>The GAO&#8217;s Sullivan said the reasons for the cost overruns and delays are threefold: There are too many programs chasing too few dollars; technologies are often not mature enough to go into production; and it takes too long to design, develop and produce a system.</p>
<p>&#8220;They&#8217;re asking for something that they&#8217;re not sure can be built, given existing technologies, and that&#8217;s risky,&#8221; Sullivan said in an interview.</p></blockquote>
<p>That engineering is faulty is cultural.  When a program goes into Full Development (the government manager knows what can be developed, built and sustained at given set of costs) the underlying technology is supposed to be proven.  NASA has a series of technology readiness levels which DoD has adopted.  The rush is to get into production to help the industry make money.  Money is the reason we see all these &#8220;do-overs&#8221;.  The profit is the same the third time around.</p>
<blockquote><p>Steven L. Schooner, co-director of the government procurement law program at George Washington University, said the GAO&#8217;s report reveals the recurring problems the Pentagon faces with its costly procurements.</p>
<p>&#8220;The nature of major weapon systems development is that you have to expect that the initial estimates, and typically the initial contracts, are overly optimistic and unrealistic,&#8221; he said. &#8220;Unfortunately the purchaser &#8212; the government &#8212; typically lacks the discipline to freeze the configuration such that the contractor has any reasonable chance of developing what it promised on time and for the price promised.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>This is a straw man, most of the specification changes are relieving the designer of requirements for things like quality manufacturing, technical data, eliminating testing and on occasion a new requirement is added to give the appearance that the added funding is not a bail out. An example, when the government requires a certain outcome which will cause the developer to lose money the developer asks the government to change the contract to pay again for the work already required. This seems to be a requirement change but it is not rooted in any technical aspect but in paying twice for the work to be done in a different manner a hidden &#8216;do over&#8217; to compensate for an overrun.</p>
<blockquote><p>Defense Department officials have tried to improve the procurement process, the GAO said, by doing more planning and review in the early stages of a contract. But &#8220;these significant policy changes have not yet translated into best practices on individual programs,&#8221; Gene L. Dodaro, acting comptroller general of the GAO, wrote in the report.</p>
<p>&#8220;Flagship acquisitions, as well as many other top priorities in each of the services, continue to cost significantly more, take longer to produce, and deliver less than was promised,&#8221; Dodaro said. &#8220;This is likely to continue until the overall environment for weapon system acquisitions changes.</p></blockquote>
<p>The DoD must, but won&#8217;t, require the contractors perform as promised in the development contracts or put them out of business not give a company overrunning and not delivering a 99% rating on &#8220;past performance&#8221; in the next competition. Also, DoD managers must consider the value to the taxpayer, not their career or some recondite agenda to &#8216;take care&#8217; of the soldier. </p>
<p>&#8212;</p>
<p>This one is by ILSM.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/04/ilsm-whittle-a-break.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
