<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>honor &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Ms Parker, Mc Cain, Party and Honor</title>
		<link>./../../2008/09/ms-parker-mc-cain-party-and-honor.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/09/ms-parker-mc-cain-party-and-honor.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2008 05:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[honor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John McCain]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Palin]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/09/ms-parker-mc-cain-party-and-honor.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Divorced one like Bush Before we get to excited about Ms. Parker&#8217;s recent calling out, consider her 9/5 opinion in What Sarah Palin brings to the Republican Party: And relief that the first Republican woman on a presidential ticket wasn’t going to let them down. No one was going to be embarrassed by John [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Divorced one like Bush</p>
<p>Before we get to excited about Ms. Parker&#8217;s recent calling out, consider her 9/5 opinion in <a href="http://www.tcpalm.com/news/2008/sep/05/kathleen-parker-what-sarah-palin-brings-republican/">What Sarah Palin brings to the Republican Party</a>:<br />
<blockquote>And relief that the first Republican woman on a presidential ticket wasn’t going to let them down. <strong>No one was going to be embarrassed</strong> by John McCain’s maverick pick.</p></blockquote>
<p> Referring to Palin&#8217;s convention speech:<br />
<blockquote>Palin delivered&#8230;What she showed was strength, conviction, determination, confidence, a willingness to rumble and fearlessness. No caribou caught in the headlights, she.</p></blockquote>
<p>I guess Ms. Parker is referring to herself here:<br />
<blockquote>Whatever conclusions the punditry might draw from Palin’s remarks, we can be fairly certain that Middle America felt nothing but redemption and salvation.</p></blockquote>
<p>Ms. Parker note&#8217;s Palin was the savior to the point of being Democratic like:<br />
<blockquote>Behind closed doors around the Twin Cities, talk focused on the need for new templates, new models. Republicans have to communicate that they, too, care about the issues Democrats have claimed as their own — education, health and the environment. They need new ideas and new — younger — faces to deliver the message.</p>
<p>Voila. Enter Palin.</p>
<p>She has animated voters who had little enthusiasm for the race. She has given them the very thing Democrats have been enjoying the past several months: hope and change.</p></blockquote>
<p>In the end, did Ms. Parker know she was so prophetic?<br />
<blockquote>That’s potent medicine. It also should come with a warning label: “May cause delusions and a false sense of power.”</p></blockquote>
<p>Ironic no?  Of course, maybe Ms. Parker really knew what was real and was hedging her bets.  But that would mean all the good stuff written on 9/5/08 was just BS?    Well by 9/22 she was coming out of the <a href="http://www.news-press.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20080922/OPINION/809220331/1015">delusion and sense of power</a>. </p>
<p>The 9/5/08 opinion and her now calling for Mrs. Palin to step down pretty much confirms that McCain et al&#8217;s campaign has been and is nothing more than one man&#8217;s quest for a trophy to the exclusion of the calling he so desires.  Palin stepping down vs McCain firing her will not change the fact that she was chosen as a coach picks a play and a player.  It&#8217;s all about the trophy.  It&#8217;s just a game, about the win of the contest.  Not about the win of the ideology of governance as Ms. Parker would have us believe. </p>
<p>Face it Ms. Parker, the only way for Mc Cain et al to save face and affirm that his campaign is about the country is to keep Palin.  It is the only way to show conviction of his professed American ideals.  If he looses the election on his ideals, he has no shame.  If Palin goes, he perjures his entire campaign. </p>
<p>I hear Mc Cain is an honorable man.  Is he?  It is his honor, Ms Parker, that you are holding in your hands with this call.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/09/ms-parker-mc-cain-party-and-honor.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
