<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>offshore wealth &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Much of MNEs&#8217; &#034;offshore&#034; (and hence untaxed) cash hoards held onshore</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/much-of-mnes-offshore-and-hence-untaxed-cash-hoards-held-onshore.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/much-of-mnes-offshore-and-hence-untaxed-cash-hoards-held-onshore.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 25 Jan 2013 13:59:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Linda Beale (Tax law)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[off shore disclosure]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[offshore taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[offshore wealth]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/much-of-mnes-offshore-and-hence-untaxed-cash-hoards-held-onshore.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Beale Much of MNEs&#8217; &#8220;offshore&#8221; (and hence untaxed) cash hoards held onshore The Wall Street Journal, in its editorial pages a great friend to big business and low taxes for same, had a decent front-page article  on the corporate hoard of cash designated as &#8220;permanently invested offshore&#8221;.  In fact, much of that cash [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Linda Beale</p>
<p>Much of MNEs&#8217; &#8220;offshore&#8221; (and hence untaxed) cash hoards held onshore</p>
<p>The Wall Street Journal, in its editorial pages a great friend to big business and low taxes for same, had a decent front-page article  on the corporate hoard of cash designated as &#8220;permanently invested offshore&#8221;.  In fact, much of that cash is sitting in U.S.-dollar-denominated assets in the good ole USA.  Nonetheless companies are permitted under the tax rules to claim that those profits are earned overseas and kept there.  See  Kate Limbaugh, <a href="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424127887323301104578255663224471212.html">Firms keep stockpiles of cash in U.S</a>., Wall St. J. (Jan 22, 2013).</p>
<p>Some companies, including Internet giant <a href="http://online.wsj.com/public/quotes/main.html?type=djn&#038;symbol=GOOG">Google</a> Inc., <a href="http://online.wsj.com/public/quotes/main.html?type=djn&#038;symbol=GOOG?mod=inlineTicker">GOOG +5.74%</a>software maker <a href="http://online.wsj.com/public/quotes/main.html?type=djn&#038;symbol=MSFT">Microsoft</a> Corp. <a href="http://online.wsj.com/public/quotes/main.html?type=djn&#038;symbol=MSFT?mod=inlineTicker">MSFT +1.36%</a>and data-storage specialist <a href="http://online.wsj.com/public/quotes/main.html?type=djn&#038;symbol=EMC">EMC</a> Corp.,<a href="http://online.wsj.com/public/quotes/main.html?type=djn&#038;symbol=EMC?mod=inlineTicker">EMC +1.03%</a>keep more than three-quarters of the cash owned by their foreign subsidiaries at U.S. banks, held in U.S. dollars or parked in U.S. government and corporate securities, according to people familiar with the companies&#8217; cash positions.</p>
<p>In the eyes of the law, the Internal Revenue Service and company executives, however, this money is overseas. As long as it doesn&#8217;t flow back to the U.S. parent company, the U.S. doesn&#8217;t tax it. And as long as it sits in U.S. bank accounts or in U.S. Treasurys, it is safer than if it were plowed into potentially risky foreign investments.</p>
<p>***<br /><a name="more"></a><br />Of course, the designation can be changed in an instant if the company is prepared to accept the tax bite.  United Technologies Corp., for instance, used $4 billion of such &#8220;permanently&#8221; reinvested funds held by foreign subsidiaries to help pay for last year&#8217;s acquisition of Goodrich Corp. Id.<br />That last quoted paragraph is a giveaway.  Thse foreign subsidiaires are controlled by the US MNE and have no real say in the ultimate use of the cash.  When the MNE wants it for something, it can get it in an instant.  As my colleague Calvin Johnson at University of Texas has noted, this &#8220;reinvorces the idea that a foreign sub is just a ledger entry, with no significance&#8221;  (email statement quoted with permission).</p>
<p>Meantime, these US-based MNEs are busy lobbying Congress to give them even more tax breaks.   They want a so-called territorial system or the ability to bring home their hoarded cash at low (or effectively negative) tax rates.   MNEs are married to the idea of pushing for paying nothing for the many ways the US economy has boosted their profits through tax expenditures and nothing for the many other ways in which the US system has increased their profits&#8211;both at home and abroad.</p>
<p>Remember that their owners already get an extraordinarily preferential rate of tax on dividends paid out to them (treated as net capital gains, recently made permanent in one of the sillier giveaways of the &#8220;deal&#8221; between Dems and Republicans on whether or not to let the Bush tax cuts expire as the Republicans originally wrote the bill) and on capital gains when they sell the shares.  The very low effective corporate tax rate&#8211;not infrequently a negative rate because of the way the rules and time value of money works&#8211;means that wealthy shareholders are still getting very much a free ride to accumulated wealth through the US tax system.  It&#8217;s time that stopped.</p>
<p>The Journal article&#8217;s suggestion&#8211;that the Congress needs to &#8220;set[] the [corporate income tax] rate low enough that companies opt to pay the tax rather than continue to pile up an estimated $300 billion a year beyond Uncle Sam&#8217;s reach.&#8221;  Id.  That suggestion must be tongue in cheek&#8211;no matter how much the rate is lowered on the wealthy corporations making incredibly high profits, they still insist that they don&#8217;t want to pay any tax.  They will not be happy unless the rate is zero or negative.  That is the reason that Oracle &#8220;derives about half of its revenue from the US but keeps more than three-quarters of its cash and short-term investments&#8211;or $26 billion-in the hands of its foreign subsidiaries&#8221; and has established a bunch of new foreign subsidiaries in tax havens for holding these profits.  Id.</p>
<p>From my perspective, Congress should not lower the rate.  It should instead stop many of the loopholes that permit companies to claim to &#8220;sell&#8221; essential IT property to offshore affiliates in order to then claim profits offshore.  And it ought to deal with similar gambits to lower US taxes, such as disallowing completely any interest deductions for debt to the extent that the company holds &#8220;offshore&#8221; funds of its controlled foreign subsidiaires in US-dollar-denominated assets in the United States &#8211;i.e., no interest deduction for debt of the US MNE consolidated group that is matched by a US-dollar denominated, US asset held by a controlled foreign subsidiary.</p>
<p>Professor Johnson recommends a &#8220;global consolidated return&#8221; for multinationals, with international negotiations to determine each country&#8217;s taxing jurisdiction on that whole. <br />These and similar ideas should be considered by a Congress truly intent on reasonable reform, economic justice, and distributional justice. </p>
<p><a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2013/01/mnes-offshore-and-hence-untaxed-cash-hoards-often-held-onshore.html">ataxingmatter</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/much-of-mnes-offshore-and-hence-untaxed-cash-hoards-held-onshore.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Yves Smith has been all over the Standard Chartered story</title>
		<link>./../../2012/08/yves-smith-has-been-all-over-the-standard-chartered-story.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/08/yves-smith-has-been-all-over-the-standard-chartered-story.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Aug 2012 16:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[offshore wealth]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[regulation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Standard Chartered]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Yves Smith]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/08/yves-smith-has-been-all-over-the-standard-chartered-story.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Yves Smith has been all over the Standard Chartered story: Reuters Runs Interference for Elite Corruption, Scrubs Article That Shows How Banks Get Out of Jail Free &#8211; 08/09/2012 &#8211; Yves Smith Standard Chartered Makes Empty Threat to Sue New York Regulator Over Iran Money Laundering &#8211; 08/09/2012 &#8211; Yves Smith NYS Order on Standard [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Yves Smith has been all over the Standard Chartered story:
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/08/reuters-runs-interference-for-elite-corruption-scrubs-article-that-shows-how-banks-get-out-of-jail-free.html">Reuters Runs Interference for Elite Corruption, Scrubs Article That Shows How Banks Get Out of Jail Free</a> &#8211; 08/09/2012 &#8211; Yves Smith</li>
<li><a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/08/standard-chartered-makes-empty-threat-to-sue-new-york-regulator-over-iran-money-laundering.html">Standard Chartered Makes Empty Threat to Sue New York Regulator Over Iran Money Laundering</a> &#8211; 08/09/2012 &#8211; Yves Smith</li>
<li><a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/08/nys-order-on-standard-chartereds-iran-transfers-opens-up-us-uk-regulatory-pig-fight.html">NYS Order on Standard Chartered’s Iran Transfers Opens Up US, UK Regulatory Pig Fight</a> &#8211; 08/08/2012 &#8211; Yves Smith</li>
</ul>
<p>Also see this <a target="_blank" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/08/09/business/how-a-lax-banking-law-obscured-money-flow.html?ref=business&#038;nl=business&#038;emc=edit_dlbkam_20120809">NYT article</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/08/yves-smith-has-been-all-over-the-standard-chartered-story.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>New Estimate of Offshore Wealth Shows Big Increase Since 2004</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/new-estimate-of-offshore-wealth-shows-big-increase-since-2004.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/new-estimate-of-offshore-wealth-shows-big-increase-since-2004.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 27 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Kenneth Thomas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[offshore wealth]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/new-estimate-of-offshore-wealth-shows-big-increase-since-2004.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Kenneth Thomas New Estimate of Offshore Wealth Shows Big Increase Since 2004 A new report by the Tax Justice Network, &#8220;The Price of Offshore Revisited,&#8221; shows that the amount of wealth held in tax havens has increased enormously since 2004, and confirms what I previously wrote about the huge cost to tax coffers of [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Kenneth Thomas</p>
<p>New Estimate of Offshore Wealth Shows Big Increase Since 2004</p>
<p>A <a href="http://www.taxjustice.net/cms/upload/pdf/Price_of_Offshore_Revisited_120722.pdf">new report</a> by the <a href="http://www.taxjustice.net/cms/front_content.php?idcat=148">Tax Justice Network</a>, &#8220;The Price of Offshore Revisited,&#8221; shows that the amount of wealth held in tax havens has increased enormously since 2004, and confirms <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2011/11/tax-havens-cost-middle-class-untold.html">what I previously wrote</a> about the huge cost to tax coffers of money hidden offshore.    </p>
<p>The report was authored by the former Chief Economist of McKinsey and Company, James Henry. Its findings advance our understanding of tax havens and demonstrate that typical estimates of wealth inequality are significantly understated.    </p>
<p>The major finding is that offshore financial holdings now come to some $21-32 trillion, compared with the estimate in <a href="http://www.richard.murphy.dial.pipex.com/ThePriceofOffshore.pdf">TJN&#8217;s 2005 report</a> of $9.5 trillion (this excludes non-financial wealth, such as real estate). James makes a <i>very</i> conservative estimate of how much governments lose in taxes of $189 billion a year, based on earning just 3% on this $21 trillion, taxed at 30%. How conservative? This is actually less than the $255 billion annually estimated in the first TJN report, but that is based on earning 7.5% annually on offshore wealth. We can get an idea of how conservative this estimate of lost taxes by seeing how sensitive it is to changing the rate of return and wealth estimate used:    </p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Rate of Return Wealth Estimate Lost Taxes    <br />3% $21 Trillion $189 billion (Henry&#8217;s actual estimate)    <br />4% $21 Trillion $252 billion    <br />5% $21 Trillion $315 billion    <br />6% $21 Trillion $378 billion    <br />3% $32 Trillion $288 billion    <br />4% $32 Trillion $384 billion    <br />5% $32 Trillion $480 billion    <br />6% $32 Trillion $576 billion    </p>
<p>Note that none of these hypothetical estimates use an earnings rate for offshore wealth as high as the original TJN report&#8217;s 7.5%.    </p>
<p>Since these assets are hidden, we of course have no way of knowing how much the money is earning. I think it is fair to say that Henry&#8217;s estimate is more likely low than high.    </p>
<p>On the inequality of financial wealth, Henry says:<br />
<blockquote>By our estimates, at least a third of all private financial wealth, and nearly half of all offshore wealth, is now owned by world&#8217;s richest 91,000 people &#8211; just 0.001% of the world&#8217;s population. The next 51 percent of all wealth is owned by the next 8.4 million, another trivial 0.14% of the world&#8217;s population.</p></blockquote>
<p>In the companion report on inequality by Nicholas Shaxson et al., <a href="http://taxjustice.blogspot.co.uk/">the authors asked</a> a number of well-known experts on inequality if they thought these data showed inequality has been underestimated. The answer from Thomas Piketty (of Piketty and Saez, the most widely quoted set of papers on inequality that I know of) was blunt: &#8220;Yes, definitely.&#8221;  </p>
<p>Despite<a href="http://blogs.reuters.com/felix-salmon/2012/07/23/how-not-to-report-on-the-poor-and-the-wealthy/"> Felix Salmon&#8217;</a>s characterization of the report as &#8220;long on hyperbole,&#8221; I find no reason to disagree with its conclusion that tax havens are a &#8220;black hole,&#8221; one which costs the middle class (through uncollected taxes on the super-rich) untold billions of dollars and increases inequality around the world.</p>
<p>cross posted with <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2012/07/new-estimates-of-offshore-wealth-show.html">Middle Class Political Economist</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/new-estimate-of-offshore-wealth-shows-big-increase-since-2004.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
