<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Paul Krugman &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Pulitzer-Caliber Photo Journalism …</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/pulitzer-caliber-photo-journalism.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/pulitzer-caliber-photo-journalism.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 27 Feb 2013 02:07:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[mainstream-journalism gimmickry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Krugman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the sequester]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/pulitzer-caliber-photo-journalism.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Forget that being-worth-a-thousand-words thing. The picture and its caption in this Krugman blog post are … priceless.  (I just about fell out of my chair when I saw that.  And, five minutes later, I’m still laughing.)]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Forget that being-worth-a-thousand-words thing. The picture and its caption in <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/02/26/fantasies-of-presidential-will/">this Krugman blog post</a> are … priceless.  (I just about fell out of my chair when I saw that.  And, five minutes later, I’m still laughing.)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/pulitzer-caliber-photo-journalism.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>National Journal Editorial Director* Ron Fournier Missed Eighth-Grade Civics Class the Day They Discussed the Separation-of-Powers Thing. He Should Now Get a Tutor.</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/national-journal-editorial-director-ron-fournier-missed-eighth-grade-civics-class-the-day-they-discussed-the-separation-of-powers-thing-he-should-now-get-a-tutor.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/national-journal-editorial-director-ron-fournier-missed-eighth-grade-civics-class-the-day-they-discussed-the-separation-of-powers-thing-he-should-now-get-a-tutor.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 22 Feb 2013 20:22:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Darren Samuelsohn]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ezra Klein]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Greg Sargent]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Boehner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jonatha Chait]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Krugman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politico]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ron Fournier]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Scott Wong]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The National Journal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the sequester]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/national-journal-editorial-director-ron-fournier-missed-eighth-grade-civics-class-the-day-they-discussed-the-separation-of-powers-thing-he-should-now-get-a-tutor.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[It’s hard to know who will end up taking the biggest political hit if the latest Washington-induced crisis moves from theoretical to real — but the answer may well lie in which side can get the public to buy into its finger-pointing at the other side. That’s why the excuses matter: Polls show Obama has [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">It’s hard to know who will end up taking the biggest political hit if the latest Washington-induced crisis moves from theoretical to real — but the answer may well lie in which side can get the public to buy into its finger-pointing at the other side.</div>
<div dir="ltr">That’s why the excuses matter: Polls show Obama has the upper hand now over unpopular lawmakers, but much can change if sequestration upends the country’s economic recovery and Americans lose their jobs and access to popular government services.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://www.politico.com/story/2013/02/sequestration-excuses-excuses-excuses-87924.html#ixzz2Le8LVAVd">Sequestration: Excuses, excuses, excuses</a>, Darren Samuelsohn and Scott Wong, Politico, yesterday</div>
<p>I agree.  If the sequester upends the country’s economic recovery and Americans lose their jobs and access to popular government services because of its deep cuts in federal spending, the public  may well rage against Obama for refusing to accede to the Republicans’ demand that federal spending be cut much more dramatically (except for the Defense Department’s spending, which would not be cut at all)&#8211;therefore costing at least as many Americans their jobs and further denying access to those popular government services and to additional ones.  They may well be livid with Obama that he wanted to lessen the number of job losses and the loss of access to popular government services by claiming more tax revenues from wealthy individuals and corporations.  </p>
<p>Especially since about three-fourths of the public supports Obama&#8217;s proposed route.  The public may be marching in the streets, demanding impeachment.   And demanding further deep spending cuts in order to cut more jobs and popular services, and lower taxes on the wealthy and on corporations.  At least if they&#8217;re really, <i>really</i> angry about the job losses, the damage to the economy, and the loss of popular government services. </p>
<p>It isn’t a certainty that they will, though, even <i>if</i> they&#8217;re really, really angry about the job losses, the damage to the economy, and the loss of popular government services.  Which is why the Politico piece says only that it’s hard to tell whether or <i>not</i> they will.  Such things just can’t be predicted with reasonable accuracy. </p>
<p>One thing John Boehner is right about: The public does understand&#8211;his word, not mine&#8211;that tax increases are off the table, because the Republicans agreed to $600 billion in tax increases on people with very high incomes as part of the “fiscal cliff” deal seven weeks ago.  </p>
<p>They also understand exactly why further tax revenue from the very wealthy is off the table.  And they know that it&#8217;s not actually because the Republicans agreed to $600 billion in tax increases on people with very high incomes as part of the “fiscal cliff” deal seven weeks ago.  </p>
<p>The Politico piece, which I’m betting was not the idea of the two reporters but was instead an assignment handed to them, along with an opening script, by top management there&#8211;it is not a reporting piece at all&#8211;is an interesting variation on the highly-in-vogue-this-season pseudo-journalism pox-on-both-their-houses sequestration/fiscal-cliff/debt-ceiling/shut-down-the-government routine.  It passes for journalism.  But it is not journalism.  It is propaganda.  </p>
<p>The Politico piece subtlely varies the usual technique. Instead of saying, as most of the genre’s pieces do, that these crises really are the fault of both sides&#8211;equally, of course&#8211;this article says the public probably can’t distinguish between suddenly and dramatically cutting federal spending, causing substantial job losses and gutting popular government services, and cutting federal spending less and more slowly and helping to reduce the budget deficit by raising more tax revenue from the wealthy individuals and corporations.  </p>
<p>But most members of this Lewis-Carroll-as-journalists crowd do the straight from of it.  In fact, a few of them seem more like the Mad Hatter than like the Mad Hatter’s creator.  Ron Fournier appears to be among them.<br /><a name="more"></a><br />For those of you who don’t know, and there probably are few of you who don’t, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ron_Fournier">Ron Fournier is</a> a Republican-leaning, somewhat controversial Washington political journalist who a few years ago was himself major news in journalism circles when he was appointed the Associated Press’s acting Washington bureau chief.  (Until I read his Wikipedia page a few minutes ago, I wasn’t aware that it was intended as just a temporary appointment.)  The Wikipedia paragraph about this explains the controversy:</p>
<div dir="ltr">In May 2008, Fournier was named the acting Washington bureau chief, replacing his &#8220;mentor&#8221; Sandy Johnson. Since taking over the position, Fournier has led a dramatic shift in the AP&#8217;s policy, moving it away from the neutral and objective tone it had become known for and toward a more opinionated style that would make judgments when conflicting opinions were presented in a story.</div>
<p>The judgments Fournier favored were ones that the Republican Party favored as well, if I remember right.  It wasn’t a hit with Fournier’s AP colleagues, nor apparently with many of the AP’s news media clients.  So he left the AP to become editor at the venerable <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Journal">National Journal</a>, which, for those of you who don’t know, and there probably are a few of you who don’t, is a (mainly) print journal that at least in recent years quietly leans Republican but that clothes itself as neutral.  </p>
<p>Sort of like <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Politico">Politico</a>.  Except that, unlike Politico, no one outside Washington reads it and no one outside Washington cares about it.  Which is understandable, since no one outside Washington has ever heard of it. (Except me, but I do qualify as someone who doesn’t read it and someone who doesn’t care about it.)</p>
<p>Anyway, Greg Sargent, who is inside Washington and who does read the National Journal, <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/plum-line/wp/2013/02/22/the-morning-plum-questions-for-the-blame-it-on-both-sides-crowd/">writes this morning</a>:</p>
<div dir="ltr">To summarize, Fournier and Pfeiffer argued over who is to blame for the sequester. Pfeiffer criticized <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/22/opinion/brooks-the-dc-dubstep.html?hp">David Brooks’ “pox on both houses” column this morning</a> and noted that only one side (the GOP) is not willing to compromise to avoid the sequester. Fournier, who also tweeted a link to Brooks’ column, replied with several tweets arguing that it’s on the President to secure compromise from the opposition, such as <a href="https://twitter.com/ron_fournier/status/304927154578272256">this one</a>: “only one side is president. Both sides should be ashamed.”</p>
<p>This echoes Fournier’s <a href="http://mobile.nationaljournal.com/politics/you-may-be-right-mr-president-but-this-is-crazy-20130220">recent column</a> arguing that while Republicans have adopted a fundamentally uncompromising position (which to Fournier’s credit he’s been willing to acknowledge), “in any enterprise, the chief executive is ultimately accountable for success and failure.” Brooks’s column, meanwhile, argues that both sides are to blame, because Obama doesn’t have a plan to avert the sequester (which is <a href="http://www.whitehouse.gov/sites/default/files/docs/deficit_reduction_table_bucketed_r8.pdf">false</a>). So, some questions for the “blame it on both sides” crowd:</p>
</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">1) Let’s grant Fournier’s premise that a president should do all he can to secure cooperation from the other side. What more, if anything, could Obama actually do to win cooperation from today’s Republican Party on averting the sequester, short of giving in to the GOP demand that we replace it only with spending cuts? Republicans say no compromise to avert the sequester is acceptable. That’s not an exaggeration: It’s the party’s explicit, publicly stated position. What more specifically could Obama do to change this? If the answer is “nothing,” then why are both sides equally to blame?</div>
<p>Okay, look.  The president can be appropriately analogized to the CEO of the executive branch of the federal government.  It’s not a perfect analogy; obviously, there are laws that limit the president’s control over the executive branch&#8211;the Federalist Society’s silly Reagan-era “unitary executive” theory of law (don’t ask) to the contrary, notwithstanding.  But it’s a useful analogy nonetheless.  </p>
<p>But unless you recognize that Congress is not the president’s subordinate, whose membership he can hire and fire, and that federal fiscal policy is not established by fiat of top management, or unless you realize this but aren’t astute enough to understand that these are, to use a favorite word of lawyers, “material” differences between corporate CEOs and the president of the United States, you do know that it is deeply stupid to say that “in any enterprise, the chief executive is ultimately accountable for success and failure,” and not realize that some enterprises actually don’t have a chief executive and that the federal government is among those enterprises that do not.</p>
<p>I guess this is confusing, because, after all, the president is the chief of the executive branch of the federal government.  You have to know that this particular enterprise has three separate branches that, as per the Constitution, operate independent of one another, in order to understand the difference between being the chief of the executive branch and being the chief executive.  And Fournier apparently does not. </p>
<p>Greg Sargent, Paul Krugman, The New Yorker’s Jonathan Chait, Slate’s Matthew Yglesias, and a few other political writers have been sounding sirens of alarm and utter dismay at this increasingly dangerous and perverted juggernaut by so many self-styled neutral mainstream political journalists, including two days ago a Washington Post editorial writer, to engage in a campaign of deceit and propaganda in reporting on these sequential Republican-orchestrated federal fiscal crises.  </p>
<p>In my opinion, the very best of the deconstruction-of-the-pretzel-positions pieces&#8211;and one of the most piercing and quietly eloquent political opinion pieces I’ve ever read&#8211;is <a href="http://nymag.com/daily/intelligencer/2013/02/beltway-brain-fever-sequester-edition.html">this one</a>, from Wednesday, by Chait, which Yglesias linked to on Wednesday and which Sargent links to today. Yglesias&#8217;s excellent posts are <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/moneybox/2013/02/20/bipartisanthink_and_the_seriousness_principle.html">here</a> and <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/moneybox/2013/02/21/romney_and_the_sequester_bipartisanthink_takes_the_counterfactual_turn.html">here</a>.</p>
<p>I think we’re about to reach an epiphany point, at which enough important journalists become genuinely scared of what is by now creepily similar to a government-controlled mainstream press in totalitarian countries that this will cease.  No, not by the stupid Ron Fournier or by the silly, robotic David Brooks.  But maybe at least by the Washington Post’s editorial writers and by reporters who certainly need their current jobs but who also are young enough to need reputations as credible and intelligent journalists, going forward.</p>
<p>And once that happens, maybe mainstream journalism will have a similar epiphany about the austerity juggernaut.  Or, <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/wonkblog/wp/2013/02/20/the-problem-with-alan-simpson/">as Ezra Klein points out</a>, mainstream journalism&#8217;s <i>really weird</i> role in it.</p>
<p>As for Fournier, according to Wikipedia, he&#8217;s won several prestigious journalism awards.  But never one for commentary.  Maybe this year.  </p>
<p>*<i>Originally, this post said Fournier was the National Journal&#8217;s title was editor</i>.</p>
<p>&#8212;<br />POSTSCRIPT: I hadn’t seen <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/02/21/alan-simpson-and-bernie-madoff/">this pos</a>t of Paul Krugman’s from yesterday until just now. Talk about cutting to&#8211;cutting into, really&#8211;the heart of something slimy yet seemingly ever-evading analysis and puncture!</p>
<p>Enough.  Enough.  Time now to end it.  Psychiatrists are standing by to offer withdrawal counseling. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/national-journal-editorial-director-ron-fournier-missed-eighth-grade-civics-class-the-day-they-discussed-the-separation-of-powers-thing-he-should-now-get-a-tutor.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Marco Rubio Needs to Travel More. Seriously. [Updated and lightly edited.]</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/marco-rubio-needs-to-travel-more-seriously-updated-and-lightly-edited.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/marco-rubio-needs-to-travel-more-seriously-updated-and-lightly-edited.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2013 19:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Chris Christie]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jonathan Martin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Marco Rubio]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Krugman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politico]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The New York Times]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/marco-rubio-needs-to-travel-more-seriously-updated-and-lightly-edited.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Mr. President, I still live in the same working-class neighborhood I grew up in. My neighbors aren’t millionaires. They’re retirees who depend on Social Security and Medicare. They’re workers who have to get up early tomorrow morning and go to work to pay the bills. They’re immigrants, who came here because they were stuck in [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">Mr. President, I still live in the same working-class neighborhood I grew up in. My neighbors aren’t millionaires. They’re retirees who depend on Social Security and Medicare. They’re workers who have to get up early tomorrow morning and go to work to pay the bills. They’re immigrants, who came here because they were stuck in poverty in countries where the government dominated the economy.</div>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; Marco Rubio, last night. </div>
<p>I lifted that quote from <a href="http://dyn.politico.com/printstory.cfm?uuid=6A9DCC73-62AF-402E-9EED-3F327BE18F7B">a Politico article by Jonathan Martin</a> that went on to say that Rubio left school with more than $100,000 in student-loan debt, which he finished paying off only a few months ago. Presumably, those loans were government-sponsored.  Although maybe at the age of 18, he had some collateral to offer the bank.</p>
<p>Rubio’s parents, like so many of his working-class neighbors now, emigrated from Cuba before 2001, when the first of the two sets of Bush tax cuts were passed.  Apparently, he hasn’t checked the federal income tax rates on individuals and corporations when his parents and his neighbors came here because they were stuck in poverty in countries where the government dominated the economy.  Because, best as I can tell, that comment about immigrants from countries where the government dominated the economy was intended as a warning about Obama’s and the congressional Democrats’ plans to have the government dominate the economy.  </p>
<p>So I’d like some specifics.  What policies and programs, current and proposed, does he have in mind?  Exactly?  Maybe next time he’s interviewed by some high-profile journalist, he’ll be asked that.  And maybe he’ll answer.  But I doubt it.</p>
<p>Anyway, for now, I’m left to speculate that he means raising tax rates to Clinton-era tax levels for people with non-investment incomes above $250,000 a year, and on corporations, and on investment income.  He also might mean Obamacare, but that’s questionable unless he thinks that only people who qualify for Medicare get cancer or other serious illnesses, because he also said this last night:</p>
<div dir="ltr">[Medicare] provided my father the care he needed to battle cancer and ultimately die with dignity.  And it pays for the care my mother receives now.</div>
<p>But the title of this post suggests that Rubio travel more.  Both within this country and outside of it.  First he should visit communities where immigrants from, say, Pakistan and Central America live.  People who came here to escape poverty but whose homeland governments did not, and do not, dominate the economy.*  </p>
<p>Then, if he has a passport, he might consider traveling outside the United States.  Maybe to Canada, or Germany, or Sweden, or Holland, or Australia.  Or France. Or, for that matter, Singapore.  Or Taiwan.  Or he could save the plane fare and just use the Internet to check the rates of poverty in those countries, the tax rates there, the social safety nets there, the education systems there, the healthcare systems there. </p>
<p>I didn’t watch the Rubio Show last night, so I missed the reaching-for-a-water-bottle-but-wishing-it-were-a-Vodka-bottle-instead moment.  I wish I’d watched, but I didn’t.  So I’m relying on tidbits reported by others.  And <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/02/13/marco-rubio-has-learned-nothing/">Paul Krugman provides one</a> that, unlike the quotes above, have not garnered much attention.  It’s this:</p>
<div dir="ltr">This idea – that our problems were caused by a government that was too small – it’s just not true. In fact, a major cause of our recent downturn was a housing crisis created by reckless government policies.</div>
<p>Krugman points out that numerous studies, as well as observation by, say, ordinary folks, dispel that claim. Specifically, Krugman writes:<br /><a name="more"></a>
<div dir="ltr">OK, leave on one side the caricature of Obama, with the usual mirror-image fallacy (we want smaller government, therefore liberals just want bigger government, never mind what it does); there we go with the “Barney Frank did it” story. Deregulation, the explosive growth of virtually unregulated shadow banking, lax lending standards by loan originators who sold their loans off as soon as they were made, had nothing to do with it — it was all the Community Reinvestment Act, Fannie, and Freddie.</div>
<div dir="ltr">Look, this is one of the most thoroughly researched topics out there, and every piece of the government-did-it thesis has been refuted; see <a href="http://rortybomb.wordpress.com/2011/11/01/bloombergs-awful-comment-what-can-we-say-for-certain-regarding-the-gses/">Mike Konczal for a summary.</a> No, the CRA wasn’t responsible for the epidemic of bad lending; no, Fannie and Freddie didn’t cause the housing bubble; no, the “high-risk” loans of the GSEs weren’t remotely as risky as subprime.</div>
<p>So I guess I was wrong when I said above that Rubio must have had only tax rates and Obamacare in mind.  He apparently also had finance-industry regulation in mind, too. And on this he was specific. </p>
<p>But on this too, I suggest some overseas travel&#8211;either physically, or virtually, on the Internet. He&#8217;d learn that Spain, Ireland and Iceland must have had a Fannie Mae and a Freddie Mac. Not to mention a Barney Frank. Because those countries’ current and recent fiscal and economic woes were caused entirely by a housing bubbles virtually identical to, or worse than, ours, spurred by Deregulation, the explosive growth of virtually unregulated shadow banking, lax lending standards by loan originators who sold their loans off as soon as they were made. </p>
<p>Then Rubio might consider returning to Canada and Germany, physically or virtually, and checking out why those countries had little or no such bubble.  And before he leaves, or after he returns, he should travel to Texas.  Yes, Texas, of all states.  It had almost no housing bubble.  Something to do with government involvement in the economy, i.e., legislation regulating the mortgage industry, post-savings-and-loan debacle, circa 1989.  State government, in this case. </p>
<p>What is the national debt of Canada and Germany?  And the poverty levels and standards of living in those countries?  </p>
<p>The Politico article, by the way, is called “Marco Rubio as the anti-Romney.”  The title of Krugman’s post indicates disagreement with that assessment. It’s called “Marco Rubio Has Learned Nothing.”  </p>
<p>But a majority of Americans, I think, have.  They’ve learned that you can’t judge a book by it’s jacket cover. And that ideology can’t substitute for fact. 
<div></div>
<div>&#8212;-<br />UPDATE:  Oh, dear. As I said, I didn’t watch Rubio last night.  I also haven’t read a transcript of his speech.  And I didn’t know until just now, when I read Jazzbumpa’s post below, that Rubio said that proposals to deal with climate change, including trying to slow its progression, are attempts to have the government “control the weather.”</p>
<p>Um.  Yeah.  That’s the idea.  </p>
<p>Yikes.</p></div>
<div>Why do I think Chris Christie is the happiest person in America today?</p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />UPDATE II:  I’m getting the strong feeling that there are a lot of people who are downright dumbfounded by that speech last night&#8211;that this guy who’s being touted as the Republican savior went on national television and established himself as stunningly stupid. </p>
<p>We’re going to elect a global warming denier as president in 2016?  We’re going to elect as president someone who is unaware of such things as financial derivatives, and the role they played in the financial meltdown?  We’re going to elect as president someone who seems not to know that student loans and Medicare are government programs&#8211;or at least what it means that they are?  We’re going to elect as president someone who thinks Clinton-era tax rates are a government-dominated economy?</p>
<p>I’ll certainly agree that he’s no Romney.  Romney isn’t stupid, by any stretch.  He just pretended to be.  With Rubio, it’s apparently no act. </p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />*<i>Paragraph edited for clarity</i>. 2/14. (I figured that since this post is getting a decent number of &#8220;hits&#8221; and Google+ links, it should be edited so that typos and such are corrected.)</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/marco-rubio-needs-to-travel-more-seriously-updated-and-lightly-edited.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Paul Krugman Steps on Marco Rubio’s Parade. And Kills My Entertainment.</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/paul-krugman-steps-on-marco-rubios-parade-and-kills-my-entertainment.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/paul-krugman-steps-on-marco-rubios-parade-and-kills-my-entertainment.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2013 22:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Marco Rubio]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Krugman]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/paul-krugman-steps-on-marco-rubios-parade-and-kills-my-entertainment.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Just a quick observation: for the past couple of days I’ve been seeing in a lot of places, including comments on this blog, the assertion that federal spending has risen 37 percent under Obama — that specific number. Does anyone know where it’s coming from? Because if I look at the actual data, I see [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">Just a quick observation: for the past couple of days I’ve been seeing in a lot of places, including comments on this blog, the assertion that federal spending has risen 37 percent under Obama — that specific number. Does anyone know where it’s coming from? </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Because if I look at the <a href="http://research.stlouisfed.org/fred2/data/W019RCQ027SBEA.txt">actual data</a>, I see federal spending rising from $3.475 trillion in fourth-quarter 2008 to $3.917 trillion in fourth-quarter 2012 — a rise of 12.7 percent.</p>
</div>
<div dir="ltr">Obviously this is coming from somewhere, and being broadcast by Rush or somebody. But it’s still kind of amazing how a totally wrong number can become part of what everyone on the right just knows to be true.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/02/12/where-do-facts-come-from/">Where Do “Facts” Come From?</a>, Paul Krugman, New York Times, today</div>
<p>Damn.  Now Marco Rubio will have to scratch that line from his response to the State of the Union address tonight.  Depriving those of us who enjoy political comedy of the fun of watching Rubio explain this fact during the next couple of days, after the CEO of Chrysler Corp. makes a public statement that federal spending has risen 12.7 percent, not 37 percent, since the fourth quarter of 2008.  And that Chrysler has absolutely no plans whatsoever to close the Ohio Jeep plant that it just spent more than $1 million expanding in order to hire 1,200 new workers, and ship those jobs to China. </p>
<p>You shouldn’t have let that cat out of the bag today, Prof. Krugman!</p>
<p>Sheeesh.  You’d almost think the Republicans hired me as their statistician/mathematician.  Hmm.  Maybe I’ll apply to Fox News for consulting work.  My math abilities are every bit as good as those of the person who did the math on that statistic.  Trust me.</p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />Okay, okay.  I don’t actually know that Rubio planned to include this hot statistic in his response tonight.  It’s just my speculation. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/paul-krugman-steps-on-marco-rubios-parade-and-kills-my-entertainment.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The People-as-Props That Obama SHOULD Use During His Speech Tomorrow Night: John Boehner and Joe Barton. And They’re Already Invited!</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/the-people-as-props-that-obama-should-use-during-his-speech-tomorrow-night-john-boehner-and-joe-barton-and-theyre-already-invited.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/the-people-as-props-that-obama-should-use-during-his-speech-tomorrow-night-john-boehner-and-joe-barton-and-theyre-already-invited.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2013 19:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[#obamaquester]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#pleasegrowupspeakerboehner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#spendingstheproblem]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Glenn Thrush]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Greg Sargent]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Joe Baarton]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Boehner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Krugman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the State of the Union address]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/the-people-as-props-that-obama-should-use-during-his-speech-tomorrow-night-john-boehner-and-joe-barton-and-theyre-already-invited.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Speaker John Boehner  @SpeakerBoehner House GOP has voted to replace the president’s sequester twice. Here’s why, courtesy @whitehouse: http://j.mp/WzhNgY #obamaquester &#8212; Twitter, h/t Politico, Boehner’s office dubs it “Obamaquester,” Feb. 8 Oh, dear.  I guess this is going to be a regular thing.  A few days earlier, our dignified House Speaker created the twitter hashtag #spendingstheproblem. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr"><a href="https://twitter.com/SpeakerBoehner?tw_i=299963148268621826&#038;tw_p=tweetembed">Speaker John Boehner  @SpeakerBoehner</a></div>
<div dir="ltr">House GOP has voted to replace the president’s sequester twice. Here’s why, courtesy <a href="https://twitter.com/whitehouse">@whitehouse</a>: <a href="http://t.co/vbir4JzR">http://j.mp/WzhNgY </a><a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23obamaquester&#038;src=hash">#obamaquester</a></div>
<p>     &#8212; Twitter, h/t Politico, <a href="http://www.politico.com/politico44/2013/02/boehners-office-dubs-it-obamaquester-156511.html">Boehner’s office dubs it “Obamaquester</a><a href="http://www.politico.com/politico44/2013/02/boehners-office-dubs-it-obamaquester-156511.html">,”</a> Feb. 8</p>
<p>Oh, dear.  I guess this is going to be a regular thing.  A few days earlier, our dignified House Speaker <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/02/yup-john-boehner-and-paul-ryan-are.html">created the twitter hashtag #spendingstheproblem</a>. Which it certainly is when you deliberately dramatically reduce revenues by drastically cutting taxes, especially on the wealthy and on corporations, and wage two wars, significantly increase expenditures on homeland security, and expand the Medicare program to include prescription drugs.  </p>
<p>And which it surely is when those tax cuts are called, obviously tongue-in-cheek, temporary and are enacted only a decade before the huge baby-boomer generation begins to retire and to qualify for Medicare, and then are in fact mostly not allowed to expire because some of the folks who brought you the tax cuts in the first place, and <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/02/yup-john-boehner-and-paul-ryan-are.html">who think spendingstheproblem</a>, keep blocking attempts to raise revenues even by closing egregious loopholes that benefit only the wealthy.  </p>
<p>Something about the Democrats having to take those tax cuts from their cold dead hands, I guess.  Which if the sequester actually does occur, the Democrats will have little trouble doing, because the Repubs’ political hands will be very cold and very dead.  </p>
<p>The Republicans delude themselves into thinking otherwise, based upon the presumption that the public doesn’t even yet grasp that spendingistheproblem only when you reduce tax rates to historically low levels and allow mega-loopholes through which hedge fund managers and Mitt Romney fly their private or chartered jets through on their way from one of their several homes to another one.  The public, though, does grasp that, and showed it last November 6.  And in the late December polls during the “fiscal cliff” crisis.  And in the polls last month during the debt-ceiling crisis.  </p>
<p>Yet if the Boehner’s Tweet is any indication, he still thinks that all the Repubs have to do is vote to replace the president’s sequester.  And they’ve done that.  Twice.  </p>
<p>No matter what they voted to replace the sequester with.  Nope.  What matters is that they voted to replace the sequester, and that they did so twice.  And that the sequester is “the president’s.”  And that in fact it’s not even a sequester; it’s Obamaquester.  The substance of what they want to enact won’t matter to the public.  All that will matter to the public is that the House Republicans voted to replace the sequester with something and that therefore the Senate Dems and Obama are obligated to adopt it.  That’s because the Republicans won the election last November&#8211;er, because there’s now a cutesy, juvenile twitter hashtag out there saying that the sequester is Obamaquester.  First things first, you know.<br /><a name="more"></a><br />The Speaker, as Paul Krugman pointed out <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/02/07/the-undecade/">on Thursday</a> and again <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/08/opinion/krugman-kick-that-can.html?_r=0">on Friday</a>, suffers not just from short-term memory problems but also from long-term memory problems. Boehner said last week that the budget deficit has continued to increase throughout his 22-year tenure in Congress. Which, of course, is why in 2001 and again in 2003, as the wars in Iraq and Afghanistan accellerated rather than wound down, and after we began to spend considerably more on homeland security in the wake of 9/11, and after Medicare was expanded to include prescription drug coverage, he joined nearly all his Republican colleagues to vote for the drastic tax cuts, most of it benefiting the wealthy and large corporations.  </p>
<p>I guess that’s because #spendingstheproblem even when the budget deficit has recently been eliminated with the help of tax rate increases mostly on upper-income folks. And even when the huge baby boomer generation is beginning to retire.  </p>
<p>Longtime House member Joe Barton (R-Texas), who apparently doesn’t favor a strategy of posting juvenile twitter posts, does nonetheless agree with Boehner that we should simply allow the sequester to take effect unless the Senate Dems and Obama agree to rubberstamp the House Repubs’ offered substitute for the sequester.  The one they passed.  Twice.  He <a href="http://dyn.politico.com/printstory.cfm?uuid=F5E99E93-7EC0-49FE-8A8C-86EB5FD8FEDE">explained to Politico</a> why he favors the sequester, despite pleas from constitutions who will be furloughed as a result:</p>
<div dir="ltr">I’m a lot more concerned about trillion-dollar deficits every year stretching to infinity. That’s obviously a more indirect issue to somebody who’s about to lose their job or has lost their job, and I respect that 100 percent.</div>
<p>It’s the next generation that he’s concerned about, he said.  Which is why he refuses to consider raising taxes on this generation of wealthy taxpayers and corporations by closing loopholes through which hedge fund managers and cutely offshore-based-for-tax-purposes American corporations fly their Learjets. </p>
<p>Politico’s Glenn Thrush <a href="http://www.politico.com/story/2013/02/state-of-the-union-2013-obama-aggressive-87440.html?hp=t1_3">reports this morning</a> that Obama plans to be forceful tomorrow night in explaining his economic-policy position and in refuting the Republicans’.  But, as Greg Sargent <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/plum-line/wp/2013/02/11/the-morning-plum-go-on-offense-mr-president/?hpid=z3">says today</a>, Obama’s preference for pussyfooting, generic, brief catchphrases, such as “self-inflicted wounds” and “We can’t cut our way to prosperity,” need actual several-sentence explanations.  They’re worthless unless they’re spelled out, with actual clarity and specificity. </p>
<p>But here’s something else&#8211;something absolutely critical&#8211;that Obama needs to make clear.  To make clear.  That the Republicans have settled on a strategy of pretending that additional tax revenue doesn’t decrease the budget deficit, and of pushing that strategy via the tactic of simply making repeated public comments that ignore that additional tax revenue does exactly that.  Thus, #spendingstheproblem, the sequester is <a href="http://www.politico.com/politico44/2013/02/boehners-office-dubs-it-obamaquester-156511.html">#obamaquester</a>, and neither the Clinton presidency nor the G.W. Bush presidency happened. </p>
<p>Both Boehner and Barton will be in the audience tomorrow night.  They won’t be sitting next or right in back of Michelle, special guests of the president.  But they’ll be there.  And Obama should address them by name, in a comment along the lines of: </p>
<div dir="ltr">Rep. Barton, you’ve said you’re a lot more concerned about trillion-dollar deficits every year stretching to infinity than you are about the jobs of the National Weather Service employees and air traffic controllers and food safety inspectors who live in your district.  And you’re a lot more concerned about keeping income tax rates at 15% for hedge fund managers, and about keeping the corporate offshoring tax advantages intact, than you are about trillion-dollar deficits every year stretching to infinity.  Even though, in light of the fiscal-cliff compromise that the Democrats forced at the beginning of the year, and the economic recovery that will continue if you and your colleagues stop the sequential Russian roulette and start taking your oath of office at least a little bit seriously, infinity could turn out to be not that far away after all.</div>
<p>Of course, the president could instead create a hashtag on twitter.  My suggestion: #pleasegrowupspeakerboehner.</p>
<p>Or maybe he should just sit tight.  Doesn’t the tornado season begin in Texas right about the time that the sequester does?  And in Ohio soon after?  </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/the-people-as-props-that-obama-should-use-during-his-speech-tomorrow-night-john-boehner-and-joe-barton-and-theyre-already-invited.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Stories That Will Continue to Get Far Too Little Attention As Long As Obama Allows Them To. [Appended]</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/stories-that-will-continue-to-get-far-too-little-attention-as-long-as-obama-allows-them-to-appended.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/stories-that-will-continue-to-get-far-too-little-attention-as-long-as-obama-allows-them-to-appended.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Feb 2013 17:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[filibuster]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Greg Sargent]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Krugman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Cordray]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[State of Union Address]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the Consumer Protection Financial Bureau]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the Dodd-Frank law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The New York Times]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Washington Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/stories-that-will-continue-to-get-far-too-little-attention-as-long-as-obama-allows-them-to-appended.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[* Don’t forget about the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau: Paul Krugman has the goods on a story that’s getting far too little attention: In filibustering Richard Cordray, Obama’s choice to head the consumer protection bureau, and demanding major changes to the agency, Republicans are trying to transform it into something that’s essentially unable to carry [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">* Don’t forget about the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau: <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/04/opinion/krugman-friends-of-fraud.html?hp&#038;_r=0">Paul Krugman</a> <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/04/opinion/krugman-friends-of-fraud.html?hp&#038;_r=0">has the goods on a story that’s getting far too little attention</a>: In filibustering Richard Cordray, Obama’s choice to head the consumer protection bureau, and demanding major changes to the agency, Republicans are trying to transform it into something that’s essentially unable to carry out its mission.</div>
<div dir="ltr">How can the G.O.P. be so determined to make America safe for financial fraud, with the 2008 crisis still so fresh in our memory? In part it’s because Republicans are deep in denial about what actually happened to our financial system and economy. [&#8230;] Just four years after runaway bankers brought the world economy to its knees, Senate Republicans are using every means at their disposal, violating all the usual norms of politics in the process, in an attempt to give the bankers a chance to do it all over again.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Krugman notes that Cordray has drawn praise even from the bankers, which I’ve seen elsewhere, too. So: Do the financial institutions even favor what the GOP is up to here? </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Worth some more reporting, I’d say.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; Greg Sargent, Washington Post, <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/plum-line/wp/2013/02/04/the-morning-plum-the-problem-with-the-obama-skeet-shooting-controversy/">today</a></div>
<p>One of the most dismaying and frustrating of Obama’s first-term communication failures was, for me, his utter absence of any real attempt to apprise the public of the existence of the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau, what its mandate is, and that (and how) the congressional Republicans have concertedly tried to undermine it, via Senate filibuster of any nominee&#8211;not just, first Elizabeth Warren, and then Richard Cordray, but, by their own admission, any nominee&#8211;to head this bureau, and by attempts to fail to appropriate operating funds for it. </p>
<p>Eight days from now, in his State of the Union address, Obama will have a terrific opportunity to educate the public about all this.  All this.  By which I mean: Not just a clause or a sentence near the end of the speech, alluding to it in listing this, that, and the other thing, but instead an actual explanation of it and of the undermining of it by the Repubs. Near the opening of the speech, before viewers click to whatever because they, like me, want to avoid gagging at the extremely tired James Baker’s great-idea-for-staging-at-Reagan’s-State-of-the-Union-addresses-and-used-by-every-president-sinnce-then real-Americans-as-props thing. (Talking about a program to help oil-company workers? Cue two oil-company workers flanking the First Lady, sitting in the first row. You know what I’m talking about.  Ad nauseum.)  </p>
<p>But since the invites of real Americans surely have already been sent out, and there’s no stopping that juggernaut anyway, however more eyes it causes to roll each year, I suggest the addition of some real Americans who already have benefited from the Bureau’s actions.  </p>
<p>I also, by the way, suggest the addition of a real American or two who, because of the provision in Dodd-Frank&#8211;or maybe it was a separate statute, all its own, effective in August 2011 but enacted in 2010 by a Dem-controlled Senate and Dem-controlled House; I’m not sure&#8211;that ended what millions of Americans fondly came to call the $400 Starbucks/McDonalds/Dunkin’Donuts coffee/sandwich/dessert, the result of inadvertent, momentary checking-account overdrafts when the mortgage payment, the doctor’s co-pay, and payment for the brake job the SUV all just by chance happened to post to your checking account moments before you swiped that ATM/credit/debit card at the Starbuck, McDonald’s or Dunkin’ Donuts.  I’ll nominate myself for an invite on that one, even though I’ve never actually owned an SUV and don’t like them much.  </p>
<p>No, <i>that</i> doesn’t involve something that changed the state of the union this past year.  But it’s long past time for our Dem politicians to start pointing out things of exactly this sort, and to ask what exactly the congressional Republicans have done along those lines since Jan. 2011. And to start educating the public about what the specifics of what they’ve done to undermine protections against financial-industry abuse, whether legal or illegal.</p>
<p>Stories that will continue to get far too little attention as long as Obama allows them to.  Or until maybe Prof. Krugman becomes President Krugman&#8211;which sounds like a plan, to me!
<div></div>
<div>&#8212;-<br />UPDATE: Oh, dear.  Turns out that Mitt Romney isn’t the only one who wasn’t familiar with the pre-Aug. 2011 $400 McDonald’s sandwich paid for (many times over) with ATM card payment charges (a.k.a., multiple overdraft fees within a period of 30 seconds.)  Regular reader coberly wasn’t either.  So he and I just exchanged the following comments in the Comments thread:</p>
<p> cobery: 
<div dir="ltr">Beverly</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">You did not exactly take advantage of your own opportunity to explain the Starbucks $400 dessert, but I can guess.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Back when it might have been a problem for me, I kept track of the checks I wrote and did not write them for any more than I had in the bank. I think this prevented even &#8220;inadvertent&#8221; overdrafts.</div>
<p> Me: 
<div dir="ltr">Ah. Actually, I just threw that in there to be funny.  Or to try to be. (It&#8217;s not really a funny subject, so maybe I shouldn&#8217;t have tried.)  But unless you keep a lot of cash in your checking account or tie it automatically to a savings account, or were extremely careful to keep track of your checking account&#8211;and a lot of people have more than one checking account&#8211;you would, before that law came into effect in 2011, have to keep enough money in your account to include an  overdraft fee of $36 (or whatever) each for a single inadvertent overdraft, or you would find yourself charged repeated overdraft fees in a single day for every charge that came in until you realized you were overdrawn.  </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">The new law applies only to debit/credit card/ATM transactions, not to actual checks, so you still have to be careful about checks, especially since you can&#8217;t be sure when they&#8217;ll be cashed. </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">It also helps if you can add and subtract, I’ve learned the hard way.  One of my tax-law profs. used to say that his wife was always the one to actually do their income tax returns. The guy was friggin’ brilliant in discussing legal theory and tax strategy&#8211;best as I could tell, anyway&#8211;but swore that he couldn’t do actual math, or even competently use a calculator, worth a damn.  Makes me feel better when I recall that. (Calculators sorta throw me off, too, since I can’t figure out what all those funny-looking math symbols are.  Like the + and &#8211; signs.)</div>
<p>Back in the pre-Dodd-Frank days, there were looooads of stories on the web and elsewhere about this kind of thing.  So I assumed everyone was familiar with the issue.  Not so, though. So I thought I’d add this explanation. </div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/stories-that-will-continue-to-get-far-too-little-attention-as-long-as-obama-allows-them-to-appended.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Joe Scarborough on the Deficit</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/joe-scarborough-on-the-deficit.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/joe-scarborough-on-the-deficit.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Feb 2013 16:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[econospeak]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Krugman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[pro growth liberal]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/joe-scarborough-on-the-deficit.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Pro Growth Liberal at Econospeak also takes Joe Scarborough to task on Krugman and Keynes: Joe Scarborough on the Deficit After his interview with Paul Krugman this morning Joe Scarborough wrote: Mr. Krugman&#8217;s view is that Americans would be better off if its government ran deeper deficits and ignored its longterm debt.To suggest that Keynesians like [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>Pro Growth Liberal at <i>Econospeak</i> also takes Joe Scarborough to task on Krugman and Keynes:</div>
<p>
<blockquote><a href="http://econospeak.blogspot.com/2013/01/joe-scarborough-on-deficit.html">Joe Scarborough on the Deficit</a></p>
<p>After his interview with Paul Krugman this morning <a href="http://www.politico.com/story/2013/01/paul-krugman-vs-the-world-86822.html?hp=l9">Joe Scarborough</a> wrote:</p>
<p>Mr. Krugman&#8217;s view is that Americans would be better off if its government ran deeper deficits and ignored its longterm debt.<br />To suggest that Keynesians like Paul Krugman ignore the long-term government budget constraint is either dishonest or shows that Mr. Scarborough does not understand what we are saying. Which is why Mr. Scarborough should check out <a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/10-people-who-disagree-with-joe-scarborough-2013-1">this list</a> of commentary on the current economics and fiscal situation compiled by Joe Weisenthal.  </p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/joe-scarborough-on-the-deficit.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Paul Krugman, Angry Bear, and Jazzbumpa</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/paul-krugman-angry-bear-and-jazzbumpa.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/paul-krugman-angry-bear-and-jazzbumpa.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Feb 2013 15:54:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Beverly Mann]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bruce Webb]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jazzbumpa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mike Kimel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NYT]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Krugman]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/paul-krugman-angry-bear-and-jazzbumpa.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Update: Noahpinion takes on the same in How to win arguments by pretending to be stupid.  The comments section offers other points of view. Ron T. aka Jazzbumpa received an unusual thank you from Paul Krugman for this post on a Mish Shedlock post about debating PK. Krugman recommended Beverly Mann  on January 15th this year [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Update: <a href="http://noahpinionblog.blogspot.com/2013/02/how-to-win-arguments-by-pretending-to.html" target="_blank">Noahpinion</a> takes on the same in <i>How to win arguments by pretending to be stupid.  </i>The comments section offers other points of view.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/02/how-to-debae-paul-krugman.html">Ron T. aka Jazzbumpa</a> received an unusual thank you from Paul Krugman for this post on a Mish Shedlock post about debating PK.</p>
<p>Krugman recommended <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/01/15/short-takes-2" target="_blank">Beverly Mann</a>  on January 15th this year as part of a  recommended reading post.  </p>
<p>Other <i>Angry Bear</i> contributors gaining mention and recommendation by name in the recent past that immediately come to mind are <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/04/what-is-question-responding-to-paul.html" target="_blank">Mike Kimel</a> and <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/01/15/early-social-security-projections/" target="_blank">Bruce Webb</a>.</p>
<p><img alt="" src="https://mail.google.com/mail/u/0/images/cleardot.gif"><a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/02/03/despicable-me/">Despicable Me &#8211; Paul Krugman</a></p>
<blockquote><p>Funny: <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/02/how-to-debae-paul-krugman.html?utm_source=feedburner&#038;utm_medium=feed&#038;utm_campaign=Feed%3A+blogspot%2FHzoh+%28Angry+Bear%29">Angry Bear</a> finds some of the usual suspects explaining <a href="http://globaleconomicanalysis.blogspot.com/2013/01/how-to-debate-paul-krugman-ask.html">How to Debate Paul Krugman</a>, and the answer appears to be this: invent a straw man who bears no resemblance at all to the economist/columnist of the same name, and ridicule that imaginary person. I have to say, never in my wildest dreams did I imagine that I could play the role of History’s Greatest Monster to so many people. Thank you for the honor!</p>
<p>Aside from the silliness of the exercise, this little exchange is another illustration of a point I’ve noticed before: the way hard-right commentators assume that the other side must be <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/10/12/i-am-not-your-mirror-image/">their mirror image</a>. They insist that no government intervention is ever justified; so liberals must support any and all government interventions. They want smaller government, as a principle; liberals must want bigger government, never mind what for. They believe that deficits and printing money are always evil; liberals must be for deficits and money-printing under all circumstances.</p>
<p>An hour spent browsing this blog would quickly refute all of this, together with the bizarre charge that I never look at evidence; you may not agree with my conclusions, but I sure do post a lot of numbers. But obviously looking at what I actually write would just be too painful.</p>
<p>Anyway, thanks guys, you made my day.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/paul-krugman-angry-bear-and-jazzbumpa.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>How To Debate Paul Krugman</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/how-to-debate-paul-krugman.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/how-to-debate-paul-krugman.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2013 21:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[austerity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Austrian economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jazzbumpa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mish Shedlock]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Krugman]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/how-to-debate-paul-krugman.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[On Saturday Mish wrote a really awful article with those words in it&#8217;s title. The article borrows these words and includes a quote from an even more awful article by Austrian school economist and author Detlev Schlichter.  Part of that quote is presented here. What makes him [PK] so annoying is his unquestioning, reflexive and [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>On Saturday Mish wrote a <a href="http://globaleconomicanalysis.blogspot.com/2013/01/how-to-debate-paul-krugman-ask.html">really awful article</a> with those words in it&#8217;s title.</p>
<p>The article borrows these words and includes a quote from <a href="http://detlevschlichter.com/2012/05/how-to-debate-paul-krugman/">an even more awful article</a> by Austrian school economist and author <a href="http://detlevschlichter.com/about/">Detlev Schlichter</a>.  Part of that quote is presented here.<br />
<blockquote>What makes him [PK] so annoying is his unquestioning, reflexive and almost  childlike enthusiasm for state intervention, even in the face of its  obvious failure, and his apparent unwillingness to probe any deeper into  the real causes of our present economic problems or to show any  willingness to investigate the effectiveness or ineffectiveness of his  particular medicine.</p></blockquote>
<p>I want to  make something perfectly clear before we go any further.  It is fine to  disagree with Krugman, or me, or the Pope, or anyone else, as long as  you bring facts, data, and some basic skill in rational discourse.  What  is not fine is misrepresenting someone&#8217;s position and then holding the  misrepresentation up to ridicule.  That is both vile and stupid.</p>
<p>Back to the quote: does that sound anything like the Paul Krugman who puts his ideas <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/">out there for the world to see</a> on a daily basis?  What I see in Krugman is thoughtful analysis, and  deep probing into both the causes of our problems and the consequences  of economic policy decisions.  You don&#8217;t have to agree with his  assesments, but you cannot validly deny that he is making them.</p>
<p>When the opportunities smack me in the face like  this, I put on my <a href="http://jazzbumpa.blogspot.com/2010/01/deep-stupid-14.html"><u><i>Krugman Truth Squad</i> </u></a>hat.   Schlichter offers us a standard issue stale Austrian anti-Krugman  diatribe. You have to wonder if he has ever bothered to read anything  that Krugman has written.   His wordy, repetitive, rambling, semi-coherent, desperate-sounding  article &#8211; which I cannot recommend highly enough &#8211; is an impressive  exercise in partial-truths, distortions, make believe, and straw man  stuffing.  He then hints that we should go back to the gold standard and  totally unfettered free markets.</p>
<p>Schlichter lists Krugman&#8217;s alleged assumptions, condensed here:</p>
<blockquote><p>1)   Recessions, depressions and crises are the result of the unhampered market. <br />2)   The Great Depression was caused by uncontrolled markets.<br />3)    Recessions, depressions and crises are practically the result of one  problem: a lack of aggregate demand.  .  .  .   It is the role of  government to get people spending again. This is done  by printing money and causing inflation so that people spend. <br /> 4)   The Great Depression was solved by the government spending lots of money and the central bank printing lots of money.</p></blockquote>
<p>Let&#8217;s  pause here for a moment and set aside the redundancy.  I&#8217;m not sure  points 1 and 2 represent PK&#8217;s view with any degree of accuracy.   Certainly they are gross oversimplifications and neglect other factors.   But if they are true, then point 3 can&#8217;t be.  Let&#8217;s set that aside, as  well.  Points 3 and 4 are reasonably close to the truth, though if you  read the original, point 3 runs off the rails as it continues.  </p>
<p>From there it only gets worse.</p>
<blockquote><p>5)   This explains ALL economic problems.</p></blockquote>
<p>So,  according to Schlechter, Keynes taught, Krugman believes &#8211; and would  have us believe &#8211; that loose money policies and causing inflation are  the right policy measures not only for recessions, but for boom times,  and periods of inflation, hyper-inflation, stag-flation, or any other  problem you can think of.  Even I <a href="http://jazzbumpa.blogspot.com/2011/02/accidental-keynesians.html">know enough about Keynes</a> to call that out as false. </p>
<p>The  redundency continues to pile up.  I&#8217;ll extract one more point. [#&#8217;s  6,7, and 8 are repetitions of #4 with various degrees of elaboration and  snark.]</p>
<blockquote><p>7)   If after many rounds of money printing and deficit spending, there  is still a recession, then only one conclusion is permissible: There was  obviously not enough money printing and deficit spending. We need more  of it.</p></blockquote>
<p>I don&#8217;t claim to  know everything, but I&#8217;m not aware of any situation in recent history  that has played out like this, so it looks like a Schlichterian  fantasy.  In the post WW II era, the combination of loose money and  fiscal expansion has generally kept recessions rather short, leading to  V-shaped recoveries, and putting the brakes on too quickly has  occasionally led to a double dip.  England has recently experienced an <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/business/2012/apr/25/uk-sinks-double-dip-recession-gdp">austerity-induced double dip recession</a>.   In the current U. S. doldrums, Krugman tells us fiscal frugality has  led to a slow and limping recovery.  This is credible since spending is  flat and GDP growth is anemic. [Graph 1]</p>
<p>
<div><a href="http://research.stlouisfed.org/fredgraph.png?g=f65"><img border="0" height="240" src="http://research.stlouisfed.org/fredgraph.png?g=f65" width="400"></a></div>
<div>Graph 1, Current Expenditures and GDP (log scale)</div>
<p>Has any modern major economy had a recession persist after &#8220;many rounds of money printing and deficit spending&#8221;?  Even in the Great Depression things <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/10/19/1933-and-all-that/">turned around pretty quickly</a> once New Deal policies were implemented.  But, as PK also tells us, recessions brought on by a financial crisis are <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/10/08/fact-checking-financial-recessions/">different from the typical post WW II recession</a>.</p>
<p>Schlichter doesn&#8217;t let up. Though this statement [emphasis added], &#8220;Krugman is the one who should be made to explain his policy  recommendations and who has to answer the criticism that <u><i>policies like  the ones he is recommending got us into this mess in the first place</i> </u>and  that <i><u>his policy ideas have been implemented for years to no effect</u></i>, at  least no positive effect.&#8221;  is hard to beat for sheer negation of reality [and for channeling Ron Paul],  the real capper is this: &#8220;Krugman is practicing Keynesianism as a religion.&#8221;</p>
<p>It is because of statements like this that I lose patience with people who use words like &#8220;<i>disingenuous</i>.&#8221; You can supply your own alternative vocabulary   Check Krugman&#8217;s Op-Eds and blog  posts, where he repeatedly demonstrates reality with <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/01/23/martin-wolf-hippie/">graphs and tables</a>, shows how <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/12/11/bleeding-europe/">austerity is failing right now</a> with real-world examples, and <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/12/30/is-our-austerians-learning/">admits it when he gets something wrong</a>.  When is the last time you saw a Krugman-hater do that?</p>
<p>Mish, to his eternal discredit, says of this nonsense: &#8221; Moreover, it appears to be 100% accurate.&#8221;</p>
<div>But, Mish continues, the real way to debate Krugman is demonstrated by Economist Hans Hermann-Hoppe in this one minute video.</div>
<p>This is genuinely awesome.   That an economist can be so thoroughly  wrong &#8211; wrong in general and wrong in every particular &#8211; about what  Keynesianism is and does, leaves me speechless, and that&#8217;s saying  something.</p>
<p>OK &#8211; almost speechless.  Any child can see  that the earth is flat and the sun revolves around it.  So let&#8217;s forget  the trivially unimportant technical  details and ask simple-minded, allegedly probing questions that in this  case are  totally unrelated not only to the policies Keynes and Krugman propose,  but to anything else in the real world, and then point and stare when  these questions cannot be answered &#8211; by anyone, while your minions nod  approvingly.</p>
<p>But would it work?  Mish concludes this way:</p>
<blockquote><p>Krugman would respond with incomprehensible gibberish &#8220;for wonks only&#8221;  as well as typical Keynesian nonsense about how paying people to dig  holes and other people to fill them up would start a chain reaction of  growth.</p></blockquote>
<p>
<blockquote>A child would see the answer was preposterous, but not a trained  economist, politician, or brainwashed academic. Paul Krugman, keynesian  economists in general, politicians wanting a free lunch, and most  academics are all incurable.</p></blockquote>
<p>
<blockquote>Nonetheless, Hans Hermann-Hoppe&#8217;s answer is indeed the correct one. By  asking questions a child will understand, some non-brainwashed people  will see Keynesian and Monetary stimulus for what they really are:  economic stupidity.</p></blockquote>
<p>In <a href="http://globaleconomicanalysis.blogspot.com/2013/01/libertarian-turned-keynesian-responds.html">a follow up article</a> [with a 5 point list that includes 2 naked assertion and 3  irrelevancies {seriously &#8211; Zimbabwe?!?}] Mish makes it clear that in his view monetary  and fiscal stimulus are BOTH stupid.   So, at this point it looks as if he &#8211;  with his straw man army and blatant intellectual nihilism &#8211;  and I have  devolved into a schoolyard game of calling each other <i>stupid</i>.</p>
<p>But I&#8217;m quite sure Mish is not stupid, and I&#8217;m fairly certain I&#8217;m not  either.  The real questions are these: who is paying attention to  reality, whose policies make things better or worse <i>in a given situation</i> [absolutism, anyone?] and whose concepts have had some predictive power  over the last several years.  [Here&#8217;s a hint:<a href="http://delong.typepad.com/sdj/2012/12/when-will-robert-murphy-conclude-that-he-just-does-not-know-what-he-is-doing.html"> it&#8217;s not the Austerians</a>.]</p>
<p>So, maybe a better way to phrase it is, &#8220;<a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/01/28/failures/"><u><i>Who is practicing their economics as a religion</i></u></a>?&#8221;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/how-to-debate-paul-krugman.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Brian Williams Thinks Raising the Debt Ceiling Means Increasing BUDGET APPROPRIATIONS. O Peter Jennings, Walter Cronkite, and Edward R. Murrow, Where Art Thou? &#8212; [UPDATED]</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/brian-williams-thinks-raising-the-debt-ceiling-means-increasing-budget-appropriations-o-peter-jennings-walter-cronkite-and-edward-r-murrow-where-art-thou-updated.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/brian-williams-thinks-raising-the-debt-ceiling-means-increasing-budget-appropriations-o-peter-jennings-walter-cronkite-and-edward-r-murrow-where-art-thou-updated.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2013 15:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[austerity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Brian Williams]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Keynesian economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NBC Nightly News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Krugman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the debt ceiling]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The New York Times]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/brian-williams-thinks-raising-the-debt-ceiling-means-increasing-budget-appropriations-o-peter-jennings-walter-cronkite-and-edward-r-murrow-where-art-thou-updated.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I watched NBC Nightly News with Brian Williams last night.  Big Mistake. Big mistake. Because now I’m really confused.  I was pretty darn sure until then that “raising the debt ceiling” meant allowing the Treasury Department to pay financial obligations already incurred, such as interest on bonds, Medicare payments, and contract obligations, and to allow [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I watched NBC Nightly News with Brian Williams last night.  Big Mistake. </p>
<p>Big mistake. </p>
<p>Because now I’m really confused.  I was pretty darn sure until then that “raising the debt ceiling” meant allowing the Treasury Department to pay financial obligations already incurred, such as interest on bonds, Medicare payments, and contract obligations, and to allow continued payments for ongoing financial obligations such as Social Security payments, Veterans’ benefits, and salary payments to federal employees, some of whose jobs are sort of important.  (Think: air traffic controllers.)  I had thought that because I had followed the recurring-crisis news reports about it since 2011, when the first of the crises began.  And because Obama had actually explained it in his Jan. 14 press conference. </p>
<p>But now, well, I think I might have misunderstood, because after Williams reported that the Senate yesterday had approved the House bill to “suspend” the debt ceiling through May 19, he added, shaking his head in disapproval, something like: “This is Washington’s version of kicking the can down the road.  Our debt is now more than a trillion dollars.”</p>
<p>I suggest that next time Williams is onboard one of NBC’s corporate jets, he might read, say, Paul Krugman’s <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/01/opinion/krugman-looking-for-mister-goodpain.html?_r=0">column in today’s New York Times</a>.  It doesn’t explain the difference between the debt ceiling statute and budget-appropriations statutes, so Williams will continue to conflate the two until he digs deeper and reads earlier Krugman columns or other mainstream-media articles that did that.  But it does (yet again)&#8211;<a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/01/paul-ryan-says-taxes-should-be-raised.html">to borrow a phrase from Paul Ryan</a> in his Meet the Press interview aired last Sunday&#8211;debate the efficacy of Keynesian economics, and whether anti-Keynesian “austerity” measures reduce or instead increase national debt in real terms and, more important (although Williams apparently doesn’t know this), decrease or instead increase debt relative to GDP.</p>
<p>But if he is going to wait until he’s up there in the air in that Learjet to read the Krugman column, I hope the trip occurs before May 20.  </p>
<p>&#8212;-</p>
<p>UPDATE: Additional recommended reading for Brian Williams: Joe Scarborough, Paul Krugman and the economist-pundit divide on debt and deficits, Neil Irwin, Washington Post, yesterday. </p>
<p>Scarborough, though, at least knows what the debt ceiling law is, and that it isn’t the same as budget-appropriations legislation.  He does, after all, work for MSNBC, not, say, NBC News. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/brian-williams-thinks-raising-the-debt-ceiling-means-increasing-budget-appropriations-o-peter-jennings-walter-cronkite-and-edward-r-murrow-where-art-thou-updated.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
