<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Bible &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The Economic System of the Apostles</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/the-economic-system-of-the-apostles.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/the-economic-system-of-the-apostles.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 31 Oct 2012 13:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Bible]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mike Kimel]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/the-economic-system-of-the-apostles.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Mike Kimel The Economic System of the Apostles I am not a Christian, but if I was, I suspect the following verses from the Acts of the Apostles would have an impact on my life. Acts of the Apostles, 2: 44-47 And all that believed were together, and had all thingscommon; And sold their possessions and [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Mike Kimel</p>
<p>The Economic System of the Apostles</p>
<p>I am not a Christian, but if I was, I suspect the following verses from the Acts of the Apostles would have an impact on my life.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.blueletterbible.org/Bible.cfm?b=Act&#038;c=2&#038;v=1&#038;t=KJV">Acts of the Apostles, 2: 44-47</a><br />
<blockquote>And all that believed were together, and had all things<br />common; And sold their possessions and goods, and parted them to all<br />[men], as every man had need.  And they, continuing daily with one<br />accord in the temple, and breaking bread from house to house, did eat<br />their meat with gladness and singleness of heart, Praising God, and<br />having favour with all the people. And the Lord added to the church<br />daily such as should be saved.</p></blockquote>
<p><a href="http://www.blueletterbible.org/Bible.cfm?b=Act&#038;c=4&#038;v=1&#038;t=KJV">Acts of the Apostles, 4: 32-35</a></p>
<blockquote><p>And the multitude of them that believed were of one heart<br />and of one soul: neither said any [of them] that ought of the things<br />which he possessed was his own; but they had all things common. And<br />with great power gave the apostles witness of the resurrection of the<br />Lord Jesus: and great grace was upon them all. Neither was there any<br />among them that lacked: for as many as were possessors of lands or<br />houses sold them, and brought the prices of the things that were sold,<br />And laid [them] down at the apostles&#8217; feet: and distribution was made<br />unto every man according as he had need.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.blueletterbible.org/Bible.cfm?b=Act&#038;c=5">Acts of the Apostles, 5: 1-11</a></p>
<blockquote><p>But a certain man named Ananias, with Sapphira his wife,<br />sold a possession, And kept back [part] of the price, his wife also<br />being privy [to it], and brought a certain part, and laid [it] at the<br />apostles&#8217; feet. But Peter said, Ananias, why hath Satan filled thine<br />heart to lie to the Holy Ghost, and to keep back [part] of the price<br />of the land?  Whiles it remained, was it not thine own? and after it<br />was sold, was it not in thine own power? why hast thou conceived this<br />thing in thine heart? thou hast not lied unto men, but unto God.  And<br />Ananias hearing these words fell down, and gave up the ghost: and<br />great fear came on all them that heard these things.  And the young<br />men arose, wound him up, and carried [him] out, and buried [him].  And<br />it was about the space of three hours after, when his wife, not<br />knowing what was done, came in.  And Peter answered unto her, Tell me<br />whether ye sold the land for so much? And she said, Yea, for so much.<br />Then Peter said unto her, How is it that ye have agreed together to<br />tempt the Spirit of the Lord? behold, the feet of them which have<br />buried thy husband [are] at the door, and shall carry thee out.   Then<br />fell she down straightway at his feet, and yielded up the ghost: and<br />the young men came in, and found her dead, and, carrying [her] forth,<br />buried [her] by her husband.   And great fear came upon all the<br />church, and upon as many as heard these things.</p></blockquote>
<p>How do you interpret these selections?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/the-economic-system-of-the-apostles.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
