<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Economic Principals &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>In Which I Worry about the swimming pools of Casey Mulligan and Greg Mankiw</title>
		<link>./../../2010/08/in-which-i-worry-about-the-swimming-pools-of-casey-mulligan-and-greg-mankiw.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/08/in-which-i-worry-about-the-swimming-pools-of-casey-mulligan-and-greg-mankiw.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 12 Aug 2010 20:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[bad economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[data]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Economic Principals]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Macroeconomic Theory]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/08/in-which-i-worry-about-the-swimming-pools-of-casey-mulligan-and-greg-mankiw.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Tim Duy takes a gracious lead pipe to silly analysis: It really makes one understand why the public often dismisses academics as out of touch in their ivory towers. One has to imagine that neither Mulligan nor Mankiw ever held a real summer job. Nor, apparently, have they looked at any other nonseasonally adjusted data. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Tim Duy <a href="http://economistsview.typepad.com/economistsview/2010/08/it-such-a-silly-analysis.html">takes a gracious lead pipe to silly analysis</a>:<br />
<blockquote>It really makes one understand why the public often dismisses academics as out of touch in their ivory towers. One has to imagine that neither Mulligan nor Mankiw ever held a real summer job. Nor, apparently, have they looked at any other nonseasonally adjusted data. Nor do they appear to have much understanding of the basic ebb and flow of US economic activity over the course of the year&#8230;.</p>
<p>It seems to entirely escape them that aggregate demand has a very predictable season pattern &#8211; a seasonal pattern that exists in a recession or expansion.</p>
<p>These seasonal patterns in demand activity are not new. Indeed, I imagine that if the data existed, we would see the pattern has remained virtually unchanged since the dawn of human existence, as least in parts of the world where seasonal weather patterns govern economic life. Indeed, it is the reason we have an influx of teenage labor in the summer. It is a throwback to the days of America&#8217;s agricultural past, when the DEMAND for additional labor in the summer months necessitated closing schools for the summer.</p>
<p>As sure as the sun rises each day and winter turns to spring, sales spike at the end of the year as the holiday season approaches, collapse at the beginning of the year, rise in the summer, and then decline in the fall&#8230;</p>
<p>You can set your clock to this trend. Every retail analyst knows this trend. Every teenager who has ever held a summer job knows this trend. And a huge swath of data follows similar trends, albeit usually without the pronounced end of year impact. Building activity, waste disposal, tourism, you name it, it has a seasonal demand pattern. I only have to look out my ivory tower to see it &#8211; stuff grows faster in the summer, and the city hires crews of teenagers to cut it back. The pool down the road is open and staffed by teenage lifeguards only in the summer. Not because the lifeguards are available, but because there is no demand for an outdoor pool most of the year in Eugene.</p></blockquote>
<p>Read <a href="http://economistsview.typepad.com/economistsview/2010/08/it-such-a-silly-analysis.html">the whole thing</a>. Especially you, <a href="http://www.marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2010/08/the-mulligan-and-mankiw-challenge-to-extreme-keynesians.html">Tyler</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/08/in-which-i-worry-about-the-swimming-pools-of-casey-mulligan-and-greg-mankiw.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Reasons I Haven&#8217;t Needed to Post</title>
		<link>./../../2008/12/reasons-i-havent-needed-to-post.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/12/reasons-i-havent-needed-to-post.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2008 20:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Bush]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Economic Principals]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[journamalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WSJ]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/12/reasons-i-havent-needed-to-post.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[davenoon at LG&#038;M and Kikuchiyo Jones subbing for the good Roger Ailes both clobbered the WSJ&#8217;s most egregious fluffing this year. Martin Feldstein continues to try to destroy the previously-brilliant David Warsh&#8217;s reputation by openly declaring that the major Bush administration policy initiative was a complete failure, and that a dollar spent with a multiplier [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://lefarkins.blogspot.com/2008/12/cooking-books.html">davenoon at LG&#038;M</a> and <a href="http://rogerailes.blogspot.com/2008/12/oh-for-book-and-shady-crook.html">Kikuchiyo Jones subbing for the good Roger Ailes</a> both clobbered the <a href="http://sec.online.wsj.com/article/SB123025595706634689.html">WSJ&#8217;s most egregious fluffing this year</a>.</p>
<p>Martin Feldstein continues to try to destroy the <a href="http://www.booksamillion.com/product/9780393329889?id=4304931603686">previously-brilliant</a> David Warsh&#8217;s reputation by <a href="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB123008280526532053.html">openly declaring that the major Bush administration policy initiative was a complete failure</a>, and that a dollar spent with a multiplier of at best 1.0 should be preferred to investments with spillover effects into private industry (and therefore <a href="http://rodrik.typepad.com/dani_rodriks_weblog/2008/12/some-unpleasant-keynesian-arithmetic.html">multipliers definitionally greater than 1.0</a>).</p>
<p>Warsh may never live down <a href="http://www.economicprincipals.com/issues/2008.07.27/328.html">this piece</a>, though economic historians may well find the seeds of the destruction of the discipline outlined therein.</p>
<p>UPDATE: PGL at Econospeak <a href="http://econospeak.blogspot.com/2008/12/feldstein-advocates-surge-in-defense.html">was there first</a>, but is nicer than I am.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, it was left to the WaPo to explain <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/12/24/AR2008122402193_pf.html">Moral Equivalence in the Beltway</a>:<br />
<blockquote>Bill Clinton was sharply criticized for issuing dozens of pardons in his final days that included fugitive financier Marc Rich, while Bush&#8217;s father came under fire for forgiving Caspar Weinberger and others involved in the Iran-contra affair.</p></blockquote>
<p>Yep, a man whose prosecution was viewed by the publisher of the New York Sun as &#8220;<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/12/07/opinion/07lipsky.html?sq=Marc%20Rich&#038;st=cse&#038;scp=4&#038;pagewanted=print">an error and a tragedy</a>&#8221; is at least as evil as actively violating U.S. and international laws while working to support terrorists and destabilize democratic governments.  Glad we got that one straight, guys.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/12/reasons-i-havent-needed-to-post.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
