<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>health insurance reform &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The Age Rating Game</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/the-age-rating-game.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/the-age-rating-game.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2013 12:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Health Insurance]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health insurance reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[intergenerational equity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Maggie Mahar]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/the-age-rating-game.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Maggie Mahar Health Care Blog discusses some of the rhetoric employed in media on how to pay for health insurance. In other words, when costs are distributed over a large group, older adults save more than younger adults lose. Still, many believe that older Boomers can and should pick up the higher tab for their [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://thehealthcareblog.com/blog/2012/08/20/the-age-rating-game-will-older-americans-pay-more-under-health-reforma/">Maggie Mahar</a> Health Care Blog discusses some of the rhetoric employed in media on how to pay for health insurance.</p>
<blockquote><p>In other words, when costs are distributed over a large group, older adults save more than younger adults lose.</p>
<p>Still, many believe that older Boomers can and should pick up the higher tab for their own care. After all, throughout their financial lives, they have been luckier than most: they enjoyed first crack at the employment market when jobs were plentiful, and first dibs on housing when homes were affordable.</p>
<p>&#8230;</p>
<p>Yet in recent years, the economy has not been kind to the rock ‘n roll generation. One in six is now unemployed, and from 2000 to 2011, the average (mean) after-tax income of Americans age 45 to 54 (who are now in their 50s and early 60s) <a href="http://www.advisorperspectives.com/dshort/updates/Household-Incomes-by-Age-Brackets.php">plunged by 13.3 percent</a>.</p>
<p>By that measure, the recession has hit them harder than other age groups except Americans aged 15 to 24. Over those years, this cohort should have been enjoying their peak earning years. But as <a href="http://www.advisorperspectives.com/dshort/charts/census/household-income-age-brackets.html?household-income-age-45-54-mean-real-growth.gif">the chart below reveals</a>, they didn’t.</p>
<p><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-RlS-9tu562Y/UR4aUozDPBI/AAAAAAAABgc/EPUnBjRdAKU/s1600/household-income-by-age-bracket-mean-real.gif" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-RlS-9tu562Y/UR4aUozDPBI/AAAAAAAABgc/EPUnBjRdAKU/s320/household-income-by-age-bracket-mean-real.gif"></a></p>
</blockquote>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />
<blockquote>Yet there’s a trade off: if age rating were abolished, younger adults would be charged more, and some would decide they can’t afford insurance. Bottom line: “the number of uninsured older Americans would be roughly offset by increases in the number of uninsured adults in the two younger age groups (18-34 and 34-44).”</p>
<p>This worries policymakers for two reasons. First, we need young, healthy Americans in the pool to keep insurance costs down. Secondly, if young families decide to forego insurance, many won’t buy separate policies for the children.<br />How do we choose between children and their grandparents?</p>
<p>If we don’t want to ration care, the only rational solution is to bring down the cost by trimming waste in our health care system. This will be difficult. Most of the fat isn’t hanging out on the edges of the steak – it’s marbled throughout in the form of unnecessary treatments and over-priced products. It needs to be removed carefully, with a scalpel. But it can be done.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/the-age-rating-game.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Congressman Ryan’s Health Care Booby Trap</title>
		<link>./../../2012/04/congressman-ryans-health-care-booby-trap.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/04/congressman-ryans-health-care-booby-trap.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 02 Apr 2012 16:18:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[health care law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health insurance reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Michael Halasy]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/04/congressman-ryans-health-care-booby-trap.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Michael Halasy Congressman Ryan’s Health Care Booby Trap Much has been said about “repeal and replace” it has become almost as much a part of GOP lexicon as “drill baby, drill”. The GOP despite having been supportive of the framework for the ACA previously, wants badly to discredit the administration and claim a victory [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Michael Halasy</p>
<p>Congressman Ryan’s Health Care Booby Trap</p>
<p>  Much has been said about “repeal and replace” it has become almost as much a part of GOP lexicon as “drill baby, drill”.  The GOP despite having been supportive of the framework for the ACA previously, wants badly to discredit the administration and claim a victory in the name of “freedom”. Too bad history shows that the Heritage Foundation and VP Stuart Butler supported a plan almost virtually identical to the ACA.</p>
<p>  Now, along comes Congressman Ryan, despite being rebuffed last year for the “Roadmap”, he has come along with a v 2.0. Unfortunately, he is making headway. I won’t comment on the other aspects of the new and improved Roadmap, but it seems to be just as much of a disaster as the previous one. The House has already passed it of course, and Romney, aka etch a sketch, has enthusiastically received the Congressman’s endorsement and has endorsed Ryan’s plan as well.</p>
<p>So we know that the GOP, primarily the Tea Partier’s, despise the individual mandate as a violation of their freedom. Ezra Klein had a great article last week about the hidden mandate in the Ryan bill , but does not discuss the fact that it will <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/ezra-klein/post/there-was-a-reason-conservatives-once-supported-the-individual-mandate/2012/03/30/gIQAiddnlS_blog.html" target="_blank">essentially eliminate employer based insurance</a>. Now, Ryan’s plan assumes that the state based exchanges (sound familiar?) will produce a lot of savings, and he assumes that market forces will do even more. To that end, he offers a couple of tax credits. But, oh by the way, you LOSE employer based coverage under Ryan. It severs it completely. So an individual gets a 2,300 dollar tax credit (family is 5,700) to buy insurance. I can tell you now, that the average per the Kaiser Family Foundation for a single individual is much higher than 2,300. <br /><a name="more"></a><br />Family plan premiums are $15,073 on average, while coverage for single employees is about $5,429.  </p>
<p>Workers contributed an average of $921 toward the premium of single coverage and $4,129 for family plans.   </p>
<p>What this means, is, that under the Ryan plan, your single insurance premium will cost you 2,208 MORE per year out of your own pocket at current cost. Family plans will cost you 5,244 MORE per year out of your own pocket.  </p>
<p>That&#8217;s the repeal and replace plan folks&#8230;..That&#8217;s what the House voted on and passed&#8230;..That&#8217;s what Romney endorsed&#8230;.THAT&#8217;s the GOP plan&#8230;  </p>
<p>It&#8217;ll save businesses money, and it&#8217;s great for corporate America. However, it is not so great for the average small family living on 40-45k per year combined income.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/04/congressman-ryans-health-care-booby-trap.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
