<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Martha Raddatz &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Why Last Night’s Debate Will Really Matter—and, yes, it will. [&#8211; UPDATE: Dana Milbank GETS IT! It’s a start. Hopefully only JUST a start.]</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/why-last-nights-debate-will-really-matter-and-yes-it-will-update-dana-milbank-gets-it-its-a-start-hopefully-only-just-a-start.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/why-last-nights-debate-will-really-matter-and-yes-it-will-update-dana-milbank-gets-it-its-a-start-hopefully-only-just-a-start.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 12 Oct 2012 17:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dana Milbank]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Joe Biden]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Martha Raddatz]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Washington Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/why-last-nights-debate-will-really-matter-and-yes-it-will-update-dana-milbank-gets-it-its-a-start-hopefully-only-just-a-start.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Not surprisingly, the pundits have concluded that, while the debate last night will stop the bleeding for the Dem ticket—stop the momentum for Romney/Ryan—it won’t make a difference beyond that. People don’t vote for the vice presidential candidate; they vote for, or against, a presidential candidate. And anyway, Biden smiled too much!  And Ryan was [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>Not surprisingly, the pundits have concluded that, while the debate last night will stop the bleeding for the Dem ticket—stop the momentum for Romney/Ryan—it won’t make a difference beyond that. People don’t vote for the vice presidential candidate; they vote for, or against, a presidential candidate.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And anyway, Biden smiled too much!  And Ryan was serious and wonkish! 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The problem with that analysis is that Biden was wonkish, too.  And in being wonkish—and in smiling and even laughing at Ryan’s canned claims repeating Romney’s from last week—Biden began the process of pointing the public to the fact that Romney’s biggest hits from last week are based on nonsense.</div>
<div></div>
<div>It is, in other words, the <i>substance</i> of Biden’s performance, rather than the <i>performance</i>stuff that the pundits fixate on, that actually will matter.  In my opinion, one of the most effective moments was Biden’s giving the lie to an important part of the supposed Reagan/Tip O’Neill analogy: that, heading into the negotiations with O’Neill, Reagan didn’t give specifics about what he wanted.  
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Another important moment—moments, actually; he did it two or three times—was Biden’s challenge to the claim that six studies showed that the Romney/Ryan tax math would work.  Biden’s emphatically shaking his head and, yes, smiling and then laughing—he wasn’t able to inject comments, and Raddatz (who impressed me less than she did everyone else) played Lehrer; she asked no questions at all about this—his facial reactions got the message across.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I have two complaints, though.  One is that Biden didn’t point out that the Five Point Plan is actually not a plan at all but instead just a statement of generic goals—as is the claim that it will create 12 million jobs, like magic.  Presumably, Obama will do that at the debate next week, and do so clearly and repeatedly.   
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The other is that Biden didn’t say, much less emphasize, that it mattered for the <i>policy </i>outcome that Reagan was dealing with a Democratic House as well as a Democratic Senate.*  After the election, the House will continue to be controlled by the Tea Party—and, by Romney’s and Ryan’s own account, they’ll let Congress play a big role in drafting legislation.  That is, the House will support the Romney-Ryan administration in trying to force enactment of … the Ryan budget.  Presumably, Obama will do this, too, at the debate next week, and do so clearly and repeatedly.   
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>But Biden succeeded, I’m pretty sure, in raising questions in people’s minds about the forthrightness of Romney’s representations last week (reiterated by Ryan last night) , and the truthfulness of his claims.  Obama might actually pick up the ball from Biden and run with it.  </div>
<div></div>
<div>Could happen!
</p>
<p>&#8212;-</p>
<div>UPDATE: Dana Milbank of the Washington Post <i><a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/dana-milbank-in-vice-presidential-debate-biden-rattles-ryan/2012/10/12/427cd0c0-1430-11e2-be82-c3411b7680a9_story.html?hpid=z3">gets it</a></i>! It’s a start.  Hopefully only <i>just </i>a start. 
</p>
</div>
<div>But &#8230; woo-hooo!</p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />*CORRECTION: The sentence was corrected for the sake of clarity to include the words &#8220;for the <i>policy </i>outcome&#8221;.</div>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/why-last-nights-debate-will-really-matter-and-yes-it-will-update-dana-milbank-gets-it-its-a-start-hopefully-only-just-a-start.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
