<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>econoblogs &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Popularity, influence, and econoblogs&#8230;top 21 includes AB</title>
		<link>./../../2012/11/popularity-influence-and-econoblogs-top-21-includes-ab.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/11/popularity-influence-and-econoblogs-top-21-includes-ab.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 28 Nov 2012 00:22:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[econoblogs]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/11/popularity-influence-and-econoblogs-top-21-includes-ab.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Angry Bear made it to 21st on the list in popularity and influence this time around (I counted). I don&#8217;t really know how they determine this in detail, but next time Mrs. Rdan asks why I spend a lot of time blogging, I&#8217;ll use it. From Onalytica Indexes: ALTERNATIVE ECONOMIC INDICATORS A small number of [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><i>Angry Bear</i> made it to 21st on the list in popularity and influence this time around (I counted). I don&#8217;t really know how they determine this in detail, but next time Mrs. Rdan asks why I spend  a lot of time blogging, I&#8217;ll use it.</p>
<p>From <a href="http://onalyticaindexes.com/2012/11/26/top-200-most-influential-economics-blogs/" target="_blank">Onalytica Indexes: ALTERNATIVE ECONOMIC INDICATORS</a></p>
<blockquote><p>A small number of blogs have a higher rank than before.  Sometimes, such as in the case of The Becker-Posner Blog, the number and quality of citations account for an increased rank. However, most of the blogs that are ranked higher than before have received citations from more influential blogs. This is the case with Angry Bear, a blog that has the same level of Popularity but has more than doubled its Influence in the last months.</p>
<p>In our analysis, the data covers the period May 2011- November 2012.</p></blockquote>
<p>(h/t rjs)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/11/popularity-influence-and-econoblogs-top-21-includes-ab.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Bill McBride, Krugman, and Business Insider</title>
		<link>./../../2012/11/bill-mcbride-krugman-and-business-insider.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/11/bill-mcbride-krugman-and-business-insider.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 24 Nov 2012 20:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Calculated Risk]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[econoblogs]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/11/bill-mcbride-krugman-and-business-insider.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Congratulations Bill. Joe Weisenthal at Business Insider offers some hyperbole in The Genius Who Invented Economics Blogging Reveals How He Got Everything Right And What&#8217;s Coming Next, but also offers well deserved praise for Bill McBride and Calculated Risk.  Paul Krugman in the NYT posts  All Hail Calculated Risk and praises Bill&#8217;s work as well. Bill [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Congratulations Bill.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/bill-mcbride-of-calculated-risk-2012-11" target="_blank">Joe Weisenthal at Business Insider</a> offers some hyperbole in <i>The Genius Who Invented Economics Blogging Reveals How He Got Everything Right And What&#8217;s Coming Next</i>, but also offers well deserved praise for Bill McBride and Calculated Risk.  Paul Krugman in the NYT posts  <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/11/21/all-hail-calculated-risk/" target="_blank">All Hail Calculated Risk</a> and praises Bill&#8217;s work as well. </p>
<p>Bill has a gift for telling an evolving story in graph form that readers can follow over time, such as this one on jobs, and picking data that has held up over time as well as being useful.  (Economist Spencer England praises Bill&#8217;s data in our own <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/09/state-unemployment-rates.html" target="_blank">Employment Situation Reports</a> this year)</p>
<div><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-DgbFoh95Nxk/ULEQOo1pW5I/AAAAAAAABL8/APcf7YNKU1g/s1600/bill.jpg" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="128" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-DgbFoh95Nxk/ULEQOo1pW5I/AAAAAAAABL8/APcf7YNKU1g/s200/bill.jpg" width="200"></a></div>
<p>As Bill makes clear on his website, <a href="http://www.calculatedriskblog.com/p/doris-tanta-dungey.html" target="_blank">Tanta</a> was an important part of Calculated Risk beginnings. (See Ken Houghton&#8217;s note <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2008/12/what-brad-delong-said-rest-in-peace.html" target="_blank">here</a>).</p>
<p>With unabashed enthusiasm I am happy to highlite that Bill was a Bear until moving to his own site full time in late 2005.</p>
<p>Here are some <i><a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/">Angry Bear</a> </i> links posted by CR  from those times.  A bit of fun to color this post with some reflected glory.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2005/07/regulatory-substitute-to-burst-housing.html" target="_blank">A Regulatory Substitute to Burst Housing Bubble?</a> ,  <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2005/05/when-will-housing-slowdown.html" target="_blank">When will housing slowdown</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2005/07/housing-update.html" target="_blank">Housing update</a> ,   <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2005/08/housing-and-recession.html" target="_blank">Housing and recession</a> ,  <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2005/04/after-housing-boom-impact-on-economy.html" target="_blank">After the housing boom impact on the economy</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/11/bill-mcbride-krugman-and-business-insider.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Andrew Sullivan reviews &#034;Red Ink&#034;</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/andrew-sullivan-reviews-red-ink.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/andrew-sullivan-reviews-red-ink.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 29 Jul 2012 12:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[current economic policy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[econoblogs]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/andrew-sullivan-reviews-red-ink.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Andrew Sullivan reviews the book Red Ink. Here are some shocking facts that I learned from “Red Ink: Inside the High-Stakes Politics of the Federal Budget. Where the Trillions Come From, Where They Go, and Why Inaction Imperils Our Future.” An amazing 64 percent of the 4.4 million employees on the federal payroll are either [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.salon.com/2012/07/27/blame_the_republicans/?source=newsletter">Andrew Sullivan</a> reviews the book <i>Red Ink.</i><br />
<blockquote>Here are some shocking facts that I learned from “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/0770436145/?tag=saloncom0820%20">Red Ink: Inside the High-Stakes Politics of the Federal Budget. Where the Trillions Come From, Where They Go, and Why Inaction Imperils Our Future.”</a>
<ul>
<li>An amazing 64 percent of the 4.4 million employees on the federal payroll are either uniformed military personnel or work for Defense, Veterans Affairs and Homeland Security. The U.S. defense budget is “greater than the combined defense budgets of the next 17 largest spenders.” </li>
<li>In 1981 Medicare and Medicaid accounted for 9.5 percent of all federal outlays. Twenty years later, that number had jumped to 25 percent. By 2021, if current trends continue, it will probably hit 31 percent. </li>
<li>“Today, Americans pay less of their income in taxes than citizens of nearly every other developed country.” </li>
<li>“In the early 1950s more than 30 percent of federal revenues came from the corporate income tax — in 2011, 7.9 percent.”</li>
</ul>
<p>“Red Ink” is an extraordinarily useful book. It is exactly what author David Wessel, economics editor for the Wall Street Journal, claims it to be: “a collection of uncomfortable, indisputable facts showing the unsustainable fiscal course the U.S. government is on.”</p></blockquote>
<p>Perhaps asking clearer questions might help?  How does a person ask clearer questions?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/andrew-sullivan-reviews-red-ink.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>&#034;Top X&#034; economics blogs</title>
		<link>./../../2011/05/top-x-economics-blogs.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/05/top-x-economics-blogs.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2011 12:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[econoblogs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[top blogs]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/05/top-x-economics-blogs.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Mike Kimel I recently got an e-mail from a fellow blogger asking me to link a list that blogger made of &#8220;top X&#8221; economics blogs. (And no, I will not link to the list or identify that blogger.) My response: Hi. Umm&#8230;. I looked over your list, and while there are some very good [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by <strong>Mike Kimel</strong></p>
<p>I recently got an e-mail from a fellow blogger asking me to link a list that blogger made of &#8220;top X&#8221; economics blogs.  (And no, I will not link to the list or identify that blogger.)  My response:</p>
<blockquote><p>Hi.  Umm&#8230;.  I looked over your list, and while there are some very good blogs on it, there are also some that frankly, from what I can tell, specialize in peddling misinformation.  By that I do not mean blogs that have a perspective with which I disagree.  I tend not to agree, for example, with the folks at Marginal Revolution on many things, but they produce an excellent blog with well thought out posts and which generally get the facts right.  I myself have listed them as a daily read at Angry Bear and would recommend them to anyone.  </p>
<p>On the other hand, your list contains four blogs that from what I can tell are more likely to state or link to &#8220;facts&#8221; that are not true.  There are also several blogs I do not recognize on the list so it is possible that there are more misinformation peddlers than that on the list.  I am very sorry, but I cannot recommend your list to anybody.  </p>
<p>Apologies.</p>
<p>Mike</p></blockquote>
<p>How should one deal with those that peddle misinformation?  Your thoughts?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/05/top-x-economics-blogs.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
