<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Politics &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 12:45:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Hagel for Defense Secretary</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/hagel-for-defense-secretary.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/hagel-for-defense-secretary.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 08 Jan 2013 20:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[appointments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jazzbumpa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/hagel-for-defense-secretary.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I&#8217;m actually agnostic on this choice.  The always excellent Charles Pierce makes a good case for Hagel, but why should Obama go for any Republican?  This just continues to promote the canard that Republicans are somehow stronger or more capable on defense issues than Democrats. The irony here is that the greatest opposition is coming [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;m actually agnostic on this choice.  The always excellent Charles Pierce <a href="http://www.esquire.com/blogs/politics/chuck-hagel-defense-secretary-nomination-010713?src=soc_fcbks">makes a good case for Hagel</a>,  but why should Obama go for any Republican?  This just continues to  promote the canard that Republicans are somehow stronger or more capable  on defense issues than Democrats.</p>
<p>The irony here is that the greatest opposition is coming from Republicans, some of whom have gone so far as to call him an <a href="http://www.weeklystandard.com/blogs/mr-hagel-and-jews_693993.html">anti-Semite</a>*  because he has <a href="http://www.thedailybeast.com/articles/2013/01/07/why-hagel-matters.html">spoken openly and honestly </a>about  the excessive influence the pro-Israel lobby has on American foreign  policy.   When we consider the pros and cons of any individual for any  position, we ought to do it on the basis of real qualifications and real  disqualifications, not make-believe nonsense put forward by neocons and  the cadre of rabid right-wingers whose policies have done such great  and possibly irreparable damage to the world in this century.<br />  <br />I rarely agree with Mish on anything political, and to find myself <a href="http://globaleconomicanalysis.blogspot.com/2013/01/obamas-chance-to-do-something-right.html">agreeing in principle with him</a> when he&#8217;s <a href="http://www.creators.com/opinion/pat-buchanan/why-the-war-party-fears-hagel.html">agreeing in principle with Patrick Buchanan</a> has my stomach turning and my head spinning.  </p>
<p>Vertigo,  nausea and angular momentum aside, this appointment is the president&#8217;s  decision, and I want to see the debate procede along substantive rather  than ideological, illogical or untruthful  lines.   And I most  particularly don&#8217;t want to see him <a href="http://www.weeklystandard.com/articles/hagel-thesis_666589.html">get Riced</a>.</p>
<p>Now, where do I pick up my pony?</p>
<p>__________________________</p>
<p>* On 1/07 I heard <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elliott_Abrams">Eliot Abrams</a> do exactly that <a href="http://www.npr.org/2013/01/07/168817789/hagel-critic-he-seems-to-have-some-kind-of-problem-with-jews">in an NPR interview</a>.  Abrams was an Iran-Contra cohort of Paul Wolfowitz and Oliver North.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/hagel-for-defense-secretary.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Links Worth Noting: Stealth (Class) Warfare</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/links-worth-noting-stealth-class-warfare.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/links-worth-noting-stealth-class-warfare.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 02 Dec 2012 14:49:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[economic politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linda Beale]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/links-worth-noting-stealth-class-warfare.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Beale Links Worth Noting: Stealth (Class) Warfare(Op-ed) Paul Krugman, Class Wars of 2012, New York Times (Nov. 30, 2012). When Mitt Romney disparaged ordinary Americans, it was visible, obvious, and clearly an indication of the lack of esteem he held for ordinary Americans. The same arrogance is at work in the class warfare [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Linda Beale</p>
<p>Links Worth Noting: Stealth (Class) Warfare<br />(Op-ed)</p>
<p>Paul Krugman, <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/11/30/opinion/krugman-class-wars-of-2012.html">Class Wars of 2012</a>, New York Times (Nov. 30, 2012).</p>
<p>When Mitt Romney disparaged ordinary Americans, it was visible, obvious, and clearly an indication of the lack of esteem he held for ordinary Americans. The same arrogance is at work in the class warfare that the radical right is waging against the social programs that have been partof the great stabilization of the middle class and a singular pathway to a more sustainable lifestyle for those who are underprivileged in America&#8211;Social Security, Medicare, and Medicaid.</p>
<p>The drumbeat for &#8220;fiscal cliff&#8221; worries continues to build in the media. The right wants us to think that they are worried about future generations facing mountains of debt. They aren&#8217;t. The right wants us to think that they are worried that the only way to combat skyrocketing health care costs is by cutting back on benefits for ordinary Americans. They aren&#8217;t, and it isn&#8217;t. The right wants us to think that the wealthy have sacrificed already and are truly noble if they bear even minimal tax increases from the expiration of the Bush tax cuts. They haven&#8217;t and they aren&#8217;t. The right wants the progressives to roll over and play dead, so they can insist that they have the good of the country at heart when they demand cuts to infrastructure spending and cuts to &#8220;entitlements&#8221; as a condition for petty little increases in the taxes of the ultra rich who have greedily sucked up all the juice in the economy for forty years. We won&#8217;t.</p>
<p>Readers may think this blog has become a broken record of arguments for higher taxes&#8211;at least on the wealthy, at least through the removal of the preferential capital gains rate&#8211;and holding firm on protecting Social Security, Medicare, Medicaid. Maybe so. But we must continue to speak out until those we elected to lead the country act like they heard the prevailing sentiment of the election: we want more taxes on the upper class; we want an economy that is stimulated by government spending when private spending won&#8217;t do it; we want a sustainable economy that distributes resources more equitably and not a winner-take-all economy that allows those with monetary power to dictate the lifestyles of the rest of us.</p>
<p>Krugman is, as usual, correct. What they can&#8217;t get by buying an election the rich will try to get by lobbying and pretending to worry about the fiscal cliff. Let them try. Progressives in Congress should start talking, on any available outlet, about &#8220;going over the cliff&#8221; because it really isn&#8217;t so bad. It will free us once and for all of the ridiculous Bush tax cuts and allow us to undertake thinking about the tax code without that &#8220;status quo&#8221; hanging over our head like the sword of Damocles. And we can pass some really decent tax cuts for the lower income quintiles at the first of the year, without having to deal yet again with the &#8220;extenders&#8221; on the table. We can reform corporate tax&#8211;getting rid of loopholes; getting rid of the transfer pricing games&#8211;without lowering rates. And we can deal with the sequester in reasonable ways. What should we spend on and why. Let the rest go. We would finally begin the process of lowering the expectations of the military-industrial complex.</p>
<p>The following are excerpts from Krugman&#8217;s piece.</p>
<blockquote><p>The important thing to understand now is that while the election is over, the class war isn’t. The same people who bet big on Mr. Romney, and lost, are now trying to win by stealth — in the name of fiscal responsibility — the ground they failed to gain in an open election.<br />***<br />Consider, as a prime example, the push to raise the retirement age, the age of eligibility for Medicare, or both. This is only reasonable, we’re told — after all, life expectancy has risen, so shouldn’t we all retire later? In reality, however, it would be a hugely regressive policy change, imposing severe burdens on lower- and middle-income Americans while barely affecting the wealthy. Why? First of all, the increase in life expectancy is concentrated among the affluent; why should janitors have to retire later because lawyers are living longer? Second, both Social Security and Medicare are much more important, relative to income, to less-affluent Americans, so delaying their availability would be a far more severe hit to ordinary families than to the top 1 percent.<br />***<br />[A]ny proposal to avoid a rate increase is, whatever its proponents may say, a proposal that we let the 1 percent off the hook and shift the burden, one way or another, to the middle class or the poor.<br />***<br />The point is that the class war is still on, this time with an added dose of deception. And this, in turn, means that you need to look very closely at any proposals coming from the usual suspects, even — or rather especially — if the proposal is being represented as a bipartisan, common-sense solution. In particular, whenever some deficit-scold group talks about “shared sacrifice,” you need to ask, sacrifice relative to what?<br />***<br />America’s top-down class warriors lost big in the election, but now they’re trying to use the pretense of concern about the deficit to snatch victory from the jaws of defeat. Let’s not let them pull it off.</p></blockquote>
<p>cross posted with <a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2012/11/113012-links-worth-noting-stealth-class-warfare.html" title="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2012/11/113012-links-worth-noting-stealth-class-warfare.html">ataxingmatter</a>   11/30/12</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/links-worth-noting-stealth-class-warfare.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Waldmann’s thoughts on voting districts</title>
		<link>./../../2012/11/waldmanns-thoughts-on-voting-districts.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/11/waldmanns-thoughts-on-voting-districts.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2012 14:36:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[representation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Robert Waldmann]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[voting]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/11/waldmanns-thoughts-on-voting-districts.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Robert Waldmann I think this is the best post I have read so far on the topic by Kathleen Geier.  Just go read it before reading my comment below. Of course I have my usual comments: Thank you Kathleen Geier  for your excellent post based on good shoe leather (OK leather ear to the phone) reporting.  I [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Robert Waldmann</p>
<p>I think this is <a href="http://www.washingtonmonthly.com/political-animal-a/2012_11/why_are_the_democrats_underrep041272.php">the best post I have read so far on the topic</a> by Kathleen Geier.  Just go read it before reading my comment below.</p>
<p>Of course I have my usual comments:</p>
<p>Thank you Kathleen Geier  for your excellent post based on good shoe leather (OK leather ear to the phone) reporting.  I should also thank the political scientists who have been doing their job while I pretend to do it commenting on blogs (I&#8217;m supposed to be an economist).</p>
<p>But (of course there is a but) in those comments I have been stressing that bipartisan and court-drawn maps systematically cause Republicans to win a larger fraction of seats than votes.  The reason is that a bipartisan and court (except sometimes the Supremes) principal is that the House should look like the country and not like the White plus some brown and no black at all Senate.  There is an absolutely deliberate effort to create majority minority districts.  Those districts are overwhelmingly Democratic districts.  The intent isn&#8217;t partisan, but the effect is to cause Republicans to be over represented.  I add that I support the effort to make the House look like the country and not like the Senate.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Also, while I see why incumbency helps the party with more seats I do not at all find an explanation for why it explains the gap between popular vote and seats won.  The advantages of incumbency discussed in the post should cause the party with more incumbents to get more votes, yet they are discussed as if they affect seats won but not vote totals.  To explain the gap, one has to argue that incumbents generally win by narrow margins or lose by wide margins.    <br />Here I think the problem may be with the reported vote totals.  Some states don&#8217;t report votes in races where there is only one candidate on the ballot.  Incumbents often get on the order of 99% of votes or more.  That&#8217;s a lot of wasted votes which would cause the party of incumbents to have a lot of votes per seat won.  But only if they are counted.</p>
<p>Even if the votes are counted, they may be few.  Some people (definitely including me) are irritated when invited to vote for the only candidate on the ballot (if I wanted to live in the USSR I would have moved there back when it existed).  For decades I chose Michael Capuano over write in, but I&#8217;m sure lots of other people left the oval empty out of irritation (this year I actually got to vote in a contested congressional election for the first time since hmmm voting for O&#8217;Neill over Abt in 1982 IIRC).  I think some correction for races with only one candidate on the ballot is needed.</p>
<p>Finally I don&#8217;t get this bit about fewer people in red districts.  What geographic boundaries are being considered ?  I can see how the requirement that each state have 1 representative could in theory create a small population at large district.  However, I think it doesn&#8217;t as even Wyoming is not an unusually small district.  I don&#8217;t see why representation of low population states would be rounded up more often than down.  If the boundaries are, say, county boundaries, then current redistricting does not respect them (I vote in the same county and a different district).  I tend to suspect that the random districting which respects geographic boundaries doesn&#8217;t correspond to anything but a silly modeling assumption.<br />    <br />Polite conclusion about how this is a great post and political scientists are awesome.</p>
<p>cross posted with   <a href="http://rjwaldmann.blogspot.com/2012/11/how-did-republicans-win-house-with-less.html">Robert&#8217;s Stochastic Thoughts</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/11/waldmanns-thoughts-on-voting-districts.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>One Nation, Divisible</title>
		<link>./../../2012/11/one-nation-divisible.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/11/one-nation-divisible.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Nov 2012 18:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2012 Presidential elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jazzbumpa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/11/one-nation-divisible.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[We are a country not just divided, but fragmented along axes of race, age, religion, economic status and geography.  There are now 15 States where citizens have filed petitions to secede from the Union.  &#8220;These include Louisiana (which led the charge), the Republic of Texas, Kentucky, Colorado, New Jersey, Montana, North Dakota, Indiana, Mississippi, North [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We are a country not just divided, but fragmented along axes of race,  age, religion, economic status and geography.  There are now 15 States  where citizens have filed petitions <a href="http://m.now.msn.com/15-states-start-petitons-to-leave-the-usa">to secede from the Union</a>.  &#8220;<i>These  include Louisiana (which led the charge), the Republic of Texas,  Kentucky, Colorado, New Jersey, Montana, North Dakota, Indiana,  Mississippi, North Carolina, Alabama, Florida, Georgia and Oregon</i>.&#8221;  I don&#8217;t know which is number 15, but I&#8217;m gong to guess Oklahoma.  </p>
<p>I&#8217;m  not going to get flip about it.  While these petitions have virtually  no chance of achieving anything, it&#8217;s important to remember two things:</p>
<p>1)  You never hear anything like this when Republicans win.<br />2)  All but 4 of these states represent the (since 1965) <a href="http://elections.huffingtonpost.com/2012/results/">solid Republican South</a>.</p>
<p>Another  geographic dimension is urban vs rural.  When I do get flip, I say  Obama won everywhere that people outnumber cattle, deer, goats or  alligators.  This comes distressingly close to being the truth.  Look at  the electoral map of just about any State.  I like to consider Ohio,  since it is my home State and in many ways represents the U.S. in  miniature.  But pick a State at random [or Texas in particular] and  you&#8217;ll probably see the same scenario.   The <a href="http://elections.huffingtonpost.com/2012/results/ohio">Ohio electoral map</a> shows that Obama carried 16 of Ohio&#8217;s 88 counties.  Half of these are  strung along the Lake Erie shore, four more are contiguous in the  densely populated north-east corner, and the other four contain  Columbus, Dayton, Cincinnati and Athens.</p>
<p>I&#8217;m not  ambitious enough to undertake the study, but I&#8217;ll hypothesize that  Obama&#8217;s vote percentage in each county is directly proportional to the  total population &#8211; and this in a State where the counties don&#8217;t vary  much in physical size.  Consider that Lucas Co. [essentially my home  town, Toledo] with 198,000 votes cast went for Obama by 64 to 34%, while  Mercer Co. along the IN border with 21,000 votes cast went for Romney  by 77 to 22%.  You can find these kinds of results all over the country.</p>
<p>Another divide is along <a href="http://forums.gardenweb.com/forums/load/hottopics/msg1209375230522.html">education level</a>.   Among the 15 States with the best public school systems, Obama carried  13, while among the 15 States with the worst public school systems,  Romney carried 12.  I see this as a big component in the recent  Republican war on education.  One thing you develop as a result of good  education is a set of critical thinking skills, which then give you the  ability to see through nonsense peddlers like Rush, Trump, and the whole  Fox roster.</p>
<p>All of this tends to make me pessimistic  about our nations future.  But I see rays of hope amidst the great  divide.  Even in Georgia, which went 53 to 45% for Romney, you find  Obama winning by huge margins in Atlanta, Macon, Augusta, Columbus,  Savannah, and Albany.</p>
<p>Plus, another thing is happening that you have to see a <a href="http://blu.stb.s-msn.com/i/9E/7C97D308B1C896D58FC9AAEEB71D_h231_w308_m4_cZXQyhRYy.jpg">country-wide county level electoral map</a> to notice.</p>
<div><a href="http://blu.stb.s-msn.com/i/9E/7C97D308B1C896D58FC9AAEEB71D_h231_w308_m4_cZXQyhRYy.jpg"><img border="0" height="300" src="http://blu.stb.s-msn.com/i/9E/7C97D308B1C896D58FC9AAEEB71D_h231_w308_m4_cZXQyhRYy.jpg" width="400"></a></div>
<p>There  is a blue streak that starts along the Mississippi river valley where  Arkansas, Louisiana and Mississippi converge and runs almost  continuously through Alabama, Georgia and the Carolinas to join with the  blue States along the coast.</p>
<p>I call it the band of  sanity running through the South, and it might just represent an  opportunity for progressives to build on going forward.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/11/one-nation-divisible.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Strategic Lying as Political Art</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/strategic-lying-as-political-art.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/strategic-lying-as-political-art.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2012 03:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2012 Presidential elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[debates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jazzbumpa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romeny]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Republican]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/strategic-lying-as-political-art.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[If you listen to Randi Rhodes, you know she is still livid over Romney being declared the &#8220;winner&#8221; in last week&#8217;s &#8211; we&#8217;ll call it a &#8220;debate&#8221; for the nonce. Alas, though, the reason he won is that poll numbers have moved in his favor.  Whether that bounce is robust remains to be seen.  But [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you listen to Randi Rhodes, you know she is still livid over Romney being declared the &#8220;<i>winner</i>&#8221; in last week&#8217;s &#8211; we&#8217;ll call it a &#8220;debate&#8221; for the nonce.</p>
<p>Alas, though, the reason he won is that <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2012/oct/08/romney-gains-lead-obama-poll">poll numbers have moved in his favor</a>.  Whether that bounce is robust remains to be seen.  But it did gain Romney some sort of advantage, at least in the near term.</p>
<p>Randi&#8217;s  objection is that Romney lied, repeatedly, and about almost  everything.  In the process, he flatly repudiated some of the major  planks in his platform &#8211; the destruction of Medicare as we know it, the  $5 Trillion dollar tax cut, the reduction of tax share paid by high  income people, and an insurance plan not covering pre-existing  conditions stand out in that regard.   And these are but a few of the <a href="http://thinkprogress.org/politics/2012/10/04/958801/at-last-nights-debate-romney-told-27-myths-in-38-minutes/">27  debate lies that can easily be recognized and refuted</a>.</p>
<p>Indeed,  the one rare moment of lucid candor came when he eagerly, gleefully  announced that he would send Big Bird to the unemployment line in order  to avoid borrowing money from China.  Big NPR whoop!  To put this in  perspective, for CY 2012, the Federal Government, via the Corp. for  Public Broadcasting, is contributing $26.65 million in support of PBS,  or 0.0007% of total Federal expenditures ($3.77 Trillion) for 2012.     In fact, the entire Federal contribution to CPB is $445.2 million, or  0.0118% of total expenditures. That&#8217;s sure going to help balance $5  Trillion in tax cuts over ten years. (CPB data from <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corporation_for_Public_Broadcasting#Funding_of_and_by_the_corporation">Wikipedia</a>, current expenditure data from the <a href="http://research.stlouisfed.org/fred2/series/FGEXPND">St. Louis Fed</a>.)   Romney isn&#8217;t lying about our creditor position with China, but he was certainly misleading.  According to <a href="http://www.foxnews.com/politics/2012/09/04/who-do-owe-most-that-16-trillion-to-hint-it-isnt-china/">Fox News</a> (!) &#8220;<i>China, it turns out, holds less than 8 percent of the money our government has borrowed over the years</i>.&#8221;</p>
<p>OK,  I get where Randi is coming from &#8211; to have a totally unprincipled  opportunist in charge of running the world&#8217;s greatest super power is not  a recipe for any kind of enduring success, either for the U.S.A.  specifically, or for the world at large.  There are many historical  examples one could cite, but we really needn&#8217;t go back any further than  the &#8220;compassionate conservatism&#8221; of unprosecuted war criminal and  would-be social security privatizer George W. Bush to make the point.</p>
<p>But  what Randi refuses to acknowledge is that what we witnessed last week  was not a debate, by any recognizable definition of the term.  Lying  will get you disqualified in a real debate &#8211; right?  This was <i>political theater</i> &#8211; and what is theater but staged fiction?  </p>
<p>And there is nothing unusual here.  I&#8217;ve been saying for years that <a href="http://jazzbumpa.blogspot.com/2010/04/you-cant-fool-all-of-kentucky-all-of.html">all Republicans do is lie</a>, and then lie about their lies. (I might have gotten that phrase from Randi &#8211; the memory is foggy.)  Here is a four-year-old exposé of some of Romney&#8217;s shape shifting.  (H/T to <a href="http://www.lawyersgunsmoneyblog.com/2012/10/catch-this-guy-on-the-right-day-and-hes-che-frickin-guevara">Dave Brockington at LGM</a>.)</p>
<p>A more insidious kind of lie is simply denying  reality, as characterized by birtherism, New Deal and global warming  denialism, and Friday&#8217;s epidemic of <a href="http://m.apnews.com/ap/db_289563/contentdetail.htm?contentguid=dkjMKAA6">conspiracy theories surrounding the latest favorable jobs report</a>.   But I digress.</p>
<p>Here is my point.  <a href="http://delong.typepad.com/sdj/2012/10/george-hw-bush-press-secretary-in-1984-lying-during-debates-is-a-republican-strategy.html">Brad Delong points</a> us to a 1984 Fay Joyce  article in the N. Y. Times uncovered by <a href="http://delong.typepad.com/sdj/2012/10/george-hw-bush-press-secretary-in-1984-lying-during-debates-is-a-republican-strategy.html">Michael Moore</a>.   It turns out that lying during a debate is a time honored Republican  strategy.  Even 28 years ago, when there was some chance of the main  stream media doing actual journalism, they were confident in their lying  strategy.</p>
<blockquote><p>The Republicans are unabashed in their discussion of their ability to use the television medium. &#8220;You can say anything you want during a debate and 80 million  people hear it,&#8221; observed Peter Teeley, press secretary to Vice  President Bush. If reporters then document that a candidate spoke  untruthfully, &#8221;so what?&#8221; </p>
<p> &#8221;Maybe 200 people read it or 2,000 or 20,000,&#8221; he said.</p></blockquote>
<p>Now,  they have honed it into an art form.  And it&#8217;s worth remembering the  one reason that always accounts for every person&#8217;s lie: their agenda is  not compatible with the truth.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/strategic-lying-as-political-art.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>More on Michigan Voting</title>
		<link>./../../2012/03/more-on-michigan-voting.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/03/more-on-michigan-voting.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2012 14:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[jazzbumpa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[winners and losers]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/03/more-on-michigan-voting.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The U.S. Election Atlas shows the Michigan county by county results for the general election in 2008.  Note that they have inexplicably reversed the normal Red-Blue color coding.   Contrast those results with the 2012 Republican primary results. In the Lower Peninsula, the counties that went for Romney in a big way generally went for Obama [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The U.S. Election Atlas shows the <a href="http://uselectionatlas.org/RESULTS/state.php?f=0&#038;fips=26&#038;year=2008">Michigan county by county results for the general election in 2008</a>.  Note that they have inexplicably reversed the normal Red-Blue color coding.   Contrast those results with the 2012 <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/02/28/map-michigan-primary-2012-results_n_1307981.html?ncid=edlinkusaolp00000009">Republican primary results</a>.</p>
<p>In the Lower Peninsula, the counties that went for Romney in a big way generally went for Obama in a big way in 2008.  Wealthy, densely populated Oakland county went for Obama  by 56% to 42% (660,000 total votes.)  Romney crushed Santorum there by  50% to 29%. (116,000 total votes.) Romney tended to win the counties  that were close between Obama and McCain four years ago.   Along the  west coast, though, many counties that were solidly in Obama&#8217;s camp in  2008 went overwhelmingly for Santorum in the Republican primary.  But  these counties had big margins on Tuesday with small turnouts.</p>
<p>Commenter CSH <a href="http://plainblogaboutpolitics.blogspot.com/2012/02/romney-wins-two.html">at Johnathon Bernstein&#8217;s blog</a> remarked, &#8220;I can&#8217;t recall  seeing the rich-poor, East-West gap in that state as strongly  represented as last night.&#8221;  CSH also pointed out that Romney won the  State by 32,000 votes.  Coincidentally, he won Oakland County by 32,000  votes.  The rest of the State was a wash.</p>
<p>The Upper Peninsula as always, has its own different  story.  Santorum carried all but two counties, and generally by large  margins, while the the &#8217;08 vote was split among counties between Obama  and McCain.  The primary was closest in the eastern section of the U.P.,  which McCain carried in &#8217;08.  But vote counts in the U.P. on Tuesday  were very sparse &#8211; in the range of a few hundred to about 3,000 total,  per county.  </p>
<p>It&#8217;s far from one-to-one, but Romney&#8217;s  results vs Santorum more or less parallel Obama&#8217;s results vs. McCain  four years ago.  Romney&#8217;s best showings were in places where he has  virtually no chance in the general election.  Santorum&#8217;s best showings  were in less populated areas that are likely to vote Republican,  regardless. </p>
<p>The other significant factor is voter  turnout.  Romney and Santorum together collected 787,420 votes,  Statewide.  In 2008, McCain got over <strike>20</strike> 2 million votes in Michigan, and  lost the State by 16%.</p>
<p>Despite the hype, the  stark differences between the two front runners, and Romney&#8217;s alleged  home field advantage, the total turnout was less than half of McCain&#8217;s votes in &#8217;08 this looks <strike>like a lot of</strike> less Republican apathy than I first thought, but still a significant lack of interest.  Can that bode well for their prospects in November?  (Corrections made in last 2 paragraphs.) </p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/03/more-on-michigan-voting.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Michigan Primary Results</title>
		<link>./../../2012/02/michigan-primary-results.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/02/michigan-primary-results.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 29 Feb 2012 16:49:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[jazzbumpa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[winners and losers]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/02/michigan-primary-results.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Mitt Romney won the Michigan Republican primary yesterday by a margin of 41.1% to 37.9%, the remainder going to the rest of the overpopulated field &#8211; Herman Cain, Jon Huntsman and others were on the ballot. Romney and Santorum each gained 11 delegates. This Huffpo article has an interactive map showing results by county. The [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Mitt Romney won the Michigan Republican primary yesterday by a margin of 41.1% to 37.9%, the remainder going to the rest of the overpopulated field &#8211; Herman Cain, Jon Huntsman and others were on the ballot.  Romney and Santorum each gained 11 delegates.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/02/28/map-michigan-primary-2012-results_n_1307981.html?ncid=edlinkusaolp00000009">This Huffpo article</a> has an interactive map showing results by county.</p>
<p>The spread in the results is interesting.  Along the west coast of the Lower Peninsula is Michigan&#8217;s bible belt.  Santorum carried most of those counties by Margins of 10 to 20%.  Kent county, which contains the city of Grand Rapids, it the exception.  Santorum won that county by only 42.4% to 40.3%.  This illustrates the other part of the Michigan dynamic.  Romney did better in urban areas, while Santorum did better in places where cows or deer outnumber the people. Santorum won many more counties, but lost the total vote count.</p>
<p>This population effect shows up in the victory margins of the counties that Romney won.  In the 5 by 2 band of counties that Romney won in the southern part of the state, Romney&#8217;s take generally decreases while Santorum&#8217;s generally increases as you move west.  Then, when you reach the bible belt, it flips to Santorum.  Along the Ohio border is a band of sparsely populated counties that Santorum swept.  Monroe, Lenawee and Branch counties have towns of significant size in them, and in those counties Romney did better by a couple of percentage points.</p>
<p>Ron Paul got between 10 and 12% of the vote almost everywhere. This illustrates something about the modern Republican party.  It is an unholy alliance of far-right Christian fundamentalists, pro-business (pseudo-fiscal) conservatives and libertarians &#8211; and the cracks are starting to show.  If nothing else, the endless campaign of Republican debates has cast these differences into bold relief.</p>
<p>Logically, the fundamentalists and libertarians should hold each other in contempt.  The libertarians and the pro-business faction can agree on many things, but not isolationism and the gold standard.  To the business crowd, the fundamentalists are prey.</p>
<p>For decades, the Republicans have drawn the religious right into their fold with emotional hot button issues that have very little actual relevance, like abortion and gay marriage.  The recent campaign against birth control has been an over-reach that is finally causing a back-lash.</p>
<p> In my dreams, the Republican party tears itself apart, and becomes a marginalized political minority.  The Michigan results give me hope that this dream might become reality.</p>
<p>H/T to my lovely wife.</p>
<p>Cross posted at <a href="http://jazzbumpa.blogspot.com/2012/02/michigan-primary-results.html">Retirement Blues</a>. <br /><a name="more"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/02/michigan-primary-results.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Ron Paul Challenges Liberals &#8211; or Maybe Not</title>
		<link>./../../2012/01/ron-paul-challenges-liberals-or-maybe-not.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/01/ron-paul-challenges-liberals-or-maybe-not.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2012 17:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[jazzbumpa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[libertarian]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[pseudoliberals]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ron Paul]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/01/ron-paul-challenges-liberals-or-maybe-not.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Matt Stoller, the former Senior Policy Advisor to Rep. Alan Grayson and a fellow at the Roosevelt Institute has a couple of very interesting articles posted at Naked Capitalism,  Why Ron Paul Challenges Liberals, and the follow-up, Naked Capitalism, “A Home for All Sorts of Bircher Nonsense” These are thought-provoking, in many ways insightful, and [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Matt Stoller, the former Senior Policy Advisor to Rep. Alan Grayson  and a fellow at the Roosevelt Institute has a couple of very interesting  articles posted at Naked Capitalism,  <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2011/12/matt-stoller-why-ron-paul-challenges-liberals.html">Why Ron Paul Challenges Liberals</a>, and the follow-up, <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/01/naked-capitalism-a-home-for-all-sorts-of-bircher-nonsense.html">Naked Capitalism, “A Home for All Sorts of Bircher Nonsense”</a></p>
<p>These  are thought-provoking, in many ways insightful, and strike me as  required reading, for a variety of reasons, including some valuable  historical insights.  However, one thought they provoke from me is that  the main thesis is spectacularly wrong-headed.  Stollar talks about what  a great ally Paul&#8217;s staff was, when working on certain issues.  I  should say, &#8220;when working <i>against</i> certain issues&#8221; or  things, like war and the unfettered evil workings of the Federal  Reserve.  The correct vocabulary is worth emphasizing.  Liberals and  Libertarians may find common ground in what they are against, but it is  quite unlikely that they will ever find anything substantial that they  both are for.</p>
<p>Stollar goes on to point out what he calls &#8220;<i>a big problem</i>&#8221;  with liberalism.  This is the mixture of two elements, support for  federal power and the anti-war sentiment that arose with Viet Nam and  has continued though today.  In the same paragraph, Stollar says, &#8220;<i>Liberalism doesn’t really exist much within the Democratic Party so much anymore.</i>&#8221;   This is an important thought, but he doesn&#8217;t pursue it, and as he goes  on seems to conflate Democrats with Liberals, as suits his convenience.   In the final paragraph of the first post he refers to: &#8220;<i>a completely hollow liberal intellectual apparatus arguing for  increasing the power of corporations through the Federal government to  enact their agenda.</i>&#8221;  Seriously, WTF?  I have absolutely no idea what the hell that is supposed to mean.</p>
<p>The second article is especially weak, and essentially devoid of any intellectual content.  Stollar decides to &#8220;<i>highlight a few of the reactions here without much of a rebuttal.</i>&#8221;   Why would anyone do that?  Does he believe the reactions are  self-refuting?   Is he too lazy to rebut, or does he simply not have a  good rebuttal?<br /><a name="more"></a><br />At least he clearly sets forth the thesis of the first article:  &#8220;<i>that the same financing structures that are used to  finance mass industrial warfare were used to create a liberal national  economy and social safety.</i>&#8221;   Here is the source of Stollar&#8217;s  alleged intra-liberal conflict, that Paul is somehow supposed to  illuminate and inform.  Though Stollar says: &#8220;<i>I’ll be describing in much more detail the shifting of the social  contract underlying this failure, which has nothing to do with Ron Paul  and would exist with or without him</i>.&#8221;  So referencing Paul in the first place was a bit of a red herring.</p>
<p>He then goes on to provide extended quotes from posts by <a href="http://digbysblog.blogspot.com/2012/01/no-stoller-and-sullivan-there-is-no.html">David Atkins</a>, who he describes as &#8220;<i>wrestling with what liberalism is</i>&#8221; and <a href="http://digbysblog.blogspot.com/2012/01/on-coherent-liberalism.html">Digby</a>, who he simply rejects out of hand, though with a lot of words that don&#8217;t quite reach the level of snark</p>
<p>What Stollar describes as &#8220;<i>contradictions within modern liberalism</i>&#8221;   boils down to liberalism needing big government to be interventionist,  as Atkins demonstrates, but not imperialistic.  But this is a totally  coherent position. The problem lies not with progressive liberalism, but  with the practical realities of managing a power system &#8211; which is what  governemnt is &#8211; in a way that advances the common good, while holding  the drive for imperialistic and domestic domination in check.  This is  going to be a central practical problem with any governing system or  political philosophy &#8211; at least for one that takes seriously the idea of  advancing the common good.  To say it is the problem of liberalism is  to ignore human nature, political reality, and the entirety of history.</p>
<p>Thus,  a liberal can hold the positions that American involvement in WW II was  necessary, but that our involvement in Viet Nam was not.  Ditto Kosovo,  vis-a-vis Iraq.   One can also recognize that the only entity with  enough heft to balance the power of trans-national mega-corporations is  government, but Stollar does not choose to give that any consideration.</p>
<p>Stollar concludes: &#8220;<i>As the New Deal era model sheds the last trappings of anything  resembling social justice or equity for what used to be called the  middle class (a process which Tom Ferguson has been relentlessly  documenting since the early 1980s), the breakdown will become impossible  to ignore.  You can already see how flimsy the arguments are, from the  partisans.</i>&#8220;</p>
<p>I don&#8217;t know how one gets from the  systematic dismantling of the New Deal by successive Republican  administrations (and you can include both Clinton and Obama in this  list) to the New Deal model shedding anything at all.  And, no, I can&#8217;t  see how flimsy liberal partisan arguments have anything to do with an  assault on the middle class that has taken place from the right.</p>
<p>Stollar  has constructed a straw man problem.  Which is a shame, since there are  real problems to be dealt with.  One is the growth of right wing  populism, as exemplified by the Tea Party &#8211; at least to the extent that  is is real, and not a Fox News fabrication.  Another is to harness the  energy of the Occupy Movements, which provide some evidence that there  is progressive populism that could be a source of real political  strength.  Most critically, though, as things stand now, there is no  political left in this country with any actual power.  </p>
<p><a href="http://coreyrobin.com/2012/01/03/ron-paul-has-two-problems-one-is-his-the-other-is-ours/">Corey Robin describes</a> the central problem of American liberalism in the 21st Century, and closes the loop back to Stollar&#8217;s Ron Paul idea like this.</p>
<div><i>Our problem—and again by “our” I mean a left that’s social democratic  (or welfare state liberal or economically progressive or whatever the  hell you want to call it) and anti-imperial—is that we don’t really have  a vigorous national spokesperson for the issues of war and peace, an  end to empire, a challenge to Israel, and so forth, that Paul has in  fact been articulating.  The source of Paul’s positions on these issues  are not the same as ours (again more reason not to give him our  support).  But he is talking about these issues, often in surprisingly  blunt and challenging terms. Would that we had someone on our side who  could make the case against an American empire, or American supremacy,  in such a pungent way.</i></div>
<p>Digging a level  deeper, the reason we don&#8217;t have such a spokesperson is that our  political system is essentially owned by corporate interests, which is  why we get alleged liberals like Clinton and Obama in Democratic  leadership, while genuine progressives like Bernie Sanders, Dennis  Kucinich, and even Alan Grayson are marginalized.  On top of this, the  right has a vigorous and powerful propaganda machine &#8211; hence the Tea  Party; and the small number of progressive voices in broadcast media is  nowhere close to providing a balance.</p>
<p>Money owns  politics, and corporate interests, along with a small entrenched elite,  own the vast majority of the money.  The key to achieving progressive  solutions is to get the money out of politics.  But in the wake of  Citizens United, that prospect is a forlorn hope.  That is my &#8220;<i>coherent structural critique of the American political order</i>&#8221; in one short paragraph.</p>
<p>Cross posted at <a href="http://www.jazzbumpa.blogspot.com/2012/01/ron-paul-challenges-liberals-or-maybe.html">Retirement Blues</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/01/ron-paul-challenges-liberals-or-maybe-not.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Graph That Explains Everything About Amity Shlaes</title>
		<link>./../../2011/10/graph-that-explains-everything-about-amity-shlaes.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/10/graph-that-explains-everything-about-amity-shlaes.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2011 14:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Amity Shlaes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bad economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Great Depression]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linda Beale]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/10/graph-that-explains-everything-about-amity-shlaes.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Mike Kimel Thanks to Linda Beale, I headed over here: The George W. Bush Institute announced today that Amity Shlaes has been named director of the 4% Growth Project, a key part of the Institute’s focus on economic growth. Miss Shlaes will open the project&#8217;s office in New York. The aim of the project [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by <strong><a href="http://presimetrics.com/">Mike Kimel</a></strong></p>
<p>Thanks to <a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2011/10/steve-rattners-and-amity-shlaes-w-style-economic-policy-.html">Linda Beale</a>, I headed over <a href="http://www.bushcenter.com/downloads/pressReleases/Amity_Schlaes_Press_Release.pdf">here</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>The George W. Bush Institute announced today that Amity Shlaes has been named director of the 4% Growth Project, a key part of the Institute’s focus on economic growth. Miss Shlaes will open the project&#8217;s office in New York. The aim of the project is to illuminate ideas and reforms that can yield faster, higher quality growth in the United States, and to underscore the importance of growth in America&#8217;s future. Part of that work involves finding ways to make growth and economics generally accessible to more Americans, especially younger Americans. The program will conduct and sponsor research on all aspects of economic growth, host conferences, as well as partner with other institutions in such endeavors.</p></blockquote>
<p>The following graph, I think, illustrates you need to know about Amity Shlaes:
<p><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-yMzB1D3FDDc/Tp2LNdVRysI/AAAAAAAAAnY/uiVEyy820Rs/s1600/Figure%2B1.jpg"><img src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-yMzB1D3FDDc/Tp2LNdVRysI/AAAAAAAAAnY/uiVEyy820Rs/s320/Figure%2B1.jpg" border="0" alt=""></a></p>
<p>OK.  I lied.  The graph is actually missing something.  See, we only have <a href="http://www.bea.gov/national/xls/gdplev.xls">official data going back to 1929</a>.  And the Great Depression began very, very early in Hoover&#8217;s term.  And Hoover had been a cabinet secretary under Coolidge, and ran for office under a platform which essentially called for continuing Coolidge&#8217;s policies. And Shlaes&#8217; forthcoming book is in praise of Calvin Coolidge.  It should be noted that the economy was in recession during over 38% of the months in which Coolidge took office, which makes much of the Coolidge era a dry run (so to speak) for the monster that would come in 1929.</p>
<p>Put another way&#8230;  Shlaes is part of a movement to praise policies responsible for a lousy economy culminating in the Great Depression (i.e., those of Coolidge and Hoover).  Shlaes is also part of a movement to praise the policies responsible for a lousy economy culminating in the start of the Great Recession and the mess we&#8217;re in today.  (Yes, the Great Recession started in 2007, and no, Obama hasn&#8217;t made any substantial changes on taxes or regulation from the way GW Bush ran the country.)  Conversely, Shlaes is a well-known critic of the policies that produced the fastest period of peace time economic growth this country has seen.</p>
<p>To me this feature of economics is kind of odd.  For some reason, policies that have failed spectacularly over and over continue to have adherents.  Policies that have worked spectacularly have critics.   Debating the merits of a cavalry charge into the teeth of an armored column was barely excusable in August of 1939, but at least that debate was put to a rest by the German blitzkrieg.  Its been generations since anyone argued that horsemen can go toe to toe with tanks.</p>
<p>Which leads me to a hypothetical.  Say we lived in a parallel universe where Shlaes was a quisling, a real villain whose goal was to harm this country as much as she could by convincing the nation to commit economic suicide.  How would the graph above and the two paragraphs that followed it look any different?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/10/graph-that-explains-everything-about-amity-shlaes.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Why Are You Out There?</title>
		<link>./../../2011/10/why-are-you-out-there.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/10/why-are-you-out-there.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2011 17:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[fraud]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jobless recovery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[populism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[risk management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[solvency crisis]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/10/why-are-you-out-there.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[When someone attempts to impede democracy actions are good things: Writer and naturalist Henry David Thoreau was once locked up for refusing to pay a poll tax. He opposed the tax on moral grounds – in a democracy, he argued, a man shouldn’t have to pay to vote&#8230;. That night, so the story goes, Thoreau [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When someone attempts to impede democracy <a href="http://bentleyvillepresbyterian.com/2011/03/27/march-27-2011-john-831-47-the-truth/">actions are good things</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>Writer and naturalist Henry David Thoreau was once locked up for refusing to pay a poll tax.  He opposed the tax on moral grounds – in a democracy, he argued, a man shouldn’t have to pay to vote&#8230;.</p>
<p>That night, so the story goes, Thoreau looked up from his jail cell to see Ralph Waldo Emerson&#8230;standing outside.  Emerson looked at him and asked, &#8220;Henry, why are you in there?&#8221;  Thoreau fired right back: &#8220;Ralph, why are you out there?&#8221;&#8230;</p>
<p>The man outside the bars may be every bit as much a prisoner as the one inside.  Or even more so, if his so-called freedom is built on a foundation of denial and lies.</p>
<p>Now, Thoreau was anything but a Christian.  That particular idea, though, was downright Biblical.  It’s more or less what Jesus is getting at [in John 8:31-47].  Jesus is comparing two kinds of freedom: the outward kind, built on a foundation of happy lies and outright denial, which in the end turns out to be just another kind of slavery; and the inward kind, which comes from a clean conscience before God, and can never be taken away.</p></blockquote>
<p>Far be it for me to cite The Sequel; I&#8217;ll take Bentleyville&#8217;s current Presbyterian minister* at his word. And tell anyone who happens to be <a href="http://occupywallst.org/">in the area of One Liberty Plaza</a> this afternoon to say &#8220;hello.&#8221;</p>
<p>*Full disclosure: one of the previous Ministers is an ex-roommate of mine.  That said, the above was found from a Google search, purely a fortuitous coincidence. At least as far as I know.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/10/why-are-you-out-there.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
