<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Robert Reich &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Looking Beyond Election Day</title>
		<link>./../../2011/11/looking-beyond-election-day.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/11/looking-beyond-election-day.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 27 Nov 2011 23:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2012 Presidential elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[comparing presidents]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[econnomic growth]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Job creation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Robert Reich]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/11/looking-beyond-election-day.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[NYT Robert Reich calls our attention to post election 2012 life and political realities: Looking Beyond Election Day By Robert Reich, Robert Reich&#8217;s Blog Most political analysis of America’s awful economy focuses on whether it will doom President Obama’s reelection or cause Congress to turn toward one party or the other. These are important questions, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>NYT Robert Reich calls our attention to post election 2012 life and political realities:</p>
<p><a target="_blank" href="http://www.robertreich.org/">Looking Beyond Election Day</a>
<p>By Robert Reich, Robert Reich&#8217;s Blog</p>
<blockquote><p>Most political analysis of America’s awful economy focuses on whether it will doom President Obama’s reelection or cause Congress to turn toward one party or the other. These are important questions, but we should really be looking at the deeper problems with which whoever wins in 2012 will have to deal.
</p>
<p>Not to depress you, but our economic troubles are likely to continue for many years &#8211; a decade or more. At the current rate of job growth (averaging 90,000 new jobs per month over the last six months), 14 million Americans will remain permanently unemployed. The consensus estimate is that <a href="http://www.epi.org/publication/rate-job-growth-unemployment-rate-stay-disastrously/">at least 90,000 new jobs are needed just to keep up with the growth of the labor force</a>. Even if we get back to a normal rate of 200,000 new jobs per month, unemployment will stay high for at least ten years. Years of high unemployment will likely result in a vicious cycle, as relatively lower spending by the middle-class further slows job growth.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/11/looking-beyond-election-day.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Occupiers’ Responsive Chord</title>
		<link>./../../2011/11/the-occupiers-responsive-chord.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/11/the-occupiers-responsive-chord.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2011 19:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[OWS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Robert Reich]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/11/the-occupiers-responsive-chord.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I believe Robert Reich points us in the right direct when he suggests in The Occupiers’ Responsive Chord: A combination of police crackdowns and bad weather are testing the young Occupy movement. But rumors of its demise are premature, to say the least. Although numbers are hard to come by, anecdotal evidence suggests the movement [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I believe Robert Reich points us in the right direct when he suggests in <a target="_blank" href="http://robertreich.org/post/12168464049">The Occupiers’ Responsive Chord:</a>
</p>
<blockquote><p>A combination of police crackdowns and bad weather are testing the young Occupy movement. But rumors of its demise are premature, to say the least. Although numbers are hard to come by, anecdotal evidence suggests the movement is growing.</p>
<p>As importantly, the movement has already changed the public debate in America.</p>
<p>Consider, for example, last week’s Congressional Budget Office report on widening disparities of income in America. It was hardly news – it’s already well known that the top 1 percent now gets 20 percent of the nation’s income, up from 9 percent in the late 1970s.</p>
<p>But it’s the first time such news made the front page of the nation’s major newspapers.</p>
<p>Why? Because for the first time in more than half a century, a broad cross-section of the American public is talking about the concentration of income, wealth, and political power at the top.</p>
<p>Score a big one for the Occupiers.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I have noticed in the burbs small group meetings (20-30) comprised of some &#8216;younger&#8217; people but also a range of support from small business people in town, successful traders and financial people, increasing church participation (ie. Vespas at Dexter Park), teachers&#8230;people who are setting up ways to be part time supporters for what are to planned to be long term discussion/education but as importantly also are for active and participatory support (showing up to be counted).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/11/the-occupiers-responsive-chord.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Robert Reich&#8217;s After Shock and Corey Robin&#8217;s Freedom Arguments</title>
		<link>./../../2011/04/robert-reichs-after-shock-and-corey-robins-freedom-arguments.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/04/robert-reichs-after-shock-and-corey-robins-freedom-arguments.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2011 11:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Corey Brown]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[distributive justice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fair tax policy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[freedom]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income inequality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linda Beale (Tax law)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[progressive taxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Robert Reich]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Nation]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/04/robert-reichs-after-shock-and-corey-robins-freedom-arguments.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Beale In earlier posts on ataxingmatter (here and here), I reviewed Robert Reich&#8217;s 2010 book, After Shock, and wrote about his suggested cures for the problems made most visible in the 2007 crash and the Great Depression that followed. The gist of the book is summed up in the following quote: &#8220;[L]eft to [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by <strong>Linda Beale</strong></p>
<p>In earlier posts on ataxingmatter (<a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2011/04/robert-reichs-after-shock.html" target="_blank" _mce_href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2011/04/robert-reichs-after-shock.html">here</a> and <a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2011/04/robert-reichs-after-shock-prescriptions-for-the-cure-1.html">here</a>), I reviewed Robert Reich&#8217;s 2010 book, <em>After Shock</em>, and wrote about his suggested cures for the problems made most visible in the 2007 crash and the Great Depression that followed.</p>
<p>The gist of the book is summed up in the following quote:</p>
<blockquote><p>&#8220;[L]eft to its own devices, the market concentrates wealth and income&#8211;which is<br />disastrous to an economy as well as to a society.&#8221; at 59</p></blockquote>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Corey Robin writes in the Nation about the same problem, <a href="http://www.thenation.com/article/159748/reclaiming-politics-freedom">Reclaiming the Politics of Freedom, The Nation</a>, Apr. 26, 2011. But he notes that harping on the distributional inequality doesn&#8217;t resonate with voters. If the left wants to influence policies and capture the hearts of voters, he suggests, it needs to demonstrate that this distributional mayhem, which leaves everybody but the rich vulnerable, has even broader consequences that reach to the very fundamental creation myths of our society&#8211;the desire to be our own masters, to free ourselves from a tyrannical monarchy and colonial overlords who seemed to want to dictate how we could work, what we could drink, and where we could live. That is, to make what we are saying comprehensible at the &#8220;yeah, that&#8217;s what counts for me&#8221; level, we need to connect to America&#8217;s own Founding Moment. We need to &#8220;reclaim[] the politics of freedom.&#8221;</p>
<p>And I think he is correct. Because the problem we are facing today, with corporate lobbying and campaign contributions reinforcing the elite class&#8217;s wining and dining of politicians, is more than the dysfunction of the economy. Yes, there is too much money at the top where there is not enough ability to spend it. Yes, there is too little money at the bottom where there is no way to provide for basic needs. Yes, there is barely enough in the middle, resulting in stagnation in local businesses who don&#8217;t have enough customers to sell to and can&#8217;t afford to give credit to those who want to buy. </p>
<p>It is not just that banks, connected to power through their managers and shareholders, are able to speculate with other people&#8217;s money (our money!) in the international derivatives casino and then push their losses off on us. It is not just that corporate bosses rake in as much in a day as many of their workers make in an entire year of hard labor. It is not just that we can no longer talk to anybody local when there is a problem with our phone or our order from a company. It is not just that ordinary people are ignored, disregarded, almost shunned, because the elite really are only comfortable in the company of other elites. It is not just that we can&#8217;t get an appointment with a doctor unless we have (expensive) health insurance, or can&#8217;t get that crown we need on the broken tooth because it costs as much as some of us make in half a year.</p>
<p>No. These things are real, they affect us every day, they make us angry every day because we recognize our powerlessness to deal with the highly impersonal Big Business world that has been fostered by the four decades of reaganomics&#8217; deregulation, privatization, tax cuts and militarization. But still, the problem goes much deeper than these things. </p>
<p>Our very freedom is threatened. When we are economically powerless, we are also powerless in our lives because we lose our freedom to make choices that are right for us. </p>
<ul>
<li>we lose our rights to bargain with our employers (look at how Wisconsin and Ohio have treated their public employees or how WalMart treats its workers and anyone who talks unions), </li>
<p>
<li>we lose the power to improve ourselves by pulling ourselves up by the bootstraps through publicly funded education from grade school through university, </li>
<p>
<li>we are dominated in the marketplace by powerful businesses that use automated systems to turn us off, ignore our calls and letters seeking redress for a mischarge or a poorly done job,</li>
<p>
<li>we lose our jobs, are forced to accept paycuts or furloughs, when the company claims times are tought, yet we watch the same public companies to pay their CEOs millions more </li>
</ul>
<p>Our freedom to improve ourselves, freedom to choose the kind of work we want to do, freedom to prepare for our retirement and then retire with some security about our future, freedom from worry about whether or not a catastrophic medical emergency will eat up all our savings and leave family without an adequate living&#8211;all these freedoms are being threatened today by the concentration of wealth in the hands of an elite few who thereby become emplowered to set the market terms as they choose. </p>
<p>The idea of the &#8220;free market&#8221; is a bill of goods sold to replace the real concepts of freedom we should be considering. Markets, of course, can only function well for the people where government constraints prevent the owners and managers from setting all the terms to suit themselves, leaving externalities of their profitmaking to be borne by the people. literally ripping them off. The sloganeers have persuaded ordinary Americans to think that the American Dream of freedom is encapsulated in that little bitty notion of a &#8220;free market&#8221; so that they will unknowingly throw away the big idea of freedom&#8211;the freedom to set one&#8217;s own course in life, in a cooperative society that works to provide those tools.</p>
<p>The reason we need a progressive tax policy&#8211;including at the least progressive tax rates with brackets that reach much higher into the stratosphers of the ultra rich (55% for those making $1 million or more annually) ; elimination of the capital gains preference (so that all income is taxed under the same rate structure); and an estate tax with bite (meaning a graduated rate that protects a reasonable nest egg for the next generation while serving as one method of limiting the concentration of wealth)&#8211; is to ensure the freedom of each and every one of us, from rich to poor, from newly arrived immigrant to elderly Native American.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/04/robert-reichs-after-shock-and-corey-robins-freedom-arguments.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
