<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Bruce Webb (Social Security) &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>North West Plan for Social Security</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/north-west-plan-for-social-security.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/north-west-plan-for-social-security.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 Jan 2013 06:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Bruce Webb (Social Security)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dale Coberly]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/north-west-plan-for-social-security.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Note that in this table from 2010 a full fix is 0.6. And that the North West Plan is close to Options 2 and 3.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Note that in this table from 2010 a full fix is 0.6. And that the North West Plan is close to Options 2 and 3.</p>
<div><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-86vvO0wa8so/UOuCG_55ZJI/AAAAAAAABU8/wuzG-_IOaM4/s1600/CBO-SS%2Boptions%2BFig%2B1.jpg" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="548" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-86vvO0wa8so/UOuCG_55ZJI/AAAAAAAABU8/wuzG-_IOaM4/s640/CBO-SS%2Boptions%2BFig%2B1.jpg" width="640"></a></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/north-west-plan-for-social-security.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>CBO: SS Scheduled vs Payable Benefits (Rosser&#8217;s Equation illustrated)</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/cbo-ss-scheduled-vs-payable-benefits-rossers-equation-illustrated.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/cbo-ss-scheduled-vs-payable-benefits-rossers-equation-illustrated.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 06 Jan 2013 12:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Bruce Webb (Social Security)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/cbo-ss-scheduled-vs-payable-benefits-rossers-equation-illustrated.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Bruce Webb CBO: SS Scheduled vs Payable Benefits (Rosser&#8217;s Equation illustrated) &#8216;Rosser&#8217;s Equation&#8217; is something between an in-joke and tribute to Prof. Barkley Rosser, Jr of JMU, an economist friend of mine who pointed out a surprising result: real payable benefits after projected Trust Fund depletion and subsequent 25% cut will still be higher [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Bruce Webb</p>
<p> CBO: SS Scheduled vs Payable Benefits (Rosser&#8217;s Equation illustrated)</p>
<p><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-9bLHAYFroVQ/UN_ZjJm-YwI/AAAAAAAAAGc/2k_zd3cc_5c/s1600/2012+CBO+Ex+9+(Rosser's+Equation).tiff"><img border="0" height="228" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-9bLHAYFroVQ/UN_ZjJm-YwI/AAAAAAAAAGc/2k_zd3cc_5c/s1600/2012+CBO+Ex+9+(Rosser's+Equation).tiff" width="320"></a></p>
<p>&#8216;Rosser&#8217;s Equation&#8217; is something between an in-joke and tribute to Prof. Barkley Rosser, Jr of JMU, an economist friend of mine who pointed out a surprising result: real payable benefits after projected Trust Fund depletion and subsequent 25% cut will still be higher in actual basket of goods terms than those of current retirees. This is because the scheduled benefit formula delivers something like 160% of the current benefit and as Prof Rosser pointed out to me long ago 75% of 160%=120%.   </p>
<p>The above Exhibit 9 from CBO&#8217;s 2012 Long Term Projections for Social Security resolves Rosser&#8217;s equation for selected demographic cohorts and income quintiles. And the results show that the retiree born in 1947 who reached FRA (Full Retirement Age) in 2012 would see an initial benefit ranging from $10k to $25k and representing 100% of the schedule. On the other hand the retiree born in 1970 and who will reach FRA at age 67 in 2037, that is after TF Depletion would see initial benefits in 2012 dollars ranging from $12k to $33k.    </p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Now there is no doubt that an overnight 25% cut in benefits at Trust Fund Depletion would represent huge sticker shock for then retirees. And there are very good reasons based in societal equity for scheduled benefits to rise at the real rate the formula delivers. As such we should make every effort to find ways of closing the gap between payable and scheduled from the bottom up rather than forcing scheduled down simply to avoid the shock of of cut. Because the risk is that the &#8216;cure&#8217; might deliver a worse result in real terms than the &#8216;crisis&#8217; left unaddressed.    </p>
<p>Which is why I have been maintaining for years that &#8216;Nothing&#8217; IS a Plan. Not as good a plan as it was when Prof Rosser and I started corresponding five plus years ago, circumstances have changed. Still it represents the &#8220;First Do No Harm&#8221; alternative, after all a check in 2040 20% better in real terms than an equivalently situated retiree gets today doesn&#8217;t exactly meet the definition of existential crisis for Social Security. </p>
<p>cross posted with <a href="http://socialsecuritydefender.blogspot.com/2012/12/cbo-ss-scheduled-vs-payable-benefits.html" title="http://socialsecuritydefender.blogspot.com/2012/12/cbo-ss-scheduled-vs-payable-benefits.html">Social Security Defender</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/cbo-ss-scheduled-vs-payable-benefits-rossers-equation-illustrated.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Three definitions of Solvency for Social Security</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/three-definitions-of-solvency-for-social-security.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/three-definitions-of-solvency-for-social-security.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 21:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Bruce Webb (Social Security)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security for the young]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[solvency]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/three-definitions-of-solvency-for-social-security.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Bruce Webb brings an interesting perspective to the current situation as pundits and politicians figure out &#8216;what is acceptable&#8217; and what &#8216;they can live with&#8217; her at AB and at his new website Social Security Defender: (see link below): Scheduled vs Payable Benefits: three definitions of Solvency As usual click to embiggen. When it comes [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://socialsecuritydefender.blogspot.com/2012/12/scheduled-vs-payable-benefits-three.html">Bruce Webb</a> brings an interesting perspective to the current situation as pundits and politicians figure out &#8216;what is acceptable&#8217; and what &#8216;they can live with&#8217; her at AB and at his new website Social Security Defender: (see link below):</p>
<p><a href="http://socialsecuritydefender.blogspot.com/2012/12/scheduled-vs-payable-benefits-three.html">Scheduled vs Payable Benefits: three definitions of Solvency</a></p>
<p><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-RG1R_IqWysg/UOEZDIweP8I/AAAAAAAAAGs/zNlEhN2VAmI/s1600/CBO+2012+SS-Scheduled+vs+Payable.tiff"><img border="0" height="180" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-RG1R_IqWysg/UOEZDIweP8I/AAAAAAAAAGs/zNlEhN2VAmI/s1600/CBO+2012+SS-Scheduled+vs+Payable.tiff" width="320"></a><br />As usual click to embiggen.   </p>
<p>When it comes to Social Security there are three definitions of &#8216;Solvency&#8217;, one used by the &#8216;Actuary&#8217; another by the &#8216;Defender&#8217; and the third by the &#8216;Reformer&#8217;. And it is this difference that lays at the heart of the policy disagreements on how to achieve it. Something ostensibly all three seek.    </p>
<p>For the &#8216;Actuary&#8217; &#8216;Solvency&#8217; is mostly a value free concept. Social Security is solvent when all income from all sources equals all costs leaving Trust Fund assets equalling 100% of the next years projected cost. This is known as having a &#8216;Trust Fund Ratio&#8217; of 100. If the Trust Funds are projected to be solvent for the upcoming 10 year window Social Security is judged to be in &#8216;Short Term Actuarial Balance&#8217;. If the Trust Funds are projected to maintain that solvency, or at least end up with it without going into the hole over a 75 year period it is judged to be in &#8216;Long Term Actuarial Balance&#8217;. And since 2003 the Trustees added an additional measure of solvency measured over the &#8216;Infinite Future Horizon&#8217;.    </p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Under current law Social Security has a &#8216;scheduled benefit&#8217; which is the arithmetic result of a formula calculated ultimately on the course of Real Wage increases over the worker&#8217;s lifetime. It also has a &#8216;payable benefit&#8217; based on a formula that is calculated by a combination of Real Wage setting the initial benefit, inflation setting the continuing benefit, and total wages driving the income. The details are not important for the present purpose, suffice it to say that &#8216;scheduled benefit&#8217; is the measure of Cost while &#8216;payable benefit&#8217; is the measure of Income minus Cost. And as such &#8216;involvency&#8217; represents that point here Cost exceeds Income to the extent that Trust Fund assets are driven below a TF Ratio of 100. Or in an alternative formulation when those assets are driven to zero. At which time we have a scenario as depicted in the above figure: a sudden reset of payable benefits from the schedule (where they were topped off by asset redemptions) to the new payable equal to then current income from taxation.    </p>
<p>In percentage terms that sudden reset amounts to right on 25% of then current scheduled benefits and it is that discontinuity that defines &#8216;solvency crisis&#8217;. But here is where &#8216;defenders&#8217; and &#8216;reformers&#8217; depart.    <br />For Social Security Defenders the crisis is one of a cut in benefits and the solution is putting in place policy that would maintain the scheduled benefit. For Social Security &#8216;reformers&#8217; the crisis is more political, the risk that a reset in benefits from &#8216;scheduled&#8217; to &#8216;payable&#8217; will result in demands that the schedule be maintained via transfers from outside the dedicated income stream of FICA and tax on benefits. As a result the proposed solutions to this same &#8216;solvency crisis&#8217; via benefit reset are diametrically opposed with defenders advocating measures to maintain current scheduled benefits while reformers see their task as reconciling future retirees to accepting then payable.    </p>
<p>The key here, and the stopping point for this post is that either the prescription of the defender in saving scheduled or the reformer in reconciling retirees with payable will, if accomplished by appropriate changes in current law, satisfy the actuary&#8217;s test for solvency. As will outcomes in between. From a purely technocratic standpoint any set of policies that has scheduled and payable share the same ultimate projected line with no discontinuity meets the &#8216;solvency&#8217; test. Meaning that each has &#8216;fixed&#8217; Social Security by &#8216;preserving&#8217; benefits in a &#8216;sustainable&#8217; fashion. Without at any point addressing the question of whether the resulting benefits actually meet any standard of societal inequity.    </p>
<p>Are cuts to scheduled actually the &#8216;Road to Catfood&#8217; or a &#8216;Concession to Reality&#8217;? Well interestingly neither question has anything to do which the metric of &#8216;Solvency&#8217;. The question, while of course of the utmost importance in real terms, is somewhat orthogonal to discussions revolving around &#8216;actuarial balance&#8217;. Because from the latter perspective the &#8216;crisis&#8217; IS the &#8216;discontinuity&#8217; and not the real world implications thereof.</p>
<p>And a &#8216;fix&#8217; is a &#8216;fix&#8217;.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/three-definitions-of-solvency-for-social-security.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Social Security and the current fad of being balanced and comprehensive</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/social-security-and-the-current-fad-of-being-balanced-and-comprehensive.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/social-security-and-the-current-fad-of-being-balanced-and-comprehensive.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2012 17:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Bruce Webb (Social Security)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[chained cpi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Democratic Party]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fiscal cliff]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Republican Party]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security for the young]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/social-security-and-the-current-fad-of-being-balanced-and-comprehensive.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Salon writer  Natasha Lennard reports that a sticking point around Social Security stalled &#8216;fiscal cliff&#8217; back and forth rejoinders between the two parties, but also points out that the topic continues to be on the table (and has been offered by President Obama before these talks a couple years ago).   Notice both parties using the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.salon.com/2012/12/30/gop_demands_social_security_cuts_setting_back_fiscal_talks/" target="_blank">Salon writer</a>  Natasha Lennard reports that a sticking point around Social Security stalled &#8216;fiscal cliff&#8217; back and forth rejoinders between the two parties, but also points out that the topic continues to be on the table (and has been offered by President Obama before these talks a couple years ago).   Notice both parties using the same language of &#8220;<i>part of a balanced, comprehensive agreement</i>&#8221; as the fix is in without looking at other parts of the budget&#8230;these back and forth sallies are bi-partisan in appearance, but do not address the current version of &#8216;fical cliff&#8217; responsibilities.
<p>A free gift to the political players and the cover of the moment, a matter not even related to current fiscal responsibility, nor to the real world impact it has on poverty and seniors, nor the carefully thought out and responsible plans offered to address real issues.</p>
<blockquote><p>In what Democratic aides told reporters was a “major setback” in fiscal cliff negotiations, Republicans proposed throwing a Social Security cut into the scaled-back deal Congress is attempting to cobble together in advance of the New Year deadline. As things stand at the time of writing, negotiations are close to breakdown.
<p>Aides to Republican Senate Minority Leader Mitch McConnell presented the Social Security proposal, which included a method of calculating benefits with inflation. The plan would lower cost of living increases for Social Security recipients. Democrats were swift to reject the offer.</p>
<p>A Democratic aide told <a href="http://abcnews.go.com/Politics/OTUS/fiscal-cliff-talks-hit-major-setback-social-security/story?id=18095739&#038;page=2#.UOCptLamAeM">ABC News</a> that the proposal was a “poisoned pill” in the current negotiations. However, it should be noted that President Obama has suggested a similar proposal within the context of negotiations on a broad deficit-reduction deal. Such a measure had been taken off the table in discussions over a scaled-back, short-term agreement.</p>
<p>Senate Majority Leader Harry Reid said on the Senate floor Sunday, “We’re willing to make difficult concessions as part of a balanced, comprehensive agreement but we’ll not agree to cut social security benefits as part of a small or short-term agreement, especially if that agreement gives more handouts to the rich.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>How do I know this?  Well, it is worth the time to follow posts at <i>Angry Bear </i> over the next few months, and to compare the analysis to your own understandings.  Bruce Webb will be writing with updated numbers, a must to understand the words others are using, and to gain further understanding of the big numbers used to argue political points of view.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/social-security-and-the-current-fad-of-being-balanced-and-comprehensive.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Workers will have MORE money in their pockets AND will have paid for a longer retirement at a higher standard of living</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/workers-will-have-more-money-in-their-pockets-and-will-have-paid-for-a-longer-retirement-at-a-higher-standard-of-living.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/workers-will-have-more-money-in-their-pockets-and-will-have-paid-for-a-longer-retirement-at-a-higher-standard-of-living.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 21 Dec 2012 16:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Bruce Webb (Social Security)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dale Coberly]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social safety net]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/workers-will-have-more-money-in-their-pockets-and-will-have-paid-for-a-longer-retirement-at-a-higher-standard-of-living.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[There are a number of well thought out plans to handle the problems proposed by opponents of Social Security and also those concerned about its sustainability. To have our political and media debate confined to one item like chained-cpi should make any reasonable voter pause and wonder &#8220;Is that all? How dumb can we be?&#8221; [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There are a number of well thought out plans to handle the problems proposed by opponents of Social Security and also those concerned about its sustainability.  To have our political and media debate confined to one item like chained-cpi should make any reasonable voter pause and wonder &#8220;Is that all?  How dumb can we be?&#8221;  Take a breath and a half hour to review trhe fact that there a a lot of alternatives&#8230;don&#8217;t let your politician quote you a bumper sticker slogan.  There are plenty of alternatives that won&#8217;t cut benefits for a well functioning program that could deliver a decent result.</p>
<p>&#8220;Workers will have MORE money in their pockets AND will have paid for a longer retirement at a higher standard of living.&#8221;   <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/12/social-security-cuts-offeredwhy.html" title="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/12/social-security-cuts-offeredwhy.html">Social Security cuts offered&#8230;why?</a>  </p>
<blockquote><p>According to the 2010 CBO report Options for Social Security the chained CPI will &#8220;solve&#8221; about one third of the projected shortfall.<br />Since a tax raise of forty cents per week per year over the same time would solve the entire projected shortfall, it looks as though the chained CPI is going to save workers about 13 cents per week per year while their wages are going up eight dollars per week per year.<br />Of course the chained CPI is going to cost them a thousand dollars a year when they are too old to do anything about it.<br />Makes you wonder who the President&#8217;s financial advisor is.<br />&#8230;<br />The CBO report was from 2010. raising the cap to cover 90% of earnings would put the cap at about 150k, and their benefits would be increased.<br />This might be salable to them&#8230; if they figured the extra tax was a reasonable price to pay for the extra insurance&#8230; I am guessing their SS benefit would go from about 26k to about 35k. I don&#8217;t think they would be happy with that ratio.<br />In any case I would prefer to pay the extra 13 cents per week and keep Social Security &#8220;worker paid.&#8221;<br />You don&#8217;t want welfare. it&#8217;s ugly.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Dale Coberly</p>
<blockquote><p>Everyone interested in actual SS numbers <a href="http://www.cbo.gov/publication/21547">should read that CBO 2010 report &#8216;Social Security Policy Options&#8217;</a> or just refer to special figure 1. CBO scored 30 different policy options taken in isolation and although some would interact if enacted together for the most part you can treat the fixes as a cafeteria plan and mix and match to reach your 0.6 target. For example there is one fix that closes 0.9 of that 0.6 which makes room for proposals that shift benefits to the bottom in a way that still mets out at 0.6. Now in the event I agree with Dale that this particular combination adds up to &#8216;welfare&#8217; and moreover that that would be a bad thing. But your views may vary.<br />The point being that most obvious changes to SS have already been scored, all you need to do is Google the cited document.</p></blockquote>
<p>Bruce Webb</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/workers-will-have-more-money-in-their-pockets-and-will-have-paid-for-a-longer-retirement-at-a-higher-standard-of-living.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Steady State Social Security: What Would it Look LIke?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/steady-state-social-security-what-would-it-look-like.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/steady-state-social-security-what-would-it-look-like.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 06 Dec 2012 17:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Bruce Webb (Social Security)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security for the young]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/steady-state-social-security-what-would-it-look-like.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[What would Social Security look like if it met all current law requirements for &#8216;solvency&#8217;? Well unfortunately we have to start with the most eye-glazing opening ever deployed: &#8216;first lets define our terms&#8217;. To which I would add &#8216;within an artificial economic model&#8217;. Because real life is messy, particularly right now, and that introduces unnecessary [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>What would Social Security look like if it met all current law requirements for &#8216;solvency&#8217;? Well unfortunately we have to start with the most eye-glazing opening ever deployed: &#8216;first lets define our terms&#8217;. To which I would add &#8216;within an artificial economic model&#8217;. Because real life is messy, particularly right now, and that introduces unnecessary conceptual confusion. So lets begin.</p>
<p>First assume a solid state economy. For my purposes I will define that as 5.5% unemployment, 5% nominal yield on 10 year Treasuries, 2.5% Real GDP, 2% inflation, 1% annual growth in SS beneficiaries. (Yes in the real world these interact, and maybe this precise combination is unlikely, though each number in isolation is in intermediate ranges, but that will not effect the basic argument).</p>
<p>Second assume that Social Security is currently &#8216;solvent&#8217;, meaning that income from all sources is sufficient to pay all costs, leaving a reserve numerically equal to next year cost. What would it take to keep it &#8216;solvent&#8217;?</p>
<p>Well in our simplified model Social Security cost increases year over year as a sum of inflation growth and beneficiary population. Which ignoring interactions means an increase of 3% per year. Which in turn means that maintaining &#8216;solvency&#8217; requires bringing in enough income from all sources to pay 103% of Year One cost AND add 3% to Trust Fund principal and so leaving the Trust Fund ratio (reserves as a percentage of NEXT year cost) at the end of Year Two at 100 or one year&#8217;s worth of Year Three cost.</p>
<p>Now in our model the 5% nominal yield on Trust Fund assets (mostly invested in a mirror of 5 year bonds) would boost the TF ratio to 105% by interest effects alone, assuming that is that no portion of current interest was needed to pay current cost. Turning that around this means that 2 points of interest are available to reduce the need for &#8216;income excluding interest&#8217; to match cost. Meaning that such income has to total 98% of the new 103% of previous year cost.</p>
<p>Now in year over year terms this has two effects on the overall economy. First &#8216;income excluding interest&#8217; has to increase year over year to pick up its 98% share of the new year&#8217;s new increased cost. And second some part of the 5% interest on Trust Fund assets has to be transferred in cash to pick up its 2% share.</p>
<p>What does this leave us? Well a Social Security system that is cash flow negative each and every year. But with a wrinkle. Since that portion of the 5% nominal interest retained simply to meet the 3% growth in TF balance to maintain a TF ratio of 100 is credited in the form of NEW Special Treasuries, which are NOT financed directly by borrowing, that nominal interest is discounted in cash terms by some 60% from the perspective of the General Fund and the taxpayers who pay into it. AND the system is picking up basic income support for the 1% of the population being added on net to the beneficiary pool.</p>
<p>It seems to me that once having established steady state solvency that people paying taxes on non-wage income are getting a pretty good deal out of Social Security. To the degree that basic income support for seniors, widows/widowers/orphans, the disabled is some societal wide responsibility then 98% is being paid by current wage workers in FICA and by retired workers in tax on benefits and an additional percentage by income tax on wage workers leaving a pretty damn small levy on gains from capital. Forgive the language.</p>
<p>All this of course stems from a condition of &#8216;solvency&#8217;, which translates to keeping the income excluding interest/cost ratio approximating 98%. Which in theory can be done on either the benefit or cost side. But either way the resultant post-solvency is not remotely &#8216;unsustainable&#8217;. Or if so leave some numbers in comments. The only real policy question it seems to me is determining the actual costs and trade-offs getting from where we are now to solvency as defined. And not as is too common now trying to calculate the costs of paying off all the principal going forward. Because as noted in a previous post in a Steady State Social Security system principal NEVER needs to be paid down, instead all of it has to be retained to meet reserve requirements.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/steady-state-social-security-what-would-it-look-like.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Current Law Social Security: &#034;Scheduled&#034; vs &#034;Payable&#034; Benefits</title>
		<link>./../../2012/09/current-law-social-security-scheduled-vs-payable-benefits.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/09/current-law-social-security-scheduled-vs-payable-benefits.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 05 Sep 2012 18:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Bruce Webb (Social Security)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/09/current-law-social-security-scheduled-vs-payable-benefits.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Okay, more jargon. But important jargon because the policy proposals are starting from different baselines themselves defined by this jargon. So while some of the following is basic, it is equally a rhetorical (in the classical definition) baseline. Under current Social Security law future benefits are set by a formula. For a given individual this [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Okay, more jargon. But important jargon because the policy proposals are starting from different baselines themselves defined by this jargon. So while some of the following is basic, it is equally a rhetorical (in the classical definition) baseline.</p>
<p>Under current Social Security law future benefits are set by a formula. For a given individual this formula starts from income history but if we take total benefit payouts in the aggregate we have cost totals primarily driven by employment numbers, Real Wage, and CPI. And this aggregate number represents 99% or so of the category that the Report Tables label as &#8220;Cost&#8221;. These projected future benefits are in turn offset by projected income deriving from one main and two minor sources, that is FICA payroll tax, tax on certain benefits, and interest on Trust Fund assets, with the totals being labeled in the Tables as &#8220;Income&#8221;. In an ideal world the trend of projected Income would exceed projected Cost in just the amount needed to maintain a specific, relative level of reserves. This state of affairs for any given year or set of years is called &#8220;actuarial balance&#8221; and if projected to continue beyond the 75 year actuarial window, and with an upward trend is called &#8220;sustainable solvency&#8221;.</p>
<p>As it turns out current mid-range projections of future employment, Real Wage, CPI, payroll income, tax on benefits, and interest on Trust Fund assets do not project &#8220;sustainable solvency&#8221;, instead there is a projected gap between total income and accumulated assets available to pay out future benefits and total projected costs. That is if we simply assume ALL mid-range projections, something that is labeled in the Reports &#8220;Intermediate Cost&#8221;  and follow current law that requires payment of full &#8220;scheduled benefits&#8221; as long as total income and assets allow those benefits to be &#8220;payable&#8221;, at some point the latter level falls below the former. The state in which &#8220;scheduled benefits&#8221; exceeds &#8220;payable&#8221;  can be called &#8220;insolvency&#8221;, or working up the shrillness index &#8220;crisis&#8221; or even &#8220;bankruptcy&#8221;.</p>
<p>But before we start hyperventilating it would be useful to slow down and actually examine the financial and legal implications for actual beneficiaries at this &#8220;crisis&#8221; point. Because one thing we know for sure the end result will NOT be &#8220;no check&#8221;. Maybe not the SAME check on the SAME day, but the system won&#8217;t grind to a complete halt. To see what is likely to happen under current law and realistic political projections you will need to follow under the fold.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />(Lucky you, a computer crash wiped out a bunch of text. So a shorter version.) The takeaway most readers of the Social Security Report would have is that at the point at which projected &#8220;Income&#8221; (which defines &#8220;payable benefit&#8221;) falls below &#8220;Cost&#8221; (which defines &#8220;scheduled benefit&#8221;) current law simply reduces the latter to the former overnight resulting in around an immediate 22-25% cut in benefit checks.</p>
<p>But this is where the two groups I will call fairly neutrally Social Security &#8220;Defenders&#8221; vs &#8220;Reformers&#8221; start talking past each other. While each sees this cut as tremendously disruptive &#8220;Defenders&#8221; see that disruption in the form of Gramma spending her remaining shopping dollars in the Catfood Aisle, while &#8220;Reformers&#8221; see armies of Greedy Geezers storming Capitol Hill in their Lexus&#8217;s demanding their God-given right to pay Country Club dues with their full scheduled Social Security check.</p>
<p>As such their definitions of &#8220;Fix&#8221; and even &#8220;Preserve&#8221; take very different forms.  I like to think of this in the logicians terms of &#8220;direction of fit&#8221;. &#8220;Defenders&#8221; want to &#8220;fix&#8221; Social Security by ensuring that &#8220;payable&#8221; is fitted to &#8220;scheduled&#8221; while reformers prefer fixes that will defuse the crisis by fitting &#8220;scheduled&#8221; to &#8220;payable&#8221;. Both sides would argue that their respective fixes avoid the dreaded &#8220;slash&#8221; in benefits in the interest of &#8220;preserving&#8221; Social Security, it is just that &#8220;Defenders&#8221; are preserving a particular projected standard of living while &#8220;Reformers&#8221; are seeking to preserve a certain political peace, in their terms an avoidance of &#8220;intergenerational warfare&#8221;.</p>
<p>And as a &#8220;Defender&#8221; I am even willing to concede that certain &#8220;Reformers&#8221; are actually sincere. Where I see a perfectly fixable case of &#8220;under funded&#8221; they see an equally fixable case of &#8220;over promised&#8221;.  Which is one of many reasons why the Social Security debate is not really one of numbers, but is really at root one of values and perceived equity. Which is not an argument for civility, just a suggestion that not all &#8220;Reformers&#8221; are liars or fools. Heartless sociopaths willing to use whatever tactics and number twisting they can to keep Greedy Geezers at bay? Sure. Fools? Well not ALL of them. And given a generous interpretation of whether &#8220;scheduled&#8221; or &#8220;payable&#8221; is the correct baseline to build your analysis even liar is too harsh. For some. Who simply consider themselves hard-headed realists.  </p>
<p>(Dan here&#8230;paragraphs added after the jump for readability)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/09/current-law-social-security-scheduled-vs-payable-benefits.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Cut Social Security Gang</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/the-cut-social-security-gang.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/the-cut-social-security-gang.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 31 Jul 2012 12:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Barkley Rosser]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bruce Webb (Social Security)]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/the-cut-social-security-gang.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Barkley Rosser at Econospeak opines on: Bill Keller Joins The Cut Social Security Gang In today&#8217;s New York Times, former editor Bill Keller has an especially obnoxious column about baby boomer entitlement. I am not going to dispute at all his listing of various selfishnesses that we baby boomers have indulged in from Gordon Gekko type [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://econospeak.blogspot.com/2012/07/bill-keller-joins-cut-social-security.html">Barkley Rosser</a> at <i>Econospeak</i> opines on:</p>
<p>Bill Keller Joins The Cut Social Security Gang </p>
<p>In today&#8217;s New York Times, former editor Bill Keller has an especially obnoxious column about baby boomer entitlement. I am not going to dispute at all his listing of various selfishnesses that we baby boomers have indulged in from Gordon Gekko type follies to self-obsessing about 60s music and other such stuff. Fine. However, partway in the column morphs into yet another of these Social Security bashes by yet another of the Very Serious People, all for the purpose of reducing the deficit to save the future generations from the awful selfishness of the otherwise overly entitled baby boomers. I grant that he briefly mentions taxes and defense spending, but only to dismiss them as insufficient to solve the problem (that is, by raising the former and cutting the latter). Social Security is what must be seriously hit.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a>   <br />Now good old Dean Baker takes him to task pretty strongly today at <a href="http://www.cepr.net/index.php/blogs/beat-the-press">http://www.cepr.net/index.php/blogs/beat-the-press</a> . He focuses on how rich Bill Keller is, and how he will not be affected by cuts the way most people will be. He also brings up the point that it is health care costs that are most responsible for the dramatic upsurge in past and projected future entitlement spending, which Keller simply said nothing about, thereby really making himself look Seriously Foolish. That is a killer for Keller right there. While he did not comment on Keller I also note Bruce Webb&#8217;s latest post on angrybear in which after going through a lot of useful analysis he recites his old ditty: &#8220;If privatization is necessary, it won&#8217;t be possible. If privatizatization is possible, it won&#8217;t be necessary,&#8221; which about sums it up, at <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/07/a-social-security-ditty-if.html#more">http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/07/a-social-security-ditty-if.html#more</a> .<br />    <br />Let me add two more points particularly to Dean&#8217;s justified screed against Keller&#8217;s pompous silliness. One is that he left out the matter of economic growth. We know how the surplus that Clinton left got turned into the current massive budget deficit. There were the tax cuts, vaguely recognized by Keller. There were those two wars, not quite fully finished, which Keller did not name but did also vaguely note defense spending. But then there was the recession, which has been the biggest souce of the problem. If this could be overcome and we could return to growth of the sort we have previously seen, this would do wonders for alleviating the deficit, and also for putting us back into the second condition noted by Bruce Webb, that we would not need a privatization fix for social security because it would easily fund itself. Of course cutting Social Security and other spending while raising taxes threatens to be the sort of growth-killing austerity we see all those Europeans dragging themselves down with, thus undercutting the effort to get growth going again.<br />    <br />The other point, which may be the key to the real tendentiousness of the hypocrisy of this column, is that he is calling for sacrifices by the baby boomers while guilt tripping the lot of us, the people who would really pay for his proposed social security changes would not be baby boomers at all, but those very young people he is supposedly standing up for against our wickedness. Everybody knows that any changes will affect neither those already on SS, which includes some front end baby boomers already along with some set that will be due to get onto it pretty soon, which will probably expand the set of the unaffected at least haflway down into the baby boomer pile, with only some of the rump end tagalongs vulnerable. No, while changing cost of living indexes may affect even current recipients, the effects will be much greater down the road for those much younger who are supposedly being protected, and of course any increases in future eligilibity ages will be borne by those much younger than baby boomers. Keller is basically selling a fraud here.<br />    <br />So, we are back to one of my favorite lines. Those seeking to convince the young on the basis of the spoiled wickedness of the baby boomers that they should support cuts in future Social Security benefits are being told in effect, &#8220;Accept definite cuts now in your future Social Security benefits, because otherwise you might have to accept some cuts in the future to your future Social Security benefits!&#8221; Gag.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/the-cut-social-security-gang.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Social Security: Trust Funds, Actuarial Balance, Sustainable Solvency</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/social-security-trust-funds-actuarial-balance-sustainable-solvency.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/social-security-trust-funds-actuarial-balance-sustainable-solvency.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2012 17:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Bruce Webb (Social Security)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/social-security-trust-funds-actuarial-balance-sustainable-solvency.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Social Security arithmetic isn&#8217;t hard. Tedious perhaps and with counter-intuitive results but once certain terminological obstacles are swept away not requiring advanced math skills. But oy that terminology! This post proposes to start demolishing those conceptual barriers. Social Security is considered &#8216;solvent&#8217; when its &#8216;Trust Fund&#8217; is in &#8216;actuarial balance&#8217;. The Social Security Trust Fund [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Social Security arithmetic isn&#8217;t hard. Tedious perhaps and with counter-intuitive results but once certain terminological obstacles are swept away not requiring advanced math skills. But oy that terminology! This post proposes to start demolishing those conceptual barriers.</p>
<p>Social Security is considered &#8216;solvent&#8217; when its &#8216;Trust Fund&#8217; is in &#8216;actuarial balance&#8217;. The Social Security Trust Fund was created pursuant to the Social Security Amendments of 1939 to hold any excess of dedicated Social Security revenue over cost and serves primarily as a reserve fund. Those excess revenues are held in the form of interest earning Special Treasuries with that interest being included as revenue. When the accumulated principal including retained interest equals 100% of projected NEXT YEAR cost the Trust Fund is considered to be in &#8216;actuarial balance&#8217;. Now since Social Security income and cost project to change each year &#8216;actuarial balance&#8217; cannot effectively be measured in nominal dollar terms because a year end 2012 balance equal to 100% of 2013 projected cost will generally be something less than 100% of 2014 cost. And this quite aside from any fluctuations in the economy, that is all things being equal a steady-state Social Security system requires a steadily increasing Trust Fund principal balance to be judged in &#8216;actuarial balance&#8217;.</p>
<p>Meaning &#8216;fixing&#8217; Social Security, making it &#8216;solvent&#8217;, means something more than restoring actuarial balance for the current year, instead it requires having the system project to maintain &#8216;actuarial balance&#8217; over time. Historically the Trustees of Social Security established two different measures of solvency: &#8216;short term actuarial balance&#8217; and &#8216;long term actuarial balance&#8217;. &#8216;Short term&#8217; here means the same 10 year budget window used by the rest of government, if year end principal balance in the SS Trust Funds projects to be 100% or greater (in SS jargon a &#8216;trust fund ratio of 100 or more&#8217;) in EACH of the next 10 years Social Security &#8216;meets the test for short term actuarial balance&#8217;. Similarly if the TF ratio projects to be 100 or more in EACH of the next 75 years Social Security meets the test for &#8216;long term actuarial balance&#8217;. In the last couple decades &#8216;short term&#8217; and &#8216;long term&#8217; actuarial balance have been supplemented by two new ways of considering solvency. In 2002 we saw the introduction of  &#8216;Infinite Future Horizon&#8217;, that is in principle extending solvency to Heat Death of the Sun. More reasonably for long-term planning purposes is something called &#8216;sustainable solvency&#8217; which takes into account the predictable increase in structural cost year over year and argues that &#8216;long term actuarial balance&#8217; should include not just years 1-75, but also the trend for year 76 and after. That is we shouldn&#8217;t just fix Social Security for 2012, we should take steps to make sure it won&#8217;t fail the test for &#8216;long term actuarial balance&#8217; come 2013.</p>
<p>Okay having (I hope) adequately defined &#8216;solvency&#8217;, &#8216;actuarial balance&#8217;, &#8216;trust fund ratio&#8217;, &#8216;Infinite Future Horizon&#8217; and &#8216;sustainable solvency&#8217; we can develop some implications below the fold.<br /><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>What would &#8216;sustainable solvency&#8217; look like? Now given that year 76 total cost will be predictably more than year 75 year total cost even if the current year 75 year model is perfect, it follows that maintaining a trust fund ratio of EXACTLY 100 requires a small increase in Trust Fund balance EACH year. Which is where things start getting odd.</p>
<p>Okay assume we have a Trust Fund with a principal balance equal to 100% of next year&#8217;s cost where that principal is held in interest earning Special Treasuries whose interest is in turn counted as income. Further assume that all non-interest SS income for the upcoming year projects to be equal to projected cost. What is the result for the Trust Fund? Well one thing to recognize is that maturing Special Treasuries are not in themselves counted as &#8216;income&#8217;. If the dollars represented by those Treasuries are not needed for current year cost they are simply retained and rolled over into new issues. The second is that interest on the current portfolio IS counted as &#8216;income&#8217; but if not needed to pay current year cost is itself rolled over into new Special Treasuries. That is under the assumptions of our current scenario, where NON-interest income equals current cost, the result will be retention of 100% of principal augmented by interest converted to new principal in the form of new issues along side those rolled over.</p>
<p>Simple enough but with some odd results. Under our scenario maturing principal is not redeemed for cash, it is simply exchanged for new Special Treasuries with new (typically) 10 year maturities. And a few seconds of thought shows that in a steady state system of  &#8216;sustainable solvency&#8217; they might NEVER need to be redeemed for cash. In fact, and this is a key point, they would all need to be retained and augmented with new principal sufficient to maintain that Trust Fund ratio of 100. Meaning that those Treasuries, though real interest earning obligations of the U.S. government, never actually get paid off.</p>
<p>This tends to throw supporters of Social Security for a loop. Because they often believe that the Trust Funds were established in 1983 as a method of pre-funding Boomer retirement and were ALWAYS expected to be paid down to zero and so be temporary: &#8220;Reagan borrowed the money to pay for tax cuts, they NEED to pay it back&#8221;. Well actually under ideal circumstances they don&#8217;t need to pay it back. They only need to honor the obligation by continuing to pay and/or credit interest on the accumulated principal with the latter being retained to maintain the crucial function of &#8216;sustainable solvency&#8217; as measured by &#8216;trust fund ratio&#8217;.</p>
<p>And this is where things get hairy, because note I said in reference to interest that it needs to be paid and/or credited. And by &#8216;credited&#8217; I mean retained in the form of new Special Treasuries sufficient to maintain a trust fund ratio of 100. Which means that portion of interest retained to maintain an overall condition of &#8216;sustainable solvency&#8217; is never paid off by cash transfers either. In terms understandable to Paulite TeaTards those Special Treasuries used to roll over existing principal and to &#8216;finance&#8217; retained interest are just &#8216;fiat money&#8217;. Or in terms understandable by the rest of us &#8216;Interest Earning Obligations backed by Full Faith and Credit of the U.S.&#8217;</p>
<p>If this sounds crazy it is probably because Social Security is not now in &#8216;sustainable solvency&#8217;. Although on a combined basis the OASDI Trust Funds do meet the test for &#8216;short term actuarial balance&#8217; they DO NOT meet the &#8216;long term&#8217; test and still less either the test for &#8216;sustainable solvency&#8217; (i.e. year 76 and some years after) or &#8216;infinite future&#8217; (i.e. year 76 and EVERY year for centuries to come). Under current projections Trust Fund principal will need to be redeemed for cash starting in the 2020s and project to be totally redeemed by the mid 2030s. But given a sensible worker friendly fix that starts by taking the numbers and methodology of the Social Security Reports seriously they don&#8217;t need to be.</p>
<p>(After all it is eminently sensible to maintain a prudent reserve and reasonable enough to consider a TF ratio of 100 to be a simple minimum. On the other hand there is a limit beyond which too much reserve actually becomes dangerous (topic for another post). And when I started blogging on this in 2004 it appeared we were on that dangerous &#8216;over-funded&#8217; path. But the 2007 recession took care of THAT problem with the result that TF ratios are already dropping from their peak even as they still remain right around 350 (three and a half years of reserve). Of course there is no real world problem with those ratios dropping, that is after all what the extra reserve is for, to be tapped as needed. On the other hand simple prudence mandates putting into place a plan to keep them from dropping to levels which would cause the failure of  &#8216;short term actuarial balance&#8217; and even to put them onto a glide path towards &#8216;long term actuarial balance&#8217; and heck even &#8216;sustainable solvency&#8217;. Which (cough, cough) the Northwest Plan for a Real Social Security Fix does even as it maintains 100% of the current law scheduled benefit. Even as it largely avoids substantial paydown of Trust Fund principal in nominal terms, instead putting Social Security on the path to permanent TF ratios in the 130 range.)</p>
<p>What then would &#8216;sustainable solvency&#8217; look like from the perspective of the General Fund? Well for one thing the Social Security Trust Fund balance, while still being a very real claim on the future, with a minimum amount of due diligence never actually become itself &#8216;due&#8217;. Not in cash anyway. And interestingly neither will that portion of accrued interest needed to maintain the targeted TF ratio whether that be 100 or 130 or whatever. On the flip side not all interest can simply be credited to the Trust Fund as new Special Treasuries without potentially boosting the TF ratio to a point where worker&#8217;s rebel as a prudent &#8216;reserve&#8217; transmutes into an interest free loan to the General Fund. I mean who is the &#8216;moocher&#8217; or &#8216;looter&#8217; in that scenario?</p>
<p>I leave as an exercise for the reader to poke at the numbers and see what part of Trust Fund interest simply gets retained as Special Treasuries (and so not financed from the real economy) to maintain minimum TF ratios as opposed to that portion of that interest that needs to be paid out in benefits to keep that TF ratio below acceptable sustainable maximums, which for the sake of argument we could put at 166. Whatever is the result of the offset due to retained interest is in effect the discount on the cash interest rate and under standard Intermediate Cost assumptions is something like 40% off the nominal rate. But it doesn&#8217;t discount to zero, the Trust Fund never becomes (or shouldn&#8217;t anyway) a purely free lunch. Pretty cheap for the social utililty and equity Social Security delivers but not cost free. As Chief Actuary of SS Steve Goss explained in a crucially important article in the 70th anniversary edition of the Social Security Bulletin: <a href="http://www.ssa.gov/policy/docs/ssb/v70n3/v70n3p111.html">The Future Financial Status of the Social Security Program </a> (bolding mine)<br />
<blockquote>However, the occurrence of a negative cash flow, when tax revenue alone is insufficient to pay full scheduled benefits, does not necessarily mean that the trust funds are moving toward exhaustion. In fact, in a perfectly pay-as-you-go (<abbr title="pay go">PAYGO</abbr>) financing approach, with the assets in the trust fund maintained consistently at the level of a &#8220;contingency reserve&#8221; targeted at one year&#8217;s cost for the program, the program might well be in a position of having negative cash flow on a permanent basis. This would occur when the interest rate on the trust fund assets is greater than the rate of growth in program cost. In this case, interest on the trust fund assets would be more than enough to grow the assets as fast as program cost, leaving some of the interest available to augment current tax revenue to meet current cost. Under the trustees&#8217; current intermediate assumptions, the long-term average real interest rate is assumed at 2.9 percent, and real growth of <abbr>OASDI</abbr> program cost (growth in excess of price inflation) is projected to average about 1.6 percent from 2030 to 2080. Thus, if program modifications are made to maintain a consistent level of trust fund assets in the future, interest on those assets would generally augment current tax income in the payment of scheduled benefits.</p></blockquote>
<p>That is within stated limits neither the fact nor the timing of Social Security going cash flow negative means a damn thing in the bigger picture. Something some commenters have a hard time grasping.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/social-security-trust-funds-actuarial-balance-sustainable-solvency.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Why we don&#8217;t need to repay Social Security principal</title>
		<link>./../../2011/03/why-we-dont-need-to-repay-social-security-principal.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/03/why-we-dont-need-to-repay-social-security-principal.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 13 Mar 2011 20:36:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Bruce Webb (Social Security)]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/03/why-we-dont-need-to-repay-social-security-principal.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[{Cross posted from dKos Social Security Defenders group. Some parts will be pretty familiar to AB readers} You may have to bear with me here. Because very few people have seriously examined what a solvent Social Security system would actually look like. One of those that has is (thankfully) Steve Goss, the Chief Actuary of [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>{Cross posted from dKos Social Security Defenders group. Some parts will be pretty familiar to AB readers}</p>
<p>You may have to bear with me here. Because very few people have seriously examined what a solvent Social Security system would actually look like. One of those that has is (thankfully) Steve Goss, the Chief Actuary of Social Security, who last year wrote what may be the single most important article on Social Security that I have ever read. It was included in the 75th Anniversary edition of the Social Security Bulletin under the title <a href="http://www.ssa.gov/policy/docs/ssb/v70n3/v70n3p111.html">The Future Financial Status of the Social Security Program</a></p>
<p>The whole thing is important but I want to focus on and then unpack the following passage, because the implications are simply transformational.<br />
<blockquote>However, the occurrence of a negative cash flow, when tax revenue alone is insufficient to pay full scheduled benefits, does not necessarily mean that the trust funds are moving toward exhaustion. In fact, in a perfectly pay-as-you-go (PAYGO) financing approach, with the assets in the trust fund maintained consistently at the level of a &#8220;contingency reserve&#8221; targeted at one year&#8217;s cost for the program, the program might well be in a position of having negative cash flow on a permanent basis. This would occur when the interest rate on the trust fund assets is greater than the rate of growth in program cost. In this case, interest on the trust fund assets would be more than enough to grow the assets as fast as program cost, leaving some of the interest available to augment current tax revenue to meet current cost. Under the trustees&#8217; current intermediate assumptions, the long-term average real interest rate is assumed at 2.9 percent, and real growth of OASDI program cost (growth in excess of price inflation) is projected to average about 1.6 percent from 2030 to 2080. Thus, if program modifications are made to maintain a consistent level of trust fund assets in the future, interest on those assets would generally augment current tax income in the payment of scheduled benefits.</p></blockquote>
<p>Unpacking below the fold. <a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Let&#8217;s start with this phrase: &#8220;assets in the trust fund maintained consistently at the level of a &#8220;contingency reserve&#8221; targeted at one year&#8217;s cost for the program&#8221;.  The Trust Funds individually and combined are considered in &#8216;actuarial balance&#8217; if they reach year&#8217;s end with a balance equal to the next year&#8217;s projected cost. If they are projected to meet this test for the next ten years they are considered to be in &#8216;short term actuarial balance&#8217;, if they are projected to meet it for the next 75 years they are considered to be in &#8216;long term actuarial balance&#8217;.</p>
<p>Simple enough but it gives us an odd result. For example if we look at the following table from the 2010 Report Table <a href="http://www.ssa.gov/OACT/TR/2010/VI_OASDHI_dollars.html#176345">VI.F9.—OASDI and HI Annual Income Excluding Interest, Cost, and Balance in Current Dollars, Calendar Years 2010-85</a> we can see the Social Security Cost is projected to increase every year in nominal terms until it ultimately reaches $27 TRILLION a year. Not to panic though this still remains the same percentage of projected GDP after 2030 at around 5.8%, the combination of real economic growth and inflation simply making for eye-popping numbers. But equally it means that for Social Security to reach the end goal of &#8216;sustainable solvency&#8217; which in Goss&#8217;s definition requires it to be in &#8216;long term actuarial balance&#8217; with the tail trending upwards, the Trust Fund year end balance would need to increase at at least the rate of Cost growth. Which in the case of what Goss calls a &#8220;perfectly pay-as-you-go (PAYGO) financing approach&#8221; means rolling over the ENTIRE principal each year and augmenting it with enough of the accrued interest to maintain that one year of Cost in reserve, or in Social Security lingo a Trust Fund Ratio of 100.</p>
<p>Which gets us to the point in the title of the diary, once Social Security is &#8216;fixed&#8217; one way or another there will be no need to redeem the principal in the Trust Fund. This doesn&#8217;t mean it becomes irrelevant, those assets still being available to perform their primary function as a reserve in times of temporary slowdown in revenues, and being a real obligation to Treasury in that they will still be earning interest but, and this is a key point, only a portion of that interest has to come in form of cash, the rest simply coming in the form of newly issued Special Treasuries in the amount needed to augment existing principal to reach a continuing TF Ratio of 100. Or as Goss puts it &#8220;In this case, interest on the trust fund assets would be more than enough to grow the assets as fast as program cost, leaving some of the interest available to augment current tax revenue to meet current cost.&#8221;</p>
<p>Under this ideal scenario the Trust Fund becomes an interest only loan and with a discount on that interest to boot as part of it is simply credited to principal in the form of Special Treasuries that are not financed in the normal sense, simply being instruments backed by Full Faith and Credit if and when they were ever needed.</p>
<p>Of course we are not in a Pay-Go status long term, although the combined OASDI Trust Funds meet the Trustees&#8217; test for &#8216;short term actuarial balance&#8217; and then some, current projections under the Intermediate Cost projection show the TF Ratio falling from a peak of 403 in 2012 downs to 110 in 2035 meaning actuarial imbalance starting in 2036. <a href="http://www.ssa.gov/OACT/TR/2010/IV_LRest.html#371491">Table IV.B3.—Trust Fund Ratios, Calendar Years 2010-85</a> Which by extension means failing the ten year &#8216;short term actuarial test&#8217; in 2027, or a dozen years before the actual crisis point of Trust Fund Depletion and benefit cuts. Which on a practical basis gives us all the years between now and 2026 to thoughtfully plan a fix, it is not like 1983 when TF ratios were already sitting weeks from zero. Now THAT was a crisis, today&#8217;s situation is not remotely similar.</p>
<p>So we don&#8217;t need to let this debate devolve down to &#8220;we can&#8217;t afford to pay back what we borrowed&#8221; vs &#8220;the hell you say! That&#8217;s our money you are stealing!!&#8221;. After all if the capitalists don&#8217;t want to pay down that principal they don&#8217;t have to, they just need to accept very modest increases in revenue sufficient to restore the system to Pay-Go status, an amount currently projected at just under 2% of payroll. (Or if they can, make the case why the current schedule of benefits is in fact too generous on its own terms.) After that they only have to commit to servicing a portion of Trust Fund interest in cash. Or to repack it:</p>
<blockquote><p>In fact, in a perfectly pay-as-you-go (PAYGO) financing approach, with the assets in the trust fund maintained consistently at the level of a &#8220;contingency reserve&#8221; targeted at one year&#8217;s cost for the program, the program might well be in a position of having negative cash flow on a permanent basis.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/03/why-we-dont-need-to-repay-social-security-principal.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
