<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>2016 presidential elections &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Health Care Thoughts: More Complexity Grumbling</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/health-care-thoughts-more-complexity-grumbling.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/health-care-thoughts-more-complexity-grumbling.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2013 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2016 presidential elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[healthcare thoughts]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/health-care-thoughts-more-complexity-grumbling.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt Health Care Thoughts: More Complexity Grumbling I have made the point many times that if anything stops Obamacare it will be the inability to implement an extremely complicated program. Call it “Rusty’s Theory of Complexity.” The feds have now published (link below) the draft application for financial assistance in health care [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt</p>
<p>Health Care Thoughts: More Complexity Grumbling</p>
<p>I have made the point many times that if anything stops Obamacare it will be the inability to implement an extremely complicated program. Call it “Rusty’s Theory of Complexity.”</p>
<p>The feds have now published (link below) the draft application for financial assistance in health care exchanges and low income plans. Oh boy.</p>
<p>With attachments this could easily run 30 + pages, and of course someone is going to have to process this (there will be an online version). Having helped people with paperwork for nearly 40 years I can guarantee this will be intimidating and confusing to many people.</p>
<p>Complication is the enemy of implementation. Count on it.<br /><a href="http://cms.gov/Regulations-and-Guidance/Legislation/PaperworkReductionActof1995/PRA-Listing-Items/CMS-10440.html">     </a><br /><a href="http://cms.gov/Regulations-and-Guidance/Legislation/PaperworkReductionActof1995/PRA-Listing-Items/CMS-10440.html">http://cms.gov/Regulations-and-Guidance/Legislation/PaperworkReductionActof1995/PRA-Listing-Items/CMS-10440.html</a></p>
<p>PS: HR Block has already positioned itself as a likely fee-for-service form fill-in service. Somebody is going to profit here.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/health-care-thoughts-more-complexity-grumbling.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Thus Spake the Rube</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/thus-spake-the-rube.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/thus-spake-the-rube.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2013 17:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2016 presidential elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jazzbumpa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Marco Rubio]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Republican brand]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tea Party]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/thus-spake-the-rube.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[For the hundredth time the foreign-born Muslim commie Nazi extends an olive branch across the aisle, and for the hundredth time it&#8217;s dashed to the floor, stomped on and set ablaze &#8211; along with the latest spokes-liars trousers.   It became a conflagration that the infamous water-stop could not staunch. Early in Marco Rubio&#8217;s alleged rebuttal [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For the hundredth time the foreign-born Muslim commie Nazi extends an  olive branch across the aisle, and for the hundredth time it&#8217;s dashed  to the floor, stomped on and set ablaze &#8211; along with the latest  spokes-liars trousers.   It became a conflagration that the infamous  water-stop could not staunch.</p>
<p>Early in Marco Rubio&#8217;s  alleged rebuttal to B. Hoover Obama&#8217;s latest exercise in political  theater it became painfully obvious that his pants were on fire.  This  was even before it became obvious that his diatribe was utterly  incoherent.  <a href="http://maddowblog.msnbc.com/_news/2013/02/13/16948495-putting-the-rube-in-rubio?lite">Steve Benen explains</a>.</p>
<blockquote><div>By  any sensible measure, Rubio&#8217;s entire pitch was incoherent gibberish. He  thinks President Obama is hostile to free enterprise and wants to  increase the deficit, neither of which makes any sense. Rubio thinks the  housing crisis was caused by big government, <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/02/13/marco-rubio-has-learned-nothing/?smid=tw-NytimesKrugman&#038;seid=auto">which is simply idiotic</a>.  Rubio celebrates his family&#8217;s history of dependence on government  social programs like student loans and Medicare, while articulating a  policy agenda that guts government social programs like student loans  and Medicare.</div>
<div>Forget  ideology, subjectivity, and areas of opinion &#8212; the fact is Marco  Rubio&#8217;s speech was filled with a series of claims with no meaningful  connection to reality. The senator even thinks combating the climate  crisis means asking government to &#8220;control the weather,&#8221; which is just  genuinely dumb.</div>
</blockquote>
<p>Part  way through I started taking notes, and discovered an unappetizing  platter of rewarmed left-overs [or more accurately: right-overs] of  Romney&#8217;s failed presidential campaign, where <a href="http://jazzbumpa.blogspot.com/2012/10/strategic-lying-as-political-art.html">lying and incoherence were the norm</a>.  It was deja vu all over again. Viz:</p>
<p>Obama&#8217;s obsession with raising taxes<br />Solyndra [God help us &#8211; I am not making this up]<br />We should open Federal lands to energy exploration<br />Grow Energy industry [but not renewables]<br />Lower Corp tax rate [Highest in the world, don&#8217;t cha know]<br />Incentivise school districts<br />Schools of choice<br />Solve the debt problem [As if BHO ignored it &#8211; or, more importantly &#8211; as if it were a real problem]<br />Obama created the debt with excessive spending  [my personal favorite]<br />Need a balanced budget amendment  [the ignorance &#8211; it burns, too]<br />Obama&#8217;s in favor of leaving Medicare just the way it is [though he clearly stated otherwise]<br />He also wants to unconstitutionally undermine 2nd amendment rights<br />The President&#8217;s devastating cuts to our military [Seriously &#8212; WTH?!?]<br />Moral breakdown in society &#8211; need more faith<br />Economic liberty</p>
<p>That&#8217;s  what I was able to capture as Rubio&#8217;s litany of [mostly] decades old  Republican clap-trap spewed forth almost faster than I could record it.</p>
<p>One  of the MSNBC commentators pointed out that this nonsense wasn&#8217;t  directed to the American public, who I hope are beginning to see through  the smoke screen, but to the hard-core right-wing base.  As such, it&#8217;s  Rubio&#8217;s first gambit in his run for the 2016 presidential nomination.</p>
<p>I don&#8217;t know if I should laugh, cry, or drink myself into a stupor.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/thus-spake-the-rube.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
