<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Medicare fraud &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Omigod</title>
		<link>./../../2012/09/omigod.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/09/omigod.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 06 Sep 2012 14:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2012 Presidential elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medicare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medicare fraud]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/09/omigod.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[(Dan here…Lifted from Robert’s thoughts) Robert writes: Omigod Sept 4 2012 really is opposites day.  Ezra Klein made an incorrect claim of fact about health care financing.  He wrote: But I’m not going to make that argument. I’m on-record saying that trust-fund accounting is by and large a ridiculous way to look at the federal [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>(Dan here…Lifted from Robert’s thoughts)</p>
<p>Robert writes:</p>
<p>Omigod Sept 4 2012 really is opposites day.  Ezra Klein made an incorrect claim of fact about health care financing.  He wrote:</p>
<blockquote><p>But I’m not going to make that argument. I’m on-record saying that trust-fund accounting is by and large a ridiculous way to look at the federal government’s finances, but both parties do it, and so Ryan isn’t committing any foul here. And within the trust-fund accounting rules, Obama is using his Medicare cuts to pay for the Affordable Care Act and Ryan is using his Medicare cuts to finance the Medicare program in the future.</p></blockquote>
<p>My amazed comment follows.    </p>
<p>I agree that trust fund accounting is absurd, but your trust fund accounting is totally wrong.  The balance of the Medicare plan A trust fund would be identical under the ACA and the Ryan budget.  There is just no difference at all.  The ACA did not take any money out of the Medicare trust fund to pay for anything.  That&#8217;s why it extended the forecast time till the fund is empty by 8 years.   </p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>The ACA spending increases are, by trust fund accounting (which I agree is nonsense) separate from the Medicare spending cuts (and the Medicare tax increases).  The effect on the deficit is the sum.  The Medicaid expansion and the subsidies for insurance bought on exchanges are not at all funded by any money which would otherwise be in the Medicare plan A trust fund.   </p>
<p>Amazingly uber wonk Ezra Klein is just wrong on a health care financing fact (a meaningless one I agree but you are just wrong).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/09/omigod.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Does, or did, Romney own shares in the Bain fund that is an owner of HCA (which appears to be engaging in Medicare fraud)?*</title>
		<link>./../../2012/08/does-or-did-romney-own-shares-in-the-bain-fund-that-is-an-owner-of-hca-which-appears-to-be-engaging-in-medicare-fraud.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/08/does-or-did-romney-own-shares-in-the-bain-fund-that-is-an-owner-of-hca-which-appears-to-be-engaging-in-medicare-fraud.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 14 Aug 2012 18:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Bain Capital]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[HCA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medicare fraud]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax returns]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/08/does-or-did-romney-own-shares-in-the-bain-fund-that-is-an-owner-of-hca-which-appears-to-be-engaging-in-medicare-fraud.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[During the Great Recession, when many hospitals across the country were nearly brought to their knees by growing numbers of uninsured patients, one hospital system not only survived — it thrived. In fact, profits at the health care industry giant HCA, which controls 163 hospitals from New Hampshire to California, have soared, far outpacing those of most [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div></div>
<div>During the Great Recession, when many hospitals across the country were nearly brought to their knees by growing numbers of uninsured patients, one hospital system not only survived — it thrived.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div itemprop="articleBody">In fact, profits at the health care industry giant <a href="http://topics.nytimes.com/top/news/business/companies/hca-holdings-inc/index.html?inline=nyt-org" title="More information about HCA Holdings Inc">HCA</a>, which controls 163 hospitals from New Hampshire to California, <a href="http://phx.corporate-ir.net/phoenix.zhtml?c=63489&#038;p=irol-newsArticle&#038;ID=1722510&#038;highlight=" title="Latest earnings statement. ">have soared</a>, far outpacing those of most of its competitors.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The big winners have been three <a href="http://topics.nytimes.com/top/reference/timestopics/subjects/p/private_equity/index.html?inline=nyt-classifier" title="More articles about private equity.">private equity</a> firms — including Bain Capital, co-founded by Mitt Romney, the Republican presidential candidate — that bought HCA in late 2006.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div itemprop="articleBody">HCA’s robust profit growth has raised the value of the firms’ holdings to nearly three and a half times their initial investment in the $33 billion deal. The financial performance has been so impressive that HCA has become a model for the industry. Its success inspired 35 buyouts of hospitals or chains of facilities in the last two and a half years by private equity firms eager to repeat that windfall.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div itemprop="articleBody">HCA’s emergence as a powerful leader in the hospital industry is all the more remarkable because only a decade ago the company was badly shaken by a wide-ranging <a href="http://topics.nytimes.com/top/news/health/diseasesconditionsandhealthtopics/medicare/index.html?inline=nyt-classifier" title="Recent and archival health news about Medicare.">Medicare</a> fraud investigation that it eventually settled for more than $1.7 billion.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div itemprop="articleBody">Among the secrets to HCA’s success: It figured out how to get more revenue from private insurance companies, patients and Medicare by billing much more aggressively for its services than ever before; it found ways to reduce emergency room overcrowding and expenses; and it experimented with ways to reduce the cost of medical staff, a move that sometimes led to conflicts with doctors and nurses over concerns about patient care.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div itemprop="articleBody">In late 2008, for instance, HCA changed the billing codes it assigned to sick and injured patients who came into the emergency rooms. Almost overnight, the numbers of patients who HCA said needed more care, which would be paid for at significantly higher levels by Medicare, surged.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div itemprop="articleBody">HCA, which had lagged the industry for those high-paying categories, jumped ahead of its competitors and was reimbursed accordingly. The change, which HCA’s executives said better reflected the service being provided, <a href="http://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/hca-reports-first-quarter-2009-results-61986062.html" title="The earnings statement.">increased operating earnings</a> by nearly $100 million in the first quarter of 2009.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div itemprop="articleBody">To some, HCA successfully pushed the envelope in its interpretation of existing Medicare rules. “If HCA can do it, why can’t we?” asked a hospital consulting firm, the Advisory Board Company, in a presentation to its clients.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div itemprop="articleBody">In one instance, HCA executives said a private insurer, which it declined to name, questioned the new billing system, forcing it to return some of the money it had collected.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212; <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/08/15/business/hca-giant-hospital-chain-creates-a-windfall-for-private-equity.html?partner=rss&#038;emc=rss&#038;src=igw&#038;pagewanted=all">Giant Hospital Chain Creates a Windfall for Private Equity,Julie Creswell and Reed Abelson</a>, New York Times, today
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Let me speculate here: Might Romney’s tax returns for the few years preceding 2010 show an interest in the Bain fund that continues to own a large share in HCA even though HCA went public last year?*  
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Just asking.
</p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />*The New York Times article explains:
<div>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>In the spring of 2011, in one of the most closely watched public offerings since the financial crisis, HCA became a public company once again. Its three buyout owners each sold another $500 million worth of stock, allowing them to recoup all their initial investment.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div itemprop="articleBody">Last fall, HCA agreed to buy back the stake held by Bank of America, which had purchased Merrill Lynch in 2009, for $1.5 billion, giving the bank a return of two and a half times its initial investment. And earlier this year, HCA paid out $900 million in dividends, of which $360 million went to K.K.R. and Bain.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div itemprop="articleBody">The 40 percent stake in HCA still held by K.K.R. and Bain is worth about $4.8 billion at current levels, giving them a potential profit, with the dividends they have received, of three and a half times their initial investment of $1.2 billion each.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/08/does-or-did-romney-own-shares-in-the-bain-fund-that-is-an-owner-of-hca-which-appears-to-be-engaging-in-medicare-fraud.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
