<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Bear Stearns &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Bear Stearns: The NY Fed Speaks</title>
		<link>./../../2008/04/bear-stearns-the-ny-fed-speaks.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/04/bear-stearns-the-ny-fed-speaks.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2008 01:22:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Bear Stearns]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/04/bear-stearns-the-ny-fed-speaks.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Here&#8217;s some information provided by the Federal Reserve Bank of NY about the Bear Stearns bailout: The $29 billion credit extension is supported by assets that were valued at $30 billion by Bear Stearns, which valued the assets at market value on March 14. Oh, come on. If someone other than Bear Stearns was willing [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Here&#8217;s some information provided by the Federal Reserve Bank of NY about the <a rhef="http://www.newyorkfed.org/newsevents/speeches/2008/AnnexII.html">Bear Stearns bailout</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>The $29 billion credit extension is supported by assets that were valued at $30 billion by Bear Stearns, which valued the assets at market value on March 14.</p></blockquote>
<p>Oh, come on.  If someone other than Bear Stearns was willing to value those assets at $30 billion, would the Fed have had to step in? FWIW, the Fed should be aware I&#8217;ve got all sorts of assets lying around the house that I&#8217;d be happy to let the Fed take off my hands for what I valued them on March 14.  Heck, I&#8217;d be willing to let the Fed have them at a 10% discount off the value I claim to place on them.  In fact, in the cactus abode, we&#8217;re all in it together &#8211; the cat is depositing something in the litter box as I type that I&#8217;ll throw in for free.</p>
<blockquote><p>JPMorgan Chase will extend a subordinated loan for $1 billion that will absorb losses, if any, on the sale of these assets before the Federal Reserve.</p></blockquote>
<p>In theory, this means that at least right now, JPM has some skin in the game.  In practice&#8230;  well, if it happens that JPM does lose money on this, what&#8217;s to prevent another announcement by the Fed just like this one, but with the funds going to bail out JPM, or whatever entity gets created to hold JPM&#8217;s toxic waste?  (Paulson&#8217;s guarantee that the Treasury would make up the Fed&#8217;s losses just add to that likelihood.)</p>
<p>The reason to give us at least the illusion that JPM might actually lose money on this is to ensure that if things go well, JPM will be the one to make the money, not the Fed which even on paper is taking up the bulk (29/30ths) of the risk.   Which raises the question I (and others) have asked over and over&#8230; if the bailout of Bear Stearns really was necessary and worth breaking all sorts of precedents to achieve, then why didn&#8217;t the Fed just take over Bear Stearns directly, sit on it until things got better, and then sold it off piece by piece?  Its hard to see how the Fed&#8217;s risk would be all that much greater, but its easy to see how the potential benefit to the taxpayer would be.</p>
<p>&#8212;</p>
<p>Update&#8230;  In comments, some readers object to the idea of the Fed owning Bear Stearns.  Well, here&#8217;s another option&#8230;  given that the Fed has assumed most of the risk but little of the potential upside of BS&#8217; most toxic securities, why didn&#8217;t it simply buy those outright?   The risk would have been essentially the same, but the profits, should there be any, would then accrue to the Fed, not JPM.  Even assuming the goal was to ensure that those bonds in particular didn&#8217;t go belly-up, there were ways of doing it that were a lot a less of a giveaway to JPM.</p>
<p>&#8212;</p>
<p>Update 2&#8230;  Yves Smith at <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2008/04/bear-hearings-charade.html">Naked Capitalism</a> has a post on the Bear Stearns hearings before Congress yesterday.</p>
<p>And here&#8217;s a line from <a href="http://atbozzo.blogspot.com/">Ken Houghton</a> which sums it all up:</p>
<blockquote><p>Congress has ready access to Wall Street bailout advocates. It&#8217;s only on vacation that they speak with the people who elect them.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/04/bear-stearns-the-ny-fed-speaks.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Bear Stearns &#8211; The End of the Beginning, and a Preview of the Ending</title>
		<link>./../../2008/04/bear-stearns-the-end-of-the-beginning-and-a-preview-of-the-ending.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/04/bear-stearns-the-end-of-the-beginning-and-a-preview-of-the-ending.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2008 18:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[bailout]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bear Stearns]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/04/bear-stearns-the-end-of-the-beginning-and-a-preview-of-the-ending.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I had a few posts in the past few weeks noting that whatever terms were announced for the Bear Stearns deal (and related deals), it was irrelevant, because in the end, the taxpayer would be footing the bill. The Fed&#8217;s M.O. so far has been to announce a little bit of help, then to announce [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I had a few posts in the past few weeks noting that whatever terms were announced for the Bear Stearns deal (and related deals), it was irrelevant, because in the end, the taxpayer would be footing the bill.  The Fed&#8217;s M.O. so far has been to announce a little bit of help, then to announce a little bit more, and so forth. In the end, what it comes down to is this:  someone is going to have to pay, and that someone will be the taxpayer.</p>
<p>Which leads to this <a href="http://calculatedrisk.blogspot.com/2008/04/treasury-agrees-to-absorb-any-losses-to.html">Calculated Risk post</a> that I&#8217;m going to just go ahead and steal whole:</p>
<blockquote><p>Treasury Agrees to Absorb any Losses to the Fed from Bear Stearns</p>
<p><a href="http://www.cnbc.com/id/15840232?video=699856105&#038;play=1">Video from CNBC</a> (hat tip idoc)</p>
<p>CNBC&#8217;s Steve Liesman reports on a letter from Treasury Secretary Paulson to New York Fed President Tim Geithner. In the letter, Treasury agrees that the Fed can bill Treasury for any losses from the Bear Stearns deal.</p></blockquote>
<p>We&#8217;re not quite at the end-state yet.  We have JPM paying $2 and now $10 a share for BS, we have the Fed agreeing to take on at least a big portion of the losses that JPM might suffer for that purchase, and now we have the Treasury promising to take on a big part of the losses the Fed might suffer for that deal.  In nine months, the circle closes, and we&#8217;ll start to find about the size of those losses, which in turn will depend on the magnitude of BS&#8217; obligations.  (As I noted many times, my expectation, based on cynicism alone, is that they&#8217;re negative.) By then, the story will be off the front page, Paulson won&#8217;t be at the Treasury, Jim Cayne will have a few hundred million more in the bank, and folks like Kudlow and Cramer will be telling us how things are going to go to pot if the new President raises taxes to pay for the GW-sized hole in the nation&#8217;s balance sheet or tries to regulate banks to ensure this kind of thing won&#8217;t happen again.</p>
<p>&#8212;</p>
<p>Update&#8230;  Title originally contained a mis-spelling.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/04/bear-stearns-the-end-of-the-beginning-and-a-preview-of-the-ending.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Yves Smith on Bear Stearns</title>
		<link>./../../2008/03/yves-smith-on-bear-stearns.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/03/yves-smith-on-bear-stearns.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2008 11:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[bailout]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bear Stearns]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/03/yves-smith-on-bear-stearns.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Yves Smith has a post about JPM&#8217;s buyout of Bear Stearns, that, coincidentally, says something that I was thinking when I woke up this morning. If I hadn&#8217;t read his post, I might have written something like this myself after letting it simmer for a bit: A hedge fund correspondent pointed us to an article [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2008/03/grim-outlook-for-jp-morgan.html">Yves Smith</a> has a post about JPM&#8217;s buyout of Bear Stearns, that, coincidentally, says something that I was thinking when I woke up this morning.  If I hadn&#8217;t read his post, I might have written something like this myself after letting it simmer for a bit:</p>
<blockquote><p>A hedge fund correspondent pointed us to an article at Institutional Risk Analytics on the Bear-JP Morgan deal. While we don&#8217;t subscribe to its view that Bear was &#8220;raped&#8221; (please, the firm was going to file for bankruptcy a week ago Monday), it contains an intriguing analysis of JP Morgan.</p>
<p>Differing with popular opinion, IRA argues that JPM is far from a financially strong institution. It has the highest gearing of any of the three large US banks (and remember, that includes the CDO-laden, walking wounded Citigroup) and by their measures, also has the highest level of economic risk per their metrics. JPM&#8217;s chickens have not yet come home to roost because its book is heavily weighed toward consumer business, and those problems are coming to the fore later. (The cognoscenti may take issue with their use of RAROC as another measure, but I&#8217;m not troubled when making cross company comparisons if you have access only to published financials).</p>
<p>Although IRA does not say so explicitly, the reasoning appears to be that the Fed pushed Bear into JPM&#8217;s arms as a way to shore up JPM. If asking a firm to take on a $13 trillion derivatives book, of which only $2 trillion is exchange traded, is a favor, I&#8217;d hate to see what punishment looks like.</p></blockquote>
<p>The Fed is guaranteeing JPM it will cover any losses if JPM buys BS.  That started out as a $2 a share gift to BS shareholders (since the value of BS&#8217; assets without any assurances from the Fed are exceeded by its obligations) and now that gift seems about to get sweetened.</p>
<p>But&#8230;  I was wondering, why not give the gift directly?  Why do it in this convoluted way?  My first thought was &#8211; well, if you go through JPM, its somewhat more opaque (and hence less likely to raise the taxpayer&#8217;s ire).  But the Fed could be opaque in more direct ways too&#8230;  which leaves one thing&#8230;  for whatever reason, the Fed wants to provide a gift to JPM too.</p>
<p>And BTW, <a href="http://atbozzo.blogspot.com/2008/03/efficient-markets-and-stock-arbitrage.html">Ken Houghton</a> has another collection of follow-ups to this mess.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/03/yves-smith-on-bear-stearns.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Why the Bailout of Bear Stearns Really is a Bailout</title>
		<link>./../../2008/03/why-the-bailout-of-bear-stearns-really-is-a-bailout.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/03/why-the-bailout-of-bear-stearns-really-is-a-bailout.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2008 17:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[bailout]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bear Stearns]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/03/why-the-bailout-of-bear-stearns-really-is-a-bailout.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[There seems to be a reluctance among many people to accept that the whole Bear Stearns thing constitutes a bailout. Let me try an analogy&#8230; Let&#8217;s say The Cactus Corp. sells squirrel carcasses as fillet mignon. After a few years, The Cactus Corp. is a strong business with a market cap of $150 million. Eventually, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There seems to be a reluctance among many people to accept that the whole Bear Stearns thing constitutes a bailout. Let me try an analogy&#8230;</p>
<p>Let&#8217;s say The Cactus Corp. sells squirrel carcasses as fillet mignon.  After a few years, The Cactus Corp. is a strong business with a market cap of $150 million.  Eventually, a few of the customers realize that fillet mignon purchased from The Cactus Corp. tastes very, very different than fillet mignon purchased (at much greater expense) from a reputable grocer.  After a few months, there are no buyers for The Cactus Corp.&#8217;s products.</p>
<p>Now, you may be thinking:  The Cactus Corp. is worth nothing.  But you&#8217;d be wrong.  See, The Cactus Corp., like any other company, is going to have a big inventory&#8230; and health code regulations don&#8217;t just allow it to chuck its inventory onto the street. Worse, it has forward contracts to purchase as many more squirrel carcasses as folks who troll the highways can provide for the next few years.  Which means that The Cactus Corp. is not worth nothing &#8211; its value is negative.</p>
<p>Now, the gubmint decides that guaranteeing a safe supply of food is important, and that The Cactus Corp. is an important part of that process.  So they make the following offer to the guy down the street:  &#8220;We know that The Cactus Corp. has negative value.  But, if you buy out The Cactus Corp. for $2 million, you might still find some use for all those squirrel carcasses and make money.  People do eat squirrel meat, after all, and you&#8217;re getting it very cheap.  But we&#8217;ll also sweeten the pot &#8211; if you don&#8217;t make money, we&#8217;ll make up whatever losses you might have.&#8221;</p>
<p>When that happens, shareholders, officers, and employees of The Cactus Corp. will complain because they&#8217;re getting $2 million for an entity that not long ago was valued at $150 million.  They&#8217;ll insist this was no bailout.  But the fact that company no longer has any positive value whatsoever means that the $2 million is not just a bailout, its a gift.  And its a gift to both those associated with The Cactus Corp. and to the guy down the street.  And its a gift paid for by the tax payer.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/03/why-the-bailout-of-bear-stearns-really-is-a-bailout.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
