<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>healthcare thoughts &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Health Care Thoughts: More Complexity Grumbling</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/health-care-thoughts-more-complexity-grumbling.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/health-care-thoughts-more-complexity-grumbling.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2013 12:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2016 presidential elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[healthcare thoughts]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/health-care-thoughts-more-complexity-grumbling.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt Health Care Thoughts: More Complexity Grumbling I have made the point many times that if anything stops Obamacare it will be the inability to implement an extremely complicated program. Call it “Rusty’s Theory of Complexity.” The feds have now published (link below) the draft application for financial assistance in health care [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt</p>
<p>Health Care Thoughts: More Complexity Grumbling</p>
<p>I have made the point many times that if anything stops Obamacare it will be the inability to implement an extremely complicated program. Call it “Rusty’s Theory of Complexity.”</p>
<p>The feds have now published (link below) the draft application for financial assistance in health care exchanges and low income plans. Oh boy.</p>
<p>With attachments this could easily run 30 + pages, and of course someone is going to have to process this (there will be an online version). Having helped people with paperwork for nearly 40 years I can guarantee this will be intimidating and confusing to many people.</p>
<p>Complication is the enemy of implementation. Count on it.<br /><a href="http://cms.gov/Regulations-and-Guidance/Legislation/PaperworkReductionActof1995/PRA-Listing-Items/CMS-10440.html">     </a><br /><a href="http://cms.gov/Regulations-and-Guidance/Legislation/PaperworkReductionActof1995/PRA-Listing-Items/CMS-10440.html">http://cms.gov/Regulations-and-Guidance/Legislation/PaperworkReductionActof1995/PRA-Listing-Items/CMS-10440.html</a></p>
<p>PS: HR Block has already positioned itself as a likely fee-for-service form fill-in service. Somebody is going to profit here.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/health-care-thoughts-more-complexity-grumbling.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Health Care Thoughts: The CPR Kerfluffle</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/health-care-thoughts-the-cpr-kerfluffle.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/health-care-thoughts-the-cpr-kerfluffle.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2013 13:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[healthcare thoughts]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/health-care-thoughts-the-cpr-kerfluffle.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[ by Tom aka Rusty RustbeltHealth Care Thoughts: The CPR Kerfluffle According to numerous media reports: On February 26th, Lorraine Bayless, an 87 year old resident of the Glendale Gardens independent living facility, collapsed in the dining hall. Someone called 911, and eventually a person identifying herself as a &#8220;nurse&#8221; was on the call (whether she [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p> by <strong>Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt</strong><br /><strong><br /></strong><strong>Health Care Thoughts: The CPR Kerfluffle</strong></p>
<p>According to numerous media reports:</p>
<p>On February 26th, Lorraine Bayless, an 87 year old resident of the Glendale Gardens independent living facility, collapsed in the dining hall. Someone called 911, and eventually a person identifying herself as a &#8220;nurse&#8221; was on the call (whether she was working as a &#8220;nurse&#8221; appears to be in doubt).</p>
<p>The 911 operator pleaded, implored and demanded someone do something, and the &#8220;nurse&#8221; replied that facility policy prevented any such actions. The &#8220;nurse&#8221; refused to hand off the phone or to get anyone else involved. Ms. Bayless died. Someone notified the media (911 calls are public record in many states). Ka-boom!!! This became a media feeding frenzy. The stuff has hit the fan.</p>
<p>The initial media reports, both broadcast and written, were inconsistent on the facts. Recent reports (several dozen) seem to be more consistent, many based on AP reporting.</p>
<p>This has become a debate about possible legal duties, ethical duties, the duties of licensed health personnel in a non-medical setting, the need for advanced directives and consumer advocate criticism. Ms. Bayless&#8217; family has issued a statement to the effect she would not have wanted life prolonging intervention and the family is not upset or litigious.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>So have we learned anything here?</p>
<p>1) Most of us should have advanced directives and make copies of those directives available to anyone who might in anyway be responsible for our health and safety.</p>
<p>2) Anyone living in any sort of elder care facility should verify the presence or lack of medical services, both routine and trauma.</p>
<p><a href="http://usnews.nbcnews.com/_news/2013/03/05/17199790-family-of-california-woman-who-died-after-being-denied-cpr-says-she-wanted-no-intervention?pc=25&#038;sp=75">http://usnews.nbcnews.com/_news/2013/03/05/17199790-family-of-california-woman-who-died-after-being-denied-cpr-says-she-wanted-no-intervention?pc=25&#038;sp=75</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/health-care-thoughts-the-cpr-kerfluffle.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Health Care Thoughts: Essential Benefit Regulations</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/health-care-thoughts-essential-benefit-regulations.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/health-care-thoughts-essential-benefit-regulations.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 25 Feb 2013 22:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[healthcare thoughts]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/health-care-thoughts-essential-benefit-regulations.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Tom aka Rusty RustbeltHealth Care Thoughts: Essential Benefit RegulationsThe final regulations were published on &#8220;essential benefits.&#8221; No major surprises. The best summary I can find is at:http://www.healthinsurance.org/blog/2013/02/22/hhs-gets-specific-on-acas-essential-benefits/]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by <strong>Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt</strong><br /><strong><br /></strong><strong>Health Care Thoughts: Essential Benefit Regulations</strong><br /><strong><br /></strong>The final regulations were published on &#8220;essential benefits.&#8221; No major surprises.</p>
<p>The best summary I can find is at:<br /><a href="http://www.healthinsurance.org/blog/2013/02/22/hhs-gets-specific-on-acas-essential-benefits/">http://www.healthinsurance.org/blog/2013/02/22/hhs-gets-specific-on-acas-essential-benefits/</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/health-care-thoughts-essential-benefit-regulations.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Health Care Thoughts: PPACA Health Exchange Oops</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/health-care-thoughts-ppaca-health-exchange-oops.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/health-care-thoughts-ppaca-health-exchange-oops.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2013 03:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[healthcare thoughts]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/health-care-thoughts-ppaca-health-exchange-oops.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt Health Care Thoughts: PPACA Health Exchange Oops On March 1, 2013 employers were supposed to notify employees in writing of information relating to the health insurance exchanges, including a 1) description of services, 2) employee eligibility for a premium tax credit IF the employee purchases an exchange insurance product, and [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt</p>
<p>Health Care Thoughts: PPACA Health Exchange Oops</p>
<p>On March 1, 2013 employers were supposed to notify employees in writing of information relating to the health insurance exchanges, including a 1) description of services, 2) employee eligibility for a premium tax credit IF the employee purchases an exchange insurance product, and 3) the downside of the employee purchasing through the exchange.</p>
<p>On January 24<sup>th</sup> the Department of Labor announced the suspension of the notice rule, because there is very little guidance currently available, as the feds are behind on implementation actions and exchanges are still in a confused infancy.</p>
<p>It is possible the DOL will require the notices to be issued in late summer or fall, ahead of an October (?) startup.</p>
<p>I am now putting the probability of a major delay of exchange start ups at 30%. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/health-care-thoughts-ppaca-health-exchange-oops.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Healthcare Reform; Socialism or Fascism?</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/healthcare-reform-socialism-or-fascism.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/healthcare-reform-socialism-or-fascism.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 20 Jan 2013 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[health care reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[healthcare thoughts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[run 75441]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/healthcare-reform-socialism-or-fascism.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Run75411 Healthcare Reform; Socialism or Fascism? Whole Foods CEO John Mackey in 2009 originally called President Obama&#8217;s healthcare plan a form of Socialism while writing an op-ed for the Wall Street Journal: &#8220;The problem with socialism is that eventually you run out of other people&#8217;s money.&#8221; Margaret Thatcher&#8221; and added to Thatcher&#8217;s statement: &#8220;While [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Run75411</p>
<p> Healthcare Reform; Socialism or Fascism?</p>
<p>Whole Foods CEO John Mackey in 2009 originally called President Obama&#8217;s healthcare plan a form of Socialism while writing an op-ed for the Wall Street Journal:</p>
<blockquote><p><i>&#8220;The problem with socialism is that eventually you run out of other people&#8217;s money.&#8221;</i> <i>Margaret</i> <i>Thatcher&#8221;</i></p></blockquote>
<p>and added to Thatcher&#8217;s statement:</p>
<blockquote><p><i>&#8220;While we clearly need health-care reform, the last thing our country needs is a massive new health-care entitlement that will create hundreds of billions of dollars of new unfunded deficits and move us much closer to a government takeover of our health-care system,&#8221; he wrote.</i></p></blockquote>
<p>Mackey joins other CEO&#8217;s (Papa Johns, Olive Garden, Applebees, etc.) (<a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/12/raising-price-of-pizza-10-to-14-cents.html"><i>Raising the Cost of Pizza 10 to 14 cents</i></a>); who refuse to understand the need for healthcare reform, support a commercial healthcare insurance and industry solution even though both have done little to voluntarily rein in costs, are willing to penalize their employees for the PPACA, and ignore the results of doing nothing and associated increased costs. Since Hillarycare (1994), the industry has ignored increasing costs and has not provided solutions to mitigate them. As shown in Figure 1 annual healthcare cost has grown much faster than inflation. Figure 4 shows the increase in House hold expenditures since 1994 when Hillarycare was considered.<i></i></p>
<div><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-c-GJxlk8UzQ/UPrc-bnrVHI/AAAAAAAABbY/PtRATj7wSK0/s1600/hillarycare.PNG" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="263" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-c-GJxlk8UzQ/UPrc-bnrVHI/AAAAAAAABbY/PtRATj7wSK0/s400/hillarycare.PNG" width="400"></a></div>
<p><a href="http://www.americanprogress.org/wp-content/uploads/issues/2009/01/pdf/1994_health_memo.pdf"><i>&#8220;American Healthcare since 1994&#8221; Center for American Progress</i></a></p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Recently during an NPR interview, John Mackey changed his opinion calling the PPACA fascism instead of Socialism:</p>
<blockquote><p><i>&#8220;Technically speaking, it&#8217;s more like fascism. Socialism is where the government owns the means of production. In fascism, the government doesn&#8217;t own the means of production, but they do control it — and that&#8217;s what&#8217;s happening with our health care programs and these reforms.&#8221; </i><a href="http://www.newsmax.com/TheWire/whole-foods-obamacare-facist-socialist/2013/01/16/id/471765">Obamacare Is Fascist, Not Socialist</a></p></blockquote>
<p>In a short period after labeling the PPACA as fascism, John Mackey reconsiders his words after a public uproar and retracted his name-calling of President Obama as a fascist and the PPACA as fascism. All of this from a Liberal now turned Libertarian.</p>
<blockquote><p>&#8220;<i>The term fascism today stirs up too much negative emotion with its horrific associations in the 20th century,&#8221; he said.</i> </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p><i>&#8220;I believe that, if the goal is universal health care, our country would be far better served by combining free enterprise capitalism with a strong governmental safety net for our poorest citizens and those with preexisting conditions, helping everyone to be able to buy insurance. This is what Switzerland does and I think we would be much better off copying that system than where we are currently headed in the United States.</i>&#8221; <a href="http://www.nbcnews.com/business/whole-foods-ceo-regrets-comparing-obamacare-fascism-1B8022914">Whole Foods CEO Regrets . . .&#8221;</a></p></blockquote>
<p>It has only been since the passage of the PPACA (see S&#038;P Healthcare Indices) has the healthcare industry begun to rein in costs as reflected in Medicare, Medicaid, and SCHPS through efficiencies. Much of this is due to the healthcare industry rapidly preparing for the 2014 final implementation of the PPACA. More will come after 2014.</p>
<p>You would think this would be enough? At the same time, the Republicans are calling for cuts to the three programs to lower deficit spending; the President is offering to consider modest cuts and shows willingness to sell-out the citizens to achieve his Grand Deal. Cuts in any of the programs will do nothing to lower healthcare industry cost as these programs are a reflection of the industry. In the end, such a Grand Deal will lay the burden of healthcare costs on the elderly, the poor and the children of this nation. The &#8220;I Made This&#8221; John Mackeys of the world who became rich as a result his customers buying from Whole Foods will absolve themselves of any social responsibility.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/healthcare-reform-socialism-or-fascism.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Health Care Thoughts: Electronic Medical Record Meltdown</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/health-care-thoughts-electronic-medical-record-meltdown.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/health-care-thoughts-electronic-medical-record-meltdown.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 Jan 2013 06:34:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[healthcare thoughts]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/health-care-thoughts-electronic-medical-record-meltdown.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt Health Care Thoughts: Electronic Medical Record Meltdown In the past I have predicted the EMR focus of the Obama administration might not work as well as intended. Sadly, and many billions of dollars later, I may be correct.(The New York Times has run many pieces on this, the latest on [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt</p>
<p>Health Care Thoughts: Electronic Medical Record Meltdown</p>
<p>In the past I have predicted the EMR focus of the Obama administration might not work as well as intended. Sadly, and many billions of dollars later, I may be correct.<br />(The New York Times has run many pieces on this, the latest on the hard copy business page on 1/11/2013 – I can’t find the link.)</p>
<p>And next year we make the ICD-10 conversation, sort of throwing gasoline on a raging fire.</p>
<p>There are a multitude of problems:</p>
<ul>
<li>Too many vendor systems, making EMR to EHR linkages difficult</li>
<li>Crazy long and complex federal regulations</li>
<li>The input devices irritate physicians and disrupt the flow of the office practice</li>
<li>Medicare thinks EMRs are inflating billings, due to text cloning and auto-coding</li>
<li>The hospital and nursing home systems are distractions to nursing</li>
<li>Going totally paperless is largely a myth so far</li>
<li>HIPAA security issues abound</li>
</ul>
<p>So where will EMRs work? Based on recent observations perhaps in very large integrated systems where every provider is on the same system, although some of the front line personnel are singing the same sad songs as others.</p>
<p>E-prescribing may be one area with some success.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/health-care-thoughts-electronic-medical-record-meltdown.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Health Care Thoughts: CPA Retirement Funding Act</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/health-care-thoughts-cpa-retirement-funding-act.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/health-care-thoughts-cpa-retirement-funding-act.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 11 Dec 2012 12:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[healthcare thoughts]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/health-care-thoughts-cpa-retirement-funding-act.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt Health Care Thoughts: CPA Retirement Funding Act So I spent a part of the weekend reading summaries of the new IRS regs on the Obamacare 3.8% net investment income tax. Holy complications Batman! These rules are so complex and convoluted CPAs will spend their spare time reading yacht catalogs. Sure, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt</p>
<p>Health Care Thoughts: CPA Retirement Funding Act</p>
<p>So I spent a part of the weekend reading summaries of the new IRS regs on the Obamacare 3.8% net investment income tax.</p>
<p>Holy complications Batman! </p>
<p>These rules are so complex and convoluted CPAs will spend their spare time reading yacht catalogs. Sure, the rules apply to high earners (although not that high, e.g. a two income professional couple may get whacked), but for those in the lofty category these rules are really really messy. There are lots of really difficult issues such as S-corp sales and what happens to real estate professionals.</p>
<p>This is not the way to finance a health care system , IMHO.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/health-care-thoughts-cpa-retirement-funding-act.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Health Care Thoughts: Re-admissions, Resident Rights and Pie</title>
		<link>./../../2012/08/health-care-thoughts-re-admissions-resident-rights-and-pie.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/08/health-care-thoughts-re-admissions-resident-rights-and-pie.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 11 Aug 2012 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[healthcare thoughts]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/08/health-care-thoughts-re-admissions-resident-rights-and-pie.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt Health Care Thoughts: Re-admissions, Resident Rights and Pie  A follow up to a post on evidence based medicine&#8230;.  PPACA is putting extreme pressure on hospitals to reduce Medicare re-admissions. Hospitals are putting increasing pressure on nursing home to reduce re-admissions, particularly due to diabetes.  Nursing homes are under constant pressure to [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt</p>
<p>Health Care Thoughts: Re-admissions, Resident Rights and Pie </p>
<p>A follow up to a post on evidence based medicine&#8230;.<br />    <br />PPACA is putting extreme pressure on hospitals to reduce Medicare re-admissions.    <br />Hospitals are putting increasing pressure on nursing home to reduce re-admissions, particularly due to diabetes.<br />    <br />Nursing homes are under constant pressure to respect &#8220;resident rights&#8221; including the right of residents to eat just about whatever they want, including piles of junk food provided by families of diabetics.    <br />Nursing home nurses are under extreme pressure to 1) respect resident rights, 2) maintain blood sugar levels at the same time, and 3) document all of this at an extreme level.<br />    <br />Mrs. Rustbelt and a couple of other nurses may be in trouble for denying pie to a really, really sick diabetic (both legs amputated) who regularly sends his blood sugar readings north of 400.<br />    <br />The fans of increased regulation should think through some of the conflicts and consequences.    </p>
<p>(My thoughts in comments&#8230;Rdan)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/08/health-care-thoughts-re-admissions-resident-rights-and-pie.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Health Care Thoughts: Regulatory Bumbling</title>
		<link>./../../2011/12/health-care-thoughts-regulatory-bumbling.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/12/health-care-thoughts-regulatory-bumbling.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 30 Dec 2011 15:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[ACO]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[healthcare thoughts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[PPACA]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/12/health-care-thoughts-regulatory-bumbling.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt Health Care Thoughts: Regulatory Bumbling The people who daily manage health care services (and their advisers) have been shocked at the inability of the Obama administration to manage the administrative regs roll out process. The 2009 stimulus act contained multi-year funding for adopting electronic medical records (EMR/EHR) systems. The funding [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt</p>
<p>Health Care Thoughts: Regulatory Bumbling</p>
<p>The people who daily manage health care services (and their advisers) have been shocked at the inability of the Obama administration to manage the administrative regs roll out process.  The 2009 stimulus act contained multi-year funding for adopting electronic medical records (EMR/EHR) systems.</p>
<p>The funding required &#8220;meaningful use&#8221; and the published regulations were and are nearly incomprehensible, especially at the physician practice level.   EMR/EHRs are making progress but it is largely due to the integration of physician practices into integrated delivery systems.</p>
<p> Then there is PPACA. The first major regulatory effort were the SSP accountable care organization (ACO) regulations, and that was a disaster. Even the administration&#8217;s allies ran for the hills.  The administration has spent the last half of 2011 creating new ACO sub programs and revising regulations, and has finally convinced some providers to jump on board the pioneer ACO program. <br /><a name="more"></a>(Some of the desired innovation and integration is happening, but it is being pushed by fear of  the future economics of health care rather than directly by PPACA.) .</p>
<p> The C.L.A.S.S. long-term care financing program died in its crib. Early on Secretary Sebelius announced the program was not financially viable, and got into a shouting match with Congressional Democrats when she announced she could change the program without Congress changing the empowering statute.  There were attempts at CPR, but the program now appears to be really dead.</p>
<p> The most recent botch (already mentioned in an earlier post here) are the &#8220;essential benefits&#8221;  regulations. As described in WAPO (12/16) the administration punted the decisions to the states.   Depending on your perspective, this could be seen as &#8220;flexibility&#8221; or seen as &#8220;surrender.&#8221; We are still digesting these rules (it occurs to me multi state employers are going to freak on this).  The 2200 pages of PPACA will be backed by many thousands of pages of administrative law.</p>
<p>At the provider and insurer level these regulations are the real meat of the act. A smooth roll out would certainly make PPACA more valuable.  Lawyers specializing in health care administrative law are delighted. Consultants and writers are happy as well (I plead guilty).  Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/12/health-care-thoughts-regulatory-bumbling.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Health Care Thoughts: Quality Commission</title>
		<link>./../../2011/03/health-care-thoughts-quality-commission.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/03/health-care-thoughts-quality-commission.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Mar 2011 14:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[healthcare thoughts]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/03/health-care-thoughts-quality-commission.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Health Care Thoughts: Quality Commission PPACA (aka Obamacare) required a commission on health care quality. The interagency working group released a report late last week. A PDF of the report is here. Probably more comments after I read it in full. Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Health Care Thoughts: Quality Commission</p>
<p>PPACA (aka Obamacare) required a commission on health care quality. The interagency working group released a report late last week.</p>
<p>A PDF of the report is <a target="_blank" href="http://www.healthcare.gov/center/reports/nationalqualitystrategy032011.pdf">here</a>.</p>
<p>Probably more comments after I read it in full.</p>
<p><strong>Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt</strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/03/health-care-thoughts-quality-commission.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
