<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>municipal finance &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Wall Street’s War Against the Cities:</title>
		<link>./../../2012/09/wall-streets-war-against-the-cities.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/09/wall-streets-war-against-the-cities.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 03 Sep 2012 10:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[municipal bonds]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[municipal finance]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Yves Smith]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/09/wall-streets-war-against-the-cities.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[From Naked Capitalism: Wall Street’s War Against the Cities: Why Bondholders Can’t – and Shouldn’t – be Paid By Michael Hudson, a research professor of Economics at University of Missouri, Kansas City, a research associate at the Levy Economics Institute of Bard College, and author of “The Bubble and Beyond,” which is available on Amazon. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>From Naked Capitalism:</p>
<p><a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/08/wall-streets-war-against-the-cities-why-bondholders-cant-and-shouldnt-be-paid.html">Wall Street’s War Against the Cities: Why Bondholders Can’t – and Shouldn’t – be Paid</a></p>
<p><strong><em>By Michael Hudson, a research professor of Economics at University of Missouri, Kansas City, a research associate at the Levy Economics Institute of Bard College, and author of “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/THE-BUBBLE-BEYOND-Michael-Hudson/dp/3981484207">The Bubble and Beyond</a>,” which is available on Amazon.</em></strong><br /><strong><em><br /></em></strong> The pace of Wall Street’s war against the 99% is quickening in preparation for the kill. Having demonized public employees for being scheduled to receive pensions on their lifetime employment service, bondholders are insisting on getting the money instead. It is the same austerity philosophy that has been forced on Greece and Spain – and the same that is prompting President Obama and Mitt Romney to urge scaling back Social <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/08/#">Security</a> and Medicare.</p>
<p>Unlike the U.S. federal government, most states and cities have constitutions that prevent them from running budget deficits. This means that when they cut property taxes, they either must borrow from the wealthy, or cut back employment and public services. </p>
<p>For many years they borrowed, paying tax-exempt interest to wealthy bondholders. But carrying charges on these have mounted to a point where they now look risky as the economy sinks into debt deflation. Cities are defaulting from California to Alabama. They cannot reverse course and restore taxes on property owners without causing more mortgage defaults and abandonments. Something has to give – so cities are scaling back public spending, downsizing their school systems and police forces, and selling off their assets to pay bondholders. </p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>This has become the main cause of America’s rising unemployment, helping drive down consumer demand in a Keynesian nightmare. Less obvious are the devastating cuts occurring in health care, job training and other services, while tuition rates for public colleges and “participation fees” at high schools are soaring. School systems are crumbling like our roads as teachers are jettisoned on a scale not seen since the Great Depression.</p>
<p>Yet <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/08/#">Wall Street<img src="http://images.intellitxt.com/ast/adTypes/mag-glass_10x10.gif"></a> strategists view this state and local budget squeeze as a godsend. As Rahm Emanuel has put matters, a crisis is too good an opportunity to waste – and the fiscal crisis gives creditors financial leverage to push through anti-labor policies and privatization grabs. The ground is being prepared for a neoliberal “cure”: cutting back pensions and health care, defaulting on pension promises to labor, and selling off the public sector, letting the new proprietors to put up tollbooths on everything from roads to schools. The new term of the moment is “rent extraction.”</p>
<p>So having caused the fiscal crisis, the legacy of decades of property tax cuts financed by going deeper into debt are now to be paid for by leasing or selling off public assets. Chicago has leased its Skyway for 99 years to toll-collectors, and its parking meters for 75 years. Mayor Emanuel has hired J.P.Morgan Asset Management to give “advice” on how to sell privatizers the right to charge user fees for previously free or subsidized public services. It is the modern American equivalent of England’s Enclosure Movements of the 16th to 18th century.</p>
<p>Read more at <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/08/wall-streets-war-against-the-cities-why-bondholders-cant-and-shouldnt-be-paid.html#QQKtocbXrmYiJq27.99">Naked Capitalism</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/09/wall-streets-war-against-the-cities.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Municipal Finance and Depression</title>
		<link>./../../2008/10/municipal-finance-and-depression.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/10/municipal-finance-and-depression.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2008 00:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[credit crisis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[depression]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[municipal finance]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/10/municipal-finance-and-depression.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Ken Houghton I&#8217;ve been trying not to talk in these terms, but I&#8217;m sick, and Walter Jon links to an article in the Chronicle of Higher Education that puts it out in the open, so let us compare: The problems had emerged around 1870, starting in Europe. In the Austro-Hungarian Empire, formed in 1867, in [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Ken Houghton</p>
<p>I&#8217;ve been trying not to talk in these terms, but I&#8217;m sick, and <a href="http://walterjonwilliams.blogspot.com/">Walter Jon</a> <a href="http://walterjonwilliams.blogspot.com/2008/10/1873.html">links to an article</a> in <a href="http://chronicle.com/temp/reprint.php?id=477k3d8mh2wmtpc4b6h07p4hy9z83x18">the Chronicle of Higher Education</a> that puts it out in the open, so let us compare:<br />
<blockquote>The problems had emerged around 1870, starting in Europe. In the Austro-Hungarian Empire, formed in 1867, in the states unified by Prussia into the German empire, and in France, the emperors supported a flowering of new lending institutions that issued mortgages for municipal and residential construction, especially in the capitals of Vienna, Berlin, and Paris. Mortgages were easier to obtain than before, and a building boom commenced. Land values seemed to climb and climb; borrowers ravenously assumed more and more credit, using unbuilt or half-built houses as collateral. The most marvelous spots for sightseers in the three cities today are the magisterial buildings erected in the so-called founder period.</p>
<p>But the economic fundamentals were shaky&#8230;.The crash came in Central Europe in May 1873, as it became clear that the region&#8217;s assumptions about continual economic growth were too optimistic. Europeans faced what they came to call the American Commercial Invasion. A new industrial superpower had arrived, one whose low costs threatened European trade and a European way of life.</p></blockquote>
<p>with <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/10/01/business/01muni.html?sq=Municipal%20borrowing&#038;st=cse&#038;scp=1&#038;pagewanted=print">this</a>:<br />
<blockquote>The sudden loss of credit, one of the ripple effects of the current financial turmoil, is affecting local governments in all parts of the country, rich and poor alike. In New York, a real estate boom has suddenly gone bust. Washington has shelved a planned bond offering to pay for terminal expansion and parking garages already under construction at Dulles and Reagan National Airports&#8230;. [other examples omitted]</p>
<p>The only alternative would be what New York City did on Monday: Go into the locked-up markets and whip up demand by offering to pay investors a very high return.</p>
<p>Analysts said the dysfunction in the municipal bond markets appeared to signal the end of an era of relatively cheap money for governments and, probably, the start of an era of tough choices for communities. When the market starts moving again, they said, it will look a lot like the municipal bond market of 10 years ago, before the arrival of financial wizardry in the form of structured-finance products, which lowered borrowing costs but added big new risks. Instead, governments will probably be issuing plain-vanilla bonds with fixed rates of interest, higher than they are accustomed to.</p></blockquote>
<p>The thing is, innovations such as auction-rate securities are, conceptually, a great idea.  One of the things that got overlooked in <a href="http://seekingalpha.com/article/90168-the-auction-rate-security-mess-read-the-writing-on-the-wall">all of the fooforah about how people couldn&#8217;t sell them</a> is what the result was:</p>
<p>If you couldn&#8217;t sell an auction-rate security, you got an above-market coupon instead.</p>
<p>Which is the way it was supposed to work.  If the securities can&#8217;t be sold, they are riskier.  If they are riskier, they compensate investors and try again the next period.</p>
<p>It is, therefore, in the interest of everyone to make certain that such securities sell the next time.*  And it reduces overall municipal financing costs, enabling tax burdens to be kept more reasonable.</p>
<p>But it appears we may lose that. And therefore infrastructure projects will become more difficult to finance, and, as with the early 1870s, the question may well have become who will be the new industrial superpower—and whether we will react more skillfully than the Europeans and Americans of the time did.</p>
<p><a href="http://chronicle.com/temp/reprint.php?id=477k3d8mh2wmtpc4b6h07p4hy9z83x18">Read the whole thing</a>.</p>
<p>*There are some exceptions to this.  A municipality may have swapped itself into a lower fixed-rate, agreeing to receive the coupon of the auction-rate security to offset that cost.  But in such a scenario, the originating <s>investment bank</s> GLB-entity <em>really</em> wants to sell the securities the second time around.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/10/municipal-finance-and-depression.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
