<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>financialization &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Social Security as you know it, it&#8217;s over, forget about it.</title>
		<link>./../../2012/02/social-security-as-you-know-it-its-over-forget-about-it.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/02/social-security-as-you-know-it-its-over-forget-about-it.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 25 Feb 2012 06:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Democratic Party]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[financialization]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Payroll Taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[risk aversion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[risk management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[screwed]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social safety net]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[unemployment benefits]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/02/social-security-as-you-know-it-its-over-forget-about-it.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I caught a bit of Jennifer Granholm&#8217;s The War Room for 2/23/12.  She was talking gasoline prices and had Ron Klain on for his ideas. He is a past chief of staff for Gore and Biden as VP&#8217;s. Mr. Klain also published his thought at Bloomberg2/20/12. This post is not about solving the rising gasoline [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>I caught a bit of Jennifer Granholm&#8217;s <a href="http://current.com/shows/the-war-room/videos/fired-up-gas-prices-are-soaring-but-who-should-take-the-blame">The War Room for 2/23/12.</a>  She was talking gasoline prices and had Ron Klain on for his ideas.  He is a past chief of staff for Gore and Biden as VP&#8217;s.  Mr. Klain also published <a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2012-02-21/defusing-political-peril-of-surging-gas-prices-commentary-by-ron-klain.html">his thought at Bloomberg2/20/12</a>.    </div>
<div></div>
<div>This post is not about solving the rising gasoline costs.  This post is about the further screwing of the 99% by further reducing their security from the risk of life and living.   </div>
<div></div>
<div>Let&#8217;s cut to the chase: </div>
<div></div>
<blockquote><div>One idea might be a “pocketbook protection” plan, which would work as follows: If the average price of gas exceeds $4 a gallon, an additional, automatic payroll tax cut of 1 percent would kick in, as much as $50 per month, per person. The cut would stay in place for at least 90 days; it would disappear when the price fell below $4.00 per gallon.  </div>
<div></div>
<div>There are three advantages to this approach. First, because the plan is of limited duration and is capped at $50 a month, its cost is relatively modest &#8212; about $5 billion a month, or $20 billion total, assuming the usual four-month gas-price surge. Second, because it isn’t a reduction in gas taxes, it doesn’t weaken any incentives for fuel conservation or efficiency: All workers get $50 to soften the blow of higher gas prices, but the less fuel they use, the more money they save. And third, the relief provides the greatest relative help to lower-income workers who need gas to commute and feel the price pinch the hardest. </div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div>I have to assume our Colberly&#8217;s head has just popped.  What Mr. Klain has proposed is the exact danger  many have warned about regarding the use of SS as a means to make up for what is a major functional problem of our current economy:<i> lack of share of income to the masses. </i>  </div>
<div></div>
<p><a name="more"></a>
<div>I have pointed out many times that we can not make up for the $1.1 to $1.4 trillion per year of income no longer in the hands of the 99% that is in the hands of the 1% with tax reductions.  It can not be done. With that fact, considering taxation reduction in any form as a method to address this specific issue is nothing more than the continuation of the false economy that financialization created as observed from the position of those in the labor part of the economy.  It quite literally is the government now using the mathematical gymnastics pioneered by Wall Street to trick the masses into believing that home equity was the same as earned income.  Getting a tax cut anywhere is not the same as receiving a greater share of the nation&#8217;s income.  It is money, by the way, that you are more than justified to receive because you helped to create it.  The rich used to have an opportunity to relearn this lesson every time there was a major strike, say the NY City trash collectors going on strike.    </div>
<div></div>
<div>People,  I hope we have learned that one&#8217;s home, your house has a more important roll to play in your life other than that of asset appreciation.  The home is one of the foundations used to reduce the risk of living, of having a life: shelter.  Social Security is another one of those life&#8217;s risk reducing foundations: longevity.  I have asked often here: How many times to do we have to relearn a lesson?</div>
<div></div>
<div> </div>
<div>Using SS as a means to offset the results created over the long term from bad policy is the polluting of a very good policy.  We can look at the housing crisis as another already experienced pollution.  The good policy was promoting home ownership.  The bad policy was setting up an economy that changed the perception of home ownership from a life risk reduction activity to an asset building activity.  Now that SS  has been used once as a solution to an unrelated problem and extended once in a manor that moves it further from the original purpose (reduction of risk of living), with Mr. Klain&#8217;s proposal, the use of SS as a back stop for non-related policy results has become an unquestioned and considered reasonable use.   </div>
<div></div>
<div>Mr. Klain&#8217;s proposal so exemplifies what our politico&#8217;s now consider acceptable for SS&#8217;s use that he even proposes to pay for it via a general funding solution: </div>
<div></div>
<blockquote><div>The plan could be almost entirely paid for with a modest, no-loopholes surcharge on corporate taxes on profit derived from the higher gas prices. The administration would be able to avoid pejorative terms such as “windfall” or “excess” profit tax, because the tax is neither confiscatory nor punitive. With higher gas prices, oil companies will make record profit &#8212; and a partial surcharge will still leave that profit at record high levels. In other words, the plan isn’t vulnerable to suggestions of creeping, soak-the-rich redistribution. It would leave in place all incentives for oil companies to increase production, do more research and development, and explore alternative fuels. But a modest surcharge would help fund at least a partial pocketbook protection program to make sure the cost of the oil companies’ gain isn’t excessive pain for the rest of us.  </div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div>Just to be clear, that Mr. Klain proposes using SS for anything other than SS is the problem.  The only difference in such action compared to the housing crisis which was tied to the removal of specific banking regulation is that it took us 10 year or so to experience<a href="http://draft.blogger.com/goog_1597648086"> the warning of Senator Byron Dorgan.</a></div>
<p><a href="http://billmoyers.com/content/a-senators-prophetic-words-then-and-now/"></a>
<div></div>
<div>For those warning about the proverbial slippery slope phenomenon of using SS as a back stop for bad policy results leading to furthering the destruction of SS,  it&#8217;s only been about 3 years since this application of SS first became a reality.  This use is now acceptable.  Social Security has now officially been changed from a purpose specific funded program to an general revenue program.  The establishment is so comfortable within this frame of use for SS we get a proposal such as Mr. Klain&#8217;s.    We also have on the record a warning in the vein of Senator Dorgan&#8217;s <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/02/17/payroll-tax-cut-tom-harkin_n_1284334.html"> from Senator Harkin</a>:   </div>
<div></div>
<blockquote><div>&#8220;This Congress will be making a grave mistake &#8212; a grave mistake &#8212; and reinforcing a dangerous precedent,&#8221; Harkin said in a dramatic Senate floor speech late Thursday.</div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div>Mr. Klain freely proposing another application of a SS tax cut is proof of the truth to Senator Harkin&#8217;s warning.  The precedent stands.  It is &#8220;codified&#8221;.    And, with this precedent the conservative/monied movement has neutralized another barrier protecting SS and it&#8217;s status as the end-all be-all of the New Deal: the Democratic Party.    </div>
<div></div>
<div>The Movement has also successfully completed the instillation of it&#8217;s virus known as Financialization into the nervous system of our government.  Social Security no longer thinks as the mind of one living in a labor economy; as the 99%.   It thinks as the mind of one living in a money from money economy; as the 1%.</div>
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/02/social-security-as-you-know-it-its-over-forget-about-it.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Update: Real world business</title>
		<link>./../../2009/07/update-real-world-business.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/07/update-real-world-business.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2009 18:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[business]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[financialization]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[floral business]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[flower shop]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/07/update-real-world-business.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by divorced one like Bush Time for an update on real world business. I posted back in 12/08 about the costs of a flower shop being in a wire service. The costs should matter, as it is what happens when one buys on line from a non-real florist. It is also a lesson as to [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by divorced one like Bush</p>
<p>Time for an update on real world business.  I posted back <a href="http://angrybear.blogspot.com/2008/12/real-world-business-for-economic-buffs.html">in 12/08</a> about the costs of a flower shop being in a wire service.  The costs should matter, as it is what happens when one buys on line from a non-real florist.  It is also a lesson as to what a real small business is dealing with.  Sales are off 25% for the year on top of 8% for last year.</p>
<p>This morning my sweetie stated that &#8220;they&#8221; are screwing up health care for us.  Her concern was that we would now have to be offering insurance for our employees.  I informed her that the cut off was 25 employees.  We are safe regarding this issue.  Unfortunately, nothing proposed will help with our health care costs (currently $7800for insurance and $4028 out of pocket with an additional $3500 still owed to the hospital and the need for cataract surgery and about $1500 in dental for the daughter).</p>
<p>So, here is what has happened regarding the wire service aspect of our business.<br />June&#8217;s Teleflora statement.<br />Total value of in and out orders: $974.78</p>
<p>Processing costs (membership, Dove, Quality program, Sending fee): $301.15<br />Advertising (directory, Co-op): $206.00<br />Publications: $3.75<br />Commissions due (orders in 27%, orders out 80%): $455.46<br />Total paid to Teleflora: $966.36</p>
<p>Balance of order value &#8211; costs: $8.42</p>
<p>Total value of orders to be filled: $614.78  That is, I had $8.42 to work with to fill orders that valued $614.78.  In a nutshell, this is how it is that bigger business have via financialization, sucked money up hill from the smaller business.</p>
<p>Percent of order value out to orders in 59% June 09.  (Year to date: 50%,  Last year to date: 60%)<br />Compared last year to date incoming value down 14%, outgoing value down 42%.</p>
<p>I can&#8217;t convince the sweetie to drop at least one of the wire services as she sees it as work and thus a cash flow perspective verses an accrual.  Overall regarding our net profit as of the end of the first half of the year, (you know, money in the pocket) on a cash flow basis, we are off 43.9% on an accrual basis we are off 88.1.  Far cry from Goldman Sachs No?  </p>
<p>And, we are now in the slow period of the flower business cycle.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/07/update-real-world-business.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
