<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Detroit &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Detroit Update</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/detroit-update.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/detroit-update.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2013 12:22:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Detroit]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/detroit-update.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt Detroit Update Today Former Mayor Kwame Kilpatrick was convicted in federal court of 24 felony courts of racketeering, extortion, mail fraud, bribery and tax evasion. His chief henchman contractor Bobby Ferguson was convicted of 9 counts of racketeering and bribery.Kilpatrick&#8217;s father was convicted of one count of tax evasion but the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt</p>
<p> Detroit Update</p>
<p> Today Former Mayor Kwame Kilpatrick was convicted in federal court of 24 felony courts of racketeering, extortion, mail fraud, bribery and tax evasion.</p>
<p>His chief henchman contractor Bobby Ferguson was convicted of 9 counts of racketeering and bribery.<br />Kilpatrick&#8217;s father was convicted of one count of tax evasion but the jury did not find him guilty on three extortion and bribery counts.</p>
<p>Jurors from the diverse jury expressed disgust after listening to and watching an immense amount of evidence.<br />Probably the biggest damage is that while Kilpatrick was running his criminal enterprise the City of Detroit was left to deteriorate and drift.</p>
<p>The next target of federal prosecutors may be Wayne County executives, perhaps including County Executive Robert Ficano.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/detroit-update.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Tragedy of Detroit</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/the-tragedy-of-detroit.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/the-tragedy-of-detroit.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2013 14:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Detroit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rusty]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/the-tragedy-of-detroit.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt The Tragedy of DetroitOne of the great highlights of my life was my first visit to Detroit in 1962. I fell in love with the metropolis and of course the Detroit Tigers. This week the governor of Michigan will appoint an emergency financial manager for Detroit, if anyone will take [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt</p>
<p><strong>The Tragedy of Detroit</strong><br /><strong><br /></strong>One of the great highlights of my life was my first visit to Detroit in 1962. I fell in love with the metropolis and of course the Detroit Tigers. </p>
<p>This week the governor of Michigan will appoint an emergency financial manager for Detroit, if anyone will take the job. Even the left-leaning Detroit Free Press is on board with a takeover. The alternative would be a Chapter 9 bankruptcy filing.</p>
<p>Detroit has probably been bankrupt for a long time, but no one really knows. The City of Detroit, the Detroit Water and Sewer department, the Detroit pension plans, and the Wayne County government are all a mess. About sixty square miles of the city have been largely abandoned.</p>
<p>Detroit has been hit hard by economic deterioration and middle class flight (more than just white flight), but the core problem in Detroit is four decades of gross mismanagement and rampant corruption.<br />Both the Bush and Obama administrations have attacked the corruption, and to Obama&#8217;s credit he redoubled the efforts to put Detroit officials and cronies in prison where they belong.</p>
<p>Why were huge obvious problems allowed to fester until Detroit is ready to collapse?</p>
<p>Political correctness and race politics. Even as Detroit is on the brink, race baiting is in full throat. And attempts to blame the GOP, although I can&#8217;t find any elected Republicans in major Detroit offices for at least two decades.</p>
<p>The people living in Detroit will continue to suffer for a long, long time.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/the-tragedy-of-detroit.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Opportunities in Detroit?</title>
		<link>./../../2010/12/opportunities-in-detroit.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/12/opportunities-in-detroit.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 18 Dec 2010 00:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Detroit]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/12/opportunities-in-detroit.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt Opportunities in Detroit? Detroit has lost about 60% of its population since the 1950s peak of about 2 million. About 50 square miles of Detroit is so thinly populated that the Mayor wants to pay for people to move to more densely populated neighborhoods so the area can be abandoned [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by <strong>Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt</strong></p>
<p><strong>Opportunities in Detroit?</strong></p>
<p>Detroit has lost about 60% of its population since the 1950s peak of about 2 million.</p>
<p>About 50 square miles of Detroit is so thinly populated that the Mayor wants to pay for people to move to more densely populated neighborhoods so the area can be abandoned for municipal services. No trash pick up, no police patrols. The first and second ring of suburbs are facing much of the same plight, and some may be headed for bankruptcy..</p>
<p>One idea for reclamation is urban farming, but that assumes people will not move into Detroit any time soon.</p>
<p>So does the 50 square miles provide us with an opportunity? New neighborhoods? New types of communities? A special immigration zone? Homesteading by young people?  Entrepreneurial zones?  If so, where do we get the money (Detroit and Michigan both being in various stages of broke)? Who leads the charge?</p>
<p>This is a country full of smart people. We should be able to think of something creative here.</p>
<p>Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/12/opportunities-in-detroit.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
