<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Reid J. Epstein &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Killing Mitt Softly: His Not Being In a Position To show Leadership By Persuading Rightwing Republicans to Agree to Their Own Policy Proposals</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/killing-mitt-softly-his-not-being-in-a-position-to-show-leadership-by-persuading-rightwing-republicans-to-agree-to-their-own-policy-proposals.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/killing-mitt-softly-his-not-being-in-a-position-to-show-leadership-by-persuading-rightwing-republicans-to-agree-to-their-own-policy-proposals.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2013 16:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Ann Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Annie Lowrey]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chris Wallace]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Fox News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[leadership]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politico]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reid J. Epstein]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The New York Times]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the sequester]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the Tea Party]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/killing-mitt-softly-his-not-being-in-a-position-to-show-leadership-by-persuading-rightwing-republicans-to-agree-to-their-own-policy-proposals.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Both Romneys said he would be more effective at navigating the current political moment. “I’ll look at what’s happening right now, I wish I were there,” Mitt Romney said. “It kills me not to be there, not to be in the White House doing what needs to be done. The president is the leader of [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">Both Romneys said he would be more effective at navigating the current political moment.</p>
</div>
<div dir="ltr">“I’ll look at what’s happening right now, I wish I were there,” Mitt Romney said. “It kills me not to be there, not to be in the White House doing what needs to be done. The president is the leader of the nation. The president brings people together, does the deals, does the trades, knocks the heads together; the president leads. And — and I don’t see that kind of — of leadership happening right now.”</p>
</div>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://www.politico.com/story/2013/03/mitt-romney-it-kills-me-not-to-be-president-88332.html#ixzz2Ma3DAStm">Mitt Romney: &#8216;It kills me&#8217; not to be president</a>, Reid J. Epstein, Politico, this morning, reporting on Mitt and Ann Romney&#8217;s recorded interview with fox News&#8217; Chris Wallace,* aired yesterday</div>
<p>Seriously, Mitt?  <i>Seriously</i>?  </p>
<p>You ran on a Tea Party fiscal agenda of lowering tax rates by 20%&#8211;a <i>huge</i> tax break for the wealthy&#8211;and increasing defense spending, and absolutely gutting social-safety-net spending.  You chose as your running mate the very architect of most of this fiscal plan, the exceptions being the across-the-board 20% tax cuts and the increased defense spending, although the tax cuts, if not the increased defense spending, would probably be an easy sell to the Tea Party folks.  And you claim that your superior <i>leadership</i> <i>skills</i> would enable you to persuade the Republican congressional delegation to agree, grudgingly, of course, to go along with this?</p>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />Yes, it would be a tough, uphill battle.  But onward, Mormon soldier.  Especially one with leadership skills.</p>
<p>The easier part, I guess, would be persuading the Senate Democrats to go along with this, by throwing them a bone or two&#8211;e.g., I’ll agree to not completely gut the Medicaid subsidies to elderly nursing home residents, since many nursing home owners vote Republican, and I’ll persuade the Tea Party legislators to give in on that!&#8211;and by reminding them that we just held an election that amounted to a referendum on my proposed fiscal plan versus the Democrats’ fiscal plan, and I won.  </p>
<p>And by reminding the Dem senators who are up for reelection in 2014 that their electoral “district,” unlike the House members’ districts, can’t be gerrymandered.  Not without changing the boundaries of your state, anyway, which might be hard to do.</p>
<p>And, well, since the Dem senators aren’t, y’know, <i>Republican</i> senators, much less Republican House members, they would understand that in fact we did just have an electoral referendum on these very issues.  And they would have enough respect for the concept of democracy to agree to compromise somewhat.</p>
<p>Elsewhere in that interview, Romney attributed his loss to the 47% videotape and to a wholesale (my word; not his) rejection by racial minorities.  Which he was tremendously effective in navigating as part of the current political moment when, a week after the election, when he no longer was soliciting campaign contributions from very wealthy Republicans but was instead apologizing to the ones who donated generously, he effectively reiterated his hostility and condescension toward both the 47% and racial minorities by attributing his loss to minorities&#8211;mainly Hispanics&#8211;who were eager for the gifts (his word; not mine) Obama was giving them, especially the gift of “free” healthcare, through Obamacare. </p>
<p>Yup, that’s what made the difference in the election.  Not a rejection of the Tea Party/Ryan/Romney fiscal plan, but gifts to Hispanics via Obamacare.   </p>
<p>Cluelessness continues to be a hallmark of Romney’s better half, as well.  Wife Ann, not to be outdone by her husband in missing the message of this election&#8211;that, by about five million votes in the presidential election. about one and one-half million votes in congressional elections, and by a clear majority in Senate elections, as well, the electorate rejected what Romney says his leadership as president would lead to&#8211;said all that was necessary for her husband to have won was for the public to learn how kind he is to members of his church, and to others he knows personally, when they need some kindnesses. </p>
<p>Really, Ann?  You really think that? </p>
<p>In an article today in the New York Times titled <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/03/04/us/politics/poor-face-most-pain-as-automatic-budget-cuts-take-effect.html?partner=rss&#038;emc=rss&#038;src=ig&#038;_r=0%20As">As Automatic Budget Cuts Go Into Effect, Poor May Be Hit Particularly Hard</a>, Times reporter Annie Lowrey reports that federal housing vouchers, including to many disabled people, in New York City and Seattle and other high-rent cities, are about to be cut off, as are federal financial assistance to homeless shelters.  But few of the people, at least outside Utah, who will be affected are members of Romney’s church or know him personally.  So neither Romney’s kindnesses in his personal life nor his leadership skills as president, had he won the election, would have helped them, although his wife fails to understand this.  </p>
<p>The fact is that Romney is not in the White House because a majority of the electorate <i>disagrees with him, </i>and with the Tea Party<i>, </i>about what needs to be done.  We do nonetheless await with bated breath his more effective navigation of the current political moment.  Assisted by wife Ann, his navigator. </p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />*CORRECTION: This post originally said the interview was with NBC&#8217;s David Gregory.  My sincere apology, NBC and Mr. Gregory.  Obviously, I didn&#8217;t watch the interview; I just read about it.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/killing-mitt-softly-his-not-being-in-a-position-to-show-leadership-by-persuading-rightwing-republicans-to-agree-to-their-own-policy-proposals.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
