<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Obamacare. Beverly Mann &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Can Your State Mandate That You Buy Broccoli or Join a Gym? (And why the excoriation of Donald Verrilli is misplaced)</title>
		<link>./../../2012/03/can-your-state-mandate-that-you-buy-broccoli-or-join-a-gym-and-why-the-excoriation-of-donald-verrilli-is-misplaced.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/03/can-your-state-mandate-that-you-buy-broccoli-or-join-a-gym-and-why-the-excoriation-of-donald-verrilli-is-misplaced.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 30 Mar 2012 20:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Anthony Kennedy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Donald Verrilli]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obamacare. Beverly Mann]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Clement]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Supreme court]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the ACA litigation]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/03/can-your-state-mandate-that-you-buy-broccoli-or-join-a-gym-and-why-the-excoriation-of-donald-verrilli-is-misplaced.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The answer to the title’s question—Can your state mandate that you buy broccoli or join a gym?—depends upon which of the two possible grounds the 5-4 Supreme Court majority overturns the ACA’s individual-mandate provision.  And which grounds the majority selects also will determine whether under the Court’s new “liberty” jurisprudence, Social Security and Medicare also [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>The answer to the title’s question—Can your state mandate that you buy broccoli or join a gym?—depends upon which of the two possible grounds the 5-4 Supreme Court majority overturns the ACA’s individual-mandate provision.  And which grounds the majority selects also will determine whether under the Court’s new “liberty” jurisprudence, Social Security and Medicare also are unconstitutional. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>That’s because if, for all their posturing about the imposition on individual liberty of having to buy healthcare insurance that the individual may not want, they ultimately base their ruling not on that imposition on individual liberty to choose whether or not to buy a health insurance policy, but instead upon—and only upon—a narrow reading of the Congress’s powers under the Commerce Clause, states will retain the right to mandate the purchase of health insurance (e.g., “Massachusetts’s “Romneycare”), and of auto insurance, and of broccoli, and of gym memberships.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>If, on the other hand, the Commerce Clause ground is simply the fig leaf used to segue into an individual-liberty-to-choose-not-to-buy-health-insurance ground, then the ruling also will imperil the legal underpinnings of Social Security and Medicare, because while those programs were enacted not under Congress’s Commerce Clause power but instead under its taxing power, both programs require payment for insurance—one, a retirement annuity, the other, eventual health insurance—that the individual may not want and may never use. Not everyone lives to age 65, after all.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The Commerce Clause issue deals only with the breadth of <i>Congress’s</i> power to regulate interstate commerce and the things that impact it.  Or, in Commerce Clause jurisprudence lingo, the power to regulate “markets” that impact interstate commerce.  The Obama administration, and the Congress that enacted the ACA, have claimed that there are two separate “markets” that the ACA regulates: the market for health insurance and the market for healthcare itself.  The Commerce Clause issue does not address what <i>states</i>can regulate, and what <i>states</i> are prohibited by concepts of “liberty” from regulating. For that, you have to look at the Fourteenth Amendment’s due process clause and the constitutional doctrine known as “substantive due process,” which concerns the limits of state governments’ powers to intrude into personal autonomy, personal decisions.  As I explained in a post earlier this week, it is the doctrine under which the Supreme Court has stricken state laws prohibiting the sale and use of contraception and state laws prohibiting sodomy, and those categorically prohibiting abortion (<i>Roe v. Wade</i>). <br /><a name="more"></a>
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The Fourteenth Amendment applies only to the states, but its due process clause is virtually identical the Fifth Amendment’s due process clause.  The Fifth Amendment applies to the federal government, and the “substantive due process” doctrine applies to that Amendment’s due process clause in the same manner in which it applies to the Fourteenth Amendment’s.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>For the last two years, the rightwing has conveniently conflated the Commerce Clause ground and the due process “liberty” ground, seamlessly seguing between the two but always calling the “liberty” ground the “Commerce Power” ground.  And, with two exceptions that until Tuesday’s argument seemed important, they’ve gotten away with it  The two exceptions were the two lower appellate court opinions, both of them written by conservative Republican appointees, upholding the constitutionality of the individual-mandate provision and, in doing so, noting both that the mandate provision concerns not only the market for healthcare insurance but also the market for healthcare itself, because a 1986 federal law requires hospitals that receive federal funds to treat people having medical emergencies, irrespective of whether or not the patient has healthcare insurance. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>What surprised me most about Tuesday’s argument is that Anthony Kennedy appears to have not <i>read</i>the government’s brief on the individual-mandate provision.  He seemed utterly unaware of the <i>nature</i> of the government’s Commerce Clause claims and unaware of the 1986 law.  “Can you create commerce in order to regulate it?” Kennedy asked Solicitor General Donald Verrilli early on.  Well, no, but if, as the government claims, one of the relevant markets under Commerce Clause jurisprudence is the market for—<i>payment</i> for—healthcare, then unless the ACA rather than the 1986 statute creates the obligation of hospitals to treat people who come there with medical emergencies and to admit them to the hospital if necessary rather than just treat them in the emergency room, then the ACA doesn’t create the market for healthcare of the uninsured.  Kennedy suggested that we don’t require hospitals to provide medical treatment to the uninsured, just as we don’t require someone in a position to stop a blind person about to step in front of a moving car, to do so.  And Scalia said we shouldn’t “obligate” ourselves to that.  We already have, which is one reason why the mandate provision comes within Congress’s Commerce powers.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Verrilli is being excoriated for answering ostensibly Commerce Clause questions with actual Commerce clause answers.  Especially for answering Kennedy’s and Roberts’s requests for a “limiting” Commerce Clause principle with a Commerce Clause answer.  Paul Clement, lead attorney for the challengers, is, by contrast, being praised for his brilliance in presenting his arguments, although his task was similar to that of a candy store owner offering children all the free candy they’d like.  Clement may be a brilliant appellate advocate.  But a monkey could have argued this one for the challengers, with the same effect.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Much is being made of Verrilli’s final few sentences on Tuesday—and Clement’s response to them.  And appropriately so.  Verrilli, ultimately realizing that the earlier questions were not really Commerce Clause questions at all, nor even Fifth Amendment substantive due process “liberty” questions, but instead public-policy questions, made an emotional plea that the Court respect the public-policy choice of Congress and the Obama administration in choosing to recognize a profound connection” between health care and liberty. “There will be millions of people with chronic conditions like diabetes and heart disease, and as a result of the health care that they will get, they will be unshackled from the disabilities that those diseases put on them and have the opportunity to enjoy the blessings of liberty,” he said.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>To which Clement responded, “I would respectfully suggest that it’s a very funny conception of liberty that forces somebody to purchase an insurance policy whether they want it or not.”  Perhaps.  But that’s a Fifth Amendment due process argument, not a Commerce Clause one.  And if it is upon that basis that the Court strikes down the individual-mandate provision in the ACA, those of us who think that the Social Security and Medicare statutes are constitutional under both the taxing power of Congress and generic “liberty” jurisprudence shouldn’t find the Court’s ruling in this case funny at all.
</p>
<p>[<i>Cross-posted at Firedoglake.com, front page</i>.]</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/03/can-your-state-mandate-that-you-buy-broccoli-or-join-a-gym-and-why-the-excoriation-of-donald-verrilli-is-misplaced.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
