<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>confidence indicators &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Euro Area Crisis Hits Confidence in the Core</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/euro-area-crisis-hits-confidence-in-the-core.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/euro-area-crisis-hits-confidence-in-the-core.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 26 Jul 2012 12:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[confidence indicators]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[euro area]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rebecca Wilder]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/euro-area-crisis-hits-confidence-in-the-core.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Rebecca Wilder Euro Area Crisis Hits Confidence in the Core France’s INSEE business confidence, Germany’s Ifo business climate, and theNational Bank of Belgium’s business survey demonstrate ongoing infection as the Euro area debt crisis hits business expectations in the core. Through July, business confidence in Germany and France continued to slide while that in [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Rebecca Wilder</p>
<p>Euro Area Crisis Hits Confidence in the Core</p>
<p>France’s <a href="http://www.insee.fr/en/themes/info-rapide.asp?id=11&#038;date=20120724">INSEE business confidence</a>, Germany’s <a href="http://www.cesifo-group.de/portal/page/portal/ifoHome/a-winfo/d1index/10indexgsk">Ifo business climate</a>, and the<a href="http://www.nbb.be/DOC/DQ/E/DQ3/HISTO/PEC1207.PDF">National Bank of Belgium’s business survey </a>demonstrate ongoing infection as the Euro area debt crisis hits business expectations in the core. Through July, business confidence in Germany and France continued to slide while that in Belgium rebounded, albeit from a low base.</p>
<p>Of note, the service industries in both Germany and Belgium may offer a “ray of hope” (the Ifo Institute puts it.), as these large economic sectors are perhaps stabilizing in the surveys.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/07/bus_co.jpg"><img alt="" height="376" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/07/bus_co.jpg" width="503"></a></p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Furthermore, consumer confidence in the <a href="http://www.cbs.nl/en-GB/menu/themas/dossiers/conjunctuur/publicaties/conjunctuurbericht/inhoud/verwachting/2012-07-19-m10.htm">Netherlands</a> and <a href="http://www.istat.it/en/archive/67623">Italy</a> remain depressed. Notably, the July prints increased 8 and 1.1 points, respectively, over the month – is this the start of a trend, or rather a dead-cat bounce? If I were a betting girl, I’d go with the latter, given the weakness in labor markets and election cycles coming up (September in the Netherlands and TBA in Italy).</p>
<p><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/07/cons_conf.jpg"><img alt="" height="376" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/07/cons_conf.jpg" width="503"></a></p>
<p>In Germany, the Ifo survey has deteriorated swiftly in recent months. This now brings this survey more in line with other business surveys, such as the German PMI, which had shown a more pronounced economic decline.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/07/ifo.jpg"><img alt="" height="376" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/07/ifo.jpg" width="503"></a></p>
<p>The Ifo Business Climate survey contains a wealth of information, but is generally dissected into assessment of the current business situation and expectations of the future business environment. The current environment survey, 111.6 in July, fell over the month but remains above the longer term average, 102. In contrast, expectations as regards the future business environment are falling swiftly. The Euro area crisis is impacting the business decision process.</p>
<p>Finally, as demonstrated in the Ifo Business Climate survey that highlighted its ‘significant deterioration’, the manufacturing base is leading the way down. In France and Germany, <a href="http://www.markiteconomics.com/Survey/Page.mvc/PressReleases">Markit Manufacturing PMIs </a>hit the low 40s, 43.6 and 43.3, respectively in July. This implies a quickening of the pace of contraction across the French and German manufacturing bases with not much hope of near-term relief, neither from domestic nor foreign demand. The <a href="http://www.cbs.nl/en-GB/menu/themas/dossiers/conjunctuur/publicaties/conjunctuurbericht/inhoud/verwachting/2012-07-25-m09.htm">Dutch Statistical Agency, CBS</a>, today reported further decline of Dutch manufacturing opinions in July, as manufacturers anticipate layoffs.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/07/pmi_manufacturing.jpg"><img alt="" height="442" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/07/pmi_manufacturing.jpg" width="503"></a></p>
<p>My only question becomes how much weakness is needed in the core (Germany) to get a(nother) significant response from the ECB?<br /><strong><em><br /></em></strong><br /><strong><em>Rebecca Wilder</em></strong></p>
<p>cross posted with <a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/2012/07/25/euro-area-crisis-hits-confidence-in-the-core/?utm">The Wilder View&#8230;Economonitors</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/euro-area-crisis-hits-confidence-in-the-core.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Confidence Indicators Deteriorated Significantly This Week</title>
		<link>./../../2012/06/confidence-indicators-deteriorated-significantly-this-week.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/06/confidence-indicators-deteriorated-significantly-this-week.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 22 Jun 2012 23:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[confidence indicators]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Eurozone]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rebecca Wilder]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/06/confidence-indicators-deteriorated-significantly-this-week.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Rebecca Wilder Confidence Indicators Deteriorated Significantly This Week This week national confidence surveys rolled in with just one story: the economic infection in Europe is spreading. Business confidence indicators in France and Germany declined 1.1% and 1.6%, respectively, in the month of June. In Italy consumer confidence hit another record low since 1996 of 85.3 after [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by <a href="http://www.economonitor.com/blog/author/rwilder3">Rebecca Wilder</a></p>
<p>Confidence Indicators Deteriorated Significantly This Week<br /> <br />This week national confidence surveys rolled in with just one story: the economic infection in Europe is spreading. Business confidence indicators in France and Germany declined 1.1% and 1.6%, respectively, in the month of June. In Italy consumer confidence hit another record low since 1996 of 85.3 after falling 1.4% in June.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/06/confidence_measures.jpg"><img alt="" height="376" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/06/confidence_measures.jpg" width="503"></a></p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>The National Bank of Belgium and Statistics Netherlands released their balance measures of consumer confidence. Both balances fell 2 points over the month of June. Notably, consumer confidence in the Netherlands is depressed, hitting a record low since 1986 at -40 in June.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/06/confidence_netherlands_belgium.jpg"><img alt="" height="376" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/06/confidence_netherlands_belgium.jpg" width="503"></a></p>
<p>These are highly credible indices with robust correlations with hard data like real retail sales and production. Given the precipitous decline in confidence, it’s hard to imagine how European economic sentiment will turn around without truly innovative policy action.<br /><strong><em><br /></em></strong><br /><strong><em>Rebecca Wilder</em></strong></p>
<p>crossposted with <a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/2012/06/22/confidence-indicators-deteriorated-significantly-this-week" target="_blank">The Wilder View&#8230;Economonitors</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/06/confidence-indicators-deteriorated-significantly-this-week.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
