<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>correlation &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>In Other News, Larry King is Selling Divorce Insurance</title>
		<link>./../../2010/02/in-other-news-larry-king-is-selling-divorce-insurance.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/02/in-other-news-larry-king-is-selling-divorce-insurance.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2010 16:43:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[correlation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[risk management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[solvency crisis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Big C]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/02/in-other-news-larry-king-is-selling-divorce-insurance.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Many months ago, I quoted the brilliant Janet Tavakoli&#8216;s book Credit Derivatives and Synthetic Structures: The trader then went on to tell me that Commercial Bank of Korea would sell credit default protection on bonds issued by the Commercial Bank of Korea.&#8220;That&#8217;s very interesting,&#8221; I countered, &#8220;but the credit default option is worthless.&#8221;&#8220;But people are [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2008/09/roubinis-not-wrong-but.html">Many months ago</a>, I quoted the brilliant <a href="http://www.tavakolistructuredfinance.com/index.html">Janet Tavakoli</a>&#8216;s book <a href="http://www.booksamillion.com/product/9780471412663?id=4214424925428">Credit Derivatives and Synthetic Structures</a>:<br />
<blockquote>The trader then went on to tell me that Commercial Bank of Korea would sell credit default protection on bonds issued by the Commercial Bank of Korea.<br />&#8220;That&#8217;s very interesting,&#8221; I countered, &#8220;but the credit default option is worthless.&#8221;<br />&#8220;But people are doing it,&#8221; persisted the trader.<br />&#8220;That&#8217;s because they don&#8217;t know what they&#8217;re doing,&#8221; I affirmed. &#8220;The correlation between Commercial Bank of Korea and itself is 100 percent. I would pay nothing for that credit protection. It is worthless for this purpose.&#8221;<br />The trader mustered his best grammar, chilliest tone, and most authoritative voice: &#8220;There are those who would disagree with you.&#8221; (p. 85)</p></blockquote>
<p>Apparently, that anonymous trader—or another <a href="http://nymag.com/daily/intel/2008/06/vikram.html">money-losing risk-mispricing hedge fund manager</a>—is <a href="http://www.risk.net/risk-magazine/news/1590861/citi-plans-crisis-derivatives">now running The Big C</a>:<br />
<blockquote>Credit specialists at Citi are considering launching the first derivatives intended to pay out in the event of a financial crisis. The firm has drawn up plans for a tradable liquidity index, known as the CLX, on which products could be structured that allow buyers to hedge a spike in funding costs&#8230;.</p>
<p>&#8220;The great thing about the index is that it hedges your funding costs while being very simple to trade. I believe it will reduce the systemic risk in the industry, akin to how the advent of swaps means people don&#8217;t worry about interest-rate exposures any more – they just pay a fee to hedge it,&#8221; he says.</p></blockquote>
<p>Because if funding dries up, The Big C will be there to support you!</p>
<p>I thought this was an attempt to make money on a premium, but it isn&#8217;t:<br />
<blockquote>Like a swap, the contracts envisaged by Citi would be entered into without an up-front premium, with money changing hands according to the index&#8217;s movements around a fair strike value.</p></blockquote>
<p>So the model is actually that you pay a higher cost of funds during good times, and during bad times, depend on the ability of your counterparty to make you whole.</p>
<p>When banks do it, it&#8217;s called &#8220;deposit insurance,&#8221; and it is valuable because in the worst-case scenario, the U.S. Treasury can print money. Since—the last time I checked—Citigroup cannot do that, the option is as valuable as the ability of the bank to perform in a crisis.  How did that work out last time?</p>
<p>Via <a href="http://twitter.com/alea_">my usually source for financial information</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/02/in-other-news-larry-king-is-selling-divorce-insurance.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Examining The Damage to the NYC-area Economy</title>
		<link>./../../2009/06/examining-the-damage-to-the-nyc-area-economy.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/06/examining-the-damage-to-the-nyc-area-economy.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2009 22:49:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[auction theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[correlation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[just life]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[market-clearing prices]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[solvency crisis]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/06/examining-the-damage-to-the-nyc-area-economy.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Being a seven-hour drive away, I don&#8217;t have as much direct knowledge of the NYC economy as I did a year or so ago. So I have to rely on Different Metrics. Here is one DrektheUninteresting (see #6) (of Scatterplot and Total Drek fame) will love, when he resurfaces. For those who want a contemporary [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Being a seven-hour drive away, I don&#8217;t have as much direct knowledge of the NYC economy as I did a year or so ago.  So I have to rely on Different Metrics.</p>
<p>Here is one <a target="_blank" href="http://totaldrek.blogspot.com/2006/03/because-you-asked-for-it.html">DrektheUninteresting (see #6)</a> (of <a target="_blank" href="http://scatter.wordpress.com/">Scatterplot</a> and <a target="_blank" href="http://totaldrek.blogspot.com/">Total Drek</a> fame) will love, when he <a target="_blank" href="http://totaldrek.blogspot.com/2009/06/sorry-but.html">resurfaces</a>.</p>
<p><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_wM5Pj6NF0jA/RraO_caEAVI/AAAAAAAAACY/Cywcc_i2QLk/s1600-h/Becoming+Jane.jpg"><img src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_wM5Pj6NF0jA/RraO_caEAVI/AAAAAAAAACY/Cywcc_i2QLk/s400/Becoming+Jane.jpg" border="0" alt=""></a>
<p>For those who want a contemporary view of how bad things have gotten in the U.S. economy in general and NYC, just check out the result of <a target="_blank" href="http://cgi.ebay.com/ws/eBayISAPI.dll?ViewItem&#038;item=270416271566">this eBay auction</a>.</p>
<p>The winning bid was $10,250.  The last time this item was auctioned, <a target="_blank" href="http://www.ecorazzi.com/2008/12/08/anne-hathaway-auctions-off-charity-date-for-12000/">a mere six months ago (though in Los Angeles)</a>, it went for $12,000.</p>
<p>And a mere three years ago, the item was sold, in NYC, to <a target="_blank" href="http://nymag.com/news/intelligencer/17134/">two separate bidders (it being relatively non-rival), for $20,000 each</a>.</p>
<p>Forget housing prices.  If you want a metric to judge the decline of the NYC-area economy, just consider the decline in bidding even as the value of the underlying <a target="_blank" href="http://us.imdb.com/news/ns0000002/#ni0858013">has gone up</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/06/examining-the-damage-to-the-nyc-area-economy.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Correlation is not Causation, but</title>
		<link>./../../2008/05/correlation-is-not-causation-but.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/05/correlation-is-not-causation-but.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 18 May 2008 17:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[baseball]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[correlation]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/05/correlation-is-not-causation-but.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[J. C. Bradbury notes that early-season weather and home runs hit, while it is noted in comments that the decline is primarily in the American League and some suggestions on developing a model are made. (No, I&#8217;m not turning this into a baseball blog. There are purposes to these posts. All will be revealed.)]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>J. C. Bradbury notes that <a href="http://www.sabernomics.com/sabernomics/index.php/2008/05/april-homers/">early-season weather and home runs hit</a>, while it is noted in comments that the decline is primarily in the American League and some suggestions on developing a model are made.</p>
<p>(No, I&#8217;m not turning this into a baseball blog.  There are purposes to these posts. All will be revealed.)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/05/correlation-is-not-causation-but.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
