<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Nancy Altman &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Obama ready to deal on Social Security?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/obama-ready-to-deal-on-social-security.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/obama-ready-to-deal-on-social-security.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 07 Oct 2012 14:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2012 Presidential elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nancy Altman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/obama-ready-to-deal-on-social-security.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Lynn Parramore notes the part of Social /security in the debates: Watching Wednesday night’s presidential debate, you’d have to be a crack political code reader to know what Obama was really saying about Social Security. It was quick. It was subtle. But it was one of the most telling moments of the debate. First, let’s get [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div><img src="http://www.alternet.org/files/styles/story_image/public/story_images/retirement_ahead.jpg"></div>
<p><a href="http://www.alternet.org/election-2012/what-you-need-know-about-obama-and-social-security-sell-out" title="http://www.alternet.org/election-2012/what-you-need-know-about-obama-and-social-security-sell-out?akid=9498.29972.aWCfov&#038;rd=1&#038;src=newsletter722541&#038;t=7">Lynn Parramore</a> notes the part of Social /security in the debates:</p>
<blockquote><p>Watching Wednesday night’s presidential debate, you’d have to be a crack political code reader to know what Obama was really saying about Social Security. It was quick. It was subtle. But it was one of the most telling moments of the debate.</p>
<p>First, let’s get a few things straight. Social Security is solvent. It’s America’s most successful retirement plan to date. It’s extremely popular <a href="http://www.iwpr.org/press-room/press-releases/survey-post-recession-americans2019-support-for-social-security-continues-across-party-lines">across party lines </a>. Social Security adds not a penny to the deficit. And, as Nancy Altman <a href="http://www.nextnewdeal.net/deficit-hawks-we-people-know-best-social-security">has argued </a>, it&#8217;s “the poster child for fiscal responsibility.” The program is prudently managed, cost-effective, and carefully monitored.</p>
<p>Obama could have mentioned these facts and cheered the success of a program that Democrats – and all Americans &#8212; should be proud of. Instead, the discussion went like this:</p>
<p>“Lehrer: Do you see a major difference between the two of you on Social Security?</p></blockquote>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />
<blockquote> Obama: You know, I suspect that, on Social Security, we&#8217;ve got a somewhat similar position. Social Security is structurally sound. It&#8217;s going to have to be tweaked the way it was by Ronald Reagan and Speaker &#8212; Democratic Speaker Tip O&#8217;Neill.”</p>
<p>Ladies and gentleman, that was the sound of your president offering to screw you on your retirement. This revealing exchange was followed by some politically strategic talk by both candidates about how current retirees shouldn’t be worried, because, as we all know, their votes are needed in the short term. But the rest of us? Be very, very worried.</p></blockquote>
<p>Photo Credit: Shutterstock</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/obama-ready-to-deal-on-social-security.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
