<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>going Galt &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Not many flee because of taxes…Dow Jones gets real</title>
		<link>./../../2012/08/not-many-flee-because-of-taxesdow-jones-gets-real.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/08/not-many-flee-because-of-taxesdow-jones-gets-real.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2012 22:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[going Galt]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linda Beale (Tax law)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[spillover effects]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/08/not-many-flee-because-of-taxesdow-jones-gets-real.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Beale Dow Jones video admits there&#8217;s not much other than anecdotal tales that even millionaires readily move from one state to another to avoid taxes OK.  Admittedly long title.  But you get the point.  The anti-tax gurus are forever saying that states (and countries) can&#8217;t increase taxes from our historically very low point [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Linda Beale</p>
<p> Dow Jones video admits there&#8217;s not much other than anecdotal tales that even millionaires readily move from one state to another to avoid taxes</p>
<p> OK.  Admittedly long title.  But you get the point.  The anti-tax gurus are forever saying that states (and countries) can&#8217;t increase taxes from our historically very low point because those that would pay them are the rich and the rich have the means of moving away. </p>
<p>But do they?  There are lots of things that come into whether one is willing to move or not&#8211;from weather to family to friends to business to custom to, yes maybe, taxes.   So if a gazillioinaire moves to another state and then is asked&#8211;did you do it to save on taxes?, he might say yes (he knows his views may influence policy inordinately) but it might not even have been a factor or it might have been a minor factor or it might even in unusual circumstances have been the primary factor.</p>
<p>So it&#8217;s good to see a Dow Jones/Wall Street Journal video that admits that is the case.  Not unsurprisingly (since it is, after all, a Wall Street Journal video) the title is &#8220;<a href="http://live.wsj.com/video/millionaires-fleeing-taxes/1218E40B-562E-4378-A0C7-D8107F4D24E1.html#!1218E40B-562E-4378-A0C7-D8107F4D24E1">millionaires fleeing taxes</a>&#8221; (Aug. 27, 2012), and the blurb underneath states (as though it were fact) &#8220;when states raise taxes, millionaires move out&#8221;.  <strong>But that isn&#8217;t really what the video interview says</strong>.</p>
<p>The video admits that there are no good studies that show that millionaires actually move from one state to another because of tax increases.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Yeah, elderly wealthy move to Florida, but that isn&#8217;t necessarily to avoid taxes and in fact may well not be related to taxes at all.  Yeah, there are anecdotal stories that people move because of taxes, but there&#8217;s no real proof.  The video acknowledges that there are many other reasons for choosing where to have one&#8217;s primary residence, and that manipulation of residence can create problems.  As the video says, &#8220;You can show residency in a state by living there a certain amount of time. &#8230;. You have to be very very careful, though.  States are being very aggressive about collecting from everybody and determining who actually lives there.&#8221;</p>
<p>cross posted with <a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2012/08/dow-jones-video-admits-theres-not-much-other-than-anecdotal-tales-that-even-millionaires-readily-mov.html">ataxingmatter</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/08/not-many-flee-because-of-taxesdow-jones-gets-real.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
