<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>banking &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>It is in the interests of bankers and landlords to masquerade as capitalists</title>
		<link>./../../2012/08/it-is-in-the-interests-of-bankers-and-landlords-to-masquerade-as-capitalists.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/08/it-is-in-the-interests-of-bankers-and-landlords-to-masquerade-as-capitalists.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 19 Aug 2012 13:49:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[banking]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Barry Ritholtz]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[capitalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[productive class]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rent seekers]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/08/it-is-in-the-interests-of-bankers-and-landlords-to-masquerade-as-capitalists.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[An comment worth noting on an  interesting post Where Are You in the Economic Strata? by Barry Ritholtz is the following (hat tip Mike K.): In my opinion, aspirational voting is the consequence of a rationaldedication to ethics based upon false assumptions of what is ethical.As I see it, there are two forms of income. The first [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.ritholtz.com/blog/2012/08/where-are-you-in-the-economic-strata/#comment-635701" target="_blank"> An comment worth noting on an </a> interesting post <a href="http://www.ritholtz.com/blog/2012/08/where-are-you-in-the-economic-strata/">Where Are You in the Economic Strata?</a> by Barry Ritholtz is the following (hat tip Mike K.):<br />
<blockquote>In my opinion, aspirational voting is the consequence of a rational<br />dedication to ethics based upon false assumptions of what is ethical.<br />As I see it, there are two forms of income. The first type of income<br />is generated through productive achievement that benefits others and<br />grows the economic pie – this is the symbiotic relationship between<br />labor and capital. The second type of income is generated through<br />rent-seeking behavior that simply alters the flow of money, but does<br />not grow the economic pie – examples of this include<br />fractional-reserve banking and the land increment of rent. It is in<br />the interests of bankers and landlords to masquerade as capitalists,<br />but they are not capitalists (since they don’t grow the capital stock)<br />– they are rent-seekers.</p>
<p>Republicans are people who correctly see the benefits of capitalism<br />(the expansion of the capital stock that adds value to labor), but<br />they are fooled into thinking bankers and landlords are capitalists.<br />Democrats are people who correctly see the evils of wealthy<br />rent-seeking individuals, but they incorrectly attribute rent-seeking<br />to capitalism. In my opinion, Democrats would be wise to change their<br />target from “the 1%”, which may include capitalists that help others<br />(Apple is not the problem), and focus their attention specifically on<br />the rent-seekers (banking is the problem). By using this strategy,<br />Democrats can align themselves with Republican voters who support<br />productive capitalist activities, while at the same time exposing the<br />rent-seekers who masquerade as capitalists. In my experience,<br />Republicans are increasingly skeptical of banking. They are starting<br />to get that banking is different from other capitalist activities.<br />There is a real opportunity for Democrats, but they’ve got to be sure<br />they select the correct bogeyman.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/08/it-is-in-the-interests-of-bankers-and-landlords-to-masquerade-as-capitalists.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
