<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>CDS &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Default Events, Legal Contracts, Derivatives, and Greece</title>
		<link>./../../2012/03/default-events-legal-contracts-derivatives-and-greece.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/03/default-events-legal-contracts-derivatives-and-greece.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Mar 2012 22:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[CDS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[credit markets]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[credit risk]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[credit swaps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[default]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[derivatives]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[euro area]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Greece]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[markets]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/03/default-events-legal-contracts-derivatives-and-greece.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Barry Ritholtz, who generally knows better, blew a gasket at ISDA for yesterday&#8217;s ruling that Greek bonds are not yet in default. Specifically, &#8220;The International Swaps and Derivatives Association said on Thursday that based on current evidence the Greek bailout would not prompt payments on the credit default swaps.&#8221; > Here is a question for [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Barry Ritholtz, who generally knows better, <a href="http://www.ritholtz.com/blog/2012/03/isda-suckers-wanted/">blew a gasket at ISDA</a> for yesterday&#8217;s ruling that Greek bonds are not yet in default.  Specifically,<br />
<blockquote>
<blockquote>&#8220;The International Swaps and Derivatives Association said on Thursday that based on current evidence the Greek bailout would not prompt payments on the credit default swaps.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>></p>
<p>Here is a question for the crowd: Exactly how brain damaged, foolish and stupid must a trader be to ever buy one of these embarrassingly laughable instruments called derivatives?</p>
<p>The claim that Greece has not defaulted — despite refusing to make good on their obligations in full or on time — is utterly laughable.</p></blockquote>
<p>Let&#8217;s sidebar the reality—that there is no true &#8220;market&#8221; for CDS in general, let alone Sovereign Debt CDS; Donald R. van Deventer of Kamakura Corporation has been all over this, both <a href="http://www.kamakuraco.com/Blog.aspx">on his blog</a> and especially <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/dvandeventer">on Twitter</a>—and just note that ISDA made the correct decision.</p>
<p>Greece has not, to borrow Barry&#8217;s phrase, &#8220;refus[ed] to make good on their obligations in full or on time.&#8221; ISDA did not declare a Default Event yesterday because there has not yet been a Default Event.</p>
<p>Default Event is a very specific term. The sample in <a href="http://www.tavakolistructuredfinance.com/index.html">Janet Tavakoli</a>&#8216;s <em><a href="http://www.booksamillion.com/product/9780471412663?id=4214424925428">Credit Derivatives and Synthetic Structures</a></em> (a book to which I <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2010/02/in-other-news-larry-king-is-selling.html">have</a> <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2008/09/roubinis-not-wrong-but.html">referred</a> <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2011/01/third-time-someone-will-believe.html">before</a> and undoubtedly will again) runs pretty much three full pages (pp. 88-91).  But the general concept is straightforward: there is a minimum threshold (say, 10% of an issue), the principal or interest due of which the entity explicitly refuses to pay or fails to pay that then materially impacts the buyer of Credit Protection (CDS).</p>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />Greece has not yet refused to pay anything.*</p>
<p>There is a payment due on 20 March—19 days still in the future. The financial markets—heck, everyone who runs a diner in Queens—may well believe that no payment will be made on 20 March, but that hasn&#8217;t happened yet.  And the Greek government specifically has <em>not</em> said it won&#8217;t make the payment; it has said, &#8220;Hey, take these bonds instead.&#8221;</p>
<p>It is true that, <em>cet. par.</em>, the market value of the bonds being offered is about 25% the supposed economic value of the current ones. So anyone taking the deal would have to be assuming that the <em>market</em> value of the current bonds is somewhere around 25, just as the French and German banks have them marked.</p>
<p>The market may also agree that one of the reasons people may well accept the offer is that, otherwise, they expect that the Greeks <em>will</em> default on the current bonds.  </p>
<p>But they haven&#8217;t yet, and this is not <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0181689/">Minority Report</a> (though we can all agree Phil Dick would recognize, if not approve of, the current financial world).</p>
<p>So ISDA correctly ruled—the key phrase is &#8220;based on current evidence&#8221;—that there is not yet a Default Event.  If everyone says &#8220;we will tender our securities due 20 March for the exchange offered,&#8221; there will not be a default of those bonds.</p>
<p>You, I, and Bill Gross can all agree that the likelihood of this happening is about equal to the chance that Rick Perry will be elected U.S. President this year.  But there has not been a Default Event.</p>
<p>Wait two or three weeks.</p>
<p>The thing Barry most overlooks is that yesterday&#8217;s ISDA ruling is, if anything, <em>good</em> for CDS buyers.</p>
<p>What will be the economic difference of waiting to holders of the CDSes?  I don&#8217;t know for certain, but if you&#8217;re looking at the standard ISDA CDS contract, there&#8217;s a reasonable assumption that (1) the market price of the bond will not change for the better and (2) it is a certainty that the Accrued Interest on the bond will be greater when they declare a Default Event than it is now.</p>
<p>Keep in mind: in a standard CDS, declaration of default <em>terminates the contract</em>. Accruals end, market pricing is to be determined by calling a few dealers, and the only thing left is to go through the pockets and look for loose change.**</p>
<p>Yesterday&#8217;s ISDA ruling means the CDS buyers will be owed more Accrued Interest when (in two, or at most three, weeks) a Default Event is declared.</p>
<p>What about the principal repayment due?  Recall again that the payment due is generally the net of the current market price <em>subtracted from</em> the initial principal amount (assumed to be par—100—but in any event greater than the current market value).</p>
<p>I&#8217;m inclined to argue there is optimism in the current market that will not be there in two weeks: it&#8217;s not that liquid a market, there is a floor on the price of the economic equivalent of the new offer, and there is time value in the option to convert.***</p>
<p>If ISDA had declared default yesterday—that is, assumed that Greece wasn&#8217;t just &#8220;mostly dead&#8221;****—they would have taken the current market price [P<sub>0</sub>]. Even before the delays and roundelays, that was likely to be greater than the market price of those bonds in a week or two[P<sub>1</sub>, when default is declared.</p>
<p>That is, P<sub>0</sub> is greater than P<sub>1</sub>. And since the payment due is based on [100*****-P<sub>t</sub>], the principal amount due to CDS holders when default is declared will also be greater.</p>
<p>ISDA followed the letter of the contract: the Greeks have not yet defaulted on an obligation, nor have they stated that they intend to do so.  When they do—there are few, if any, in the market who would treat the clause as a possible &#8220;If&#8221;—a Default Event will be declared and the CDS contracts will be expected to pay as they are due. And that payment will, in all likelihood, be higher than the payment that would have been due if ISDA had ruled differently yesterday.</p>
<p>And if they don&#8217;t, then I&#8217;ll be agreeing with Barry that the whole thing was a scam from the start—though I would still argue that JPMorganChaseBear stealing more than $1,000,000,000 in customer funds from MF Global clients is a bigger one, which is something like saying that coprophagia is even worse in liquid form.</p>
<p>When the CDS contracts actually have to be paid, then the fun will begin. If potential for insolvency is your idea of fun. But that&#8217;s another story.</p>
<p>*They have seen S&#038;P downgrade their credit rating, but that&#8217;s a separate issue.</p>
<p>**Obligatory reference.  It will pay off.</p>
<p>***The Worst Case scenario is that you assume the new bonds are the only value in the transaction, and discount their value back over the cost of basically two-week money. The best case scenario is some combination of the price of the new bonds and expectations of either getting a better deal later and/or post-litigation gains.  The lattice may be ugly, but it yields an expected value higher than the Worst Case, and therefore higher than the market price of the bonds as the time to exercise approaches.</p>
<p>****See ** above.</p>
<p>*****Or the other initial contract price; in any case, a fixed value greater than P<sub>t</sub>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/03/default-events-legal-contracts-derivatives-and-greece.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Is This A Bad Thing? Sane Economists would say No.</title>
		<link>./../../2011/10/is-this-a-bad-thing-sane-economists-would-say-no.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/10/is-this-a-bad-thing-sane-economists-would-say-no.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2011 15:34:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[CDS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[credit markets]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[risk management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sovereign debt]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/10/is-this-a-bad-thing-sane-economists-would-say-no.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Yes, I&#8217;m working with the null set again, but Peter Bockvar, chez Ritholtz, raises the most common objection to the Greek restructuring&#8217;s likely effect on the CDS market: [I]t will&#8230;potentially destroy [the sovereign CDS] market to the point where it will go away. The unintended consequence of what will be next will be those looking [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Yes, I&#8217;m working with the null set again, but Peter Bockvar, chez Ritholtz, <a href="http://www.ritholtz.com/blog/2011/10/european-deal-and-what-next-with-cds/">raises the most common objection to the Greek restructuring&#8217;s likely effect on the CDS market</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>[I]t will&#8230;potentially destroy [the sovereign CDS] market to the point where it will go away. The unintended consequence of what will be next will be those looking to hedge sovereign exposure, mostly banks, will then have to short sovereign debt or outright cut credit to the region. EU officials better be careful what they wish for the holders of Greek CDS.</p></blockquote>
<p>The English translation of this is that Mr. Bockvar suggests—I can&#8217;t swear that he believes, though I know which way to bet—that the current prices for sovereign debt are artificially high because of the existence of the Sovereign Debt CDS market.</p>
<p>So, unless you are trading acvtively in both markets, as a buyer, you are being charged too much for sovereign debt.</p>
<p>Wouldn&#8217;t it be better to know that up front?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/10/is-this-a-bad-thing-sane-economists-would-say-no.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>So the Debt Ceiling Delay Isn&#8217;t Affecting the Market?</title>
		<link>./../../2011/06/so-the-debt-ceiling-delay-isnt-affecting-the-market.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/06/so-the-debt-ceiling-delay-isnt-affecting-the-market.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2011 21:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[CDS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[debt limit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[markets]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/06/so-the-debt-ceiling-delay-isnt-affecting-the-market.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Alea gives the lie to that lie. Italy!!!?]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Alea <a href="http://www.aleablog.com/2011/06/15/sovereign-cds/">gives the lie to that lie.</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/06/15/us-italy-berlusconi-idUSTRE75E3BY20110615">Italy</a>!!!?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/06/so-the-debt-ceiling-delay-isnt-affecting-the-market.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Europe&#8217;s at it again&#8230;</title>
		<link>./../../2011/02/europes-at-it-again.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/02/europes-at-it-again.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 Feb 2011 21:36:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[CDS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Eurozone]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rebecca Wilder]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sovereign debt]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/02/europes-at-it-again.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Key European CDS are starting to turn in the more northern direction again, as the German-French &#8216;pact for competitiveness&#8217; faces near-unanimous pushback across Europe. Credit default swaps (CDS) are a market security used by investors to buy 5-yr protection (in this case) against default (or the like). As the spread rises the implied probability of [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Key European CDS are starting to turn in the more northern direction again, as the German-French &#8216;pact for competitiveness&#8217; faces <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/europe/0,1518,745383,00.html">near-unanimous pushback across Europe</a>.</p>
<p><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-ALLZu81DlW8/TVmUyM4j-XI/AAAAAAAADek/LeczhVBaunc/s1600/cds_spreads.JPG"><img alt="" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-ALLZu81DlW8/TVmUyM4j-XI/AAAAAAAADek/LeczhVBaunc/s400/cds_spreads.JPG" border="0"></a>Credit default swaps (CDS) are a market security used by investors to buy 5-yr protection (in this case) against default (or the like). As the spread rises the implied probability of default does too. Current market values imply a 39% probability of default by the Irish sovereign (listed in legend), 20% by that of Spain, and 14% by the Italian sovereign, etc. Cash bond spreads are blowing out again, too, where Spain now must pay a 216 bps premium over Germany on a 10-yr loan (the sovereign bond). I&#8217;d say that&#8217;s not totally irrational.</p>
<p>I completely understand why these negotiations are stalling. I&#8217;m Spain &#8211; it&#8217;s not clear that Spain commented against the pact based on <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/europe/0,1518,745383,00.html">this article</a>, but I digress &#8211; why would I agree to a deal that forces more &#8216;competitive&#8217; measures, which really just means quashing indexed wage growh, reducing the government deficit, adhering to a fiscal policy rule (which, by the way should be modeled after Germany&#8217;s debt brake), and adopting a standardized tax rate? Okay, I will if you (Germany) will. Meaning, I&#8217;ll increase my competitiveness by stripping away aggregate demand if you allow prices to rise. I&#8217;m Germany &#8211; no way. (<a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2010/11/eurozone-rebalancing-depends-on-german.html">Please see my previous post </a>which argues that a successful transition to a more stable Eurozone depends on higher Germany inflation.)</p>
<p><a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/europe/0,1518,742565-3,00.html">Der Spiegel spells it </a>out pretty succinctly in an article that is now two weeks old but still totally relevant:<br /><em><br />
<blockquote><em>Germany will only agree to additional guarantees for the euro rescue fund &#8212; as the Commission and other parties have called for &#8212; if its partners approve its competitiveness pact.<br /></em></p></blockquote>
<p></em><br />Simply put: we (Germany) will only agree to eventually bail you out if you agree to our harsh demands at that time, or you agree to our harsh demands now. You&#8217;re choice.</p>
<p>This political drama is far from over. (More exciting analysis below the jump)</p>
<p>(Dan here&#8230;Kantoos responds to Rebecca&#8230;http://kantoos.wordpress.com/2011/02/15/rebecca-wilder-on-eurozone-monetary-policy-and-german-inflation/ )<br /><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Here&#8217;s another little fact to think about: The price to buy protection against a default by the Japanese sovereign is just 77 bps, that&#8217;s only 23 bps above that for the German sovereign. This is ironic because Germany is the premiere demander of fiscal austerity, while Japan is not (to say the least) with gross debt equal to 221% of GDP (<a href="http://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/fm/2011/01/update/fmindex.htm">according to the IMF</a>) &#8211; <em>or is it</em>?</p>
<p>The table below lists common characteristics usually associated with rising CDS spreads (CDS spreads are current as of 4pm today and may vary according to pricing source): the stock of debt held by foreigners (any currency denomination) and the stock of gross public debt. The final column illustrates the ability of a country to print fiat currency that is not backed by anything but government decree.</p>
<p>I think it&#8217;s pretty clear: Japan and the US have very elevated government debt, but low external holdings AND can print their own money to finance liabilities (which by the way are in most part denominated in their respective currencies). Clearly markets&#8217; attach weight to this simple fact via low CDS spreads.</p>
<p><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-O3sbDf41WUM/TVmdfjhVXlI/AAAAAAAADe0/wNPz4mW5Dkk/s1600/table.JPG"><img src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-O3sbDf41WUM/TVmdfjhVXlI/AAAAAAAADe0/wNPz4mW5Dkk/s400/table.JPG" border="0" alt=""></a><br />To be continued&#8230;.</p>
<p><em><strong>Rebecca Wilder</strong></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/02/europes-at-it-again.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Egyptian CDS in line with Portuguese CDS</title>
		<link>./../../2011/01/egyptian-cds-in-line-with-portuguese-cds.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/01/egyptian-cds-in-line-with-portuguese-cds.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 30 Jan 2011 14:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[CDS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Egypt]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Portugal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rebecca Wilder]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/01/egyptian-cds-in-line-with-portuguese-cds.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[It occurred to me that some Angry Bear readers may be interested in a short analysis of the Egyptian bond market. Professionally, I&#8217;m a macroeconomic analyst and portfolio manager on a global fixed income team. Since we do trade emerging market debt, of which Egyptian debt is categorized, I&#8217;ll be happy to comment. The gist [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It occurred to me that some Angry Bear readers may be interested in a short analysis of the Egyptian bond market. Professionally, I&#8217;m a macroeconomic analyst and portfolio manager on a global fixed income team. Since we do trade emerging market debt, of which Egyptian debt is categorized, I&#8217;ll be happy to comment.</p>
<p>The gist of the article is this: markets are pricing the probability of default in Portugal and Egypt similarly &#8211; I&#8217;d sell protection on the Egyptian debt. At this point, I should state the following disclaimer: this is not a trade recommendation, nor does this represent my firm&#8217;s views on Egypt or Portugal.</p>
<p>Some bond market developments of late:
<ol>
<li>Egypt holds a BBB- rating on its local currency debt by Fitch and S&#038;P (BB+ on its foreign currency debt). The local currency debt in Egypt is at the lowest of the investment-grade ratings, while on January 20, 2011, <a href="http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=133307715">Fitch put Egypt on credit-watch negative</a>.</li>
<li>The Egyptian pound is heavily managed. Over the last week, the USD gained just 0.9% against the pound. Maintaining a stronger nominal currency is common in developing economies to temper the effects of import prices (in this case, food).</li>
<li>The 5.75% 10-yr Egyptian international bond, which is denominated in USD, sold off 7% over the last week. According to JP Morgan, Egypt is well underperforming the index (Egpyt is roughly 0.5% of the index): the year to date total return on the Egyptian international bonds is -10%, while that of the  JP Morgan Emerging Market Bond Index Global (EMBIG) is -0.7%.</li>
<li>Credit default swap spreads jumped 50% over the last week to 454 basis points (bps), according to one Bloomberg source (no link, subscription required). CDS are bilateral contracts between two parties, so pricing varies somewhat &#8211; but the trend is the same among all sources: up. This means that it&#8217;s becoming increasingly expensive to buy protection against Egyptian sovereign default.</li>
</ol>
<p>If you want to know more about CDS, please see a <a href="http://www.dbresearch.com/PROD/DBR_INTERNET_EN-PROD/PROD0000000000252032.pdf">helpful 2009 publication by Deutsche Bank.</a></p>
<p>And this is where it gets interesting: it currently costs the same to buy 5-yr protection on Egyptian bonds (454 bps) as on Portuguese bonds (456 bps). And Portugal is rated A- (negative outlook).</p>
<p><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_Et4TQ-a0gGU/TUVhBPk6BsI/AAAAAAAADcw/L3Cb1VPwO28/s1600/CDS_chart.jpg"><img src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_Et4TQ-a0gGU/TUVhBPk6BsI/AAAAAAAADcw/L3Cb1VPwO28/s400/CDS_chart.jpg" alt="" border="0"></a> (more after the jump)<br /><a name="more"></a>The chart above illustrates a panel of CDS data for countries with similar market risk, where S&#038;P&#8217;s local currency rating is listed in the legend. The CDS quoted above are priced in USD, rather than the local currency; but the spreads do quantify the market&#8217;s assigned probability of default : 29.3% for Egypt vs. 29% for Portugal (with a 30% recovery rate on both).</p>
<p>Generally the decision to default comes in two flavors: the &#8216;willingness&#8217; and &#8216;ability&#8217; to pay. Also, default can take many forms, like missed coupon payments, terming out debt liabilities, or bankruptcy (corporate).</p>
<p>Willingess. A quick analysis of &#8216;governance&#8217; indicators at the World Bank says that on the face of it, Portugal is probably more willing to pay its debts. The governance measures are corruption, government effectiveness, political stability, regulatory quality, rule of law, and voice and accountability. Read about the methodology of the governance indicators <a href="http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1682130">here</a> and get the data <a href="http://info.worldbank.org/governance/wgi/index.asp">here</a>.</p>
<p>In sum, Portugal ranks much higher on the total of the World Bank governance indicators, 6.4, compared to -2.6 for Egypt (I use a strict sum of the 6 components).</p>
<p>Ability. According to the IMF&#8217;s most recent World Economic Outlook (<a href="http://www.imf.org/external/ns/cs.aspx?id=28">October 2010 database</a>), Egypt is expected to grow an average 13.9% per year in nominal terms over the next three years (2010-2013). In contrast, Portugal is expected to grow just 1.7% on average for the next three years.</p>
<p>According to Bloomberg, on January 27, 2011, the yield on a Portuguese 1-year local bond is 3.42%, while that for a local Egyptian bond is 10.99%. I&#8217;ll take odds of payment on the one with nominal growth that exceeds the payment &#8211; Egypt.</p>
<p>A quick look at the WEI shows the following statistics for 2011:<br />
<table border="0" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="438">
<col width="64">
<col width="310">
<col width="64">
<tbody>
<tr height="20">
<td width="64" height="20">Country</td>
<td width="310">Subject Descriptor</td>
<td align="right" width="64">2011</td>
</tr>
<tr height="20">
<td height="20">Egypt</td>
<td>General government net lending/borrowing</td>
<td align="right">-7.622</td>
</tr>
<tr height="20">
<td height="20">Portugal</td>
<td>General government net lending/borrowing</td>
<td align="right">-5.232</td>
</tr>
<tr height="20">
<td height="20">Egypt</td>
<td>General government net debt</td>
<td align="right">60.993</td>
</tr>
<tr height="20">
<td height="20">Portugal</td>
<td>General government net debt</td>
<td align="right">82.864</td>
</tr>
<tr height="20">
<td height="20">Egypt</td>
<td>General government gross debt</td>
<td align="right">71.725</td>
</tr>
<tr height="20">
<td height="20">Portugal</td>
<td>General government gross debt</td>
<td align="right">87.086</td>
</tr>
<tr height="20">
<td height="20">Egypt</td>
<td>Current account balance</td>
<td align="right">-1.605</td>
</tr>
<tr height="20">
<td height="20">Portugal</td>
<td>Current account balance</td>
<td align="right">-9.171</td>
</tr>
<tr height="20">
<td height="20"></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr height="20">
<td colspan="9" height="20">International   Monetary Fund, World Economic Outlook Database, October 2010</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>The 2011 outlook demonstrates the following: government deficits are similar in Portugal and Egypt; government debt is higher in Portugal, a country that has no monetary sovereignty; Portugal has relatively fewer reserves (comparing gross debt to net debt); and the current account deficit in Portugal dwarfs that of Egypt.</p>
<p>If I was an investment bank, I&#8217;d rather sell protection on Egypt than Portugal at these prices.</p>
<p>Rebecca Wilder</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/01/egyptian-cds-in-line-with-portuguese-cds.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Congress thinks by analogy&#8230;.and so we are stuck</title>
		<link>./../../2010/02/congress-thinks-by-analogy-and-so-we-are-stuck.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/02/congress-thinks-by-analogy-and-so-we-are-stuck.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2010 08:22:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[AIG]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CDS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stockman]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/02/congress-thinks-by-analogy-and-so-we-are-stuck.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by cactus Congress thinks by analogy I don&#8217;t remember what link I followed to get to this, but never in my life did I expect to agree 100% on any issue with David Stockman. Yes, that David Stockman. Holy wow: DAVID STOCKMAN: Credit default swaps, OK? And we weren&#8217;t bailing out AIG. We were bailing [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by cactus</p>
<p>Congress thinks by analogy</p>
<p>I don&#8217;t remember what link I followed to get to <a href="http://www.pbs.org/newshour/bb/business/jan-june10/makingsense_02-05.html">this</a>, but never in my life did I expect to agree 100% on any issue with David Stockman.  Yes, that David Stockman.  Holy wow:</p>
<blockquote><p>DAVID STOCKMAN: Credit default swaps, OK? And we weren&#8217;t bailing out AIG. We were bailing out the banks, because the banks had bought a lot of low-caliber or subprime loans, wrapped some insurance around it from AIG, and said, presto, we have a AAA, a security on our balance sheet. <br />They didn&#8217;t. They had garbage on their balance sheet. And the bailout was to make sure that they didn&#8217;t suffer multi $10 billion write-downs on that AIG-supported loan.</p>
<p>PAUL SOLMAN: So, if you had been in the administration after Lehman Brothers, you wouldn&#8217;t have supported bailing out AIG?</p>
<p>DAVID STOCKMAN: No, absolutely not. It was the single most, you know, drastic error in policy in modern history, going back to the 1930s. This was exactly the wrong thing to do.</p>
<p>It&#8217;s destroyed any basis for fiscal discipline in the United States. I was a member of Congress, and I know how they think. And they think by analogy. If you did it for John, you have got to do it for Bob. There is no way that any congressman is ever going to vote against farm subsidies or ethanol subsidies or housing subsidies or anything else, refrigerator subsidies, once we have made this tremendous bailout for Wall Street, and we stepped into AIG.</p></blockquote>
<p>________________________________<br />by cactus</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/02/congress-thinks-by-analogy-and-so-we-are-stuck.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
