<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>fiscal responsibility summit &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Strangely, CATO missed the AZ, IN, and MS budget crises</title>
		<link>./../../2009/06/strangely-cato-missed-the-az-in-and-ms-budget-crises.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/06/strangely-cato-missed-the-az-in-and-ms-budget-crises.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2009 15:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2012 Presidential]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fiscal responsibility summit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GOP governors]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Indiana]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitch Daniels]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[solvency crisis]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/06/strangely-cato-missed-the-az-in-and-ms-budget-crises.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[CATO was making much hay a few days ago about budget problems in California, New York, and New Jersey, which can be explained, respectively, by the Governor&#8217;s veto of an Assembly-passed budget a few months ago, the decline in tax revenues from financial services firms and continuing loss of upstate industry, and underfunded pension obligations [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>CATO was making much hay a few days ago about budget problems in California, New York, and New Jersey, which can be explained, respectively, by the Governor&#8217;s veto of an Assembly-passed budget a few months ago, the decline in tax revenues from financial services firms and continuing loss of upstate industry, and underfunded pension obligations whose origins date back to Christie&#8217;s cocaine-inspired budgets of the mid-1990s.</p>
<p>Strangely (via Dr. Black), they missed the crises in a few other states, most especially including the state governed by <a target="_blank" href="http://www.latimes.com/news/nationworld/nation/la-na-shutdown30-2009jun30,0,1912245.story">Republic hero Mitch Daniels</a>:<br />
<blockquote>Republican Gov. Mitch Daniels has warned residents that most of the state&#8217;s services &#8212; including its parks, the Bureau of Motor Vehicles and state-regulated casinos &#8212; would be shuttered unless a budget is passed today.</p></blockquote>
<p>Closing down the casinos?  Now that is extreme.</p>
<p>Mitch Daniels, doing for my old home state <a target="_blank" href="http://delong.typepad.com/sdj/2009/06/mitch-daniels-did-not-do-his-job.html">what he did for the country</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/06/strangely-cato-missed-the-az-in-and-ms-budget-crises.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Fiscal Responsibility Summit: Guest List</title>
		<link>./../../2009/02/fiscal-responsibility-summit-guest-list.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/02/fiscal-responsibility-summit-guest-list.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2009 20:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[fiscal responsibility summit]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/02/fiscal-responsibility-summit-guest-list.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Fiscal Responsibility Summit Attendees: (noted without comment. Except for those of us who follow Social Security-Dean Baker made the cut) ADMINISTRATIONSecretary of the Treasury, Tim GeithnerSecretary of Transportation, Ray LaHoodSecretary of Homeland Security, Janet NapolitanoDeputy Secretary of State, Jack LewTreasury Department, Gene Sperling White House Chief of Staff, Rahm EmanuelOMB Director, Peter OrszagNational Economic Council, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Fiscal Responsibility Summit Attendees: (noted without comment. Except for those of us who follow <br />Social Security-Dean Baker made the cut)</p>
<p>ADMINISTRATION<br />Secretary of the Treasury, Tim Geithner<br />Secretary of Transportation, Ray LaHood<br />Secretary of Homeland Security, Janet Napolitano<br />Deputy Secretary of State, Jack Lew<br />Treasury Department, Gene Sperling</p>
<p>White House Chief of Staff, Rahm Emanuel<br />OMB Director, Peter Orszag<br />National Economic Council, Larry Summers<br />Domestic Policy Council, Melody Barnes<br />Council on Economic Advisors, Christina Romer<br />Deputy OMB Director, Rob Nabors</p>
<p>SENATE</p>
<p>Leadership<br />Senator Mitch McConnell (R), Minority Leader &#8211; will not join break-out sessions<br />Senator Dick Durbin (D), Assistant Majority Leader<br />Senator Jon Kyl (R), Assistant Minority Leader &#8211; arriving at 2:30<br />Senator Lamar Alexander (R), Republican Conference Chairman<br />Senator John Cornyn (R), Chairman, National Republican Senatorial Committee</p>
<p>Other Senators (in alphabetical order with Chairs and Ranking Members noted)<br />Senator Evan Bayh (D)<br />Senator Max Baucus (D), Chairman of Committee on Finance<br />Senator Tom Carper (D)<br />Senator Thad Cochran (R), Ranking Member of Committee on Appropriations<br />Senator Susan Collins (R), Ranking Member of Committee on Homeland Security<br />Senator Kent Conrad (D), Chairman of Committee on the Budget<br />Senator Chris Dodd (D), Chairman of Committee on Banking, Ranking Democrat on HELP<br />Senator Mike Enzi (R), Ranking Member of Committee on HELP<br />Senator Lindsey Graham (R) <br />Senator Judd Gregg (R), Ranking Member of Committee on Budget<br />Senator Daniel Inouye (D), Chairman of Committee on Appropriations <br />Senator Amy Klobuchar (D)<br />Senator Carl Levin (D), Chairman of Committee on Armed Services<br />Senator Joseph Lieberman (D), Chairman of Committee on Homeland Security <br />Senator John McCain (R), Ranking Member of Committee on Armed Services<br />Senator Claire McCaskill (D)<br />Senator Ben Nelson (D)<br />Senator Olympia Snowe (R), Ranking Member of Small Business Committee<br />Senator Arlen Specter (R), Ranking Member of Judiciary Committee</p>
<p>HOUSE</p>
<p>Leadership<br />The Honorable Nancy Pelosi (D), Speaker of the House of Representatives (will not join breakout sessions)<br />The Honorable Steny H. Hoyer (D), Majority Leader<br />The Honorable John A. Boehner (R), Minority Leader<br />The Honorable James E. Clyburn (D), Majority Whip<br />The Honorable Eric Cantor (R), Minority Whip <br />The Honorable Thaddeus G. McCotter (R), Chairman of the Republican Policy Committee<br />The Honorable Chris Van Hollen (D), Chairman of the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee</p>
<p>Other Members (in alphabetical order with Chairs and Ranking Members noted)<br />The Honorable Joe Barton (R), Ranking Member of the Committee on Energy and Commerce<br />The Honorable Allen Boyd (D)<br />The Honorable Dave Camp (R), Ranking Member of the Committee on Ways and Means<br />The Honorable Michael N. Castle (R)<br />The Honorable Raúl M. Grijalva (D)<br />The Honorable Darrell E. Issa (R), Ranking Member the Committee on Oversight and Government Reform <br />The Honorable Ron Kind (D)<br />The Honorable Barbara Lee (D), Chairwoman of the Congressional Black Caucus, <br />The Honorable Jim Matheson (D)<br />The Honorable George Miller (D), Chairman of the Committee on Education and Labor<br />The Honorable David R. Obey (D), Chairman of the Committee on Appropriations<br />The Honorable David E. Price (D) &#8211; late arrival &#8211; approx 1:30/2:00 PM<br />The Honorable Tom Price (R), Chairman of the Republican Study Committee<br />The Honorable Charles B. Rangel (D), Chairman of the Committee on Ways and Means <br />The Honorable Paul Ryan (R), Ranking Member of the Committee on the Budget<br />The Honorable Stephanie Herseth Sandlin (D), Chairwoman of the Blue Dog Coalition <br />The Honorable John M. Spratt (D), Chairman of Committee on the Budget<br />The Honorable John S. Tanner (D)<br />The Honorable Ellen O. Tauscher (D)<br />The Honorable Edolphus Towns (D), Chairman of the Committee on Oversight and Government Reform<br />The Honorable Nydia M. Velazquez (D), Chairwoman of the Committee on Small Business<br />The Honorable Henry A. Waxman (D), Chairman of the Committee on Energy and Commerce</p>
<p>Community Leaders and Stakeholders Also Attending</p>
<p>(in alphabetical order by organization name)</p>
<p>Bill Novelli, AARP <br />John Gage, AFGE<br />John Sweeney, AFL-CIO<br />Gerry McEntee, AFSCME<br />Randi Weingarten, AFT<br />Ed Coyle, Alliance for Retired Americans<br />Kevin Hassitt, American Enterprise Institute<br />Richard Umbdenstock, American Hospital Association<br />Nancy Neilson , American Medical Association<br />Becky Patton, American Nurses Association <br />Karen Narasaki, Asian American Justice Center (AAJC)<br />Dr. Ho Tran, Asian Pacific Islanders American Health Forum (APIAHF)<br />Gary Flowers, Black Leadership Forum<br />Eleanor Hinton Hoytt, Black Women&#8217;s Health Imperative<br />Alice Rivlin, Brookings Institution<br />John Castellani, Business Roundtable <br />Roger Hickey, Campaign for America&#8217;s Future<br />John Podesta, Center for American Progress<br />Larry Korb, Center for American Progress<br />Dean Baker, Center for Economic and Policy Research<br />Joe Minarek, Center for Economic Development<br />Robert Greenstein, Center on Budget and Policy Priorities<br />Anna Burger, Change to Win<br />Maya MacGuinneas, Committee for a Responsible Federal Budget<br />Karen Davis, Common Wealth Fund <br />Bob Bixby, Concord Coalition<br />Maya Rockeymoore, Congressional Black Caucus Foundation <br />Doug Elmendorf, Congressional Budget Office<br />Marty Ford, Consortium for Citizens with Disabilities <br />Lawrence Mishel, Economic Policy Institute<br />Ron Pollack, Families USA<br />Ellie Smeal, Feminist Majority<br />Stewart Butler, Heritage Foundation<br />Bill Spriggs, Howard University <br />Joe Salomonese, Human Rights Campaign<br />John Cavanagh, Institue for Policy Studies<br />Heidi Hartmann, Institute for Women&#8217;s Policy<br />Drew Altman, Kaiser Family Foundation<br />Douglas Holtz-Eakin, McCain Economic Advisor<br />Hilary Shelton, NAACP<br />Todd Stottlemyer, National Association of Independent Businesses <br />Barbara B. Kennelly, National Committee to Preserve Social Security and Medicare<br />Jackie Johnson Pata, National Congress of American Indians<br />Janet Murguia, National Council of La Raza<br />Marc Morial, National Urban League (NY)<br />Dennis Van Roekel, NEA<br />David Walker, Peter G. Peterson Foundation<br />Peter Peterson, Peter G. Peterson Foundation<br />Al From, Progressive Policy Institute<br />Andy Stern, SEIU<br />Fred Goldberg, Skadden<br />Roger Ferguson, TIAA-CREF CEO<br />Martin Regalia, U.S. Chamber of Commerce<br />Fernando Torres-Gil, UCLA<br />Robert Reischauer, Urban Institute<br />Michael Graetz, Yale</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/02/fiscal-responsibility-summit-guest-list.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
