<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Joseph N. Welch &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Oh. Guess the Paul Ryan Bubble Finally Has Burst. So Sorry For Your Loss, Paul.</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/oh-guess-the-paul-ryan-bubble-finally-has-burst-so-sorry-for-your-loss-paul.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/oh-guess-the-paul-ryan-bubble-finally-has-burst-so-sorry-for-your-loss-paul.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2013 23:16:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dana Milbank]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Joseph N. Welch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Washington Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/oh-guess-the-paul-ryan-bubble-finally-has-burst-so-sorry-for-your-loss-paul.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In subtle ways, Ryan’s budget acknowledges the results of November’s election. He isn’t seeking to do away with tax increases that have already been approved, and he accepts that tax revenue will be 19.1 percent of the economy in a decade, up from the 18.7 percent he assumed last year. But otherwise, he continues to peddle the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">In subtle ways, Ryan’s budget acknowledges the results of November’s election. He isn’t seeking to do away with tax increases that have already been approved, and he accepts that tax revenue will be 19.1 percent of the economy in a decade, up from the 18.7 percent he assumed last year.</div>
<div dir="ltr">But otherwise, he continues to peddle the same ideas: the partial privatization of Medicare; a 10 percent reduction in the federal workforce; and cuts to Medicaid, food stamps, education, job training and farm programs.</div>
<div dir="ltr">Public Radio International’s Todd Zwillich pointed out that Republicans lost the presidency, House seats and the combined popular vote in House races. “People outside this process might wonder if elections have consequences,” Zwillich said.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">“Look, whether the country intended it or not, we have divided government,” Ryan replied, suggesting that Republicans somehow won the debate while losing the election. “Are a lot of these solutions very popular, and did we win these arguments in the campaign?” Ryan asked himself. “Some of us think so.”</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/03/paul-ryan-is-joe-mccarthy-of-our-era.html">Paul Ryan’s magical budget</a>, Dana Milbank, Washington Post</div>
<p>And those very same some of us think upside-down is rightside-up and aliens from Mars ate their calculator and their voter tabulations.  They need antipsychotic medication.  </p>
<div dir="ltr">He proposes abolishing Obamacare — a futile gesture — but would pocket for other purposes $1 trillion in tax increases that came with the program. &#8230;</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">CNN’s Dana Bash asked whether Ryan was being “disingenuous” by including new taxes that he opposed.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">“We’re not going to refight the past,” he explained.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">If Ryan is “not going to fight the past,” Fox News’s Chad Pergram asked, why is he still trying to repeal Obamacare?</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">“This to us is something that we’re not going to give up on,” Ryan answered, “because we’re not going to give up on destroying the health-care system for the American people.”</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Even a skilled illusionist can have the occasional Freudian slip.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/03/paul-ryan-is-joe-mccarthy-of-our-era.html">Paul Ryan’s magical budget</a>, Dana Milbank, Washington Post</div>
<p>Game’s over.  The mainstream media has had enough. They’re finally calling this spade a spade. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joseph_N._Welch">Joe Welch</a> <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/03/paul-ryan-is-joe-mccarthy-of-our-era.html">would be proud</a>. </p>
<p>At long last, Congressman, the people who matter see that you have left no sense of decency. Nor a semblance of mental health. Like Joe McCarthy.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/oh-guess-the-paul-ryan-bubble-finally-has-burst-so-sorry-for-your-loss-paul.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
