<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>importing pharmaceuticals &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Brands and generics pharmaceuticals&#8230;</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/brands-and-generics-pharmaceuticals.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/brands-and-generics-pharmaceuticals.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 09 Dec 2012 11:49:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[importing pharmaceuticals]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[pharmaceutical industry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Supreme court]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/brands-and-generics-pharmaceuticals.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The case is Federal Trade Commission v. Watson Pharmaceuticals et al, No. 12-416.   Via the New York Times comes this note: Last year, for the third time since 2003, the 11th Circuit upheld the agreements as long as the allegedly anticompetitive behavior that results — in this case, keeping the generic drug off the market [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The case is Federal Trade Commission v. Watson Pharmaceuticals et al, No. 12-416.  </p>
<p>Via the <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/12/08/business/justices-to-take-up-generic-drug-case.html?emc=tnt&#038;tntemail1=y&#038;_r=0" target="_blank">New York Times</a> comes this note:</p>
<blockquote><p>Last year, for the third time since 2003, the 11th Circuit upheld the agreements as long as the allegedly anticompetitive behavior that results — in this case, keeping the generic drug off the market — is the same thing that would take place if the brand-name company’s patent were upheld. </p>
<p>Two other federal circuit courts, the Second Circuit and the Federal Circuit, have ruled similarly. But in July, the Third Circuit Court of Appeals said that those arrangements were anticompetitive on their face and violated antitrust law. </p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>The agreements are also affected by a peculiar condition in the law that legalized generic competition for prescription drugs. That law, known as the Hatch-Waxman Act, gives a 180-day period of exclusivity to the first generic drug maker to file for approval of a generic copy and to file a lawsuit challenging the brand-name drug’s patent. </p>
<p>Brand-name drug companies have taken advantage of that law, finding that they can settle the patent suit by getting the generic company to agree to stay out of the market for a period of time. Because that generic company also has exclusivity rights, no other generic companies can enter the market. </p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/brands-and-generics-pharmaceuticals.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Health Care: Supply Chain Meltdowns</title>
		<link>./../../2012/02/health-care-supply-chain-meltdowns.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/02/health-care-supply-chain-meltdowns.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Feb 2012 15:59:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[health care thoughts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[importing pharmaceuticals]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[supply chains]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/02/health-care-supply-chain-meltdowns.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt Health Care: Supply Chain Meltdowns First: Counterfeit vials of the cancer drug Avastin have been found in three states. The vials, sold directly to physician offices, lack the active ingredients to make the drug effective. Somewhat luckily, the packaging was so sloppy the vials were spotted, although some of the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by <strong>Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt</strong></p>
<p><strong>Health Care: Supply Chain Meltdowns</strong>   </p>
<p><em>First</em>:    <br />Counterfeit vials of the cancer drug Avastin have been found in three states. The vials, sold directly to physician offices, lack the active ingredients to make the drug effective. Somewhat luckily, the packaging was so sloppy the vials were spotted, although some of the medication was likely used. We might not be so lucky next time.<br />    <br /><em>Then</em>:    <br />The drug common Methotrexate, used to treat several kinds of cancers, is in short supply. Methotrexate is considered essential in battling acute lymphoblastic leukemia in adults and in children.    </p>
<p>As drugs become generic the cost goes down, but generic drug makers are not especially adept at making injectable medications, being better at mass production of pills. The closure of just a few plants can cause a shortage, as we have now.<br />    <br />More than 250 meds have been on the shortage list in the last year or two, as the lower costs of production are offset by lower reimbursements leading to less capital investment and production.    </p>
<p><a name="more"></a><br /><em>And Finally</em>:    <br />The Johnson and Johnson Depuy subsidiary is in hot water with the FDA for joint replacements failing too early too often (15 years is the hoped for life of joint replacement surgeons, results vary by patient). Depuy recently received some bad publicity for selling the same joint replacements in Europe.    </p>
<p>Meanwhile U.S. malpractice lawyers are having a field day, and a fake internet artificial joint registry disappeared when registrants were hustled by lawyers they had never heard of (the feds are working to start a legitimate registry).     </p>
<p><em>So</em>:    <br />Most of the medical supply chain is efficient and provides quality goods, but a few meltdowns can have horrendous impacts.<br />   </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/02/health-care-supply-chain-meltdowns.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Medical Tourism and Importing Pharmaceuticals</title>
		<link>./../../2008/03/medical-tourism-and-importing-pharmaceuticals.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/03/medical-tourism-and-importing-pharmaceuticals.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2008 11:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Health Insurance]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[importing pharmaceuticals]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medical tourism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/03/medical-tourism-and-importing-pharmaceuticals.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This is a post about 1) medical tourism and 2) importing pharmaceuticals from Canada. I heard something that piqued my interest the other day, so I did eight seconds worth of searching on-line and found this: While no one expects the Federal government to embrace medical tourism for Medicare or Medicaid reimbursement purposes, private insurance [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This is a post about 1) medical tourism and 2) importing pharmaceuticals from Canada.</p>
<p>I heard something that piqued my interest the other day, so I did eight seconds worth of searching on-line and found <a href="http://www.imakenews.com/iln/e_article001011951.cfm">this</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>While no one expects the Federal government to embrace medical tourism for Medicare or Medicaid reimbursement purposes, private insurance companies are beginning to develop, and have already developed, plans that include a medical tourism component.</p></blockquote>
<p>The article goes on, discussing some of the legal issues associated with medical tourism paid for by private insurance companies.  Its interesting, but I want to take this in a different direction:   consider the brouhaha about importing pharmaceuticals from Canada.  Pharmaceutical companies sell the same drugs in Canada (and pretty much else) for less &#8211; a lot less.  Thus, its cheaper to buy a given drug from Canada and ship it back to the US than it is to buy it in the US, even if it was designed and manufactured in the US.  But the argument made by the insurance companies and many folks on the right is that this would stifle innovation, because if you pay pharmaceutical companies only what they are willing to charge Canadians, they won&#8217;t develop new drugs.  </p>
<p>But this argument should apply to medical tourism, which in effect sets a minimum baseline price on all sorts of procedures, including exotic ones like heart surgery and brain surgery.  (Horror of horrors, it also means that while abroad, the patient will be consuming pharmaceuticals sold at much lower costs than in the US market!)  To be consistent, those who oppose allowing consumers the option of importing pharmaceuticals from Canada should also be opposed to allowing people to travel abroad for surgery.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/03/medical-tourism-and-importing-pharmaceuticals.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
