<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Main Street &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Geithner&#8217;s Baa Humbug to Jobs and Labor</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/geithners-baa-humbug-to-jobs-and-labor.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/geithners-baa-humbug-to-jobs-and-labor.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 09 Feb 2013 17:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Main Street]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[run 75441]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Timothy Giethner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wall street]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/geithners-baa-humbug-to-jobs-and-labor.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Dan here&#8230;Taking a look back to 2009: Geithner&#8217;s Baa Humbug to Jobs and Labor 12/25/2009 (h/t Run75441) &#8220;Ebenezer: Since you ask me what I wish sir, that is my answer. I help to support the establishments I have named; those who are badly off must go there.&#8221; Daniel Gross at Slate interviews Tim Geithner here: [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Dan here&#8230;Taking a look back to 2009:<br />
<h4><a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2009/12/geithners-baa-humbug-to-jobs-and-labor.html">Geithner&#8217;s Baa Humbug to Jobs and Labor</a> 12/25/2009</h4>
<p>(h/t Run75441)</p>
<p>&#8220;Ebenezer: Since you ask me what I wish sir, that is my answer. I help to support the establishments I have named; those who are badly off must go there.&#8221;</p>
<p>Daniel Gross at Slate interviews Tim Geithner here: <a href="http://www.slate.com/id/2239552/pagenum/all/#p2">“We Will Be Judged on How We Dealt with the Things that were Broken”</a> Some rather revealing statements by Tim Geithner to Daniel Gross&#8217;s questions:    </p>
<p>GROSS: There&#8217;s a perception that you regard your portfolio narrowly, as primarily focused on the health of Wall Street, with Main Street a distant second.  </p>
<p>GEITHNER: &#8220;My first and essential responsibility was to fix and reform the financial system. That was necessarily going to be the principal part of what people saw. About half my time from the beginning has been spent on the design of the broader economic strategy. The idea that we did not do much for the broader challenges facing the country is completely unjustified. The Recovery Act itself was not just a sweeping, essential force for growth but included a bunch of targeted investments in education, energy, environment, health care that will have huge long-term benefits.&#8221;</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>(Run here: Geithner misses the point or makes the point that finance is the number one concern over Main Street, even though Main Street is financing the rescue of W$. The constituency doesn&#8217;t want charity in targeted investments in education, energy, education, and environment when it can pay for those investments itself if they are working. Main Street wants jobs? Main street is still waiting for that tsunami of job creation which is one of the broader challenges of any administration and no administration has put into play any package to stimuli it or companies to do more. Jobs are left to free market influences which is content with investing profits elsewhere other than job creating infrastructure.)    </p>
<p>GROSS: So you don&#8217;t think the bailouts were too friendly to Wall Street? </p>
<p>GEITHNER: “The idea that the strategy was unfair and has principally benefited a small number of institutions in New York is a mischaracterization of the design and result of the strategy. I thought people would have understood this after the failure of Lehman Bros. But when you do too little and you leave the system with real fear that everything is going to fall apart, like any financial crisis, it hurts the poorest most. A just and fair strategy, even if it is politically hardest to explain and justify, is to use well-designed but massive force to stabilize the system.“   </p>
<p>(Run here: Over at Naked Capitalism, they are debating whether Goldman Sachs drove the collapse of AIG by calling for the mark down of CDO by companies holding too many of them thereby forcing AIG to raise collateral after it was downgraded and eventually paying off on CDO that never were expected to payoff. While AIG is at fault for seeing too many pie in the sky dollars in risk and having too little collateral to cover it, one has to wonder why Goldman Sachs should have received 100% on the dollar on its CDS for its risk with AIG and not knowing how over leveraged AIG was at the time. Goldman Sachs certainly benefited by Geithner&#8217;s negotiated settlement of AIG&#8217;s liabilities at 100% on the dollar.)</p>
<p>GROSS: The biggest downside surprise?<br />  <br />GEITHNER: &#8220;The [high] level of unemployment relative to what was happening in the economy as a whole. I&#8217;m not an economist, but almost all forecasters missed that. And that&#8217;s hugely consequential, because it&#8217;s the prism through which most people view basic economic health.&#8221; </p>
<p>(Run here:He is kidding right? During every economic downturn, it has consistently been Main Street that has been shown the street from their jobs or homes.)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/geithners-baa-humbug-to-jobs-and-labor.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Main Street America and getting to be middle class</title>
		<link>./../../2010/10/main-street-america-and-getting-to-be-middle-class.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/10/main-street-america-and-getting-to-be-middle-class.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Oct 2010 22:36:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Big Box]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ecolanguage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Main Street]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[retail sales]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/10/main-street-america-and-getting-to-be-middle-class.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[By Daniel Becker We all know the arguments about the loss of good jobs. Automation, competition, outsourcing. We&#8217;ve been told that America was striking out to raise it&#8217;s status when it came to jobs. Don&#8217;t lament the loss of those blue collar manufacturing jobs to cheap labor. They aren&#8217;t worth it. Step up. The new [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By Daniel Becker</p>
<p>We all know the arguments about the loss of good jobs. Automation, competition, outsourcing. We&#8217;ve been told that America was striking out to raise it&#8217;s status when it came to jobs. Don&#8217;t lament the loss of those blue collar manufacturing jobs to cheap labor. They aren&#8217;t worth it. Step up. The new jobs will pay more if you get educated. Well, an entire generation got educated, and they are now looking for a job that will just keep them at their status quo. </p>
<p>We seem fixated on just this singular aspect of the decline of the middle class. Well, there is an entire sector of our economy that was and is just as important to growing and keeping a middle class: Retail.</p>
<p>The entire economic focus on finance to the point of believing that all that is important to having a successful economy is to keep improving the efficiency of money has not only generated a formula for making money from money (CDO, CDS, ABS, subprime, leasing, arbitrage, shorting, longing, etc, etc, etc) it has also convinced us and made us act on the idea that consolidation is efficient and that efficiency is growth. The old &#8220;economies of scale&#8221; thingy. </p>
<p>Well, here from my friend is what he recalls of main street in Central Fall, RI. This is what we lost as a pathway into middle class for the sake of &#8220;efficiency&#8221;.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />
<blockquote>&#8220;When I was younger, Dexter Street was alive with activity. Anything you needed you could purchase on Dexter Street. There was a shoe store, two hardware stores, a jeweler, two bakeries, three or four restaurants, about 5 bars, a military store, two pharmacies, three barber shops, two liquor stores, about four of five variety stores, two meat markets and a fish store. They are all gone.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>It&#8217;s is not just the loss of the mills. Central Falls et al could have survived at a much greater level of prosperity if the people had not lost the only path to actually receiving benefit from outsourcing. But, with outsourcing came consolidation in not just manufacturing, but also in the end point distribution of all that consolidated manufacturing: Retail. The efficiency gained of the dollar producing a product outside the USA was consolidated by the move to consolidate the retail part (and wholesale too). The lack of share of productivity gains to the masses is not just do to the loss of manufacturing. It is also do to the loss of access to retailing. </p>
<p>Sure, we all thought it was grand buying something for much less than what Dexter Street Hardware USA could sell it for.  We had more money in our pockets after the purchase.  How&#8217;s your community doing now?</p>
<p>It&#8217;s not just industrial New England that lost retail as represented in the loss of &#8220;Main Street USA&#8221;, you know we are hearing of the destruction of the &#8220;heartland America&#8221; main street. I&#8217;m not talking about the loss of the cultural experience that &#8220;Main Street USA&#8221; represented, though there is that. We closed down for the sake of money efficiency, the other primary path to become middle class. In doing so, we also reduced the movement and thus booking of dollars within the local community. One dollar on Dexter Street, Central Falls, RI could potentially be booked in 31 businesses just by the owner of the business. Even if with that one dollar divided among the employees, that dollar still for the most part stayed in the community to be booked potentially 30 times. One dollar in Big Box Mall USA is divided up such that only a few cents per employee gets booked in the local community with the rest going up line to the few. </p>
<p>No, the trades related to construction can not make up for the loss of independent retail.  Retail was a major cylinder in the small business engine of our economy.  It was also a major path to political reality and activism.</p>
<p>It&#8217;s time we start broadening the discussion to beyond just money efficiency. Just as with the concept of the &#8220;free lunch&#8221; tax cut, that is, that there is no free lunch to growth via tax cuts so is it true with efficiency based on the slogan of &#8220;economies of scale&#8221; when talking about money&#8217;s roll in the entirety of society. That we can buy stuff from overseas cheaper at Big Box Mall USA is not enough of an answer to accepting this paradigm. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/10/main-street-america-and-getting-to-be-middle-class.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
