<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>foriegn trust letters &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>RS goofing on foreign trust letters, says AICPA</title>
		<link>./../../2012/08/rs-goofing-on-foreign-trust-letters-says-aicpa.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/08/rs-goofing-on-foreign-trust-letters-says-aicpa.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 30 Aug 2012 00:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[foriegn trust letters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linda Beale (Tax law)]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/08/rs-goofing-on-foreign-trust-letters-says-aicpa.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Beale RS goofing on foreign trust letters, says AICPA The American Institute of CPAs (AICPA) is asking the IRS Commissioner to resolve what it suggests is a &#8220;widespread problem&#8221; for taxpayers.  Download AICPA Letter to IRS on Erroneous Form 3520 Letters to Taxapyers.082812.   For 2010 and earlier years, the IRS apparently has made [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Linda Beale</p>
<p> RS goofing on foreign trust letters, says AICPA</p>
<p> The American Institute of CPAs (AICPA) is asking the IRS Commissioner to resolve what it suggests is a &#8220;widespread problem&#8221; for taxpayers.  <a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/files/aicpa-letter-to-irs-on-erroneous-form-3520-letters-to-taxapyers.082812.pdf">Download AICPA Letter to IRS on Erroneous Form 3520 Letters to Taxapyers.082812</a>.   For 2010 and earlier years, the IRS apparently has made a wide range of systemic mistakes in processing the form required to be filed annually by owners of a foreign trust&#8211;<a href="http://www.irs.gov/pub/irs-pdf/f3520.pdf">Forms 3520</a>, the Annual Return to Report Transactions with Foreign Trusts and REceipt of Certain Foreign Gifts.<br />  The AICPA reports errors including:
<ul>
<li>instructions to fill out Part II about ownership of a foreign trust, when the taxpayer is not the owner of a foreign grantor trust; </li>
<li>instructions to provide additional information required when a taxpayer answers a question &#8220;yes&#8221; when the question on the form was answered &#8220;no&#8221;; </li>
<li>instructions to provide identifying information required to be submitted when the information was already submitted; and </li>
<li>insturctions to provide an explanatory statementwhen such statement was already submitted.</li>
</ul>
<p>This looks like one of those kinds of things that happen when staffing at a government agency is reduced beyond what is reasonable for the kinds of tasks that have to be carried out. </p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Query&#8211;isn&#8217;t it likely that the right&#8217;s  (and now officially the GOP&#8217;s) drive to reduce staffing at all levels of government agencies (except, of course, for the right&#8217;s pet project, expansion of the military) likely to increase the headaches for ordinary citizens because those government agencies simply won&#8217;t be able to get their jobs done well with the reduced staffing and morale problems that will cause?</p>
<p>cross posted with <a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2012/08/-irs-goofing-on-foreign-trust-letters-says-aicpa.html">ataxingmatter</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/08/rs-goofing-on-foreign-trust-letters-says-aicpa.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
