<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>desalination &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Will San Diego make the desalination mistake?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/will-san-diego-make-the-desalination-mistake.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/will-san-diego-make-the-desalination-mistake.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2012 20:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[David Zetland]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[desalination]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[water]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/will-san-diego-make-the-desalination-mistake.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[(Dan here&#8230;a recent talk I attended on water in Burkina Faso reminded me to look at another important issue even for the US) by David Zetland    David Zetland is a senior water economist at Wageningen University in the Netherlands and maintains a blog on water issues at Aguanomics. Will San Diego make the desalination mistake? [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>(Dan here&#8230;a recent talk I attended on water in Burkina Faso reminded me to look at another important issue even for the US)</p>
<p>by David Zetland    <a href="http://www.blogger.com/profile/11677758798533719965">David Zetland</a> is a senior water economist at Wageningen University in the Netherlands and maintains a blog on water issues at <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/10/will-san-diego-make-desalination-mistake.html" title="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/10/will-san-diego-make-desalination-mistake.html">Aguanomics</a>.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/10/will-san-diego-make-desalination-mistake.html">Will San Diego make the desalination mistake?</a></p>
<p>Poseidon Resources has been lobbying to build a desalination plant in Carlsbad (San Diego County), California for around a decade, and I&#8217;ve been skeptical of that proposal (<a href="https://www.google.com/search?num=50&#038;hl=en&#038;safe=off&#038;q=Poseidon%7Ccarlsbad+site%3Aaguanomics.com">earlier posts</a>) &#8212; mostly because water consumption in San Diego is still quite high (ranging from 100-300 gallons/capita/day; compare that number to Sydney or Melbourne at 50 gcd!).</p>
<p>It makes more economical and environmental sense, in other words, for San Diego to reduce its demand before going for more supply (this <a href="http://www.kysq.org/docs/SDCWA_Supply%20Alternatives.pdf">year-old analysis of their supply alternatives</a> [pdf] lists desalination at $1,600/af but that cost is now up to $2,000+/af). </p>
<p>But San Diego politicians are not thinking in terms of environmental or economic sustainability. <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/03/san-diego-vs-mwd.html">They are at war with the Metropolitan Water District</a> over imported water and in alliance with <a href="http://www.water-alternatives.org/index.php?option=com_content&#038;task=view&#038;id=74&#038;Itemid=1">property developers who want more supply to build more subdivisions</a>. (It&#8217;s ironic, in fact, that SD leaders worry about the burden of <a href="http://www.kysq.org/docs/SDCWA2CNRA.pdf">paying too much for more water imported from Met via the Delta</a> [pdf] when they are prepared to throw caution to the wind for a local &#8220;solution.&#8221;)    </p>
<p>Those are just some preliminary comments and opinions based on my observations over the past 7-8 years, but there are some new developments that make these comments even more relevant.    </p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>First, the San Diego Country Water Authority is thinking of signing a <a href="http://sdcwa.org/issue-desal">30-year water purchase agreement</a> to buy water from Poseidon, an agreement that will make it possible for Poseidon to borrow money from the State of California (!) for constructing the plant.     </p>
<p>Second, that agreement does not specify how much equity (&#8220;skin in the game&#8221;) Poseidon will bring to the table in financing the $900 million project, but it DOES specify how much money Poseidon will receive for &#8220;overseeing&#8221; a project that it will neither design, nor construct, nor operate.     </p>
<p>Third, it appears that SDCWA will pay about $3.2 billion over 30 years for water that will be twice as expensive as its existing water supplies from Met. Given the industry-norm of charging average cost for water, that means that SDCWA will be selling water it buys for $2,000 per af for about $1,200 per af. Try swinging that business model past Wall Street. (The Independent Rate Oversight Committee <a href="http://www.kysq.org/docs/IROC2SDCWA.pdf">sure doesn&#8217;t like it!</a> [pdf])    </p>
<p>Fourth, you should read <a href="https://docs.google.com/file/d/0B_lZtMmwi5SXdnNCNzhLaGVzUlE/edit">my 6-page analysis of the water purchase agreement</a> (all 550 pages of what-the-hell-are-these-lawyers-saying!?!). <a href="http://sandiego.surfrider.org/independent-economist-is-leary-of-the-water-purchase-agreement-between-san-diego-county-water-authority-poseidon-resources">The Surfrider Foundation paid me to prepare it</a>, but &#8212; as usual &#8212; I acted as a consultant with a conscience: I put my original opinions in that report, since I am paid for honesty and accuracy, not groupthink. But read it for yourself.    </p>
<p>Bottom Line: San Diego should not build a desalination plant because it would be an <i>expensive non-solution</i> to water reliability problems that are actually caused by poor management of regional water at Metropolitan and a failure to restrict demand to sustainable levels.</p>
<p>reposted from <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/10/will-san-diego-make-desalination-mistake.html" title="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/10/will-san-diego-make-desalination-mistake.html">Aguanomics</a></p>
<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/will-san-diego-make-the-desalination-mistake.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
