<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>reproduction &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Reproduction, Income, and the Future</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/reproduction-income-and-the-future.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/reproduction-income-and-the-future.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 18 Feb 2013 00:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[families]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mike Kimel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[reproduction]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/reproduction-income-and-the-future.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Mike Kimel Reproduction, Income, and the Future A comment on a post at EconLog, a very libertarian website&#8230; I can say that in my lifetime, I have not earned enough money for me to have kids. I&#8217;m 36. I know some have had kids on my income or less but it certainly is not [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Mike Kimel</p>
<p>Reproduction, Income, and the Future</p>
<p>A <a href="http://econlog.econlib.org/archives/2013/02/why_have_kids_m.html#comments">comment on a post at EconLog</a>, a very libertarian website&#8230;<br />
<blockquote>I can say that in my lifetime, I have not earned enough money for me to have kids. I&#8217;m 36. I know some have had kids on my income or less but it certainly is not enough money for me. I can&#8217;t imagine how it would have been if I had kids.</p></blockquote>
<p>And this <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/02/14/the-kids-are-alright/?comments#permid=128">comment on a post by Paul Krugman, on the liberal side of the spectrum</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>I personally have never had the stability in my life where I thought it was okay for me to go off and spawn a family the way my parents did beginning in 1953. My father worked hard, and loved to work, had good employment and good pay, without a college degree. </p>
<p>Where as, he sent me to private schools, I got honor roll grades, bachelors degree, doctorate degree, I re-engineered manufacturing systems at some of America&#8217;s largest companies, but still I never felt secure in my employment, nor was I. </p>
<p>I am unemployed now, as I was in 2010, as I was in 2006, as I was in 1991, as I was for a time in 1984, 1983 and 1982 &#8211; when I graduated.</p>
<p>The current generation is facing a geometrically greater challenge than I did. So I can see why traditional family life is in decline. </p></blockquote>
<p>Interesting how the problem is the framed the same way at different ends of the political spectrum.  I note that this framing also fits my life &#8211; my wife and I got married late and had one child (one and done) very late.  Economic worries were a big part of the decision making process.  On paper, my wife and I are doing relatively well financially, but we are extremely aware that a job loss &#8211; something that has become extremely common in recent years &#8211; or one financial mis-step could mean the difference between whether our son will have far greater opportunity in life than either my wife or I did growing up, or far less opportunity.  There doesn&#8217;t seem to be much in-between.   In talking with my parents, they also seem to believe outcomes are more stark for families today.  Many of my friends tell me the same thing.  And when I talk to people ten or twenty years younger than I, in general, their costs seem to be higher than those I faced, and the potential opportunities fewer.</p>
<p>The result is that most people I know within ten years of my age have between zero and two kids.   While there are exceptions, in general, people I can name with three or more kids either are in the top 2% or so, income-wise (and most of them are in finance or have inherited wealth or both), or are well below the median.  (Note &#8211;  I went looking for data on number of children by income level in the US but couldn&#8217;t find any.)  I wonder if that&#8217;s a portent of things to come, and what it implies for the stability of society going forward.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/reproduction-income-and-the-future.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
