<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>draft &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Dear US Citizen, It is your labor being conscripted</title>
		<link>./../../2008/09/dear-us-citizen-it-is-your-labor-being-conscripted.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/09/dear-us-citizen-it-is-your-labor-being-conscripted.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2008 19:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Bank Crisis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[draft]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[labor]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/09/dear-us-citizen-it-is-your-labor-being-conscripted.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Divorced one like Bush I just have to get this out because I fear we will not learn from this experience if we do not face up to what really is being put on the line in this crisis: Our labor. I am angry. And I am making this personal. It is personal. I&#8217;m [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Divorced one like Bush</p>
<p>I just have to get this out because I fear we will not learn from this experience if we do not face up to what really is being put on the line in this crisis: Our labor.   I am angry.  And I am making this personal.  It is personal.  I&#8217;m speaking to you We the People.</p>
<p>What every solution is proposing in its most boiled down pure form is the conscription of our labor.  It is nothing less.  Only, it is not conscription for altruistic reasons.  It is conscription in service of the most basic of needs: survival.  </p>
<p>From this point forward, any gains in productivity will no longer be applied  in total toward our quest for a more perfect union and the pursuit of happiness.   Think about how much progress will  have to be made in labor productivity rise just to offset the $900 billion already tallied and the now additional $700 billion such that we do not lose our current standard of living.  If we can not make the increase, how much lost standard of living does this represent?   How much more do I have to work, or how much of what I work now will go toward this crisis resolution instead of bettering my life?  These are the questions we as citizens should be asking.  It&#8217;s not like we can all just pay this off by writing a check from our savings.  Even if we could, it represents future gains in our personal growth lost.</p>
<p>It is not  money.  It is not the taxes to be paid.  It is not the wealth lost.  It is the most basic of human life sustaining and rewarding experiences being taken: labor.  Our labor.   That which provided the bases for the value of our nation&#8217;s worth. </p>
<p>That this crisis resolution is being talked about in dollars does a complete injustice to all of the labor that has come prior to this historic moment.  The failure of the system, the loss of value, the loss of the integrate of the system is a testament to the abuse (physical and emotional) that the US citizen has been enduring.  That the discussions (and I understand that we have to discuss the mechanics to resolve the crisis) by our elected does not come from the perspective that it is our labor being taken, being assigned is the lie we have allowed ourselves to live.  We have not made what takes place in our country personal. It is always abstract in our national discussions.  </p>
<p>WAKE UP! KNOCK, KNOCK, HELLOOOOOOOO&#8230;this is real.  This is happening.  You are going to be working, laboring, sweating, getting tired, getting fustrated, longer years of work, more worn out in our retirement from now on.  No one else is going to be paying this off.  You and I will be paying this off.</p>
<p>It is our fault too, because we are the government. WE ARE THE GGOVERNMENT!  (Please keep saying this until it is as natural an understanding as is drinking water to stay healthy.)  And, that is the dichotomy to this crisis.  In the end the abuse we have endured, the labor we have wasted, the labor we will now forfeit to future social maturity is our own damn fault because, for what ever reason or excuse, we failed to labor within the primary structure of our life&#8217;s existence that supports all we believed about our wealth: One Voice, One vote.</p>
<p>So learn the lesson.  Remember the lesson.  Teach the lesson.  To not learn, to forget is to forfeit via conscription your most personal possession: Your labor.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/09/dear-us-citizen-it-is-your-labor-being-conscripted.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
