<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Rebecca Wilder &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Unemployment Rates Across the Euro Area – Tough Times in Key Markets</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/unemployment-rates-across-the-euro-area-tough-times-in-key-markets.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/unemployment-rates-across-the-euro-area-tough-times-in-key-markets.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2012 17:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[euro area]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rebecca Wilder]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[unemployment]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/unemployment-rates-across-the-euro-area-tough-times-in-key-markets.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Rebecca Wilder Unemployment Rates Across the Euro Area – Tough Times in Key Markets Today Eurostat released its unemployment rate figures for the month of August. The Euro area unemployment rate held firm at 11.4% for the third consecutive month. Spain still has the highest unemployment rate in the euro area, 25.1%, and Greece [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by <a href="http://www.economonitor.com/blog/author/rwilder3">Rebecca Wilder</a></p>
<p>Unemployment Rates Across the Euro Area – Tough Times in Key Markets</p>
<p>Today Eurostat released its unemployment rate figures for the month of August. The Euro area unemployment rate held firm at 11.4% for the third consecutive month. Spain still has the highest unemployment rate in the euro area, 25.1%, and Greece is catching up quickly, 24.4% (in June, which is the latest data point).<br />The chart below illustrates the level of the unemployment rate and its month-month change for the euro area 12 countries.<br /><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/10/urate_chart.jpg"><img alt="" height="402" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/10/urate_chart.jpg" width="604"></a></p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>The periphery are under performing the average, with Spain, Greece, Portugal, and Ireland leading the way. Internal devaluation, or driving up the unemployment rate to reduce relative prices with demand, is really taking its toll. Respectively, the unemployment rates in Spain, Greece, Portugal, and Ireland are 178.9 ppt, 234.2 ppt, 93.9 ppt, and 212.5 ppt above their pre-crisis minimums (loosely defined since January 2008) – a simple average of 179.9 ppt above the joint minimum for these four countries. The average euro area 17 unemployment rate is just 56.2 ppt above its 7.3% pre-crisis minimum. Hard days in the periphery, to be sure. Against this backdrop, weekend <a href="http://www.eurointelligence.com/eurointelligence-news/home/singleview-restricted/article/peer-steinbrueck-to-challenge-angela-merkel.html">protests in Paris, Madrid, Lisbon, and Rome</a> are not a surprise.<br />I further point out the troubling trend in the French labor market, as the new government presents its fresh austerity budget for 2013.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/10/fr-ea_urate.jpg"><img alt="" height="390" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/10/fr-ea_urate.jpg" width="605"></a></p>
<p>This budget is highly dependent on tax revenue and positive growth momentum, which is likely to disappoint amid such deterioration in domestic demand. See <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/finance/comment/ambroseevans_pritchard/9577674/Another-domino-falls-as-Hollande-pushes-France-into-depression.html">Ambrose Evans-Pritchard </a>on the expected budget impact.</p>
<p>cross posted with <a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/2012/10/01/unemployment-rate-in-the-euro-area-tough-times-in-key-markets/">The Wilder View&#8230;Economonitors</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/unemployment-rates-across-the-euro-area-tough-times-in-key-markets.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Policy transmission mechanism: Broken in Italy, better in Spain</title>
		<link>./../../2012/09/policy-transmission-mechanism-broken-in-italy-better-in-spain.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/09/policy-transmission-mechanism-broken-in-italy-better-in-spain.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 Sep 2012 17:43:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Italy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rebecca Wilder]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spain]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/09/policy-transmission-mechanism-broken-in-italy-better-in-spain.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Rebecca Wilder Policy transmission mechanism: Broken in Italy, better in SpainYesterday, the Financial Times reported that borrowing costs for small businesses in the periphery were rising relative to the core using the ECB’s release of July MFI interest rate data. I highlighted this point exactly on August 1 following Draghi’s now famous London speech, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by <a href="http://www.economonitor.com/blog/author/rwilder3">Rebecca Wilder</a></p>
<p>Policy transmission mechanism: Broken in Italy, better in Spain<br />Yesterday, <a href="http://www.ft.com/intl/cms/s/0/60ae47cc-f5e5-11e1-a6c2-00144feabdc0.html#axzz25VANEnVy">the Financial Times </a>reported that borrowing costs for small businesses in the periphery were rising relative to the core using the ECB’s release of July MFI interest rate data. <a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/2012/08/01/evidence-on-clogged-transmission-channel-of-monetary-policy-in-the-euro-area/">I highlighted this point exactly on August 1</a> following Draghi’s now famous London speech, where he cautioned that monetary transmission mechanism is ‘hampered’.</p>
<p>As opposed to the FT, though, I would argue that the transmission mechanism is at least not getting worse in Spain and Portugal, and worsening in Italy. Italy is the only periphery economy (where data is made available) where the corporate borrowing costs are higher since the peak of corporate lending rates in the Euro area in July 2011.</p>
<p>The FT is wrong. It takes Spain as the case study and uses the incorrect corporate lending rate information. Specifically, <a href="http://www.ft.com/intl/cms/s/0/60ae47cc-f5e5-11e1-a6c2-00144feabdc0.html#axzz25VANEnVy">according to the FT</a> (bolded by RW):<br />
<blockquote><em>The interest rate charged by banks on a<strong> corporate loan of up to €1m lasting between one and five years – which would typically be taken out by a small business</strong> – was 6.5 per cent in July in Spain, according to the ECB figures.</em></p></blockquote>
<p>True, the rate on new business loans up to and including €1 mn with maturity of 1-5 years did see an average <a href="http://sdw.ecb.europa.eu/quickview.do?SERIES_KEY=124.MIR.M.ES.B.A2A.I.R.0.2240.EUR.N">borrowing rate of 6.5%</a> in July. However, corporate loans up to and including €1 mn with maturity of greater than 5 years saw a <a href="http://sdw.ecb.europa.eu/quickview.do?SERIES_KEY=124.MIR.M.ES.B.A2A.J.R.0.2240.EUR.N">drop in borrowing costs of 1.4% in July to 5.17%</a> . The 5.17% rate is the rate that should be quoted, rather than the 6.5% rate.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>The 2012 Euro area stock of outstanding debt shows clearly that 57% of corporate loans had been made with maturity of greater than 5 years – the ECB provides no breakdown of loan data by maturity at the country level, so the FT must have been referring to the ECB’s Euro area data as the ‘typical loan’.<br /><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/09/stock_loans.jpg"><img alt="" height="291" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/09/stock_loans.jpg" width="483"></a><br />As demonstrated in the chart below, the story is much more complicated than the FT curtly portrays – it’s not just ‘Spain’ versus ‘Germany’. French corporate borrowing costs barely budged since July 2011. Furthermore, the corporate borrowing rates in Spain are improving rather materially compared to those in Italy and Portugal.<br /><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/09/nfc_rate_bar.jpg"><img alt="" height="379" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/09/nfc_rate_bar.jpg" width="476"></a><br />Italian corporate borrowing are up 0.67% since the peak of EA corporate lending rates in July 2011 (the <a href="http://www.ecb.int/stats/monetary/rates/html/index.en.html">ECB hiked its policy rate on July 13</a>). Spanish corporates, on the other hand, saw corporate borrowing costs fall the most of all the periphery economies, -1.35% since July 2011.<br />As demonstrated in the illustration below, the core is benefiting largely from ECB rate cuts compared to the periphery (chart 1 below). However, on a 3-month moving average (the rates moves are pretty choppy in Spain), the transmission mechanism in Spain is improving relative to that Italy and Portugal (chart 2 below). Using the correct data, the FT should have included this information in their article.<br /><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/09/time_series_1.jpg"><img alt="" height="338" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/09/time_series_1.jpg" width="507"></a><br /><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/09/time_series_2.jpg"><img alt="" height="338" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/09/time_series_2.jpg" width="507"></a><br /><em><strong>Rebecca Wilder</strong></em><br /><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/2012/09/04/policy-transmission-mechanism-broken-in-italy-better-in-spain">The Wilder View&#8230;Economonitors</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/09/policy-transmission-mechanism-broken-in-italy-better-in-spain.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Dutch Domestic Demand Dragging Real Home Values</title>
		<link>./../../2012/08/dutch-domestic-demand-dragging-real-home-values.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/08/dutch-domestic-demand-dragging-real-home-values.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 22 Aug 2012 02:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[housing and domestic demand]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rebecca Wilder]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/08/dutch-domestic-demand-dragging-real-home-values.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Rebecca Wilder Dutch Domestic Demand Dragging Real Home Values Today Statistics Netherlands (CBS) warned ”House Prices Nosedive“. Prices of existing owner-occupied dwellings sold in July 2012 were on average 8.0 percent down from July 2011. This is the most substantial price drop since the price index of existing residential property was first recorded in [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by <a href="http://www.economonitor.com/blog/author/rwilder3">Rebecca Wilder</a></p>
<p>Dutch Domestic Demand Dragging Real Home Values </p>
<p>Today Statistics Netherlands (CBS) warned ”<a href="http://www.cbs.nl/en-GB/menu/themas/bouwen-wonen/publicaties/artikelen/archief/2012/2012-08-21-m11.htm?RefererType=RSSItem">House Prices Nosedive</a>“.<br />
<blockquote><em>Prices of existing owner-occupied dwellings sold in July 2012 were on average 8.0 percent down from July 2011. This is the most substantial price drop since the price index of existing residential property was first recorded in 1995.</em></p></blockquote>
<p>In real terms and indexed to 2005, home values are down 10.1% over the year in July and dropped 21.3% since the August 2007 peak.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/08/house_price_chart.jpg"><img alt="" height="291" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/08/house_price_chart.jpg" width="483"></a></p>
<p>What explains this real depreciation in home values? I’ll give you one chart: the unemployment rate.<br /><a name="more"></a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/08/unemployment_rate.jpg"><img alt="" height="311" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/08/unemployment_rate.jpg" width="477"></a></p>
<p>The labor market is sinking, and taking with it household demand. Companies probably hoarded labor in the crisis – the peak to trough drop in GDP was 4.9% versus a 1.6% cyclical drop in employment around that period. However, in late 2011 employment peaked and unemployment is surging – the quarterly employment data through March 2012 indicate a peak was seen in Q3 2011.<br />On balance, the downtrend in Dutch home values is probably here to stay. FYI: the balance sheet of Dutch households and non-profits is roughly <a href="http://sdw.ecb.europa.eu/quickview.do?SERIES_KEY=158.IEAQ.Q.NL.N.V.LE.RF4D.S1M.A1.S.2.N.F.Z">2.5 times levered</a>.</p>
<p><strong><em>Rebecca Wilder</em></strong></p>
<p><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/2012/08/21/domestic-demand-dragging-real-home-values-in-the-netherlands/?utm_source=rss&#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=domestic-demand-dragging-real-home-values-in-the-netherlands">http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/2012/08/21/domestic-demand-dragging-real-home-values-in-the-netherlands/</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/08/dutch-domestic-demand-dragging-real-home-values.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The NY Times Is Misleading. And Who Is Correct? Eurostat or China Customs?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/08/the-ny-times-is-misleading-and-who-is-correct-eurostat-or-china-customs.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/08/the-ny-times-is-misleading-and-who-is-correct-eurostat-or-china-customs.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Aug 2012 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Eurostat]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[exchange rates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[global trade]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rebecca Wilder]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/08/the-ny-times-is-misleading-and-who-is-correct-eurostat-or-china-customs.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The NY Times Is Misleading. And Who Is Correct? Eurostat or China Customs? by Rebecca Wilder The NY Times reports quite a dire situation as regards the slump in the value of Chinese exports to the European Union in July: Data published this month showed that China’s exports to the European Union had sunk 16.2 percent [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>The NY Times Is Misleading. And Who Is Correct? Eurostat or China Customs?</h3>
<p>by <a href="http://www.economonitor.com/blog/author/rwilder3">Rebecca Wilder</a> </p>
<p><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/08/17/business/global/europes-problems-squeeze-chinese-trade-outlook.html?partner=rss&#038;emc=rss">The NY Times</a> reports quite a dire situation as regards the slump in the value of Chinese exports to the European Union in July:<br />
<blockquote><em>Data published this month showed that China’s exports to the European Union had <strong>sunk 16.2 percent</strong> in July to $29.4 billion, compared with July 2011.</em></p></blockquote>
<p>This statistic (bolded by yours truly) is misleading.</p>
<p>First, China Customs measures exports in nominal dollars. If you look at Chinese exports measured in, let’s say euros, it doesn’t look quite as bad. In July, exports to the European Union (EU 27) dropped -3.6% over the year measured in euros versus a -16.2% annual decline measured in dollars. The dollar appreciated against the euro over the measurement period so the drop in China’s exports to the EU 27 is much lower in euros.</p>
<p><em>Note: This is only an approximation since I use the average monthly exchange rate, which is unlikely to align perfectly with China Customs’ measurement period.</em><br /><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/08/china_exports_eu_chart1.jpg"><img alt="" height="354" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/08/china_exports_eu_chart1.jpg" width="477"></a></p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>An interesting corollary to the FX impact on ‘value’ statistics is the various statistical agencies that report presumably the same statistic. Eurostat publishes import data by partner and in euros. Using the average exchange rate over the month, I calculate the value of EU 27 imports from China reported in dollars for comparison to the China Customs data. Eurostat data is available only through June.<br />In June, Eurostat reports that EU 27 imports from China dropped -11.1% measured in dollars compared to the reported -1.1% annual reduction in exports from China to the EU 27 by China Customs. Clearly the trend is downward; but the Eurostat data only loosely matches the China Customs data. Balance of payments statistics are subject to large ”errors and omissions”.</p>
<p><em>Note: In the chart below, Eurostat data is illustrated in the series “EU imports from China”, while China Customs data is illustrated in the series “Exports to EU”.</em><br /><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/08/CHINA_EU_STATS.jpg"><img alt="" height="354" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/08/CHINA_EU_STATS.jpg" width="477"></a></p>
<p>So who’s right? Eurostat or China Customs? Part of the differentiation involves the timing of the FX moves (remember I use the monthly averages); but that is unlikely the full story here. I’d err on the side of Eurostat, and notice the trend looks pretty bad no matter who’s estimating the trade data.</p>
<p><em><strong>Rebecca Wilder</strong></em><br /><em><strong><br /></strong></em>cross posted with <strong> </strong>The Wilder View&#8230;Economonitors</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/08/the-ny-times-is-misleading-and-who-is-correct-eurostat-or-china-customs.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>It’s the Exchange Rate, Stupid</title>
		<link>./../../2012/08/its-the-exchange-rate-stupid.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/08/its-the-exchange-rate-stupid.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 19 Aug 2012 14:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[euro area]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Eurostat]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rebecca Wilder]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/08/its-the-exchange-rate-stupid.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Rebecca Wilder It’s the Exchange Rate, Stupid Eurostat released trade figures today, where the trade balance (exports less imports) surged €3.7 bn in the month of June (link to the .pdf release). The current figures imply a 2012 annualized trade balance of €66.9 bn, which is a meaningful boost to the -€7.4 bn deficit [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by <a href="http://www.economonitor.com/blog/author/rwilder3">Rebecca Wilder</a></p>
<p>It’s the Exchange Rate, Stupid</p>
<p>Eurostat released trade figures today, where the trade balance (exports less imports) surged €3.7 bn in the month of June (<a href="http://epp.eurostat.ec.europa.eu/cache/ITY_PUBLIC/6-17082012-AP/EN/6-17082012-AP-EN.PDF">link to the</a> .pdf release). The current figures imply a 2012 annualized trade balance of €66.9 bn, which is a meaningful boost to the -€7.4 bn deficit in 2011.</p>
<p>Eurostat breaks down the regional figures further into intra-Euro area (intra-EA) trade and extra-Euro area (extra-EA) trade.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/08/table_tb.jpg"><img alt="" height="100" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/08/table_tb.jpg" width="600"></a></p>
<p> Out of the EA 16, June intra-EA figures are available for just a few countries. Of those countries, the intra-EA trade balance improved in Portugal only, increasing by 0.26 ppt as a share of GDP on the month. From June 2011 to June 2012, where available, otherwise June 2011 to May 2012 (see Table above), the intra-EA rebalancing – i.e., roughly raising the balance of the net-importers and reducing the surplus of the net-exporters – has occurred to a certain degree. Net trade as a share of country GDP fell in Germany, and rose in Italy, Spain, Greece, and Portugal. France and Ireland worsened their positions, while the Netherlands increased its large trade surplus of 25.1% of GDP over the year.</p>
<p><img alt="" height="539" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/08/IEA_trade.jpg" width="604"><br /><a name="more"></a></p>
<p> Except in Portugal and Greece, the intra-EA ‘rebalancing’ is either not necessarily required due to the relatively low imbalances, Spain or Germany, or moving in the wrong direction, France or the Netherlands.<br />June extra-EA figures are available for all countries. With the help of the real depreciation of the trade-weighted euro over the month, the extra-EA trade balance improved in June across all EA 16 countries except for Ireland, where it fell by 0.2 ppt of GDP. Over the year through June, all countries except the Netherlands saw an improvement in the trade balance as a share of GDP (see Table above).</p>
<p><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/08/EEA_trade.jpg"><img alt="" height="468" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/08/EEA_trade.jpg" width="600"></a></p>
<p> Given the strong positive momentum in extra-EA net trade and the sluggish shift in intra-EA net trade, I conclude that it’s the depreciation of the real exchange – the 12.7% nominal depreciation of the euro against the dollar, for example, and/or falling relative price levels with extra-EA economies &#8211; that’s the primary driver of the improving trade balances in key periphery markets. With the strong exception of Portugal, where the intra-EA balance improved by 2.6 ppt of GDP over the year, the internal (infernal) devaluation of repressing wages through high unemployment has mixed results at best.</p>
<p>Rebecca Wilder</p>
<p>Note: I understand the imbalances lie in the financial accounts as well but this post is dedicated to trade only.<br />A point on the data: all numbers are seasonally adjusted.</p>
<p>cross posted with The Wilder View&#8230;Economonitors</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/08/its-the-exchange-rate-stupid.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>France is Stuck in the Mud</title>
		<link>./../../2012/08/france-is-stuck-in-the-mud.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/08/france-is-stuck-in-the-mud.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 15 Aug 2012 13:46:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[France]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rebecca Wilder]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[recession]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/08/france-is-stuck-in-the-mud.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Rebecca Wilder According to the Eurostat flash estimate, Euro area GDP fell by 0.2% in both the euro area and the EU27 in the second quarter of 2012. In the first quarter of 2012, growth rates were 0.0% in both zones. On balance, the Euro area is very likely in recession despite the fact [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Rebecca Wilder</p>
<p>According to the <a href="http://epp.eurostat.ec.europa.eu/cache/ITY_PUBLIC/2-14082012-BP/EN/2-14082012-BP-EN.PDF">Eurostat flash estimate</a>, Euro area GDP fell by 0.2% in both the euro area and the EU27 in the second quarter of 2012. In the first quarter of 2012, growth rates were 0.0% in both zones. On balance, the Euro area is very likely in recession despite the fact that the region successfully skirted the “two negative quarters of growth” rule of recession dating having stagnated in Q1 2012 following a 0.3% contraction in Q4 2011.</p>
<p>The underlying country GDP estimates for Q2, released by the various statistical agencies, do illustrate a deep divide among the growth prospects across the 17-country Euro area in Q2 2012. Here is a select list of reported growth results (all for Q2 2012 in % Q/Q not annualized):</p>
<p>Germany, +0.3%<br />France , +0.0%<br />Netherlands, +0.2%<br />Spain, -0.4%<br />Italy, -0.7%<br />Portugal, -1.2%</p>
<p>The French flash release, in particular, caught my eye: “No growth for the third consecutive quarter” is what <a href="http://www.insee.fr/en/themes/info-rapide.asp?id=26&#038;date=20120814">INSEE titled its publication</a>. The French economy has effectively stalled. Using Eurostat data, the economy has grown just 0.09% (the unrevised numbers) since July 2011. And since Q2 2011, the economy grew just 0.3%. In all, the economy is not technically in recession but it certainly isn’t expanding. To me, the question is, will it go up or down from here?</p>
<p>Compared to history, the current expansion in France has been nothing short of pathetic. Stuck in the mud.</p>
<div><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-wR26sdXZxmw/UCunoJtR27I/AAAAAAAAA90/QR_u3X15YE4/s1600/europe.png" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="231" width="320" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-wR26sdXZxmw/UCunoJtR27I/AAAAAAAAA90/QR_u3X15YE4/s320/europe.png"></a></div>
<p><em>Note: In the chart above, the French dating of business cycles is taken from the OECD, which is available through the FRED database. In the legend, those dates with a (2) indicate short recoveries with an ensuing recession (1 recession and 1 expansion with the same number of quarters as the 2009-2012 expansion). Therefore, the graphs are truncated when the next recession started over the period.</em></p>
<p><strong><em>Rebecca Wilder</em></strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/08/france-is-stuck-in-the-mud.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>World Trade Turning Down</title>
		<link>./../../2012/08/world-trade-turning-down.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/08/world-trade-turning-down.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Aug 2012 23:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[global economies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[global trade]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rebecca Wilder]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/08/world-trade-turning-down.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Rebecca Wilder World Trade Turning Down Something different for today: world trade. Recently, South Korea and Taiwan released July 2012 trade statistics, where annual export growth was seen contracting at a 8.8% and 11.6% rate, respectively. The annual pace of export growth in Taiwan contracted for the fifth consecutive month, where that in South [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by <a href="http://www.economonitor.com/blog/author/rwilder3">Rebecca Wilder</a> </p>
<p>World Trade Turning Down</p>
<p> Something different for today: world trade. Recently, South Korea and Taiwan released July 2012 trade statistics, where annual export growth was seen contracting at a 8.8% and 11.6% rate, respectively. The annual pace of export growth in Taiwan contracted for the fifth consecutive month, where that in South Korea turned negative following a 1.1% annual rate in June 2012.</p>
<p>On balance, exports in key Asian markets, such as South Korea, Taiwan, and China, are seen as leading indicators for world demand due to their intermediate nature of production in the supply chain. And the signal there is not good for global demand.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/08/exports_asia.jpg"><img alt="" height="366" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/08/exports_asia.jpg" width="524"></a></p>
<p>The <a href="http://www.cpb.nl/en/number/cpb-world-trade-monitor-including-may-2012">Netherlands Bureau for Economic Policy Analysis</a> and JP Morgan make available world trade statistics and a global PMI, respectively.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>The correlation between the 3-month percentage annual rate of change of world trade and the global PMI have a 77% correlation dating back to 1998. Although the world trade statistics are current as of May 2012, the June and July global PMI, 49.1 and 48.4, respectively, do confirm the weakness seen in the Asian country export data and portend deterioration in this measure of world trade.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/08/pmi_trade.jpg"><img alt="" height="354" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/08/pmi_trade.jpg" width="508"></a></p>
<p>A simple bivariate regression of the 3-month growth trend in world trade on the global PMI implies a 3-month annualized contraction of 0.66% in July. This is far from the pace of contraction in 2009 – according to this statistic, World trade declined at its fastest 3-month trend rate in January 2009 of 50.5%. Furthermore, there’s no precipitous downtrend in the PMI that would suggest a sharp contraction in world trade.</p>
<p>I can only conclude that it’s too early to call stabilization in World trade, rather the opposite. However, the pace of contraction could be quite mild if policy makers ease globally.</p>
<p><strong><em>Rebecca Wilder</em></strong><br /><strong><br /></strong> cross posted with  <a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/2012/08/08/world-trade-turning-down/?utm_source=rss&#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=world-trade-turning-down">The Wilder View&#8230;Economonitors</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/08/world-trade-turning-down.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Euro Area Retail Sales Portend Negative Quarter of Real Consumption</title>
		<link>./../../2012/08/euro-area-retail-sales-portend-negative-quarter-of-real-consumption.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/08/euro-area-retail-sales-portend-negative-quarter-of-real-consumption.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 05 Aug 2012 13:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[economic growth]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[euro area]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rebecca Wilder]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[retail sales]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/08/euro-area-retail-sales-portend-negative-quarter-of-real-consumption.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Euro Area Retail Sales Portend Negative Quarter of Real Consumption by Rebecca Wilder Today Eurostat released its June estimate of real retail sales for the Euro area. On a month/month basis, real retail sales increased at a rate of 0.1%. However, on a trended basis, the 3-month/3-month average growth rate was down 0.7% in the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>Euro Area Retail Sales Portend Negative Quarter of Real Consumption</h3>
<p>by <a href="http://www.economonitor.com/blog/author/rwilder3">Rebecca Wilder</a></p>
<p>Today <a href="http://epp.eurostat.ec.europa.eu/cache/ITY_PUBLIC/4-03082012-AP/EN/4-03082012-AP-EN.PDF">Eurostat released </a>its June estimate of real retail sales for the Euro area. On a month/month basis, real retail sales increased at a rate of 0.1%. However, on a trended basis, the 3-month/3-month average growth rate was down 0.7% in the three months ending in June. Given that the 3-month trended pace of contraction quickened compared to Q1, real consumption is likely to detract from Q2 GDP growth (spending components released on August 23).</p>
<p>On a Y/Y growth basis, there’s a 96% correlation between real retail sales and real private consumption by households and non-profit institutions. Using a simple linear regression, the annual growth rate of consumption should stabilize somewhat in Q2 compared to Q1.<br />\<br /><img alt="" height="362" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/08/EA_retail_sales_chart.jpg" width="489"></p>
<p>Across the region, real retail sales in Ireland, Estonia, and Germany are the only reported countries to see growth through Q2.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p><em>Note: the chart below illustrates the 3-Month/3-Month growth rate through June 2012 (Q2/Q1).</em><br /><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/08/retail_sales_country.jpg"><img alt="" height="375" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/08/retail_sales_country.jpg" width="492"></a></p>
<p>On balance, Q2 domestic consumption spending in the Euro area is expected to be buoyed by Germany through June. The problem is, German retail sales growth have just a 38% correlation with real consumption growth, so the bump in retail sales won’t necessarily feed through to consumption at the aggregate level.<br />Euro area real consumption is still contracting. The question then becomes: will the pace of consumption contraction increase or decrease in coming quarters? We’ll have to watch leading indicators such as retail and consumer confidence, <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/economy_finance/db_indicators/surveys/documents/2012/bcs_2012_07_en.pdf">both of which deteriorated in July</a>.<br /><strong><em><br /></em></strong><br /><strong><em>Rebecca Wilder</em></strong></p>
<p>cross posted with <a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/2012/08/03/euro-area-retail-sales-portend-negative-quarter-of-real-consumption/">The Wilder View&#8230;Economonitors</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/08/euro-area-retail-sales-portend-negative-quarter-of-real-consumption.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Evidence of Hampered Monetary Policy Transmission Channel in the Euro Area</title>
		<link>./../../2012/08/evidence-of-hampered-monetary-policy-transmission-channel-in-the-euro-area.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/08/evidence-of-hampered-monetary-policy-transmission-channel-in-the-euro-area.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 02 Aug 2012 11:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[interest rates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rebecca Wilder]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/08/evidence-of-hampered-monetary-policy-transmission-channel-in-the-euro-area.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Evidence of Hampered Monetary Policy Transmission Channel in the Euro Area by Rebecca Wilder Mario Draghi cautioned on the ‘hampered’ transmission channel of monetary policy in his now famous London speech last week: To the extent that the size of these sovereign premia hampers the functioning of the monetary policy transmission channel, they come within [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>Evidence of Hampered Monetary Policy Transmission Channel in the Euro Area</h3>
<p>by <a href="http://www.economonitor.com/blog/author/rwilder3">Rebecca Wilder</a> </p>
<p>Mario Draghi cautioned on the ‘hampered’ transmission channel of monetary policy in his now famous <a href="http://www.ecb.int/press/key/date/2012/html/sp120726.en.html">London speech last week</a>:<br />
<blockquote><em>To the extent that the size of these sovereign premia hampers the functioning of the monetary policy transmission channel, they come within our mandate.</em></p></blockquote>
<p>I referred to the clogging of rates policy <a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/2012/04/04/ecb-rates-policy-is-clogged-in-key-periphery-markets/">back in April </a>via evidence from mortgage lending rates.<br />
<blockquote><em>I address Draghi’s point that the ECB 1% refi rate will support economic activity through the lens of the mortgage market. Specifically, I find that the interest rate channel is clogged in the economies that are in most desperate need of lower rates: Spain, Portugal, and Italy.</em></p></blockquote>
<p>Here I show that on a relative basis, while the household lending rate is quietly trending down for key periphery markets, the real problem lies in the non-financial corporate rates transmission channel. Specifically, rates in Portugal, Italy, and Spain have seriously diverged from both the trend in the refi rate (ECB policy rate) and those of other countries in the Euro area.</p>
<p><strong>The trend in key periphery household mortgage rates is consistent with the ECB rate cuts: down</strong><br /><em>Note: All ECB refi rate data is through June 2012, so the latest rate cut to 75 bps is not included in the charts.</em><br /><em><br /></em><br /><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/08/cross_hh_rates.jpg"><img alt="" height="395" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/08/cross_hh_rates.jpg" width="578"></a><br /><strong><br /></strong><br /><strong></strong><br /><a name="more"></a><strong><br /></strong><br /><strong>The magnitude still favors the core</strong> – the drop in German mortgage rates is 91 basis points since the max mortgage rate of the Euro area as a whole in August 2011 – <strong>but the trend is down for all countries</strong>.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/08/hh_change.jpg"><img alt="" height="395" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/08/hh_change.jpg" width="537"></a><br /><strong><br /></strong><br /><strong>In stark contrast to the trend in household mortgages relative to the ECB refi rate, non-financial corporate lending rates in Portugal, Spain, and Italy diverged from the other country trends.</strong><br /><strong><br /></strong><br /><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/08/cross_nfc.jpg"><img alt="" height="395" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/08/cross_nfc.jpg" width="578"></a></p>
<p>If the ECB means business on improving the monetary transmission channel, they’ll need to attack the price of corporate loans in the Periphery markets.</p>
<p><strong><em>Rebecca Wilder</em></strong><br /><strong><em><br /></em></strong><br /><strong>Data Note:</strong> All non-financial corporate AAR lending rates is the annualized agreed rate on new business loans with a maturity of greater than 5 years and amount between €0.25 bn and €1 bn. Irish data is not available in Ireland and the Greek data is too sporadic.</p>
<p>cross posted with <a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/2012/08/01/evidence-on-clogged-transmission-channel-of-monetary-policy-in-the-euro-area/">The Wilder View&#8230;Economonitors</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/08/evidence-of-hampered-monetary-policy-transmission-channel-in-the-euro-area.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Euro Area Crisis Hits Confidence in the Core</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/euro-area-crisis-hits-confidence-in-the-core.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/euro-area-crisis-hits-confidence-in-the-core.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 26 Jul 2012 12:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[confidence indicators]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[euro area]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rebecca Wilder]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/euro-area-crisis-hits-confidence-in-the-core.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Rebecca Wilder Euro Area Crisis Hits Confidence in the Core France’s INSEE business confidence, Germany’s Ifo business climate, and theNational Bank of Belgium’s business survey demonstrate ongoing infection as the Euro area debt crisis hits business expectations in the core. Through July, business confidence in Germany and France continued to slide while that in [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Rebecca Wilder</p>
<p>Euro Area Crisis Hits Confidence in the Core</p>
<p>France’s <a href="http://www.insee.fr/en/themes/info-rapide.asp?id=11&#038;date=20120724">INSEE business confidence</a>, Germany’s <a href="http://www.cesifo-group.de/portal/page/portal/ifoHome/a-winfo/d1index/10indexgsk">Ifo business climate</a>, and the<a href="http://www.nbb.be/DOC/DQ/E/DQ3/HISTO/PEC1207.PDF">National Bank of Belgium’s business survey </a>demonstrate ongoing infection as the Euro area debt crisis hits business expectations in the core. Through July, business confidence in Germany and France continued to slide while that in Belgium rebounded, albeit from a low base.</p>
<p>Of note, the service industries in both Germany and Belgium may offer a “ray of hope” (the Ifo Institute puts it.), as these large economic sectors are perhaps stabilizing in the surveys.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/07/bus_co.jpg"><img alt="" height="376" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/07/bus_co.jpg" width="503"></a></p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Furthermore, consumer confidence in the <a href="http://www.cbs.nl/en-GB/menu/themas/dossiers/conjunctuur/publicaties/conjunctuurbericht/inhoud/verwachting/2012-07-19-m10.htm">Netherlands</a> and <a href="http://www.istat.it/en/archive/67623">Italy</a> remain depressed. Notably, the July prints increased 8 and 1.1 points, respectively, over the month – is this the start of a trend, or rather a dead-cat bounce? If I were a betting girl, I’d go with the latter, given the weakness in labor markets and election cycles coming up (September in the Netherlands and TBA in Italy).</p>
<p><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/07/cons_conf.jpg"><img alt="" height="376" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/07/cons_conf.jpg" width="503"></a></p>
<p>In Germany, the Ifo survey has deteriorated swiftly in recent months. This now brings this survey more in line with other business surveys, such as the German PMI, which had shown a more pronounced economic decline.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/07/ifo.jpg"><img alt="" height="376" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/07/ifo.jpg" width="503"></a></p>
<p>The Ifo Business Climate survey contains a wealth of information, but is generally dissected into assessment of the current business situation and expectations of the future business environment. The current environment survey, 111.6 in July, fell over the month but remains above the longer term average, 102. In contrast, expectations as regards the future business environment are falling swiftly. The Euro area crisis is impacting the business decision process.</p>
<p>Finally, as demonstrated in the Ifo Business Climate survey that highlighted its ‘significant deterioration’, the manufacturing base is leading the way down. In France and Germany, <a href="http://www.markiteconomics.com/Survey/Page.mvc/PressReleases">Markit Manufacturing PMIs </a>hit the low 40s, 43.6 and 43.3, respectively in July. This implies a quickening of the pace of contraction across the French and German manufacturing bases with not much hope of near-term relief, neither from domestic nor foreign demand. The <a href="http://www.cbs.nl/en-GB/menu/themas/dossiers/conjunctuur/publicaties/conjunctuurbericht/inhoud/verwachting/2012-07-25-m09.htm">Dutch Statistical Agency, CBS</a>, today reported further decline of Dutch manufacturing opinions in July, as manufacturers anticipate layoffs.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/07/pmi_manufacturing.jpg"><img alt="" height="442" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/07/pmi_manufacturing.jpg" width="503"></a></p>
<p>My only question becomes how much weakness is needed in the core (Germany) to get a(nother) significant response from the ECB?<br /><strong><em><br /></em></strong><br /><strong><em>Rebecca Wilder</em></strong></p>
<p>cross posted with <a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/2012/07/25/euro-area-crisis-hits-confidence-in-the-core/?utm">The Wilder View&#8230;Economonitors</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/euro-area-crisis-hits-confidence-in-the-core.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
