<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Chris Christie &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Is all of this LEGAL? &#8212; Specifics added, 2/16</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/is-all-of-this-legal-specifics-added-216.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/is-all-of-this-legal-specifics-added-216.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2013 17:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Chris Christie]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Huffington Post]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jason Cherkis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jesse Jackson Jr. Rod Blagojevich]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Marco Rubio]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ryan Grimm]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/is-all-of-this-legal-specifics-added-216.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[By “this,” I mean this.  I don’t know, but it sounds to me like some of it is not.   Wish I could ask Chris Christie, a former (very high-profile) U.S. Attorney for the District of New Jersey (2001-2008).  He would know.   &#8212;-UPDATE:  In light of the comments to this post, saying that Florida [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By “this,” I mean <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2013/02/13/marco-rubio-finances_n_2678744.html">this</a>.  I don’t know, but it sounds to me like some of it is not.  </p>
<p>Wish I could ask Chris Christie, a former (very high-profile) U.S. Attorney for the District of New Jersey (2001-2008).  He would know.  </p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />UPDATE:  In light of the comments to this post, saying that Florida law allows the type of influence-peddling that Rubio has engaged in (presumably, unless there’s some overt quid pro quo)&#8211;something that the article I linked to does make clear&#8211;I want to clarify what I think may be illegal (i.e., violate federal law, thus my reference to Chris Christie).  From the article: </p>
<div dir="ltr">For Rubio, a rising star in the Republican Party, more government did indeed create more opportunities. As <a href="http://www.tampabay.com/news/politics/national/marco-rubios-personal-finances-clash-with-call-for-fiscal-discipline/1129566">the Tampa Bay Times</a> reported during his U.S. Senate run in 2010, it&#8217;s hard to determine with Rubio where politics stops and the private begins:</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">As Rubio climbed the ranks, he began to use little-noticed political committees to fund his travel and other expenses and later had a Republican Party of Florida credit card.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">What emerged, records show, is a pattern of blending personal and political spending. Over and over again Rubio proved sloppy, at best, in complying with disclosure requirements.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Virtually broke, the 31-year-old lawmaker began campaigning to be House speaker in 2003 and created a political committee &#8212; Floridians for Conservative Leadership &#8212; to help elect other Republican candidates and curry their support.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">With his wife serving as treasurer, Rubio did not wait for the state to authorize the committee before accepting campaign donations.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">The committee listed its address as Rubio&#8217;s home, a modest place he and his wife bought in West Miami in 2002, but reported spending nearly $85,000 in office and operating costs and $65,000 for administrative costs.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Over 18 months, nearly $90,000 went for political consultants, $51,000 went for credit card payments and $4,000 went to other candidates. That&#8217;s less than the $5,700 that went to his wife, Jeanette, much of it for &#8220;gas and meals.&#8221; (Mrs. Rubio does not work and the couple file joint tax returns.)</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Virtually broke, the 31-year-old lawmaker began campaigning to be House speaker in 2003 and created a political committee &#8212; Floridians for Conservative Leadership &#8212; to help elect other Republican candidates and curry their support.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">With his wife serving as treasurer, Rubio did not wait for the state to authorize the committee before accepting campaign donations.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">The committee listed its address as Rubio&#8217;s home, a modest place he and his wife bought in West Miami in 2002, but reported spending nearly $85,000 in office and operating costs and $65,000 for administrative costs.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Over 18 months, nearly $90,000 went for political consultants, $51,000 went for credit card payments and $4,000 went to other candidates. That&#8217;s less than the $5,700 that went to his wife, Jeanette, much of it for &#8220;gas and meals.&#8221; (Mrs. Rubio does not work and the couple file joint tax returns.)</div>
<p>Some of this sounds to me like taxable (but probably undeclared) income for him and his wife, beyond just his wife’s salary and actual expenses related to the PAC.  The PAC also sounds like it was largely a fraud; its stated purpose was to help elect other Republicans to the state legislature, and I guess some of the consulting was used by or for other candidates, although the article doesn’t make that clear, but just a tiny percentage of the donations were given to other candidates.</p>
<p>But also, two other things the article mentions sound like they violate federal law:</p>
<ul>
<li dir="ltr">Rubio <a href="http://www.tampabay.com/news/politics/elections/rubios-campaign-image-belies-history-of-250-million-in-pork-requests/1078548">earmarked money</a> to Florida International University and later got an unadvertised job as a part-time professor at the school. The former school president, Mitch Maidique, said Rubio was &#8220;worth every penny.&#8221;</li>
</ul>
<p>
<ul>
<li dir="ltr">After appropriating millions of dollars to Miami Children&#8217;s and Jackson Memorial Hospitals, Rubio formed a lobby shop and<a href="http://big.assets.huffingtonpost.com/RubioHerald.pdf"> got contracts</a> with the hospitals.</li>
</ul>
<p>Some of these things sound like things that Jesse Jackson Jr. and his wife <a href="http://www.politico.com/story/2013/02/jesse-jackson-jr-to-plead-guilty-to-federal-charges-87716.html?hp=f3">were formally charged with yesterday</a>, albeit on a much quieter scale, and some of the other things sound similar in nature, if not scale, to what former Illinois governor Rod Blagojevich was convicted of.  </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/is-all-of-this-legal-specifics-added-216.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Marco Rubio Needs to Travel More. Seriously. [Updated and lightly edited.]</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/marco-rubio-needs-to-travel-more-seriously-updated-and-lightly-edited.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/marco-rubio-needs-to-travel-more-seriously-updated-and-lightly-edited.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2013 19:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Chris Christie]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jonathan Martin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Marco Rubio]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Krugman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politico]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The New York Times]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/marco-rubio-needs-to-travel-more-seriously-updated-and-lightly-edited.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Mr. President, I still live in the same working-class neighborhood I grew up in. My neighbors aren’t millionaires. They’re retirees who depend on Social Security and Medicare. They’re workers who have to get up early tomorrow morning and go to work to pay the bills. They’re immigrants, who came here because they were stuck in [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">Mr. President, I still live in the same working-class neighborhood I grew up in. My neighbors aren’t millionaires. They’re retirees who depend on Social Security and Medicare. They’re workers who have to get up early tomorrow morning and go to work to pay the bills. They’re immigrants, who came here because they were stuck in poverty in countries where the government dominated the economy.</div>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; Marco Rubio, last night. </div>
<p>I lifted that quote from <a href="http://dyn.politico.com/printstory.cfm?uuid=6A9DCC73-62AF-402E-9EED-3F327BE18F7B">a Politico article by Jonathan Martin</a> that went on to say that Rubio left school with more than $100,000 in student-loan debt, which he finished paying off only a few months ago. Presumably, those loans were government-sponsored.  Although maybe at the age of 18, he had some collateral to offer the bank.</p>
<p>Rubio’s parents, like so many of his working-class neighbors now, emigrated from Cuba before 2001, when the first of the two sets of Bush tax cuts were passed.  Apparently, he hasn’t checked the federal income tax rates on individuals and corporations when his parents and his neighbors came here because they were stuck in poverty in countries where the government dominated the economy.  Because, best as I can tell, that comment about immigrants from countries where the government dominated the economy was intended as a warning about Obama’s and the congressional Democrats’ plans to have the government dominate the economy.  </p>
<p>So I’d like some specifics.  What policies and programs, current and proposed, does he have in mind?  Exactly?  Maybe next time he’s interviewed by some high-profile journalist, he’ll be asked that.  And maybe he’ll answer.  But I doubt it.</p>
<p>Anyway, for now, I’m left to speculate that he means raising tax rates to Clinton-era tax levels for people with non-investment incomes above $250,000 a year, and on corporations, and on investment income.  He also might mean Obamacare, but that’s questionable unless he thinks that only people who qualify for Medicare get cancer or other serious illnesses, because he also said this last night:</p>
<div dir="ltr">[Medicare] provided my father the care he needed to battle cancer and ultimately die with dignity.  And it pays for the care my mother receives now.</div>
<p>But the title of this post suggests that Rubio travel more.  Both within this country and outside of it.  First he should visit communities where immigrants from, say, Pakistan and Central America live.  People who came here to escape poverty but whose homeland governments did not, and do not, dominate the economy.*  </p>
<p>Then, if he has a passport, he might consider traveling outside the United States.  Maybe to Canada, or Germany, or Sweden, or Holland, or Australia.  Or France. Or, for that matter, Singapore.  Or Taiwan.  Or he could save the plane fare and just use the Internet to check the rates of poverty in those countries, the tax rates there, the social safety nets there, the education systems there, the healthcare systems there. </p>
<p>I didn’t watch the Rubio Show last night, so I missed the reaching-for-a-water-bottle-but-wishing-it-were-a-Vodka-bottle-instead moment.  I wish I’d watched, but I didn’t.  So I’m relying on tidbits reported by others.  And <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/02/13/marco-rubio-has-learned-nothing/">Paul Krugman provides one</a> that, unlike the quotes above, have not garnered much attention.  It’s this:</p>
<div dir="ltr">This idea – that our problems were caused by a government that was too small – it’s just not true. In fact, a major cause of our recent downturn was a housing crisis created by reckless government policies.</div>
<p>Krugman points out that numerous studies, as well as observation by, say, ordinary folks, dispel that claim. Specifically, Krugman writes:<br /><a name="more"></a>
<div dir="ltr">OK, leave on one side the caricature of Obama, with the usual mirror-image fallacy (we want smaller government, therefore liberals just want bigger government, never mind what it does); there we go with the “Barney Frank did it” story. Deregulation, the explosive growth of virtually unregulated shadow banking, lax lending standards by loan originators who sold their loans off as soon as they were made, had nothing to do with it — it was all the Community Reinvestment Act, Fannie, and Freddie.</div>
<div dir="ltr">Look, this is one of the most thoroughly researched topics out there, and every piece of the government-did-it thesis has been refuted; see <a href="http://rortybomb.wordpress.com/2011/11/01/bloombergs-awful-comment-what-can-we-say-for-certain-regarding-the-gses/">Mike Konczal for a summary.</a> No, the CRA wasn’t responsible for the epidemic of bad lending; no, Fannie and Freddie didn’t cause the housing bubble; no, the “high-risk” loans of the GSEs weren’t remotely as risky as subprime.</div>
<p>So I guess I was wrong when I said above that Rubio must have had only tax rates and Obamacare in mind.  He apparently also had finance-industry regulation in mind, too. And on this he was specific. </p>
<p>But on this too, I suggest some overseas travel&#8211;either physically, or virtually, on the Internet. He&#8217;d learn that Spain, Ireland and Iceland must have had a Fannie Mae and a Freddie Mac. Not to mention a Barney Frank. Because those countries’ current and recent fiscal and economic woes were caused entirely by a housing bubbles virtually identical to, or worse than, ours, spurred by Deregulation, the explosive growth of virtually unregulated shadow banking, lax lending standards by loan originators who sold their loans off as soon as they were made. </p>
<p>Then Rubio might consider returning to Canada and Germany, physically or virtually, and checking out why those countries had little or no such bubble.  And before he leaves, or after he returns, he should travel to Texas.  Yes, Texas, of all states.  It had almost no housing bubble.  Something to do with government involvement in the economy, i.e., legislation regulating the mortgage industry, post-savings-and-loan debacle, circa 1989.  State government, in this case. </p>
<p>What is the national debt of Canada and Germany?  And the poverty levels and standards of living in those countries?  </p>
<p>The Politico article, by the way, is called “Marco Rubio as the anti-Romney.”  The title of Krugman’s post indicates disagreement with that assessment. It’s called “Marco Rubio Has Learned Nothing.”  </p>
<p>But a majority of Americans, I think, have.  They’ve learned that you can’t judge a book by it’s jacket cover. And that ideology can’t substitute for fact. 
<div></div>
<div>&#8212;-<br />UPDATE:  Oh, dear. As I said, I didn’t watch Rubio last night.  I also haven’t read a transcript of his speech.  And I didn’t know until just now, when I read Jazzbumpa’s post below, that Rubio said that proposals to deal with climate change, including trying to slow its progression, are attempts to have the government “control the weather.”</p>
<p>Um.  Yeah.  That’s the idea.  </p>
<p>Yikes.</p></div>
<div>Why do I think Chris Christie is the happiest person in America today?</p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />UPDATE II:  I’m getting the strong feeling that there are a lot of people who are downright dumbfounded by that speech last night&#8211;that this guy who’s being touted as the Republican savior went on national television and established himself as stunningly stupid. </p>
<p>We’re going to elect a global warming denier as president in 2016?  We’re going to elect as president someone who is unaware of such things as financial derivatives, and the role they played in the financial meltdown?  We’re going to elect as president someone who seems not to know that student loans and Medicare are government programs&#8211;or at least what it means that they are?  We’re going to elect as president someone who thinks Clinton-era tax rates are a government-dominated economy?</p>
<p>I’ll certainly agree that he’s no Romney.  Romney isn’t stupid, by any stretch.  He just pretended to be.  With Rubio, it’s apparently no act. </p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />*<i>Paragraph edited for clarity</i>. 2/14. (I figured that since this post is getting a decent number of &#8220;hits&#8221; and Google+ links, it should be edited so that typos and such are corrected.)</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/marco-rubio-needs-to-travel-more-seriously-updated-and-lightly-edited.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sandy, Christie and Cantor. Oh, and Joplin, Missouri.</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/sandy-christie-and-cantor-oh-and-joplin-missouri.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/sandy-christie-and-cantor-oh-and-joplin-missouri.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2013 19:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Chris Christie]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Eric Cantor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hurricane Sandy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Boehner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/sandy-christie-and-cantor-oh-and-joplin-missouri.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[“There is only one group to blame for the continued suffering of these innocent victims,” New Jersey Gov. Chris Christie (R) said Wednesday. “The House majority and their speaker, John Boehner.” But after a closed-door session with the New York and New Jersey congressional delegations, Boehner announced that the House would vote on the measure [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">“There is only one group to blame for the continued suffering of these innocent victims,” New Jersey Gov. Chris Christie (R) said Wednesday. “The House majority and their speaker, John Boehner.”</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">But after a closed-door session with the New York and New Jersey congressional delegations, Boehner announced that the House would vote on the measure in two phases — first on Friday, for $9 billion in flood assistance, and then on an additional $51 billion on Jan. 15, the first full legislative day of the new Congress in the House.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">The House had been expected to vote on the package Tuesday night, but GOP aides said that became increasingly difficult as the fiscal-cliff package took final shape.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">They said s politically untenable after the cliff plan, with higher tax rates and no spending cutsthe specter of holding a vote on a federal aid package that included no offsetting spending cuts wa, split the Republican conference and could pass the House only with a large Democratic majority.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/christie-republicans-slam-boehner-for-delay-on-hurricane-sandy-relief-measure/2013/01/02/5d22454c-54f7-11e2-8b9e-dd8773594efc_story_1.html">Christie, Republicans slam Boehner for delay on Hurricane Sandy relief measure</a>, Nia-Malika Henderson and Ed O’Keefe, Washington Post, today</div>
<p>The article goes on to note that Christie exonerated House Majority Leader Eric Cantor from responsibility for this absurd fiasco.  Christie said he had spoken with Cantor several times on Tuesday and that Cantor had worked hard to gain passage of the relief measure before the close of this Congress on Wednesday night, to no avail.  But Boehner pulled the plug.  </p>
<p>Thus avoiding the the specter of holding a vote on a federal aid package that included no offsetting spending cuts.  And bringing Cantor’s chickens home to roost&#8211;in Boehner’s front yard.  </p>
<p>Oh, the irony.  Forgive me if my memory is faulty here, but I do seem to remember that it was Cantor, along with Paul Ryan (a redundancy, I think, since I’m convinced that they’re one and the same person), who back in 2011, after the tornado devastation of Joplin, Missouri and a few smaller towns in other states, tried to hold emergency financial aid hostage to an equivalent reduction of spending on social-safety-net programs&#8211;or was it the EPA, the FDA, the Agriculture Department,  the Consumer Product Safety Commission, the National Transportation Safety Commission, road and bridge maintenance and repair?  I forget.  </p>
<p>It was a great idea, and explained why these folks don’t want any action taken to prevent global warming and the more severe and frequent natural disasters that are resulting.  Bring on the destruction of the Eastern Seaboard and heartland small cities and towns, so that we can get rid of that pesky Medicare!  But it proved politically untenable then.  And it appears that Cantor, one of its chief original proponents, understands that.  A majority of the Republican House delegation apparently does not. </p>
<p>And, no wonder.  I mean, it’s not like they agree with Mitt Romney’s proposal&#8211;highlighted a week before the election, thanks to Sandy&#8211;to simply shut down FEMA and related federal emergency disaster relief programs.  If the states want to pick up the cost for this, fine. Let them. Or, better, the private sector can do this, for a profit!  (Got that, near-miss Romney running-mate Christie?  Got that, Rep. Peter King and the rest of you northeastern Republican pols?)  </p>
<p>Okay, that wasn’t the Republican House delegation’s proposal.  Not this time around, anyway.  Their proposal was simply to use natural disasters as a ploy to starve the beast in even more Republican-preferred ways.  But to their dismay, it is becoming clear that the beast about to be starved is none other than the dinosaur crowd. </p>
<p>And then there is this, from <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/01/03/us/politics/tax-deal-shows-possible-path-around-house-gop-in-fiscal-fights.html?ref=jonathanweisman">an article</a> by Jonathan Weisman in today’s New York Times:</p>
<div dir="ltr">Michael Steel, a spokesman for Mr. Boehner, said the last-minute crunch that produced the tax accord was necessary only because the Senate refused to act earlier. The House passed legislation months ago to extend all the expiring Bush-era tax cuts and to stop automatic military cuts by shifting them to domestic programs.</div>
<p>Of course, the Senate several months ago, I believe, passed competing legislation returning tax rates for incomes above $250,000, managing to escape filibuster because it was a “reconciliation” bill, or something.  Seems to me, and undoubtedly to a spokesman for Harry Reid (not to mention Reid himself), that the last-minute crunch that produced the tax accord was necessary only because the House refused to act earlier!</p>
<p>A veritable hallmark of the House Republican crowd is its stunning, stupifying childishness.  These people really, really need to grow up.  For their sake, not for the Dem’s, or even for the country’s.  Happily for Dem prospects in 2014, though, they probably won’t.  And then we finally will get policy solutions to this country’s real problems.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/sandy-christie-and-cantor-oh-and-joplin-missouri.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Chris Christie’s Sweet Dream (And Romney’s)</title>
		<link>./../../2012/04/chris-christies-sweet-dream-and-romneys.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/04/chris-christies-sweet-dream-and-romneys.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 11 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[auto-industry bailout]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chris Christie]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[couch potatoes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[student-loan program]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/04/chris-christies-sweet-dream-and-romneys.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[“I’ve never seen a less optimistic time in my lifetime in this country and people wonder why,” the first-term Republican governor said at the Bush Institute Conference on Taxes and Economic Growth in New York City. “I think it’s really simple. It’s because government’s now telling them ‘stop dreaming, stop striving, we’ll take care of [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>“I’ve never seen a less optimistic time in my lifetime in this country and people wonder why,” the first-term Republican governor said at the Bush Institute Conference on Taxes and Economic Growth in New York City.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>“I think it’s really simple. It’s because government’s now telling them ‘stop dreaming, stop striving, we’ll take care of you.’ We’re turning into a paternalistic entitlement society,” he said.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>“That will not just bankrupt us financially, it will bankrupt us morally because when the American people no longer believe that this a place where only their willingness to work hard … determines their success in life then we’ll have a bunch of people sittin’ on a couch waiting for their next government check,” Christie said.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212; &#8220;<a href="http://www.politico.com/news/stories/0412/74987.html">Christie: Nation of couch potatoes</a>,” Politico
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>That, pretty clearly, is the message that the Republicans, party-wide, have settled on for this election: People are depressed because of the existence of the social safety net and other government programs such as student-loan and job-retraining programs, and because the very wealthy haven’t had their tax rates cut enough, the gap between the very wealthy, and all those couch potatoes who work regular jobs isn’t large enough.  
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I wish them all the best with that message.  And I hope they keep pushing it, all the way to November. </p>
<p>I think it’s simple, too. I&#8217;ll leave it at that.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Can’t wait to hear the <i>next</i> installment of Christie’s VP audition script.  Maybe something about all those auto-industry-worker couch potatoes who’ve stopped dreaming and striving now that Obama has handed GM and Chrysler to the UAW?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>By the way, did Christie ever use the student-loan program, I wonder?  Or did he, like Romney and Romney’s kids, have no need for it?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>Christie was speaking at the Bush Institute Conference on Taxes and Economic Growth. Tomorrow’s audition will be by Paul Ryan. It’s a follow-up audition, actually.</p>
<p>&#8212;-
</p>
</div>
<div>Apparently, <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/04/05/nyregion/christie-gives-new-jersey-firms-tax-breaks-for-short-moves.html?pagewanted=all">not <i>all</i> government programs</a> cause mental depression.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/04/chris-christies-sweet-dream-and-romneys.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
