<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>James Hohmann &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Did Romney Begin to Reverse-Etch-A-Sketch Today?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/did-romney-begin-to-reverse-etch-a-sketch-today.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/did-romney-begin-to-reverse-etch-a-sketch-today.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Oct 2012 20:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[auto-industry bailout]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Etch-A-Sketch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[James Hohmann]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politico]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/did-romney-begin-to-reverse-etch-a-sketch-today.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[CINCINNATI, Ohio — Mitt Romney tried Thursday to borrow the campaign themes that got President Barack Obama elected in 2008. The Republican nominee repeatedly promised “big change” in Washington, a fresh phrase for him and one that he used more than a dozen times in a 20-minute speech at a rally that kicked off a [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>CINCINNATI, Ohio — Mitt Romney tried Thursday to borrow the campaign themes that got President Barack Obama elected in 2008.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The Republican nominee repeatedly promised “big change” in Washington, a fresh phrase for him and one that he used more than a dozen times in a 20-minute speech at a rally that kicked off a day-long Ohio bus tour.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212; <i><a href="http://dyn.politico.com/printstory.cfm?uuid=D4E0C41C-CBB5-4337-96D0-DA57F52C3631">Romney borrows Obama campaign themes</a></i>, James Hohmann, Politico, today,
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Seems to me that Obama should point out <i>what</i> big changes would be in store.  He can start with Medicare and then get into some other highlights of the Ryan budget—and of Romney’s primary-campaign statements, and run ads using clips of Romney saying these things.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>He can then point out that Romney is doing what he’s so good at: writing generic fine print that he can then point to and say, “But this is what I said during the campaign that I would do! Seeee??”
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Sorta like, it depends on what the meaning of “Let Detroit go bankrupt” means.  Which depends on what the meaning of “managed bankruptcy” is, when you’re suggesting that the government shouldn’t provide GM and Chrysler with money to fund a managed bankruptcy that would <i>not</i> result in liquidation.  Which in turn, I guess, depends on what the meaning of liquidation is.  </p>
<p>Which a very large number of people who are now employed directly or indirectly by those companies would have no trouble defining.
</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/did-romney-begin-to-reverse-etch-a-sketch-today.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
