<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>tax reform &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Screw the Clinton tax rates. Lets party like it&#8217;s 1936!</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/screw-the-clinton-tax-rates-lets-party-like-its-1936.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/screw-the-clinton-tax-rates-lets-party-like-its-1936.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 28 Jul 2012 05:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Bush tax cuts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income equality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[marginal rates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax rates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[top 1%]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/screw-the-clinton-tax-rates-lets-party-like-its-1936.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Update: *Additional numbers added Digby wrote a few days ago about the“grown-up” people coming to town to save America from the deficit. She listed a few of those people and their annual income. Also, a few days ago the Senate had a vote on the tax cuts. Letting the Bush cuts go (I&#8217;m all for [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div></div>
<div>Update: *Additional numbers added </p>
<p>Digby wrote a few days ago about<a href="http://digbysblog.blogspot.com/2012/07/the-grown-ups-are-planning-coup.html"> the“grown-up” people</a> coming to town to save America from the deficit.  She listed a few of those people and their annual income.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Also, a  few days ago the Senate had a vote on the tax cuts.  Letting the Bush cuts go (I&#8217;m all for it and we can stop the payroll tax cut too as it is all stupid policy when the problem is declining wages/income going to labor) will return us to the Clinton years rates.  People have noted just how little such a rise means to those at the top.     </div>
<div></div>
<div>Well, in keeping with my define rich series and my series looking at the purpose of taxation, I thought wouldn&#8217;t it be interesting to see just what these 1%&#8217;ers might be paying if we went back to the beginning of the last great period of <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/03/defining-rich-vi-1936-tax-tables.html">mass prosperity:  1936</a>.   </div>
<div></div>
<div>Yes indeedy, I say go for the brass ring.  Let&#8217;s show our maturity and actually implement the lesson learned from our history, that period from around <a href="http://www.taxhistory.org/www/website.nsf/Web/THM1901?OpenDocument">1906 to 1932</a> and then 1936 to 1979.   </div>
<div></div>
<div>While we&#8217;re at it, let us stop pretending that global trade is something new with an unknowable to man exotic force that we just have to accept as part of the expression of our DNA.   There is RNA also (look it up).</div>
<div></div>
<p><a name="more"></a>
<div></div>
<div>The following  numbers are based on the gross incomes Digby listed.  Thus we&#8217;ll have to keep in mind that there have been no adjustments made for deductions in my calculations.  So in truth, the tax paid would be less and the purchasing power of the actual non-adjusted income would be much greater.  After all, the deductions represent benefits received from the income that was deducted including the government handout in the form of reduced taxes for various activities taken with one&#8217;s income.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Here is what it looks like:</div>
<div><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-1cMkNPATmc8/UBN2YVEaQKI/AAAAAAAAASw/WiV0pUMcLRU/s1600/Party+like+it+1936+income+tax+chart.jpg" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="177" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-1cMkNPATmc8/UBN2YVEaQKI/AAAAAAAAASw/WiV0pUMcLRU/s320/Party+like+it+1936+income+tax+chart.jpg" width="320"></a></div>
<div>All these men managed to hit the top marginal rate of 79%.  Not one of them paid that amount.  Notice how flat the percentage paid becomes.  They want a flat tax, the got it.  They just had to really, really perform to get to that level of tax nirvana in 1936.  They couldn&#8217;t just pull a <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0102609/">Lawrence Garfield</a>, or should I say a Romney?  They couldn&#8217;t just negotiate payment in stock, whack labor costs to increase the stock value, take that money and buy it&#8217;s competitors to the point of oligopoly and then move on.  They could not just raid a solid company like New England Wire and Cable turning all the assets into cash at the expense of all the other relationships such a company had and justify it by saying “I make you money”.  Greenmail?  Junk Bonds?</div>
<div></div>
<div>I wrote <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/07/wages-driven-down-now-relative-to.html">about Caterpillar </a>and their approach to negotiating with the commodity of labor.  The average yearly income of the labor was $55,000/year.  The multiples of the above net income range from 24.8 to 147.38.  (* Multiples of the gross incomes range from 104.6 to 688.)</div>
<div></div>
<div>Granted, what&#8217;s left for these gentlemen would not allow the purchase of a new Cessna Citation X, but there was a 1999 listed for $5,950,000 when I search google.  I think Mr. Sherill could afford the monthly payment on this.  Though <a href="http://www.cessna.com/citation/mustang.html">Cessna is offering the 4 passenger</a> (the X is 12 passenger) at 0% interest for the first 12 months and Wiki says they list for only $2.65 million!  You know, if buying used just curls your hair.</div>
<div></div>
<div>The point?  There is nothing with the 1936 marginal tax rates that these men can not have other than more of it.  Nothing.   Real grown-ups who developed the 1936 tax table new this along with a lot of other stuff related income how it is actually earned and it&#8217;s social effect.  All you have to do is<a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/03/defining-rich-vi-1936-tax-tables.html"> lookat the tables and graphs</a> to see that the marginal rates were not pulled out of selfish and self serving asses.  They had a desired results in mind, one of which was to prevent “economic royalists”.  I am confident the other desire was to take back rent collected from other peoples collective efforts in proportion to the lack of labor performed as one rises up the economic pyramid.    </div>
<div></div>
<div>Have you heard the one about job creation?  The one that asks: When was the last time a poor person gave you a job?  When was the last time a CEO 1%&#8217;er&#8217;s activity saved the human race?   Four people at least from 1928 to the patent granted in 1948 were involved in<a href="http://inventors.about.com/od/pstartinventions/a/Penicillin.htm"> bring penicillin to the point ofcommercial viability</a>. </div>
<div>It was one woman&#8217;s work that allowed the next step of developing additional antibiotics.  </div>
<div></div>
<div>When was the last time a CEO 1% er&#8217;s activity resulted in a leap of human progress?   I&#8217;m thinking of my favorite non-CEO/Banker/1% example of flight.  No, Gates and Jobs did not do it like the Wright Brothers did it.  </div>
<div></div>
<div>1936.  We responded in a way that attest to a time when we did learn from history and acted on lessons from history.</div>
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/screw-the-clinton-tax-rates-lets-party-like-its-1936.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Hey, didn&#8217;t the GOP say it cared about deficits?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/03/hey-didnt-the-gop-say-it-cared-about-deficits.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/03/hey-didnt-the-gop-say-it-cared-about-deficits.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 09 Mar 2012 22:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Linda Beale (Tax law)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[small business]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax reform]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/03/hey-didnt-the-gop-say-it-cared-about-deficits.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Beale  Hey, didn&#8217;t the GOP say it cared about deficits? Just when you think those on the radical right had gone about as far as they could go without recognizing their own zaniness, those in Congress have revived their version of a tax &#8220;reform&#8221; for businesses.  It was first proposed in 2009&#8211;as an [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Linda Beale</p>
<p> Hey, didn&#8217;t the GOP say it cared about deficits?</p>
<p>  Just when you think those on the radical right had gone about as far as they could go without recognizing their own zaniness, those in Congress have revived their version of a tax &#8220;reform&#8221; for businesses.  It was first proposed in 2009&#8211;as an alternative to real stimulus spending on infrastructure .  And yes, it is yet another tax cut.  An even zanier one than the rest that they&#8217;ve come up with while at the same time whining of deficits and suggesting that longstanding social programs like Social Security and Medicare must be cut back.<br />Eric Cantor, in a memo last month to fellow Republicans, announced that the House would be putting this proposal forward&#8211;let every business with 500 employees or fewer deduct off the top 20% of their income.  And they want to pass this rot by the filing deadline&#8211;on the pretense that it will help ordinary folk.<br />See Richard Rubin, <a href="http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/g/a/2012/03/08/bloomberg_articlesM0JGMG6JTSF401-M0JGM.DTL">Hedge Fund Tax Break May Come in Republican Small Business Plan</a>, San Francisco Chronicle (Bloomberg News, Mar. 8, 2012).</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Now, folks, there are some mighty BIG businesses with fewer than 500 employees.  Like just about every hedge fund and leveraged buyout fund. (The latter, of course, like to call themselves &#8220;private equity&#8221; these days&#8211;let&#8217;s people overlook the fact that they have destroyed many a stable, profitable business by loading them up with debt and sucking out all the cash while firing employees or making the business focus on paying back the debt and not on doing business).  Why would the GOP want to reward those funds with even more tax breaks than they already grab for themselves&#8211;carried interest, pass-through taxation, and the ability to avoid the payroll taxes since they treat their compensation as though it were an investment gain?  Because that is what they are all about&#8211;making sure the richest people in the country get all the breaks.</p>
<p>Then there are sports teams.  Liquor stores.  Golf courses. Gambling dens&#8230;.. Hotels. Restaurants.  Engineering firms. Accounting firms.  Law firms.  Architectural firms.  Big Business that normally make Big Money.<br />Just goes to show that the corporatist GOP never saw a tax break for the monied class that it didn&#8217;t like. </p>
<p>crossposted with <a target="_blank" href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2012/03/hey-didnt-the-gop-say-it-cared-about-deficits.html">ataxingmatter</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/03/hey-didnt-the-gop-say-it-cared-about-deficits.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>How the Internet Can Make You Smarter, Today&#8217;s FT Version</title>
		<link>./../../2012/02/how-the-internet-can-make-you-smarter-todays-ft-version.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/02/how-the-internet-can-make-you-smarter-todays-ft-version.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2012 16:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[corporate taxation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[FT]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jourmalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax reform]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/02/how-the-internet-can-make-you-smarter-todays-ft-version.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Today&#8217;s Page 1, above-the-fold, biggest type headlines for the FT: US PDF edition: &#8220;Obama proposes corporate tax rate cut: System &#8216;outdated, unfair, and inefficient&#8217; US Print edition: &#8220;Obama and Romney unveil rival tax plans: Proposals show strong support for reforms&#8221; The latter piece waits until the 7th graf to Tell the Truth and Shame the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Today&#8217;s Page 1, above-the-fold, biggest type headlines for the FT:</p>
<ol>
<li>US PDF edition: &#8220;Obama proposes corporate tax rate cut: System &#8216;outdated, unfair, and inefficient&#8217;
<p><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-MkEm56V8OE4/T0ZYbdiyGrI/AAAAAAAAAvg/iEwH74J7gMo/s1600/FTPDF20120223.PNG"><img src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-MkEm56V8OE4/T0ZYbdiyGrI/AAAAAAAAAvg/iEwH74J7gMo/s320/FTPDF20120223.PNG" border="0" alt=""></a></p>
<p></p>
</li>
<li>US Print edition:  &#8220;Obama and Romney unveil rival tax plans: Proposals show strong support for reforms&#8221;</li>
</ol>
<p>The latter piece waits until the 7th graf to Tell the Truth and Shame the Romney (as Rick Santorum might say):</p>
<blockquote><p>Mr. Romney&#8217;s advisers said that their plan would not widen the deficit, but they relied on so-called &#8220;dynamic effects&#8221;, which assume that the lower rates mean greater economic growth and therefore more revenue. They did not say which tax breaks—such as the popular deduction for mortgage interest relief—they might scrap to pay for the lower rates.</p></blockquote>
<p>The English translation of &#8220;dynamic effects&#8221; is &#8220;we&#8217;re going to reduce the velocity of money so that it is held by people whose Marginal Propensity to Consume is lower, and count that as a good thing, instead of it being used by people who will not hide it in the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TOPIX">TOPIX</a>, and who therefore don&#8217;t count in economic modeling.  Because that worked well when we did it in 2001 and especially 2003.&#8221; (See <a href="http://noahpinionblog.blogspot.com/2012/02/are-macroeconomic-methods-politically.html">Noah Smith</a> for discussion.)</p>
<p>The print edition treats this mumbo-jumbo as if it were a real &#8220;tax plan.&#8221;  Readers of the online PDF are saved such bollocks, and therefore better informed at the end of the article.</p>
<p>UPDATE: Ezra Klein (whom Google Plus seems to believe works for Bloomberg, not the web-inept Vast Wasteland that is Kaplan Prep Daily) <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/ezra-klein/post/a-narrative-of--life-under-a-romney-presidency/2011/08/25/gIQAf9ptTR_blog.html">delves into the Romney/Hubbard plan</a> and finds pretty much <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glenn_Hubbard_(economist)#Government">what you would expect from the man who led the clusterfuck of 2003</a> and <a href="http://delong.typepad.com/sdj/2011/07/glenn-hubbard-ten-years-late-and-at-least-6-trillion-short.html">an at best ambiguous relationship with Medicare Part D</a>* (&#8220;all of the expenses without any of the savings, unfunded&#8221;):</p>
<blockquote><p>But for now, the narrative is clear: A Romney presidency will be tough on those who depend on government programs, and good for those who pay high taxes. That suggests a Romney presidency would, at least in its first few years, reduce the deficit by asking much more from the poor than from the rich. Is that really the narrative they want?</p></blockquote>
<p>*Shorter <a href="http://www.democraticunderground.com/discuss/duboard.php?az=view_all&#038;address=103x562188">Glenn Hubbard</a>: &#8220;It happened on my watch, and I knew it was in the works, but the &#8220;gross mismanagement&#8221; of the Bush Administration in enacting Medicare Part D astounds me and I had nothing to do with it.&#8221;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/02/how-the-internet-can-make-you-smarter-todays-ft-version.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Warm Wind At the Backs of Some, Generated Off the Backs of Others</title>
		<link>./../../2011/10/a-warm-wind-at-the-backs-of-some-generated-off-the-backs-of-others.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/10/a-warm-wind-at-the-backs-of-some-generated-off-the-backs-of-others.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2011 13:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[dividends]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wages]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/10/a-warm-wind-at-the-backs-of-some-generated-off-the-backs-of-others.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This piece offers an understandable comparison between wages and dividend income and neatly summarizes the cost to wage earners. (h/t Mike Kimel) by Peter S. Meyers Myers Urbatsch PC A Warm Wind At the Backs of Some, Generated Off the Backs of Others Yesterday, I learned in this Mother Jones article that workers have increased [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This piece offers an understandable comparison between wages and dividend  income  and neatly summarizes the cost to wage earners.  (h/t Mike Kimel)
<p>by Peter S. Meyers</p>
<p>Myers Urbatsch PC</p>
<p><a target="_blank" href="http://petermyers.typepad.com/my_weblog/2011/07/a-warm-wind-at-the-backs-of-some-generated-off-the-backs-of-others.html">A Warm Wind At the Backs of Some, Generated Off the Backs of Others </a> Yesterday, I learned in <a href="http://motherjones.com/politics/2011/02/income-inequality-in-america-chart-graph">this Mother Jones article</a> that workers have increased their contribution to government revenue disproportionately since 1980.  In other words, payroll tax (paid by workers) is a larger portion of government revenue than it used to be.  That&#8217;s a macroeconomic analysis, which still doesn&#8217;t answer the question of whether rich people are being treated &#8220;unfairly&#8221; by the current tax system.  </p>
<p>So to elaborate a little, let&#8217;s take two people who make exactly the same amount:  $100,000 in taxable income (after the standard deduction &#8211; let&#8217;s not get complicated).  &#8220;Worker Taxpayer&#8221; earns her money by working (getting compensation by way of a W2) and &#8220;Investor Taxpayer&#8221; earns her money from dividends in a $4 million stock portfolio she holds (its about 2.5% in yield &#8211; about right).  Let&#8217;s say they are both unmarried.  Investor taxpayer does not work and has no compensation income.  They are otherwise &#8220;equal,&#8221; right? (except that investor taxpayer fits the description of those who vituperate about lazy welfare recipients who sit on the couch all day and watch TV, right?)  I&#8217;ll keep the rhetoric down, because the facts are outrageous enough to speak for themselves.</p>
<p> <a name="more"></a>
<p>Worker taxpayer will pay $7650 in payroll tax, plus $21,617 in income tax (2011 brackets), for a total tax burden of $29,267. </p>
<p>Let&#8217;s look at investor taxpayer.  You would think they would be taxed at the same rate as worker, right?  Wrong.  Because investor taxpayer receives all of her income from qualified dividends, they get a &#8220;special&#8221; tax treatment.  Bear with me, we&#8217;re almost done.  Generally, the maximum tax rate for qualified<strong></strong> dividends is 15%, BUT HERE it is actually 0% because investor&#8217;s other income (remember she doesn&#8217;t work) is taxed at the 10% or 15% rate. </p>
<p>To refresh:  worker making $100K pays about $30K in tax.  Investor making $100K in qualified dividends pays $0 &#8211; no &#8211; tax.  Huh?  Yup.  </p>
<p>What this means is that rich people &#8211; who are incented by tax policy to remain on their couches (too much earned income would otherwise trip them into the 15% dividend tax bracket) &#8211; are now getting off their couches and going to tea-party rallies to maintain this unfair redistribution of wealth in their favor.  For if they work, they risk having their dividends taxed at 15% (still half of what, say, worker taxpayer paid in taxes, but confiscatory in their view).  Perverse incentive?  Yup.  Does it sound like the rhetoric of the right wingers about unemployed persons and welfare recipients laying on couches and not incented to work?  Hm. . . .</p>
<p>Now let&#8217;s say you didn&#8217;t work, or you worked very little, and instead you made all of your income from qualified dividends.  The &#8220;magic number&#8221; (the income threshold you need to stay under to avoid paying any tax on your dividend income) is $69,000 (married), $34,500 (single or married filing separately) or $46,250 (head of household).  Thus, you can actually work a little, and you have all this extra time &#8211; to attend rallies, political functions, cook your food, clean your house or do other things that people who actually earn their income from working have to: (a) pay someone else to do (which is not deductible), (b) do in the evenings or on weekends, or (c) simply let it slide.</p>
<p>I will now illustrate how it is almost impossible for someone who is already rich to not get richer, in fact much richer.  Both working taxpayer and investor taxpayer have identical lifestyles and thus spend the exact same amount of money (not likely, given that worker has to pay for commuting expenses &#8211; again NOT deductible).  Let&#8217;s assume that&#8217;s $70,000 per year.  We know that worker taxpayer already paid $30K in tax, so let&#8217;s see what they have left to save:  uh, nothing.  Investor taxpayer paid no tax, so what do they have left over to save: $30K.  Exactly the same amount that worker taxpayer paid in taxes.</p>
<p>The rationale for the tax policy you see illustrated above is George W. Bush&#8217;s.  In 2003 he said that &#8220;double taxation is bad for our economy and falls especially hard on retired people.&#8221; He also argued that while &#8220;it&#8217;s fair to tax a company&#8217;s profits, it&#8217;s not fair to double-tax by taxing the shareholder on the same profits.&#8221;</p>
<p>Its odd to me that the above disparate treatment of otherwise similarly-situated earners is defended on the basis of &#8220;fairness.&#8221;  Is this 1984?  And I also wonder whether there is a joke in there somewhere &#8211; i.e., given that a zero-percent tax bracket would apply to someone who made all of their money from dividends and capital gains, why wouldn&#8217;t they retire?  I sure as hell would.  Working too much would bump all of their dividend income into the 15% tax bracket.  Volunteering for the tea-party rally, or perhaps some other Republican cause, would be a far better use of one&#8217;s time.</p>
<p>    reposted with permission of the author  July 23, 2011 post</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/10/a-warm-wind-at-the-backs-of-some-generated-off-the-backs-of-others.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Herman Cain, funded by Koch Bros, Says &#034;Let the Little Guys Pay Taxes</title>
		<link>./../../2011/10/herman-cain-funded-by-koch-bros-says-let-the-little-guys-pay-taxes.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/10/herman-cain-funded-by-koch-bros-says-let-the-little-guys-pay-taxes.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2011 11:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[flat tax]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linda Beale (Tax law)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax reform]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/10/herman-cain-funded-by-koch-bros-says-let-the-little-guys-pay-taxes.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Beale Herman Cain, funded by Koch Bros, Says &#8220;Let the Little Guys Pay Taxes (not the uber-rich) The New York Times&#8217; &#8220;Room for Debate&#8221; ran a &#8216;mini-op-ed&#8217; segment on Herman Cain&#8217;s 9-9-9 tax plan, called &#8220;What&#8217;s So Bad About a Flat Tax?&#8221; New York Times (Oct. 14, 2011) (with the subtitle: Isn&#8217;t Herman [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by <strong>Linda Beale</strong></p>
<p><strong>Herman Cain, funded by Koch Bros, Says &#8220;Let the Little Guys Pay Taxes (not the uber-rich</strong>)
<p>The New York Times&#8217; &#8220;Room for Debate&#8221; ran a &#8216;mini-op-ed&#8217; segment on Herman Cain&#8217;s 9-9-9 tax plan, called &#8220;<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/roomfordebate/2011/10/13/whats-so-bad-about-a-flat-tax/the-beauty-of-the-flat-tax?scp=1&#038;sq=Beale%20and%20flat%20tax&#038;st=cse">What&#8217;s So Bad About a Flat Tax?</a>&#8221; New York Times (Oct. 14, 2011) (with the subtitle: Isn&#8217;t Herman Cain&#8217;s &#8216;9-9-9&#8217; plan essentially what fiscal conservatives and good government advocates have always wanted?). Yours Truly was one of those invited to participate: others include Kotlikoff, Ulbrich, and Gale. </p>
<p>I wrote, in <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/roomfordebate/2011/10/13/whats-so-bad-about-a-flat-tax/a-plan-for-the-uber-rich">A Plan for the Uber-Rich</a>, that &#8220;there&#8217;s a lot wrong with flat taxes&#8221; (a term used to cover both the flat rate income tax and the flat-rate national sales tax ideas).</p>
<p> <a name="more"></a>
<p>Either type of flat tax is regressive, in that it places a high tax burden on the most vulnerable at the lower income scales, for the simple reason that most lower income people use all of their income to pay for food, clothing, shelter and other consumption whereas members of the upper class have lots of cash to spare that they are unlikely ever to consume in their lifetimes. There are additional significant flaws in those tax schemes, like unrealistic economic assumptions, difficult transition paths, rosy revenue scenarios, misleading propaganda about rates and the probability that a national sales tax that cuts deeply into lower income finances will repress consumption that fuels small businesses.</p>
<p>Cain&#8217;s plan is even worse, since it:</p>
<ul>
<li>exempts capital income from taxation </li>
<li>eliminates the estate tax </li>
<li>imposes a flat rate on wage income with no deductions (and apparently only some exemption for the poorest of the poor in certain &#8216;zones&#8217; defined by the national government, so that if you are poor and live with lots of other poor people, you may not have to pay as much in taxes, but if you are poor and live where there aren&#8217;t enough poor people, tough luck) </li>
<li>shifts the burden from rich to poor since the rich will only pay on their compensation income and some small additional portion due to consumption taxes, while the poor will pay on all of their income and all of their income again in consumption </li>
<li>and continues the regressivity with some type of value-added tax that will also fall mostly on wage earners.</li>
</ul>
<p>Added since the original positing is Dan Mitchell&#8211;conservative spokesperson for the Cato institute, who lauds the flat tax in &#8220;<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/roomfordebate/2011/10/13/whats-so-bad-about-a-flat-tax/the-beauty-of-the-flat-tax?scp=1&#038;sq=Beale%20and%20flat%20tax&#038;st=cse">The Beauty of the Flat Tax</a>&#8221; as &#8220;desirable&#8221; for its &#8220;simplicity, fairness, and transparency.&#8221; </p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Actually, the national sales tax version of the &#8216;flat tax&#8217; supported by Mitchell is anything but simple</strong>. It results in the government taxing itself and counting the revenues as a gain. It calculates the tax rate in a way intended to be deceptive and likely to be far too low to raise the claimed amounts of revenues. Since it is a sales tax, we normally discuss that as a tax on top of the price, so a price of $100 and a tax at 23% means a final price including tax of $123. But the way the national sales tax has been discussed is different: they say a tax of 23%, but they calculate that rate by taking the ratio of the tax to the price plus tax&#8211;so the rate looks lower than it would look calculated as a ratio of tax to price! In fact, most objective analyses of a national sales tax have suggested that the rate (as a tax to price ratio) would be at least 40% and possibly 50% or even higher, meaning that something purchased foa $100 sales price would have an added national sales tax (not taking into account local and state sales taxes) of betwen $40 and $50 or more. And, worst of all, it will inevitably require an exemption for the poorest of the poor (if not as broad an exemption as currently permitted), thus requiring poor people to pay up front, retain all of their receipts and file a very complex return that will be a request for a refund of the tax. It will, though, be quite simple for the uberrich&#8211;they will not have to file income taxes and then would consume only a small amount of their income (and probably even there find all kinds of ways to get around paying their fair share of that limited tax burden). Further, part of the &#8220;simplicity&#8221; assumption about the tax is that you can get rid of any federal tax collection bureaucracy and that tax enforcement will be minimal. Both of those assumptions are either naive or intentionally misleading: the tax collection responsibilities will fall to the states (imposing significant costs, especially with state systems that still rely on income taxation) and the federal government will nonetheless have to retain a national enforcement system. Most experts say the opportunities for crookedness will be as big in the sales tax system as in any other tax system. </li>
<li><strong>What about fairness? Well, fairness is one thing that the flat tax cannot offer. </strong>The rich get off super cheap, and the poor pay through the nose. Everybody pays only on what they consume (that is actually collected at the point of consumption), but the rich can choose whereas the poor consume all of their income. Accordingly the national sales tax is highly regressive, compared to our somewhat progressive system today. And with the elimination of the income tax and the estate tax, the role that the tax system plays in pushing against gross inequalities will be eliminated. </li>
<li><strong>Transparency is missing as well. </strong>The points about simplicity should answer that question head on. It is not a transparent system at all, for much the same reasons that it is not a simple system.
<ul>
<li>Mitchell praises the &#8220;repeal of most forms of double taxation&#8221; in Cain&#8217;s 9-9-9 plan. What he is calling &#8220;double taxation&#8221; is the fact that people currently pay some tax (though too low) on income earned by capital as well as income earned by labor. Cain repeals all taxes on income earned by capital (and taxes income earned by wages particularly hard&#8211;at about 27%, with the &#8220;income&#8221; tax on wages only, the VAT-type business tax which deducts investments but not wages, and the sales tax (on consumption, which for most wageearners is on all or most of their wage income). But the tax on capital is NOT &#8220;more than one bite of the apple&#8221; as Mitchell asserts. If you invest 20 and that 20 earns 5 in interest, then the 5 in interest is new money that should be subject to tax, just as 5 earned in payment for labor is new money. The idea that any tax on income from capital is a double tax is just &#8220;free market&#8221; doubletalk to justify the elimination of taxes on the wealthy. Although economists like to say that &#8220;only people pay taxes&#8221; and use that to justify allocating all corporate income to shareholders and then asserting that shareholders pay the corporate taxes paid on that corporate income, that is an a priori decision that ignores the reality of perpetual life, managerial renttaking, and &#8220;personhood&#8221; of corporate quasi-sovereign entities in today&#8217;s &#8220;free market&#8221; globalized economy. </li>
<li>Mitchell then asserts that getting rid of deductions and &#8220;other distortions in the tax code&#8221; will mean that &#8220;people will make decisions on the basis of good economics rather than clever tax planning.&#8221; Wrong on two counts. First, most businesspeople still do not make most decisions based on tax planning. They want to make money in their business, and if a plan will make money, they will do that plan (even if it also means paying some taxes. Second, some deductions are merely common sense&#8211;for example, not allowing businesses a deduction for wages will encourage layoffs in favor of capital investments/robotics, which will accelerate job reduction in the US, not create jobs.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Today&#8217;s Associated Press revelations about Cain&#8217;s <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/national/long-ties-to-koch-backed-americans-for-prosperity-are-foundation-of-cain-campaign/2011/10/16/gIQA6Qi9nL_story.html">longtime ties to controversial Koch brothers&#8217; group key to his surging presidential bid</a>, AP (Oct. 16, 2011) show a harmonious fit between Cain&#8217;s 9-9-9 plan, Cain&#8217;s various comments scorning the non rich and his links to wealthy plutocratic anti-populists like David and Charles Koch, billionaires who &#8220;bankroll right-leaning causes through their group Americans for Prosperity&#8221; Id. (The Koch-funded group would be more aptly named America Run for the Super-Rich, since it lobbies for the right&#8217;s agenda of New Deal elimination and targeting of earned benefits of ordinary Americans through a campaign for zero taxation on capital, deregulation, militarization, and privatization .)</p>
<p>AFP tapped Cain as the public face of its “Prosperity Expansion Project,” and he traveled the country in 2005 and 2006 speaking to activists who were starting state-based AFP chapters from Wisconsin to Virginia. Through his AFP work he met Mark Block, a longtime Wisconsin Republican operative hired to lead that state’s AFP chapter in 2005 . . ..</p>
<p>The article notes the many people in Cain&#8217;s organization now or earlier with links to AFP, including Rich Lowrie, the accountant/investment manager who serves Cain as chief economic adviser. </p>
<p>And the Koch brothers have a quite clear record of wanting to abolish Social Security, all kinds of federal welfare, minimum wage laws, and similar programs intended to redress the economic imbalance that has grown in our economy since the advent of winner-take-all economics in the Reagan era.</p>
<p>originally published at <a target="-blank" href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/10/herman-cain-funded-by-koch-bros-says-let-the-little-guys-pay-taxes.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Financial Speculation Taxes</title>
		<link>./../../2011/10/financial-speculation-taxes.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/10/financial-speculation-taxes.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2011 13:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[financial reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[financial speculation tax]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax reform]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/10/financial-speculation-taxes.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[OMB Watch points us to the idea that: Financial Taxes Can Raise Revenues, May Help Stabilize Markets The congressional Super Committee, tasked with forging a $1.2 trillion deficit reduction package by Thanksgiving, is currently deliberating on which revenues — if any — to raise and to include in its plan. With Wall Street at the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a target="_blank" href="http://www.ombwatch.org/node/11874/">OMB Watch</a> points us to the idea that:
<p><a target="_blank" href="http://community.ombwatch.org/site/R?i=HzfdDdWlAmJ6sl9vqSkTyg">Financial Taxes Can Raise Revenues, May Help Stabilize Markets</a>    <br />The congressional <a href="http://community.ombwatch.org/site/R?i=n8nXNVUb4bcV2sccivbAbA">Super Committee</a>, tasked with forging a $1.2 trillion deficit reduction package by Thanksgiving, is currently deliberating <a href="http://community.ombwatch.org/site/R?i=5Oa0ZuDVYDBw6_fqCzb8Xg">on which revenues — if any — to raise</a> and to include in its plan. With Wall Street at the center of the 2008 economic collapse, the committee should look to a pair of revenue options that would fulfill the dual roles of addressing risks to the economy posed by Wall Street and raising much needed revenue: a financial speculation tax and a financial crisis responsibility fee on large financial institutions. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/10/financial-speculation-taxes.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Are Republicans or Democrats Better for the Economy?</title>
		<link>./../../2011/02/are-republicans-or-democrats-better-for-the-economy.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/02/are-republicans-or-democrats-better-for-the-economy.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 08 Feb 2011 15:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Corporate Taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Presimetrics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax policy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax reform]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/02/are-republicans-or-democrats-better-for-the-economy.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Barry Ritholz&#8217;s The Big Picture carries a link to Presimetrics in the Reads to start your week section of his blog and Mike has been asked by Barry to post a chapter in the book section. Dan says: Mike&#8217;s book is one that people need to study and not skim to reinforce a dearly held [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>Barry Ritholz&#8217;s <strong>The Big Picture</strong> carries a link to <a href="http://www.blogger.com/" target="_blank">Presimetrics</a> in the <a href="http://www.ritholtz.com/blog/2011/02/reads-to-start-your-week/" target="_blank">Reads to start your week</a> section of his blog and Mike has been asked by Barry to post a chapter in the book section.</p>
<p><em>Dan says</em>:</p>
<p>Mike&#8217;s book is one that people need to study and not skim to reinforce a dearly held slogan.</p>
<p>One of the complexities is that the data cuts across favored soundbites for political and political/economic announcements. The &#8216;conservative&#8217; economic announcements of the day are so grossly inaccurate that they mask what liberals get wrong as well in the debate of the day.</p>
<p>Snark alert&#8230;hat tip Ken H&#8230;.<strong>The Atlantic</strong> carries an article along a similar vein and poor Megan McArdle has to contend with the growing numbers thinking along the lines of &#8216;Mike&#8217;s band of merry madmen&#8217;. )</p>
<p><a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2011/02/are-republicans-or-democrats-better-for-the-economy/70835" target="_blank">Are Republicans or Democrats Better for the Economy?</a> </p>
<p>Feb 6 2011, 12:35 PM ET By <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/james-fallows/">James Fallows</a></p>
<p>
<p><i>By Chuck Spinney</i></p>
<blockquote><p>This is my last post and I want to thank Jim and Justin [Miller, of the Atlantic web team] for the wonderful opportunity to be a guest blogger.  It has been a fun gig, but quite frankly I am running out of steam.  But life is an interplay of chance and necessity, and serendipity has just offered up a chance for a final blast.<br />For several years now, I have been in a analytical battle with an official in the Department of Defense over the question of whether Republicans or Democrats are better for the economy. <a name="more"></a><br />Newk A. Mineshaftgap is the pseudonym of a senior career official in the Pentagon, with a civilian rank comparable to that of a general in the military. He must remain anonymous for policy reasons &#8212; to borrow from the insightful reasoning used by President Merkin Muffley in Dr. Strangelove,  Minesthaftgap cannot get into a policy fight, because he works in the &#8220;the war room.&#8221;<br />I can tell you this: Newk has a PhD in physics, but he is not a geek.  In fact, he is a bit of polymath, with wide ranging interests, including nuclear weapons, ballistic missile defense, battleship and tank design, global warming and carbon default swaps, economics, and the development of metrics for measuring the quality of medical doctors.   I have known Newk for about 20 years and consider him to be a good and most interesting friend with solid if somewhat eccentric instincts.  Politically, I would categorize Newk as an independent with libertarian biases.<br />So, as my last blast, let me offer the <a href="http://www.chaliventures.com/Links_to_Reports/Links_to_Idisk_files/Are%20Republicans%20or%20Democrats%20Better%20for%20the%20Economy%3F.pdf">following link</a> [PDF]  to Newk&#8217;s latest report on whether Republicans or Democrats are better for the economy.  For a knuckle dragger from the Pentagon, his conclusions might surprise you.<br />___ 
</p>
</blockquote>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/02/are-republicans-or-democrats-better-for-the-economy.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>More on Illinois&#8217; income tax increase &#8211;thinking about globalization</title>
		<link>./../../2011/01/more-on-illinois-income-tax-increase-thinking-about-globalization.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/01/more-on-illinois-income-tax-increase-thinking-about-globalization.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 17 Jan 2011 16:23:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Globalization]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[State Taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax rates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax reform]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/01/more-on-illinois-income-tax-increase-thinking-about-globalization.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Beale More on Illinois&#8217; income tax increase &#8211;thinking about globalizationcrossposted with Ataxingmatter As states continue to face difficult times and vulnerable residents unemployed by the Great Recession come to the end of their ropes with the last of their unemployment support checks (those unemployed for 99 weeks don&#8217;t get any more help under [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by <strong>Linda Beale</strong></p>
<p><strong>More on Illinois&#8217; income tax increase &#8211;thinking about globalization</strong><br />crossposted with <a target="_blank" href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/"><strong>Ataxingmatter</strong></a>
<p>As states continue to face difficult times and vulnerable residents unemployed by the Great Recession come to the end of their ropes with the last of their unemployment support checks (those unemployed for 99 weeks don&#8217;t get any more help under the latest extension), the rhetoric continues to escalate.</p>
<p>As I noted in my last post on Illinois&#8217; decision to increase its personal and corporate income tax rates (See Illinois <a href="http://www.ilga.gov/legislation/publicacts/96/PDF/096-1496.pdf">Senate Bill 2505</a>, signed into law by Gov. Quinn on Jan. 13), tax increases&#8211;especially those that require people and companies of wealth and power to kick in a fairer share of the tax burden&#8211;may well make sense even as the country deals with the continuing fallout of the banksters&#8217;s binge of casino speculation.  Governor Quinn noted when signing the Illinois legislation that the tax increase was need to stave off fiscal insolvency.   The 5% individual income tax rate applies until January 2015, at which time the rate reverts to 3.75% for ten years and then 3.25% after 2025.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a>
<p>The right wing&#8217;s preferred solution&#8211; to see the states fire public employees or at the least reneg on their earlier commitments to fund pensions (which generally permitted them to hire highly skilled employees at lower wages than would otherwise have been possible)&#8211; would only make grave matters much worse. There are important programs to be funded in the states, and ultimately a higher tax burden that is allocated to those who can best pay it may be the best solution.  Management efficiencies need to be undertaken, and wasteful spending and corruption stifled, but in many cases those savings are relatively small.  The &#8220;no new taxes&#8221; mantra that has dominated public discourse under the Chicago School thinking has kept states from dealing forthrightly with these issues for decades.</p>
<p>Wisconsin&#8217;s new governor, right-winger Scott Walker, is a perfect illustration of the zany rhetoric and gamesmanship being played about tax matters all across this country.  He has said he would spurn federal stimulus money and ditch a planned high-speed rail line between Madison and Milwaulkee.  See James warren, <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/01/16/us/16cncwarren.html">Wisconsin Sounds Off, but Misses the Point</a>, New York Times, Jan 15, 2011.  High speed rail is the wave of the future, and the US needs to catch that wave soon or be left behind.   Walker&#8217;s rhetoric here seems designed to please wealth and power (and the kooks in the &#8220;tea party&#8221; who are foolish enough to think that federal monies for infrastructure is a waste of &#8220;their&#8221; tax money), but move the state in the opposite direction from where it needs to go.  Walker has also gone on the air in a campaign intended to take advantage of corporate dislike of the Illinois tax hike, inviting corporations to &#8220;escape to Wisconsin.&#8221;</p>
<p>James Warren&#8217;s piece in the Friday New York Times challenges that sentiment.  Seems that the Illinois personal rate (5%) is probably less than taxation under the progressive scale of 4.6% to 7.75% in Wisconsin.  And if Caterpillar or some other big corporation were to move to Wisconsin, it would face a higher rate of 7.9% compared to the 7% rate passed for Illinois.    So Walker&#8217;s rhetoric is just that&#8211;trying to make hay out of the mere fact that Illinois increased its tax rates.  As Warren points out, politicians need to start thinking about what is good for the region and &#8220;not just poach others&#8217; enterprises&#8221;.   </p>
<p>We need to think strategically, as globalization has made it much easier for companies to move to greener pastures&#8211;not just other states, but out of the states.  Congress could help that by eliminating the provision in the Code that permits companies to move active business assets abroad without paying tax on the built-in gain.  In fact, Congress ought really to consider revamping the entire reorganization provisions in the Code.  We have seen that too big to fail banks are costly for us.  Rather than aiding consolidation of companies through nonrecognition provisions, what if we made reorganizations more difficult and costly?  Combine that with a renewed anti-trust vigor, and encourage smaller businesses to stay in this country.  Localvore could take on a new meaning.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/01/more-on-illinois-income-tax-increase-thinking-about-globalization.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tax Relief, Unemployment Insurance Reauthorization, and Job Creation Act of 2010 passes</title>
		<link>./../../2010/12/tax-relief-unemployment-insurance-reauthorization-and-job-creation-act-of-2010-passes.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/12/tax-relief-unemployment-insurance-reauthorization-and-job-creation-act-of-2010-passes.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 21 Dec 2010 15:54:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[tax reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax relief]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/12/tax-relief-unemployment-insurance-reauthorization-and-job-creation-act-of-2010-passes.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[(Dan here: I am traveling right now and am posting things late or maybe not as tidy as I would like. But posts are coming.) by Linda BealeTax Relief, Unemployment Insurance Reauthorization, and Job Creation Act of 2010 passes crossposted with Ataxingmatter No big surprise here.  The House on December 16 passed the Senate-approved TRA [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>(Dan here:  I am traveling right now and am posting things late or maybe not as tidy as I would like. But posts are coming.)</p>
<p>by <strong>Linda Beale</strong><br /><strong>Tax Relief, Unemployment Insurance Reauthorization, and Job Creation Act of 2010 passes  </strong><br />crossposted with Ataxingmatter
<p>No big surprise here.  The House on December 16 passed the Senate-approved TRA by a vote of 277-148, clearing it for the President&#8217;s signature.  The bill extends the Bush tax cuts for two years and reduces the number of estates subject to the estate tax, and the rate of tax when they are taxed, even below the number subject to the tax in 2009.  It includes the usual &#8220;patch&#8221; for the AMT for two years, and various tax breaks for businesses&#8211;especially expensing provisions that will likely merely result in more pay to managers and more payouts to mostly wealthy shareholders.</p>
<p>Those most vulnerable get the relief from the lower rates (not many dollars for them, of course), the 2% cut in the payroll taxes, and the extension of unemployment compensation.</p>
<p>Those at the top of the wealth and income heap who have garnered almost all the benefits of productivity gains in the economy over the last few decades get most of the benefit of the bill&#8211;tens of thousands of dollars of tax relief for the top 20% of the income distribution, substantial estate tax reductions, and none of the burden-sharing that progressives had advocated (such as the carried interest treatment as ordinary income).  The bill even provides what amounts to an interest-free loan to the wealthy who convert regular IRAs to Roth IRAs&#8211;the &#8220;deal of the century&#8221; according to one CPA who services the wealthy.  See Leondis, <a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2010-12-17/tax-passage-gives-u-s-wealthy-interest-free-loans-for-roth-ira-transfers.html">Tax Measure Gives Deal to Wealthy Roth IRA Converters</a>, Bloomberg.com, Dec. 17, 2010.  And of course, the bill also lets the wealthy transfer up to $100,000 from regular IRAs to charities without paying the income tax they should have to pay on the appreciation. </p>
<p>All in all, the wealthy made out like bandits in the tax bill.  And in many ways, that is the appropriate way to view them&#8211;they have stolen the sustainable livelihood of the middle and lower classes for two decades and are rapidly moving into position to become a ruling oligarchy.  The bill was a big win for corporatism and the wealthy on the right.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/12/tax-relief-unemployment-insurance-reauthorization-and-job-creation-act-of-2010-passes.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Effect of Changing Top Marginal Tax Rates</title>
		<link>./../../2010/12/the-effect-of-changing-top-marginal-tax-rates.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/12/the-effect-of-changing-top-marginal-tax-rates.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2010 02:09:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[tax reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[top marginal rates]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/12/the-effect-of-changing-top-marginal-tax-rates.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Mike Kimel The Effect of Changing Top Marginal Tax Rates &#8211; an op ed free to a good homeCross posted at the Presimetrics blog. I wrote most of what follows in the anticipation of trying to get it accepted as an op ed at a newspaper, but I guess the deal cut the other [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by <strong>Mike Kimel</strong></p>
<p><strong>The Effect of Changing Top Marginal Tax Rates</strong> &#8211; an op ed free to a good home<br />Cross posted at the <a href="http://www.presimetrics.com/blog/?p=253">Presimetrics blog</a>.</p>
<p>I wrote most of what follows in the anticipation of trying to get it accepted as an op ed at a newspaper, but I guess the deal cut the other night means a bit of it needs rewriting&#8230;</p>
<p>&#8212;</p>
<p>On January 1, 2011, the “Bush tax cuts” will expire and individual marginal tax rates, the percentage of income individuals pay in taxes to the federal government, will return to Clinton-era levels.  The political consensus seems to be that the tax cuts should be kept for most taxpayers, but there is disagreement about whether to let the highest marginal tax rate expire.  That rate applies to the portion of a high-income earner’s revenues that are in excess of some large amount &#8211; $250,000 and $1 million have been recently floated as thresholds.  But, aside from rhetoric about fairness peddled by both sides in the debate, what difference does it make to the economy whether the top marginal rate goes up or not?  A little history can help make it easier to understand what is at stake.  </p>
<p>When Ronald Reagan was elected president in 1980, the top marginal tax rate was 70%.  By 1988, the top marginal tax rate had been reduced to 28%. More importantly, Reagan changed the longstanding political landscape when it comes to taxation.  While the top marginal rate was never below 70% between 1936 and 1980, it has not gone above 39.6% in the years since Reagan left office.  <br /><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>But if Reagan’s philosophy prevailed, it is fair to ask:  have his tax policies generated the promised results?  Lower taxes were supposed to usher in an era of faster economic growth and increased prosperity.  However, while the economy did better under Reagan than it did under the three presidents who preceded him, Reagan-era growth could hardly be called impressive.  Real GDP (i.e., GDP adjusted for inflation) grew more slowly under Ronald Reagan than during the eight years presided by JFK and LBJ, and slower even than during any consecutive eight year period in which Franklin Delano Roosevelt was president.  FDR, it should be noted, raised the top marginal tax rate four times, from 63% to 94%.  </p>
<p>But perhaps it is unfair to compare Reagan to big-government types like Lyndon Johnson or Roosevelt, as they served during very different eras.  Focusing instead on more recent periods, real GDP also grew faster under Bill Clinton, who raised taxes, than it did under Ronald Reagan.  In fact, from 1981 to the present, the period in which Reagan’s philosophies have reigned triumphant, the correlation between the top marginal tax rate and the annual growth in real GDP has been positive.  That is to say, higher top marginal tax rates have been associated with faster, not slower real economic growth.  Conversely, lower top marginal tax rates have coincided with less economic growth. </p>
<p>The positive relationship between the top marginal tax rate and the growth in real GDP is very nearly bullet-proof.  For instance, it extends all the way back to 1929, the first year for which the government computed GDP data.  Additionally, higher marginal tax rates are not only correlated with faster increases in real GDP from one year to the next, but also with increases in real GDP over the subsequent two, three, or four years.  This is as true going back to 1929 as it is for the period since Reagan became president.  In fact, since the Reagan Revolution took hold, similar relationships have existed between the top marginal rate and several other important variables, like real median income, real private investment, consumer sentiment, the value of the dollar relative to other major currencies, and the S&#038;P 500.  Lower tax rates in any given year are associated with slower growth rates for each of these variables, whether those growth rates are measured over periods of one, two, three or four years.  </p>
<p>On the flip-side, since 1981, unemployment rates have generally shrunk faster when tax rates were higher than when they were lower.  As with the other economic measures, this relationship holds whether one is measuring the change in unemployment over a single year, over two years, over three years or over four years.</p>
<p>None of this means that higher taxes cause better outcomes.  Still, it is clear that the supposed negative repercussions from higher taxes simply have not materialized, notwithstanding pronouncements from politicians, pundits and economists.  The reason is simple:  those who are both willing and able to engage in tax avoidance when subject to a 40% marginal rate are not likely to behave any differently when that rate changes to 50%, or 30% for that matter.  But at a slightly higher top marginal rate, the government does get more revenue, and in this way can finance more spending on things that benefit the economy, such as infrastructure, public health, scientific research, education, alleviating poverty and of course, IRS audits.  Thus, allowing the top marginal rate to rise from current rates (35%) to the level they were under Bill Clinton (39.6%) is unlikely to harm the economy, and may actually help.</p>
<p>&#8212;</p>
<p>As always, if anyone wants my spreadsheet, drop me a line at my first name (that would be &#8220;mike&#8221;) period my last name at gmail.com.  If anyone wants the op ed (changed to reflect whatever deal conditions are applicable at the time), ditto.  </p>
<p>And finally, one question &#8211; why didn&#8217;t I read any op eds like this in the newspapers in the last few weeks and months?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/12/the-effect-of-changing-top-marginal-tax-rates.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
