<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>econospeak &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Reading the story, asking normal business questions</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/reading-the-story-asking-normal-business-questions.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/reading-the-story-asking-normal-business-questions.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2013 12:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[econospeak]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Peter Dorman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[reading the news]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/reading-the-story-asking-normal-business-questions.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Peter Dorman at Econospeak writes a gem of a post asking readers to ask simple questions when offered a morality tale by journalists, or an implied cause and effect tale, and how it takes no special skill to ask simple business questions that the journalist should at least ask, even if not o tanswer all [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://econospeak.blogspot.com/2013/03/the-spin-on-tires.html">Peter Dorman</a> at <i>Econospeak</i> writes a gem of a post asking readers to ask simple questions when offered a morality tale by journalists, or an implied cause and effect tale, and how it takes no special skill to ask simple business questions that the journalist should at least ask, even if not o tanswer all of them.</p>
<p>Peter Dorman writes:</p>
<p>The Spin on Tires</p>
<p>It would be nice to have economic literacy in journalism.  Take <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/03/17/world/europe/fates-of-2-factories-show-social-schisms-in-france.html?ref=todayspaper&#038;pagewanted=print">this morning’s story</a> in the <i>New York Times </i>about a pair of tire factories in Amiens.  One is managed by Dunlop; its workers agreed to a schedule of constantly shifting workweeks and shift work, and it is still operating.  The other is managed by Goodyear.  There the workers rejected the disruptive schedule, and the factory is shutting down.  The comparison is presented as a morality tale, where the responsible workers, recognizing the new demands of productivity and competitiveness in a globalized economy, did the right thing, while their obstinate counterparts, representative of all that’s wrong with France, preferred heroic self-annihilation. </p>
<p>Reading the article, I couldn’t help but think that this analysis of The Real Reason the French Economy is Sputtering was there all along, looking for a story to attach itself to. </p>
<p>But an economist might ask a few simple questions.  First, what is the elasticity of the total production cost of a tire with respect to the changes in work hours?  I realize the reporter wants to emphasize the symbolism, the importance of workers bending to the employer’s will as a virtue in and of itself, but perhaps there is a factual dimension worth looking into.  Just a suggestion.  </p>
<p>Second, what is the market for these tires?  In particular, who if anyone will pick up the market share being abandoned by Goodyear?  Is this about outsourcing of a portion of tire production to lower-cost producers in developing countries?  Or is it about a shrinking domestic market that no longer needs the output of both plants?  Or some combination of the two or something else? </p>
<p>In particular, it is interesting that both factories, despite their different nameplates, are owned by the same company, Goodyear Dunlop.  Thus, this story describes a consolidation.  The very least an enterprising journalist can do is to inquire into the company’s overall capacity.  Is it cutting back elsewhere in Europe?  Are they shifting production geographically?  Is it possible that they might want only one operation in Amiens in any case, and that the only result of the contest over worker concessions is which plant it will be? </p>
<p>All of this is speculative, because I don’t know the tire market in France.  That’s what I would want to learn from a newspaper story, a rather long one at that, on the subject.  This might also help me understand why the US, where few workers are unionized and none have the will or ability to resist whatever schedule is dictated to them, is not blanketed in tire factories.    </p>
<p>Incidentally, there has been a ton of research in the past decade documenting the health effects of exactly the sort of work schedule being imposed at Dunlop.  It is associated with significantly elevated levels of a wide range of diseases; arguably it represents the single greatest occupational safety and health threat experienced in developed countries.  An informed journalist might want to weave that into the story too.</p>
<p>(re-posted with permission of the author)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/reading-the-story-asking-normal-business-questions.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interpreting the news of getting high on net wealth news</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/interpreting-the-news-of-getting-high-on-net-wealth-news.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/interpreting-the-news-of-getting-high-on-net-wealth-news.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2013 15:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Asymptosis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[econospeak]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[net worth distribution]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[pgl. Steve Roth]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[pre-recession highs]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/interpreting-the-news-of-getting-high-on-net-wealth-news.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[US Household wealth regains pre-recession peak!  crows this story. Steve Roth&#8216;s chart to 2010 from Asynptosis demonstrates the drop in net worth for most of us. pgl at Econospeak adds perspective: So Whose Wealth Is At a Record High? This news story must be good news for some folks: According to the Federal Reserve, household wealth [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://news.msn.com/us/us-household-wealth-regains-prerecession-peak" target="_blank">US Household wealth regains pre-recession peak</a>!  crows this story.</p>
<p>
<div><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-O4mR_zHPzVk/UTtHSPbx7vI/AAAAAAAABjg/PCkuKsKu2XU/s1600/household+median.png" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-O4mR_zHPzVk/UTtHSPbx7vI/AAAAAAAABjg/PCkuKsKu2XU/s1600/household+median.png" height="218" width="320"></a></div>
<div></div>
<p><a href="http://www.asymptosis.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/06/SCF-2010-net-worth.png">Steve Roth</a>&#8216;s chart to 2010 from <i>Asynptosis</i> demonstrates the drop in net worth for most of us.</p>
<p><a href="http://econospeak.blogspot.com/2013/03/so-whose-wealth-is-at-record-high.html" target="_blank">pgl at <i>Econospeak</i></a> adds perspective:<br />
<blockquote>So Whose Wealth Is At a Record High?</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p><a href="http://news.msn.com/us/us-household-wealth-regains-pre-recession-peak">This news story</a> must be good news for some folks:<br />
<blockquote>According to the Federal Reserve, household wealth amounted to $66.1 trillion at the end of 2012 and further gains in stock and house prices have allowed Americans to make up for the losses incurred during the recession.</p></blockquote>
<p>If you want to protest that not everyone has recovered their lost wealth, the story sort of concedes this further down:<br />
<blockquote>The recovered wealth — most of it from higher stock prices — has been flowing mainly to richer Americans. By contrast, middle class wealth is mostly in the form of home equity, which has risen much less.</p></blockquote>
<p>Households owners&#8217; equity in real estate peaked at $12.5 billion in 2005 and then plummeted. While it has partially recovered, it was only $8.2 billion at the end of 2012 according to the <a href="http://www.federalreserve.gov/releases/z1">Flow of Funds Accounts</a>. Given that consumer prices have risen by almost 20 percent over this period, our equity in real estate is still far below its 2005 peak value.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/interpreting-the-news-of-getting-high-on-net-wealth-news.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Wealth: It&#8217;s Not for Everyone</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/wealth-its-not-for-everyone.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/wealth-its-not-for-everyone.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2013 22:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[econospeak]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income inequality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Inequality of wealth or income]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sandwichman]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/wealth-its-not-for-everyone.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Via Sandwichman at Econospeak comes this well done video on Wealth: It&#8217;s Not for Everyone, which is going to 3 million views from facebook, reddit, and elswhere:]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Via <a href="http://econospeak.blogspot.com/2013/03/one-of-its-anti-growth-crowd-got-about.html" target="_blank">Sandwichman</a> at <i>Econospeak</i> comes this well done video on Wealth: It&#8217;s Not for Everyone, which is going to 3 million views from facebook, reddit, and elswhere:</p>
<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/wealth-its-not-for-everyone.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Only 6% Of Public Knows Deficit Is Declining</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/only-6-of-public-knows-deficit-is-declining.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/only-6-of-public-knows-deficit-is-declining.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2013 12:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Barkley Rosser]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[econospeak]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/only-6-of-public-knows-deficit-is-declining.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Prof Barkley Rosser at Econospeak also asks questions on the freaking out over the fiscal deficit numbers: Only 6% Of Public Knows Deficit Is Declining Yes, here we go again, massive public ignorance post # I forget how many.  This has been floating around out there for awhile but was on Rachel Maddow last night, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a target="_blank" href="http://econospeak.blogspot.com/2013/02/only-6-of-public-knows-deficit-is.html">Prof Barkley Rosser at Econospeak</a> also asks questions on the freaking out over the fiscal deficit numbers:</p>
<p>Only 6% Of Public Knows Deficit Is Declining
</p>
<blockquote><p>Yes, here we go again, massive public ignorance post # I forget how many.  This has been floating around out there for awhile but was on Rachel Maddow last night, and here is a link with suitable discussion of relevant facts from Dave Johnson, perhaps important as this silly sequester is about to land on us supposedly driven by the overwhelming need to get the deficit under control,<a href="http://blog.ourfuture.org/20130226/deficit-is-falling-dramatically-but-only-6-know-that">http://blog.ourfuture.org/20130226/deficit-is-falling-dramatically-but-only-6-know-that</a>.  As it is, apparently 62% think it is rising, while 28% think it is constant.
<p>Among things that the public is wrong about, this one sticks out for being so far off from the facts.  And as is noted, not only is the deficit declining, but it is doing so at a very dramatic rate.  Without doing anything we should be able to stabilize the debt/GDP ratio within about two to three years, although to maintain that down the road, further adjustments would need to be made.  Being an austerian is one thing, but being completely out of touch with reality is quite another.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/only-6-of-public-knows-deficit-is-declining.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Risk = Freedom?</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/risk-freedom.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/risk-freedom.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2013 16:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[econospeak]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[freedom]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Peter Dorman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[risk]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/risk-freedom.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Peter Dorman at Econospeak speaks to the current selling of big idea models of the world (re-posted with permission from the author): There’s a review on the Dissent website by Steve Randy Waldman of Freaks of Fortune: The Emerging World of Capitalism and Risk in America by Jonathan Levy. The book sounds interesting, but it [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://econospeak.blogspot.com/2013/02/risk-freedom.html">Peter Dorman</a> at Econospeak speaks to the current selling of big idea models of the world (re-posted with permission from the author):</p>
<p>There’s a review on the <a href="http://www.dissentmagazine.org/online_articles/the-risk-ownership-society#prclt-9tUWfN1s"><i>Dissent</i> website</a> by Steve Randy Waldman of <i>Freaks of Fortune: The Emerging World of Capitalism and Risk in America</i> by Jonathan Levy. The book sounds interesting, but it is apparently based on a commonplace but false understanding of the relationship between freedom and risk-taking. </p>
<p>At the individual level it is absolutely true that we face a tradeoff between risk and freedom. You can opt for a secure life, but only at the expense of creativity, individualism, moral courage and all the other Emersonian goodies. Each one of us, every day, faces this choice. Mostly it is just a matter of a tiny bit of risk-taking, but these moments add up, and from time to time there is a fundamental fork in the road. We make our own freedom.</p>
<p>But the social level is another story. Individuals take the array of risks as given; society can choose how much risk its members will face and what their risk-freedom tradeoffs will be, at least up to a point. If the objective is to minimize all risk of any sort, especially all risks to health and income, the result will be stultifying. But that’s not where we are on the Great Risk Curve.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p> Rather, the debates we have are about whether to cut back or extend social insurance programs like Social Security and Medicare, social protections like TANF and Medicaid, and more or less regulation of finance, pollution and such. It seems clear to me that more security of this sort, which limits the downside risk individuals face in their personal lives, reduces the cost of living freely.    </p>
<p>Examples are everywhere. Ample unemployment insurance makes it easier to work for a startup or switch jobs in general rather than being held down by too strong a need for job security. A stronger public pension system encourages entrepreneurship: people can hazard their savings by starting a business rather than hoarding everything for old age. Social guarantees for basic needs make it possible for artists to risk making art their day job. Professors with tenure (big time risk reduction) can take more controversial positions on public issues. (I don’t say they always do this, but they do it more than they would if all professors were temps.) In each case there is a real tradeoff between freedom and security at the individual level, but society can create programs that relax it, so it takes less courage to live freely.  </p>
<p>That’s what I don’t like about the nanny state rhetoric. Yes, of course the state can go too far and overprotect us from risks we would do better to face ourselves. But the state we actually live in goes too far in the other direction. With a stronger safety net we could have less risk and more freedom.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/risk-freedom.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>GDP Gap Stuck at 6%</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/gdp-gap-stuck-at-6.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/gdp-gap-stuck-at-6.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2013 14:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[econospeak]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GDP]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[pro growth liberal]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/gdp-gap-stuck-at-6.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Pro Growth Liberal points us to this interpretation of new economic data: GDP Gap Stuck at 6% Dean Baker gets it right with respect to the latest news on GDP: A sharp drop in government spending, heavily concentrated in defense, coupled with a decline in inventories caused GDP to shrink at a 0.1 percent rate [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://econospeak.blogspot.com/2013/01/gdp-gap-stuck-at-6.html" title="http://econospeak.blogspot.com/2013/01/gdp-gap-stuck-at-6.html?utm_source=feedburner&#038;utm_medium=feed&#038;utm_campaign=Feed%3A+espeak+%28EconoSpeak%29">Pro Growth Liberal</a> points us to this interpretation of new economic data:</p>
<p>GDP Gap Stuck at 6%</p>
<p><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-EuAq-TIIYY4/UQqNEZTBZNI/AAAAAAAAATU/9iyhlRfXSeA/s1600/a1.jpeg"><img border="0" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-EuAq-TIIYY4/UQqNEZTBZNI/AAAAAAAAATU/9iyhlRfXSeA/s400/a1.jpeg" height="274" width="400"></a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.cepr.net/index.php/data-bytes/gdp-bytes/government-spending-and-inventories-push-graowth-negative">Dean Baker</a> gets it right with respect to the latest news on GDP: <br />
<blockquote>A sharp drop in government spending, heavily concentrated in defense, coupled with a decline in inventories caused GDP to shrink at a 0.1 percent rate in the 4th quarter. Government spending fell at a 6.6 percent annual rate, driven by a 22.2 percent decline in defense spending, subtracting 1.33 percentage points from the growth rate in the quarter. A 40.3 drop in the rate of inventory accumulation reduced growth by another 1.27 percentage points. Without these factors, GDP would have grown at a 2.5 percent annual rate in the quarter. Pulling out these extraordinary factors, the GDP data were largely in line with prior quarters.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/gdp-gap-stuck-at-6.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Joe Scarborough on the Deficit</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/joe-scarborough-on-the-deficit.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/joe-scarborough-on-the-deficit.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Feb 2013 16:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[econospeak]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Krugman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[pro growth liberal]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/joe-scarborough-on-the-deficit.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Pro Growth Liberal at Econospeak also takes Joe Scarborough to task on Krugman and Keynes: Joe Scarborough on the Deficit After his interview with Paul Krugman this morning Joe Scarborough wrote: Mr. Krugman&#8217;s view is that Americans would be better off if its government ran deeper deficits and ignored its longterm debt.To suggest that Keynesians like [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>Pro Growth Liberal at <i>Econospeak</i> also takes Joe Scarborough to task on Krugman and Keynes:</div>
<p>
<blockquote><a href="http://econospeak.blogspot.com/2013/01/joe-scarborough-on-deficit.html">Joe Scarborough on the Deficit</a></p>
<p>After his interview with Paul Krugman this morning <a href="http://www.politico.com/story/2013/01/paul-krugman-vs-the-world-86822.html?hp=l9">Joe Scarborough</a> wrote:</p>
<p>Mr. Krugman&#8217;s view is that Americans would be better off if its government ran deeper deficits and ignored its longterm debt.<br />To suggest that Keynesians like Paul Krugman ignore the long-term government budget constraint is either dishonest or shows that Mr. Scarborough does not understand what we are saying. Which is why Mr. Scarborough should check out <a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/10-people-who-disagree-with-joe-scarborough-2013-1">this list</a> of commentary on the current economics and fiscal situation compiled by Joe Weisenthal.  </p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/joe-scarborough-on-the-deficit.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Moral Imperative of a Debt Ceiling</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/the-moral-imperative-of-a-debt-ceiling.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/the-moral-imperative-of-a-debt-ceiling.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 12 Jan 2013 13:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[econospeak]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Petrer Dorman]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/the-moral-imperative-of-a-debt-ceiling.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Peter Dorman at Econospeak writes a letter to Bank of America: The Moral Imperative of a Debt Ceiling From this morning&#8217;s New York Times: Representative Jerrold Nadler, Democrat of New York, signed on to the trillion-dollar [platinum] coin plan, telling Capital New York: “It sounds silly but it’s absolutely legal. And it would normally not [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Peter Dorman at <i>Econospeak</i> writes a letter to Bank of America:</p>
<p>The Moral Imperative of a Debt Ceiling</p>
<p>From this morning&#8217;s <i><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/01/10/business/a-trillion-dollar-coin-brings-a-jackpot-of-jests.html?ref=todayspaper">New York Times</a></i>:<br />
<blockquote>Representative Jerrold Nadler, Democrat of New York, signed on to the trillion-dollar [platinum] coin plan, telling Capital New York: “It sounds silly but it’s absolutely legal. And it would normally not be proper to consider such a thing, except when you’re faced with blackmail to destroy the country’s economy, you have to consider things.” </p>
<p>But he might find resistance from Representative Greg Walden, Republican of Oregon, who said he would introduce legislation to close the loophole and end the debate once and for all. </p>
<p>“My wife and I have owned and operated a small business since 1986. When it came time to pay the bills, we couldn’t just mint a coin to create more money out of thin air,” Mr. Walden said.</p></blockquote>
<p>Dear Bank of America:<br />   <br />As a lender to my small business, you should be the first to know of a decision I’ve decided to take.  It wasn’t easy, and I’ve given it a lot of thought, but now I’m convinced it’s the right course of action.  I won’t be making my next monthly payment.<br />  <br /><a name="more"></a><br />It is true that I have already ordered shipments of equipment and materials using the funds I’ve borrowed from you.  It is also true that I have adopted a pricing policy that’s designed to increase market share at the expense of current cash flow.  The result of these choices is that my financial obligations will exceed my revenues for an extended period of time.<br />    <br />I have a line of credit that can cover this shortfall; we discussed it at length in our meeting last month.  I appreciate your willingness to finance it at a negative real interest rate.  But I now believe that it is immoral for me to increase my debt, which could be a burden on my children and grandchildren.  As a result, I have imposed a debt limit on myself—a limit which I refuse to raise.<br />    <br />I’m sure you can understand the sound principles on which this choice is based: taking on more debt is evil.  That’s why I have chosen instead to default on your loan, as well as withhold wages I’ve promised to pay to my workers.  Please support me in this virtuous undertaking.<br />    <br />Sincerely yours&#8230;..</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/the-moral-imperative-of-a-debt-ceiling.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Norquist and LaPierre: Emperors Losing Their Clothes?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/norquist-and-lapierre-emperors-losing-their-clothes.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/norquist-and-lapierre-emperors-losing-their-clothes.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 26 Dec 2012 21:16:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Barkley Rosser]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[econospeak]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Grover Norquist]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wayne LaPierre]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/norquist-and-lapierre-emperors-losing-their-clothes.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Barkley Rosser at Econospeak offers his take on the current political situation and two players. (re-posted with permission from author) Norquist and LaPierre: Emperors Losing Their Clothes? Two figures have held near-dictatorial sway over a majority of members of Congress for several decades: Grover Norquist and Wayne LaPierre.  However, both may be losing their grip [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://econospeak.blogspot.com/2012/12/norquist-and-lapierre-emperors-losing.html">Barkley Rosser</a> at <i>Econospeak </i>offers his take on the current political situation and two players. <br />(re-posted with permission from author)</p>
<p>Norquist and LaPierre: Emperors Losing Their Clothes?</p>
<p>Two figures have held near-dictatorial sway over a majority of members of Congress for several decades: Grover Norquist and Wayne LaPierre.  However, both may be losing their grip to some extent at this time, although it is too soon to count them out yet.  Both may yet get their ways to some extent despite appearances to the contrary.   </p>
<p>Norquist&#8217;s schtick has been the pledge he has foisted on largely Republican members of Congress never to raise taxes in any way, shape, or form.  This effort dates to the Reagan presidency and has only gradually gained the nearly universal submission that it currently has among Republican politicians at both the state and national levels.  In the face of the current huge deficit and the oncoming &#8220;fiscal cliff&#8221; (curb, slope, whatever), some are now making noises about abandoning ship on this.  Indeed, this past Thursday saw House Speaker John Boehner proposing to raise income taxes on those earning more than $1 million per year.  While this was a cutoff higher than the $400,000 President Obama was demanding (which is in turn higher than the $250,000 he successfully campaigned on this year), it was a significant break for Speaker Boehner.  However, in the end he was unable to convince his caucus to support him.  The rank and file of Republicans in the House are simply not yet willing to go against their pledges to the will of Norquist.  Boehner&#8217;s clothing may be getting pulled at and a bit messy, but he continues to seem pretty fully dressed.    </p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Wayne LaPierre has not made Congressional members sign a specific pledge, but he has demanded that those the NRA supports do exactly as it requests on pain of facing primary or other opposition backed by strong funding and advertising.  Whereas Norquist&#8217;s group largely focuses just on Republicans, LaPierre has worked his ways on polticians of both parties, although increasingly his focus has been on Republicans as Democrats have begun to thumb their noses at him.  This movement has accelerated since the massacre at Sandy Hook Elementary School in Newtown, CT just over a week ago, and the reaction to LaPierre&#8217;s speech a week after it calling for armed guards at schools has been ridiculed widely.  Nevertheless, despite a lot of discomfiture, at least Republicans continue to appear to be completely obedient with not a single GOP member of Congress expressing support for any movement to control guns in any way.  One can expect my own representative, Bob Goodlatte, to prove to be the ultimate blocker of any efforts to change gun laws in his new position as House Judiciary Committee Chairman, as he has strongly stated opposition to any changes in gun laws.  So, LaPierre also  appears to be keeping most of his clothing on as well for the near term.    </p>
<p>A curious details is that this authoritarian pair has a curious mutual connection.  Norquist is on the board of the NRA, and both are closely connected to John R. Lott, Jr.  Lott has most recently coauthored a book with Norquist, and he has long been the most prominent pro-gun rights advocate in the nation, much relied on and praised by LaPierre.  His book, _More Guns, Less Crime_ has been cited repeatedly by those pushing to loosen gun laws in many states and also at the national level, such as when the NRA succeeded in blocking a renewal of the assault weapons ban in 2004.  Curiously, Lott&#8217;s effort to step forward to defend gun rights at this time has brought much focus on his long record of data manipulation and outright fraud, most notoriously in his creating a sock puppet named &#8220;Mary Rosh&#8221; to praise himself on the internet over a decade ago.  His studies have come under strong criticism on multiple grounds by many, such as Mark Duggan in his &#8220;More Guns, More Crime,&#8221; Journal of Political Economy, 2001.  His recent claims that mass murders happen only in gun free zones, except for the Gabby Giffords tragedy last year, appear to be false, with at least three this year happening in non-gun free zones: the Clackamas OR shopping mall attack, the Sikh Temple attack in Oak Creek WI, and the Accent Signage attack in Minneapoli, MNs.  For more detailed discussions of the various fraudulent activities Lott has engaged in see <a href="http://www.tnr.com/blog/plank/111063/meet-john-lott-the-man-who-wants-teachers-carry-guns">http://www.tnr.com/blog/plank/111063/meet-john-lott-the-man-who-wants-teachers-carry-guns</a>  and <a href="http://mediamatters.org/research/2012/12/17/who-is-gun-advocate-john-lott/191855">http://mediamatters.org/research/2012/12/17/who-is-gun-advocate-john-lott/191855</a> . </p>
<p>Ironically, while Norquist and LaPierre may just barely be able to keep their clothes on, it looks like it may end up being Lott, who may finally lose his.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/norquist-and-lapierre-emperors-losing-their-clothes.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>&#034;The young will pay more and get less.&#034; More Nonsense from Robert Samuelson</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/the-young-will-pay-more-and-get-less-more-nonsense-from-robert-samuelson.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/the-young-will-pay-more-and-get-less-more-nonsense-from-robert-samuelson.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 05 Dec 2012 12:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Barkley Rosser]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[econospeak]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/the-young-will-pay-more-and-get-less-more-nonsense-from-robert-samuelson.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Barkley Rosser  from Econospeak &#8220;The young will pay more and get less.&#8221; More Nonsense from Robert Samuelson Our old friend, Dean Baker at Beat the Press, does a good job of taking apart yet another screed by the execrable Robert J. Samuelson, faux economist for WaPo, whining about why nobody is jumping on board [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Barkley Rosser  from Econospeak</p>
<p>&#8220;The young will pay more and get less.&#8221; More Nonsense from Robert Samuelson</p>
<p> Our old friend, Dean Baker at Beat the Press, does a good job of taking apart yet another screed by the execrable Robert J. Samuelson, faux economist for WaPo, whining about why nobody is jumping on board with cuts to &#8220;entitlements,&#8221; and particularly his old bugaboo, Social Security.  Google &#8220;Dean Baker Robert Samuelson is upset&#8221; and the first hit gives you the link (Sorry, the link title is too long for me to read it and my trying to put what I saw in just sent one to the general CEPR site, bah! (Anybody out there able to tell me how to overcome this bit when urls are too damned long too read, please?).  However, I want to pound the nails in a bit more.   </p>
<p>So, RJS provides this line that if there is not an adjustment to SS (and Medicare), then &#8220;The young will pay more and get less.&#8221;  Dean quotes this, but does not go far enough in showing how totally ridiculous this is, even though he has pointed out recently that one reason there should be no adjustments for SS now is that the young are massively misinformed about what the not so bad fiscal situation of SS is.  Large proportions of them are fully convinced that they will receive no Social Security when they retire because it will be &#8220;bankrupt,&#8221; when in fact that condition will amount to them only getting something like 120% of current retirees&#8217; benefits in real terms rather than more like 170% (a bit lower, actually).  They are totally out of it, and the main threat to them losing their future benefits is if they support the sort of dreck that RJS is pushing, to cut their future benefits now because otherwise they might have their future benefits cut in the future (eeeeek!).    </p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Let me be more pointed.  RJS&#8217;s statement is simply a lie.  The proposals to cut Social Security have generally taken two forms recently: imposing a chain price index and adding another round of retirement age increases in the future beyond those that were imposed by the Greenspan Commission nearly 30 years ago and which are still coming in.  The former is estimated to reduce cost of living increases by about 0.3% per year, and this would over the next few years indeed gradually reduce what elders receive in benefits, although it is not at all clear that this will lead to any reduction in what the young will be paying, unless this is accompanied by another round of fica tax cutting, or fica is restructured to have the same revenues come in but have it paid over all income levels, thereby reducing the burden for anybody under the upper cutoff for paying it.  However, the effects of this change in the CPI used means that the cuts will get bigger and bigger as time passes, meaning that those who will be most negatively impacted will not the evil baby boomers, but the current young when they finally retire, although since they think they will get nothing, presumably they will be grateful to get even a crust of dry bread.    </p>
<p>More egregious for RJS&#8217;s arguments, and where he really is just outright lying rather than merely stretching the truth is this matter of increasing the retirement age.  Nobody is talking about any further rounds of that happening anytime soon.  RJS poses as this defender of youth against his awful generation (he trumpets his baby boomerdom to supposedly give credibility to his regularly repeated nonsense), but in fact the baby boomers, or certainly at least the front end ones like me and him, will not be affected at all by these future increases in eligibility ages.  It will be the Gen Xers and the Millennials.  RJS is just lying through his teeth.  We old farts will not pay at all as a result of this change, but today&#8217;s youth will. </p>
<p>reposted from <a href="http://econospeak.blogspot.com/2012/12/the-young-will-pay-more-and-get-less.html">Econospeak</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/the-young-will-pay-more-and-get-less-more-nonsense-from-robert-samuelson.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
