<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Iraq war &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Lt. Col. Daniel L. Davis</title>
		<link>./../../2012/02/lt-col-daniel-l-davis.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/02/lt-col-daniel-l-davis.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2012 15:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Afghanistan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Iraq war]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mideast]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/02/lt-col-daniel-l-davis.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Rolling Stone (via Reader Supported News) points us to an op-ed in Armed Forces Journal  by Lt. Col. Daniel L. Davis and the pdf at Rolling Stone. Earlier this week, the New York Times’ Scott Shane published a bombshell piece about Lt. Colonel Daniel Davis, a 17-year Army veteran recently returned from a second tour [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a target="_blank" href="http://www.rollingstone.com/politics/blogs/national-affairs/the-afghanistan-report-the-pentagon-doesnt-want-you-to-read-20120210">Rolling Stone</a> (via <a href="http://readersupportednews.org/" target="_blank">Reader Supported News</a>) points us to an op-ed in <a href="http://www.armedforcesjournal.com/2012/02/8904030" target->Armed Forces Journal</a>  by Lt. Col. Daniel L. Davis<strong> </strong>and the pdf at <a href="http://www1.rollingstone.com/extras/RS_REPORT.pdf" target->Rolling Stone</a>.<br />
<blockquote>Earlier this week, the New York Times’ Scott Shane published a <a target="_blank" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/02/06/world/asia/army-colonel-challenges-pentagons-afghanistan-claims.html?_r=1">bombshell piece</a> about Lt. Colonel Daniel Davis, a 17-year Army veteran recently returned from a second tour in Afghanistan. According to the Times, the 48-year-old Davis had written an 84-page unclassified report, as well as a classified report, offering his assessment of the decade-long war. That assessment is essentially that the war has been a disaster and the military&#8217;s top brass has not leveled with the American public about just how badly it’s been going.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/02/lt-col-daniel-l-davis.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Compare and contrast</title>
		<link>./../../2011/07/compare-and-contrast.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/07/compare-and-contrast.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2011 10:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Iraq war]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/07/compare-and-contrast.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[If Obama&#8217;s first term is a different thing than GW&#8217;s third term, why is Obama&#8217;s Secretary of Defense telling US troops that that they&#8217;re in Iraq because the US was attacked on September 11?]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If Obama&#8217;s first term is a different thing than GW&#8217;s third term, why is Obama&#8217;s Secretary of Defense telling US troops that that they&#8217;re in Iraq <a href="http://delong.typepad.com/sdj/2011/07/eschaton-maintaining-the-official-village-myths.html">because the US was attacked on September 11</a>?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/07/compare-and-contrast.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>A tax thought&#8230;A Modest Tax Proposal</title>
		<link>./../../2011/05/a-tax-thought-a-modest-tax-proposal.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/05/a-tax-thought-a-modest-tax-proposal.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2011 14:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Afghanistan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Corporate Taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[federal deficit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Iraq war]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/05/a-tax-thought-a-modest-tax-proposal.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt A Modest Tax Proposal The GOP is all breathless about deficits, but this is the same GOP of Dubya Bush that fought a war in Iraq (unnecessary) and Afghanistan (overextended) funded entirely by debt. So, the following proposal. A 3% surtax on taxable incomes over $75,000 until the cost of [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt</p>
<p><strong>A Modest Tax Proposal</strong></p>
<p>The GOP is all breathless about deficits, but this is the same GOP of Dubya Bush that fought a war in Iraq (unnecessary) and Afghanistan (overextended)  funded entirely by debt.</p>
<p>So, the following proposal.</p>
<p>A 3% surtax on taxable incomes over $75,000 until the cost of both wars is paid.</p>
<p>This level of tax should not slow the economy, and we should face up to the responsibilities of having troops in the field.</p>
<p>Your thoughts?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/05/a-tax-thought-a-modest-tax-proposal.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Nation at war</title>
		<link>./../../2010/07/nation-at-war.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/07/nation-at-war.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Jul 2010 09:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Afghanistan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Iraq war]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/07/nation-at-war.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[We actually appeared to have forgotten we are a nation &#8220;at war&#8221; if news reporting is any indication from a personal search, except for the DC centered coverage of Gen. McChrystal. Notice it was a music magazine that got the scoop, more power to them, not mainstream media. Here are some thoughts from Tomdispatch to [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We actually appeared to have forgotten we are a nation &#8220;at war&#8221; if news reporting is any indication from a personal search, except for the DC centered coverage of Gen. McChrystal.  Notice it was a music magazine that got the scoop, more power to them, not mainstream media.  </p>
<p>Here are some thoughts from <a target="blank" href="http://www.tomdispatch.com/archive/175269/">Tomdispatch</a> to remind us of the dark side of our history in the Middle East.  Follow the link for more.</p>
<blockquote><p>Doesn’t it seem, sometimes, that American history, the “people’s history,” is actually made by about 17 giant government and corporate entities, all hopelessly intertwined &#8212; and worse yet, that they never go away?  On Tuesday, TomDispatch posted Stephen Kinzer’s piece, “<a href="http://www.tomdispatch.com/archive/175267/stephan_kinzer_BP_in_the_Gulf" target="_blank">BP in the Gulf &#8212; The Persian Gulf</a>.”  It was a reminder that, more than half a century ago (when it was called the Anglo-Persian Oil Company), the giant oil corporation now despoiling the Gulf of Mexico had, in quite a different way, despoiled Iranian democracy to maintain its hold on that country’s oil.  It did so in conjunction with the Central Intelligence Agency, which, in 1953, overthrew a democratic Iranian government eager to nationalize that oil.</p>
<p>Well, neither of them has gone away.  That’s obvious enough.  Last week, the CIA popped up again, this time in conjunction with another of its favorite corporations, the infamous rent-a-gun company formerly known as Blackwater, now Xe Services.  The Agency has given that for-profit warrior outfit a new <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/06/23/AR2010062305255.html" target="_blank">$100 million contract</a> to guard its various outposts in Afghanistan “and elsewhere”&#8230;<br />&#8230;</p>
<p>Worse yet, the CIA wasn’t alone, as the State Department just agreed to shell out $120,123,293 in taxpayer dough to a unit of Xe to pay for guarding some of its facilities in Afghanistan.  (The awarding of this contract, reports CBS News which broke the story, comes barely &#8220;four months after the government of Iraq ordered hundreds of Blackwater-linked security guards to leave the country within seven days or face possible arrest.”)</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/07/nation-at-war.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Would Have Been Hoisted from Comments Elsewhere</title>
		<link>./../../2009/12/would-have-been-hoisted-from-comments-elsewhere.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/12/would-have-been-hoisted-from-comments-elsewhere.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Dec 2009 21:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[bailout]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Class war]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Interfluidity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Iraq war]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[solvency crisis]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/12/would-have-been-hoisted-from-comments-elsewhere.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[But Steve Randy Waldman already did the heavy lifting: several of the other officers had been stationed at the height of the housing bubble at facilities located near D.C. in Northern Virginia. They lived in very modest homes which were removed from their workplaces by substantial driving distances, but these homes were nevertheless particularly pricey [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>But Steve Randy Waldman already <a href="http://www.interfluidity.com/v2/384.html">did the heavy lifting</a>:<br />
<blockquote>several of the other officers had been stationed at the height of the housing bubble at facilities located near D.C. in Northern Virginia. They lived in very modest homes which were removed from their workplaces by substantial driving distances, but these homes were nevertheless particularly pricey for someone with a family and on a military salary. The humble homes ate significant chunks out of those salaries as the commutes did to the (already scarce) time these men had to spend with their families&#8230;.</p>
<p>While we were away, about halfway through our deployment, the crash began and something mysterious had gone horribly wrong with the machinery of America. The small equity positions these men has invested in their respective residences were wiped out in a matter of months. By the time they were close to returning to these homes the men were all badly underwater by over one hundred thousand dollars and, what was worse, the Army had reassigned them&#8230;.</p>
<p>Their instinct was that if they had borrowed money from a friend or a neighbor they would feel a deep, almost sacred, obligation to make good on their debt and pay it off in full plus interest as soon as they could manage it&#8230;.That was, after all, the “right thing to do” as they had been taught by their parents and grandparents.</p>
<p>But then the bailouts with taxpayer money started. The “too big to fail” talk began, and then the wave of foreclosures and layoffs and emerging scandals of the unjust excesses of the financial industry, and so on. And these men began to feel that from the personal scale of their little world, their family was also perhaps “too big to fail” by the forfeit of their hard-won life’s savings.</p>
<p>They also started to question how the bailouts could make sense without some of the benefits flowing to innocent and responsible men such as themselves&#8230;.</p></blockquote>
<p>Go <a href="http://www.interfluidity.com/v2/384.html">Read the Whole Thing</a>.</p>
<p>Note:I mentioned this near the end of my last post, but it really deserves to be seen and read by more than the six people who might read to the end of that one.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/12/would-have-been-hoisted-from-comments-elsewhere.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>6</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Another Honest Republican</title>
		<link>./../../2009/03/another-honest-republican.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/03/another-honest-republican.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2009 22:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Afghanistan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Iraq war]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[War against Terrorism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/03/another-honest-republican.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Lawrence Wilkerson tells the truth and shames the Devil: Many detainees locked up at Guantanamo were innocent men swept up by U.S. forces unable to distinguish enemies from noncombatants, a former Bush administration official said Thursday. &#8220;There are still innocent people there,&#8221; Lawrence B. Wilkerson, a Republican who was chief of staff to then-Secretary of [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Lawrence Wilkerson <a target="_blank" href="http://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/20090319/ap_on_re_la_am_ca/cb_guantanamo_wrongly_held/print">tells the truth and shames the Devil</a>:<br />
<blockquote>Many detainees locked up at Guantanamo were innocent men swept up by U.S. forces unable to distinguish enemies from noncombatants, a former Bush administration official said Thursday. &#8220;There are still innocent people there,&#8221; Lawrence B. Wilkerson, a Republican who was chief of staff to then-Secretary of State Colin Powell, told The Associated Press. &#8220;Some have been there six or seven years.&#8221;</p>
<p>Wilkerson, who first made the assertions in an Internet posting on Tuesday, told the AP he learned from briefings and by communicating with military commanders that the U.S. soon realized many Guantanamo detainees were innocent but nevertheless held them in hopes they could provide information for a &#8220;mosaic&#8221; of intelligence.</p>
<p>&#8220;It did not matter if a detainee were innocent. Indeed, because he lived in Afghanistan and was captured on or near the battle area, he must know something of importance,&#8221; Wilkerson wrote in the blog. He said intelligence analysts hoped to gather &#8220;sufficient information about a village, a region, or a group of individuals, that dots could be connected and terrorists or their plots could be identified.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>Nice to know there was a reason.  Read the whole thing, especially<br />
<blockquote>In <a target="_blank" href="http://www.thewashingtonnote.com/archives/2009/03/some_truths_abo/">his posting for The Washington Note blog</a>, Wilkerson wrote that &#8220;U.S. leadership became aware of this lack of proper vetting very early on and, thus, of the reality that many of the detainees were innocent of any substantial wrongdoing, had little intelligence value, and should be immediately released.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>I believe that counts as malice aforethought.  Can we please take back The Ancestral Party now?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/03/another-honest-republican.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Hegemony on Steroids: the NeoCons, Iraq, and Historical Revisionism</title>
		<link>./../../2009/01/hegemony-on-steroids-the-neocons-iraq-and-historical-revisionism.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/01/hegemony-on-steroids-the-neocons-iraq-and-historical-revisionism.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2009 19:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Iraq war]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[neo-cons]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[PNAC]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/01/hegemony-on-steroids-the-neocons-iraq-and-historical-revisionism.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Bruce Webb Paul Rosenberg has started an interesting series over at Open Left that in some ways could see my post What is the Nexus? as prologue. The first post in the series is Hegemony On Steroids&#8211;Episode 35,879: &#8220;The Neocons Couldn&#8217;t A Dunnit!&#8221; It starts by stating one set of revisionist talking points eagerly [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Bruce Webb</p>
<p>Paul Rosenberg has started an interesting series over at Open Left that in some ways could see my post <a href="http://angrybear.blogspot.com/2008/12/what-was-nexus.html">What is the Nexus?</a> as prologue.</p>
<p>The first post in the series is <a href="http://openleft.com/showDiary.do?diaryId=10701">Hegemony On Steroids&#8211;Episode 35,879: &#8220;The Neocons Couldn&#8217;t A Dunnit!&#8221;</a> It starts by stating one set of revisionist talking points eagerly being peddled by wingnuttia (and the Village) to keep from having to take responsibility for Iraq<br />
<blockquote>Last week, the day before Christmas, Digby took note of an eager wanker (Frank Harvey, pimped by Kelly McParland) making the argument that if Gore had been President instead of Bush, we would have had the exact same clusterfuck, because (a) the neocons had nothing to do with it, that&#8217;s just a conspiracy theory! (b) invading Iraq was inevitable and (c) Al Gore had all sorts of hawkish attitudes, towards Iraq in particular, so, case closed!</p></blockquote>
<p> Well Digby did a through take down on points (b) and (c). Mainly in that Al Gore came out publicly against the then current Bush approach on Sept 23, 2002, i.e. before the war.  (Extensive quotes and links at OL). Which allows Paul to pursue assertion (a). </p>
<p>And in the course of that he totally demolishes the twin arguments that the Neo-Cons were not powerful enough to get everyone else to go along and that in the end everybody was sharing the same intelligence analysis. Both are simple nonsense and Paul lays out the case why that is so. Conclusion of part 1<br />
<blockquote>In fact, if one looks carefully at what was going on behind the screen&#8211;and even just what was going on in plain sight&#8211;it soon becomes quite apparent that BushCo and the neocons were quite aware of how utterly flimsy their &#8220;evidence&#8221; was.  They may have fooled some other folks&#8211;or at least bluffed them into playing safe and stiffling their doubts&#8211;but they knew all along their case couldn&#8217;t stand the light of day.</p>
<p>Which is why they never laid it out for anyone else to see.  They knew very well that there was no &#8220;there&#8221; there.  They were eager to show us all the evidence.  They just didn&#8217;t have any.</p>
<p>In Part 2, we&#8217;ll take a closer look.</p></blockquote>
<p> Link to Part 2 and some comments below the fold<br /><a href="http://openleft.com/showDiary.do?diaryId=10706"><br />Hegemony On Steroids&#8211;&#8220;The Neocons Couldn&#8217;t A Dunnit!&#8221;, Part 2</a><br />
<blockquote>After the Iraq fiasco, the key to continuing neocon power was two-fold: First, disappearing the disaster. Second disappearing the neocons themselves.  The disaster was disappeared by a series of rationalizations and redefinitions, the most important of which was the replacement of the original rationale&#8211;9/11, WMDs and all that&#8211;with goal of &#8220;democratization&#8221; (which the US originally had no interest in), and the replacement of all else with the mantra, &#8220;the surge is working.&#8221;  Disappearing the neocons involved a rather extensive chameleon act, a key part of which was the erasure of their fingerprints all over everything in sight.<br />This is where we get the common bit of hegemonic narrative used to excuse the Iraq War, the claim that &#8220;everyone&#8221; believed the intelligence that Saddam had WMDs.  This narrative is not just false, it&#8217;s a textbook case of how hegemonic discourse makes it virtually impossible to think straight about anything.  There&#8217;s an old adage that if you ask the wrong questions, you can&#8217;t get the right answers.  Hegemonic discourse works best by making sure that nothing but wrong questions get asked.</p>
<p>By implicitly making the question, &#8220;did everyone believe Saddam had WMDs?&#8221;&#8211;and not even asking it, but simply asserting an answer, every question we ought to be asking is summarily swept off the table.  And the chance of making a truly fundamental break with the neocon direction is substantially weakened</p></blockquote>
<p> If some of this sounds awfully familiar it should, various commenter/war supporters here have been faithfully pushing versions of this argument for years.</p>
<p>In any event Paul goes on to give a detailed chronological timeline of how the intelligence was being consciously shaped around the war policy. In other words the Brits had it exactly right in the Downing Street Memo. The question of why Blair and Powell and Rice and Tenet (none of them neo-cons) and yes too many congressional democrats went along is really the theme of the rest of the piece. The whole thing is longish but certainly worth it.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/01/hegemony-on-steroids-the-neocons-iraq-and-historical-revisionism.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Symbolman: Dangerous lunatic or prophet before his time?</title>
		<link>./../../2008/12/symbolman-dangerous-lunatic-or-prophet-before-his-time.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/12/symbolman-dangerous-lunatic-or-prophet-before-his-time.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2008 18:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Bush]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Iraq war]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/12/symbolman-dangerous-lunatic-or-prophet-before-his-time.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Bruce WebbBack in the day even to hint at some of the subjects of Symbolman&#8217;s brilliant flash productions was to mark you as being infected with Bush Derangement Syndrome (BDS). But now in the waning days of Bush/Cheney maybe it is time to push back against the revisionism. Warning if you ever supported Bush [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Bruce Webb<br />Back in the day even to hint at some of the subjects of Symbolman&#8217;s brilliant flash productions was to mark you as being infected with Bush Derangement Syndrome (BDS). But now in the waning days of Bush/Cheney maybe it is time to push back against the revisionism. Warning if you ever supported Bush or this war you probably need to use your scroll bar. RIGHT NOW. Because I guarantee you are not going to feel comfortable with any of this content.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.takebackthemedia.com/onearmy.html">Army of One</a> If you can watch this without tearing up you may not have any heart at all. Note that this is copyright 2003 before we had any hint that the Walter Reed situation would exist. &#8216;Support the Troops&#8217;? My ass.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.takebackthemedia.com/bushnonazi.html">Bush no Nazi</a>. A little edgier, but like all of Symbolman&#8217;s work fully documented. And also well scored, in this case with Spike Jones. Chorus: &#8220;When the fuhrer says we are the master race, sieg heil, sieg heil right in the fuhrer&#8217;s face!&#8221; In any event pretty illuminating about the source of the Bush family fortune.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.takebackthemedia.com/triwimp.html">Triumph of the Wimp</a>. Whatever you do stick it out to the second half with the soundtrack of &#8216;Fortunate Son&#8217;. Which if it wasn&#8217;t written with Bush in mind certainly could have been.</p>
<p>And for people tragically stuck in print mode it is worth reviewing this Onion article published days before the Bush inaugral (Jan 17, 2001). <a href="http://www.theonion.com/content/node/28784">Bush: &#8216;Our Long National Nightmare Of Peace And Prosperity Is Finally Over&#8217;</a> Boy Howdy. Key paras?<br />
<blockquote>During the 40-minute speech, Bush also promised to bring an end to the severe war drought that plagued the nation under Clinton, assuring citizens that the U.S. will engage in at least one Gulf War-level armed conflict in the next four years.</p>
<p>&#8220;You better believe we&#8217;re going to mix it up with somebody at some point during my administration,&#8221; said Bush, who plans a 250 percent boost in military spending. &#8220;Unlike my predecessor, I am fully committed to putting soldiers in battle situations. Otherwise, what is the point of even having a military?&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>Shortest verse in the Bible? &#8216;Jesus wept&#8217;. (John 11:35)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/12/symbolman-dangerous-lunatic-or-prophet-before-his-time.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>What was the Nexus?</title>
		<link>./../../2008/12/what-was-the-nexus.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/12/what-was-the-nexus.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2008 18:17:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Iraq war]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[PNAC]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/12/what-was-the-nexus.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[(Update. Not that it matters much at this point but I fixed the link to the Letter to President Clinton. BW 1/3/09) No I am not asking about a car or misspelling LexisNexis or even talking about a new sequel to the Matrix. It is instead the question to be applied to the following list [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>(Update. Not that it matters much at this point but I fixed the link to the Letter to President Clinton. BW 1/3/09)</p>
<p>No I am not asking about a car or misspelling LexisNexis or even talking about a new sequel to the Matrix. It is instead the question to be applied to the following list of names?</p>
<p>Jeb Bush, Dick Cheney and then in alphabetical order:</p>
<p>Elliott Abrams    Richard L. Armitage     Gary Bauer   William J. Bennett</p>
<p>Jeffrey Bergner    John Bolton     Eliot Cohen   Midge Decter   Paula Dobriansky   Steve Forbes</p>
<p>Aaron Friedberg Francis Fukuyama   Frank Gaffney   Fred C. Ikle    Donald Kagan   Robert Kagan    Zalmay Khalilzad</p>
<p>William Kristol    I. Lewis Libby   Richard Perle  Norman Podhoretz   Dan Qualye   Peter W. Rodman   Stephen P. Rosen</p>
<p>Henry S. Rowen   Donald Rumsfeld    William Schneider, Jr.    Vin Weber   George Weigel   Paul Wolfowitz </p>
<p>The answer is below the fold.<br /> Is it a cross section of Republican leadership? Well no, not now and not when the list was compiled. In particular there are very few actual politicians on the list, if by politicians we mean people who ran for office and won.</p>
<p>Is it a list of people who served in the Reagan Administration in foreign policy positions or under Bush I? Well no, though you are getting close. Because some of these people have never to my knowledge had a formal position in government at all.</p>
<p>And while pretty much the entire top tier of the Bush II official security apparatus is represented (Cheney, Bolton, Rumsfeld, Abrams, Libby, Khalilzad) they far from exhaust the entire list. So that is not it either.</p>
<p>Well then is this list somehow bipartisan? Well no, I don&#8217;t think you could find a self-identified Democrat on the list. (Though there are a couple of names I am not immediately familiar with).</p>
<p>No what you have here is the combined signatories (because there is a lot of overlap) of the <a href="http://www.newamericancentury.org/statementofprinciples.htm">Project for a New American Century&#8217;s Statement of Principles</a> of June 3, 1997 and the PNAC&#8217;s <a href="http://www.newamericancentury.org/iraqclintonletter.htm">Letter to President Clinton</a> of Jan 6, 1998.</p>
<p>As the Bush/Cheney regime winds down there are some ongoing and persistent attempts to shape the historical legacy of both men, and as all agree Iraq is going to be the largest element in that. The standard story being pushed is that Bush was a reluctant warrior pushed into war by bad intelligence and retransigence by Saddam. And moreover that that decision was joined in by the entire center-right including both Clintons, Gore and every Representative and Senator who voted for the AUMF in fall 2002. Well sorry I am here to call bullshit on that one and a look at the Statement and the Letter say why. First from the Statement<br />
<blockquote>We aim to change this. We aim to make the case and rally support for American global leadership.</p>
<p>As the 20th century draws to a close, the United States stands as the world&#8217;s preeminent power. Having led the West to victory in the Cold War, America faces an opportunity and a challenge: Does the United States have the vision to build upon the achievements of past decades? Does the United States have the resolve to shape a new century favorable to American principles and interests?</p></blockquote>
<p> Note what is missing here. There is not a hint of multilateralism in any context other than &#8216;American global leadership&#8217; and not a suggestion that the goal is to spread democracy or global prosperity or  anything else for its own sake. Instead this New Century is to be an unabashedly American Century to further America&#8217;s own interests. This is a straight out call for global American hegemony. So how do we get there? Well lets look at the letter.<br />
<blockquote>Given the magnitude of the threat, the current policy, which depends for its success upon the steadfastness of our coalition partners and upon the cooperation of Saddam Hussein, is dangerously inadequate. The only acceptable strategy is one that eliminates the possibility that Iraq will be able to use or threaten to use weapons of mass destruction. In the near term, this means a willingness to undertake military action as diplomacy is clearly failing. In the long term, it means removing Saddam Hussein and his regime from power. That now needs to become the aim of American foreign policy.</p>
<p>We urge you to articulate this aim, and to turn your Administration&#8217;s attention to implementing a strategy for removing Saddam&#8217;s regime from power. This will require a full complement of diplomatic, political and military efforts. Although we are fully aware of the dangers and difficulties in implementing this policy, we believe the dangers of failing to do so are far greater. We believe the U.S. has the authority under existing UN resolutions to take the necessary steps, including military steps, to protect our vital interests in the Gulf. In any case, American policy cannot continue to be crippled by a misguided insistence on unanimity in the UN Security Council.</p></blockquote>
<p>. Which translated means &#8216;screw consultation with our allies, forget complying with our treaty obligations under the UN Charter, we need to take the bastard out using all means necessary&#8217;.</p>
<p>Feel free to browse around the rest of the PNAC website. You won&#8217;t be able to dodge the conclusion that a certain self-identified group of past national security officials, opinion makers, and selected academics committed themselves in the mid-nineties to an aggressive policy of using unilateral US military force to shape the world in America&#8217;s image or at least in America&#8217;s interest. Starting with an invasion of Iraq. They were not able to get Clinton to move as aggressively as they liked, and in the aftermath of Bush v. Gore didn&#8217;t quite have the public support needed to stage a military invasion of Iraq. Until of course 9/11 intervened.</p>
<p>In any event anyone who thinks this war was in any fundamentally contingent on anything that happened in 2001 needs to review the record. All of these people eagerly signed on to a campaign of Iraq invasion with or without ally or UN agreement four or more years prior to 9/11. And it is hard not to identify these people with those that thought Bush I was too tentative after Gulf War I. These people were itching to get a war on, and Cheney&#8217;s appointment to lead the VP search team gave them all the opening they needed. Key team members were installed at high levels in State, Defense and the WH itself and all they were waiting for was an excuse.</p>
<p>A last observation. Note that while the plans may have always included a Bush, George wasn&#8217;t the first choice, instead it seems like JEB was going to be the figurehead (or given that he is by all accounts smarter than W, perhaps the actual leader).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/12/what-was-the-nexus.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>How Not to Pay For a War</title>
		<link>./../../2007/05/how-not-to-pay-for-a-war.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2007/05/how-not-to-pay-for-a-war.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 29 May 2007 03:16:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[earmarking]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[finance]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hormats]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Iraq war]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[supplemental appropriations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[War against Terrorism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2007/05/how-not-to-pay-for-a-war.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I&#8217;d like to thank the team at Angry Bear for giving me this opportunity to answer questions about my new book, &#8220;The Price of Liberty: Paying for America&#8217;s Wars.&#8221; If you haven&#8217;t gotten a chance yet, I encourage you to read the Outlook piece I wrote for the Washington Post on May 6. This piece [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;d like to thank the team at Angry Bear for giving me this opportunity to answer questions about my new book, &#8220;The Price of Liberty: Paying for America&#8217;s Wars.&#8221; If you haven&#8217;t gotten a chance yet, I encourage you to <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/05/04/AR2007050402558.html">read the Outlook piece</a> I wrote for the Washington Post on May 6. This piece contains a few ideas distilled from my book. The Post has been kind enough to let us circulate it.</p>
<p>There&#8217;s a popular post on this blog called &#8220;How Not to Run a War.&#8221; Taking a cue from that, I want to briefly talk about &#8220;How Not to Pay For a War.&#8221;</p>
<p>We shouldn&#8217;t pay for a war by INCREASING spending on non-essential domestic programs, particularly by increasing spending for &#8220;earmarked&#8221; politically inspired projects meant to satisfy domestic constituencies. In every war of the past, our government has cut non essential spending to make room in the budget to pay for the war. Not this time.</p>
<p>We should not pay virtually the entire cost of a war with &#8220;emergency supplementals&#8221; which skirt the normal budget process and thus avoid the normal scrutiny of determining what is really needed and what the tradeoffs are; even during the unpopular Vietnam War the use of supplementals was limited after the first couple of years.</p>
<p>And we should reflect in this post-Memorial Day period on a situation in which most Americans have been treated to tax cuts and many benefit from domestic spending for politically-inspired projects and generous subsidies while Americans fighting abroad and their families are making major sacrifices. That is unfair and unjust, and not consistent with the best traditions of America. No matter what one thinks of the war the troops should be well equipped, our wounded veterans should be given the best of care, and military families should be given the help they need to live at decent standards while their breadwinners are fighting abroad.</p>
<p>The challenge now is to learn from our mistakes and take them into account as we as a country determine how to pay for the longer war against terrorism and to be sure that the US remains financially resilient enough to counter future threats to our well being &#8212; whether from a catastrophic act of terrorism,  foreign crises that may erupt in areas such as the Middle East that threaten our allies or oil, another devastating hurricane or a major    pandemic.</p>
<p>So how should we prepare to pay for our future security over coming years? It won&#8217;t be easy given other demands on the budget, particularly projections for the rapidly growing costs of Social Security, Medicare and Medicaid in the decade ahead.</p>
<p>And how do we meet the costs of these programs and our national security requirements without producing massive budget deficits and/or huge tax hikes? Or are these unavoidable?</p>
<p>I have some thoughts on these issues, which are included in my book and which I am looking forward to discussing on this blog tour over the next several days, but my major objective is to develop a dialogue in the hope that thoughtful people of various views can come up with sound solutions.</p>
<p>I welcome YOUR thoughts on these questions and promise to respond as soon as possible. Many thanks for joining me in the quest for answers to these difficult but important questions.</p>
<p>Bob Hormats, Author,<br /><a href="http://www.henryholt.com/holt/liberty.htm">&#8220;The Price of Liberty: Paying for America&#8217;s Wars&#8221; (Times Books)</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2007/05/how-not-to-pay-for-a-war.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
