<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Linda Beale &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The Evils of Corporatism</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/the-evils-of-corporatism.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/the-evils-of-corporatism.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2013 10:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Corporatism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linda Beale]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/the-evils-of-corporatism.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Beale(op-ed) The Evils of Corporatism I have often written in these pages about &#8220;corporatism&#8221;, an approach that pervades our economy and many government agencies and does not align with the interests of the majority of Americans. Corporatism runs rampant today in states&#8217; treatment of their public universities, treasures of the American educational system [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Linda Beale<br />(op-ed)</p>
<p>The Evils of Corporatism</p>
<p>I have often written in these pages about &#8220;corporatism&#8221;, an approach that pervades our economy and many government agencies and does not align with the interests of the majority of Americans.</p>
<p>Corporatism runs rampant today in states&#8217; treatment of their public universities, treasures of the American educational system that have been central in continuing basic research into ideas that transform our lives and our understanding of ourselves.  Today, many states are cutting back more and more on funding for state universities, and demanding that the universities turn themselves into contract researchers for private corporations (where the corporations, not the universities, enjoy the commercial fruits of the research).  This is just another form of subsidy for Big Business at the expense of ordinary people.  </p>
<p>In addition, many states&#8211;including regressive Michigan under regressive governor Rick Snyder&#8211;are cutting funding for state universities in order to provide even more tax cuts to their corporate Big Business buddies.  And they tend to cut funding to those that need it most to serve the neediest populations that find equality of opportunity a meaningless promise in today&#8217;s casino capitalist economy&#8211;the poor and the disadvantaged. </p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>In Michigan, for example Wayne State&#8217;s paltry increase doesn&#8217;t keep pace with inflation, but Wayne serves the region and the region&#8217;s population in ways that other institutions in Michigan do not.  Corporatism, of course, also runs rampant in the universities themselves.  Wayne&#8217;s current president, who is paid $410,000 for being here only a few days a week and has a &#8220;deputy president&#8221; paid another $400,000, was a chief corporate officer at Ford and came to the university with very little understanding of academics.  It has shown, as he has run the place like a corporation, with his &#8220;never say no to the boss&#8221; cabinet of vice presidents and associate vice presidents (ranging around 23-25 these days) operating on a &#8220;flatter your boss brings rewards&#8221; system.</p>
<p>Corporatism exists all across governments, where Big Business spends billions to win influence on legislators and agency heads, and goes to every length to present a &#8220;PR&#8221; picture of the world as they want us to believe it exists to ordinary Americans.</p>
<p>Take one example&#8211;the Bureau of Land Management.  The BLM is basically a government toady for the wealthy and influential cattlemen and other industries that want to use public lands for private enrichment.  Perhaps the most glaring (but certainly not the only) example of this is the BLM&#8217;s treatment of the native American wild mustangs on public lands.  In spite of legislation charging the BLM to protect and preserve these American treasures on public lands, it has engaged in activities that are decimating the population, herding them up and selling them at $25 a head to buyers who take them to inhumane slaughterhouses in Mexico to be butchered while still conscious.  BLM is a toady for big ranchers, not a protector of public treasures.  And it should be stopped.</p>
<p>There is a non-profit organization that works hard on this issue&#8211;the <a href="http://wildhorsefreedomfederation.org/">Wild Horse Freedom Federation</a>.  Earlier, it presented petitions to President Obama urging him to rein in the BLM and stop its use of tax dollars to wipe America&#8217;s wild horses off public lands to which they are legally entitled under the legislation passed in the mid 1970s.</p>
<p>Are you listening, President Obama?  Or is the only tune you hear the one played by Wall Street, Big Business, and corporate wealth?  If the latter, corporatism will continue to expand to cover every aspect of our lives, and the freedom that we pretend to cherish as Americans will disappear as surely as the wild mustangs will vanish from their &#8220;protected&#8221; public lands.</p>
<p>cross posted with <a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2013/03/the-evils-of-corporatism.html">ataxingmatter</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/the-evils-of-corporatism.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Same-Sex Marriage In Illinois? No Basis for Objection</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/same-sex-marriage-in-illinois-no-basis-for-objection.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/same-sex-marriage-in-illinois-no-basis-for-objection.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2013 12:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Linda Beale]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/same-sex-marriage-in-illinois-no-basis-for-objection.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Beale (op-ed) Same-Sex Marriage In Illinois? No Basis for Objection In the US today, 9 states and the District of Colombia have legalized same-sex marriages and 9 states (counting Colorado, where the legislature passed a civil union bill on March 13) have legalized some form of civil union or domestic partnership for same-sex [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Linda Beale (op-ed)</p>
<p>Same-Sex Marriage In Illinois? No Basis for Objection</p>
<p>In the US today, 9 states and the District of Colombia have legalized <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Same-sex_marriage">same-sex marriages</a> and 9 states (counting Colorado, where the legislature passed a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Civil_union">civil union</a> bill on March 13) have legalized some form of civil union or domestic partnership for same-sex couples. Now one of the civil union states&#8211;where same-sex couples have everything that married couples have except for the stigma of not being permitted to call their union a marriage&#8211;is on the verge of recognizing the hatefulness of that stigma and enacting a same-sex marriage statute.  Illinois&#8217;s Senate has passed the legislation.  Illinois&#8217;s House executive committee has said it supports it.  and Illinois&#8217;s governor has said he will sign it.  See <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geoffrey_R._Stone">Geoffrey R. Stone</a>,<a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/geoffrey-r-stone/same-sex-marriage-in-illi_b_2883601.html?utm_hp_ref=politics">Same-Sex Marriage in Illinois&#8211;Now is the Time,</a> Huffington Post (The Blog), Mar. 15, 2013.</p>
<p>As Stone points out, we have come a long way in a few short years, with a majority of Americans now supporting the concept of same-sex marriage.</p>
<blockquote><p>[W]e have changed as a society. We have come to understand that people around us &#8212; good, kind, decent, loving people &#8212; are themselves gays and lesbians. And with that awareness of individual gays and lesbians, the social view of homosexuals generally has gradually changed.</p></blockquote>
<p>Further, any state that has created an &#8220;in all but the name&#8221; civil union equivalent of same-sex marriage has recognized the injustice of not permitting same-sex couples to have the kind of legal, committed relationship that different-sex couples can have.  But that difference&#8211;in all but name&#8211;is not insignificant.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>As Stone notes:</p>
<blockquote><p>Imagine if African-Americans could enter into civil unions but not marriages. Imagine if Catholics could legally enter into civil unions but not marriages. Imagine if mixed-race couples could enter into civil unions but not marriages. The insult, the indignity, the discrimination would be apparent to all. The same is true for same-sex couples.</p></blockquote>
<p>And there really isn&#8217;t a good argument for refusing to remove this last indignity for same-sex <br />couples.  Most of the arguments against gay marriage are along the following lines&#8211;we have to uphold traditional (meaning different-sex) marriage; we want to encourage traditional marriage to encourage procreation and cprovide the &#8220;right&#8221; environment for children; we want to further the traditional &#8220;moral values&#8221; of society, etc.  These arguments don&#8217;t hold water as far as the well-being of children or the needs of society are concerned or even whether there is a relationship between refusing marriage to same-sex couples and accomplishing those goals.  They frequently amount to arguments from the religious views of those who cling to conservative religious perspectives of homosexuality as bad and same-sex marriage as prohibited by God.  Stone makes the point the following way.</p>
<p>In a nation committed to the separation of church and state, the government can never deny rights to some in order to appease the religious beliefs of others. During the civil rights struggle, for example, segregationists frequently invoked biblical authority for the separation of the races. The Rev. James E. Burks of Bayview Baptist Church in Norfolk, Virginia, for example, insisted that God had separated the races and that &#8220;when man sets aside the plain teachings&#8221; of the Bible and &#8220;disregards the boundary lines God Himself has drawn, man assumes a prerogative that belongs to God alone.&#8221; Similarly, discrimination against women was often justified by reference to &#8220;divine ordinance.&#8221; Such arguments have no place in the American constitutional system.</p>
<p>I understand and respect the strong and sincere feelings of those who think that the marriage of same-sex couples is incompatible with their religious beliefs. But they cannot legitimately or with a proper respect for the American system of law and justice attempt to impose those beliefs on those who disagree. They have every right not to marry a person of the same-sex and they have every right not to officiate at the marriage of a same-sex couple, but they have no right &#8212; no right &#8212; to attempt to prevent the government from recognizing such marriages because they offend their religious beliefs.</p>
<p>In my view, we Americans are too often afraid to address these points of religious bigotry, perhaps from a long association of religious groups with the struggle FOR civil rights and our knowledge that not all religions join in this charade (see link to article below, for example), perhaps from the long connection of religious leadership in communities with the communities&#8217; political and social leadership.  People don&#8217;t like to stand out, to fail to conform to the views of those around them, so where these fundamentalist religious views dominate, people may find it hard to go against them.  Perhaps it is also because we so often  misunderstand our own Constitutional protections&#8211;for rights to bear arms, for rights to avoid unreasonable searches, and especially for the free exercise of religion. Religious liberty protections are intended to ensure that no person is denied the right to exercise his/her religious views, so long as those religious views don&#8217;t cause real harm to others. But the Free Exercise Clause is not meant to protect religious institutions by allowing them to impose narrow dogmas on society in order that  their leaders and practitioners avoid the &#8220;offense&#8221; of others&#8217;  differing religious views. </p>
<p>Aside:  This is one reason that I think the Supreme Court&#8217;s ruling in the ministerial exception is wrong, the Tax Code provisions excluding certain income of ministers from taxation is wrong, having a federal &#8220;faith-based organizations&#8221; office is wrong, as is the concept recently in the news in connection with Obamacare that Catholic institutions shouldn&#8217;t have to provide the same health care&#8211;including abortion and birth control coverage&#8211;to all its employees who want it as other entities must do. ]<br />The Free Exercise Clause protects each American as an individual to provide that person the liberty to exercise his/her faith as s/he sees it (or not).   But not to impose his/her views on others.</p>
<p>cross posted with <a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2013/03/same-sex-marriage-in-illinois.html">ataxingmatter</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/same-sex-marriage-in-illinois-no-basis-for-objection.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Senator Warren Puts Bank Regulators on Hot Seat</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/senator-warren-puts-bank-regulators-on-hot-seat.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/senator-warren-puts-bank-regulators-on-hot-seat.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2013 23:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Linda Beale]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Senator Warren]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/senator-warren-puts-bank-regulators-on-hot-seat.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Beale Senator Warren Puts Bank Regulators on Hot Seat Elizabeth Warren started out her questioning of big bank regulators by noting that actual trials, where guilty parties are paraded before juries, information about their wrongdoing is spread over front pages, and everybody is aware that bad guys get punished for their bad deeds [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Linda Beale</p>
<p>Senator Warren Puts Bank Regulators on Hot Seat</p>
<p> <a href="http://www.law.harvard.edu/faculty/directory/index.html?id=82">Elizabeth Warren</a> started out her <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2F6YkBa_Tig&#038;feature=player_detailpage">questioning of big bank regulators </a>by noting that actual trials, where guilty parties are paraded before juries, information about their wrongdoing is spread over front pages, and everybody is aware that bad guys get punished for their bad deeds has an effect on whether the wrongdoing is committed in the first place. In the case of the big Wall Street banks, however, she notes that they made out like bandits during the speculative orgy that caused the financial system crisis, and yet not a one has paid by being taken to trial in this expressive way.</p>
<p>&#8220;Tell me,&#8221; she says to a group of bank regulators called before her Senate committee, &#8220;about the last few times you&#8217;ve taken the biggest <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Financial_institution">financial institutions</a> on Wall Street to trial. Anybody?&#8221; </p>
<p>The FCC representative, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tom_Curry">Tom Curry</a>, notes that ordinarily they are just trying to move things along and correct deficiencies. Warren interrupts and notes&#8211;&#8220;yes, and you set a price for that&#8230; that&#8217;s effectively a settlement. What I&#8217;m asking is &#8230; when did you last take a financial institution, a Wall Street Bank, to trial? &#8221; Curry &#8220;We&#8217;ve had a fair number of consent orders. We don&#8217;t have to bring them to trial.&#8221; Warren &#8220;I understand that you say you don&#8217;t &#8220;have&#8221; to but my question is when is the last time that you did?&#8221; (No further responsive answer). </p>
<p>(Dan here&#8230;a clip of her at the committee meeting is below the fold)</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>The same kind of interchange&#8211;can you identify when you last took Wall Street Banks to trial &#8211;was similarly nonresponded to by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elisse_B._Walter">Elisse Walter</a>. Nobody else even offered to comment. Certainly nobody offered a single date for &#8220;last time a Wall Street bank was taken to trial.&#8221; </p>
<p>Warren closed with a comment that made clear that she thought that a very different standard was being applied to Wall Street than is applied to ordinary citizens that commit even minor infractions. She noted that there are District Attorneys every day squeezing ordinary citizens on rather small matters and taking them to trial explicitly to set an example, but &#8220;For Wall Street banks, &#8216;<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Too_big_to_fail">too big to fail</a>&#8216; has become &#8216;too big to try [take to trial]&#8217;. That just seems wrong to me.&#8221;</p>
<p>You go, Elizabeth. Without using the words &#8220;class warfare&#8221;, she has made absolutely crystal clear the class warfare problem that exists in our country today, where Wall Street institutions and their chiefs and chief owners get all kinds of protections while the little guy is shaken down for peanuts. As a commenter on the site already noted, if only there were 99 more like her in the Senate&#8230;..</p>
<p>cross posted with <a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2013/02/senator-warren-puts-bank-regulators-on-hot-seat.html">ataxingmatter</a></p>
<p>(Dan here&#8230;via Business Insider comes this clip about Senator Warren&#8217;s questioning at the hearing)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/senator-warren-puts-bank-regulators-on-hot-seat.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lew&#8217;s Senate Finance hearing as Treasury Nominee</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/lews-senate-finance-hearing-as-treasury-nominee.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/lews-senate-finance-hearing-as-treasury-nominee.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2013 13:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Jack Lew]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linda Beale]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Treasury Department]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/lews-senate-finance-hearing-as-treasury-nominee.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Beale Lew&#8217;s Senate Finance hearing as Treasury Nominee Jack Lew, former budget director under Clinton and Obama and former Obama chief of staff, answered questions at Senate Finance today in his bid to succeed Tim Geithner as Treasury Secretary.  See, e.g., Rubin &#038; Klimasinska, Lew Says He Didn&#8217;t Know Money-Losing Investment Was in [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Linda Beale</p>
<p> Lew&#8217;s Senate Finance hearing as Treasury Nominee</p>
<p> <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacob_Lew">Jack Lew</a>, former budget director under Clinton and Obama and former Obama chief of staff, answered questions at Senate Finance today in his bid to succeed Tim Geithner as Treasury Secretary.  See, e.g., Rubin &#038; Klimasinska, Lew Says He Didn&#8217;t Know Money-Losing Investment Was in Caymans, Bloomberg.com (Feb. 13, 2013) and other related articles linked below.</p>
<p>When he was first nominated, I noted that I found his candidacy somewhat worrisome.  While there are a number of considerations that suggest a decently competent person, there are also some suggestions of a person who has lived in the &#8220;Wall Street&#8221; flow too long and thus falls into line with the typical Wall Street/mainstream economics thinking&#8211;thinking which ultimately supports policies that will continue to slide towards oligarchy.</p>
<p>The hearing focused on several interesting aspects of Lew&#8217;s career and investment choices.</p>
<p>1) Investing in the Caymans.  Lew made an investment of 50 to 100 thousand in a Citigroup fund based in theCaymans while he was at Citigroup, and claimed that he didn&#8217;t know it was an offshore investment.  He got out of it when he went into government and lost money on it. </p>
<p> ME:  There we have it&#8211;like most rich people, he just didn&#8217;t care enough to consider closely whehter his investment was in a tax haven country and certainly didn&#8217;t ponder the negatives .</p>
<p>2) Compensation at Citigroup.  Lew got a &#8220;bonus&#8221; of $940,000 in January 2009 when Citigroup was receiving federal bailout funds.  He defended it as being paid in the same way other private-sector employees in similar jobs were paid. </p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>ME:  But there was a ridiculous racheting up of financial sector compensation during the years when the big banks were feeding at the trough of easy mortgage securitization money and derivative speculation.  Shouldn&#8217;t someone that we hire as the head of Treasury have been more aware of that speculative binge?    Or shouldn&#8217;t that person be at least somewhat ashamed now that such an exorbitant &#8220;bonus&#8221; (10 times what most Americans receive in annual pay) should have been funded, in essential part, by taxpayer bailouts of his institution?</p>
<p>Now, Orrin Hatch (GOP-Utah) tried to make a big deal out of Lew overseeing the <a href="http://treasury.gov/fsoc">Financial Stability Oversight Council</a> in administering the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Volcker_Rule">Volcker Rule</a>limiting proprietary trading, saying that &#8220;it could lead to an awkward situation in which, in your role as chair of the FSOC, you would effectively be saying to financial firms: &#8216;Do as I say, not as I did.&#8217; &#8221;  Hatch claimed that this issue &#8220;bear[s] directly on your qualifications.&#8221;  I&#8217;m not so sure that is such a big worry since I think it is advantageous if Treasury has some understanding of how big banks trade, but it is just one more piece of Lew&#8217;s overall nature of being well-attuned to Wall Street (and not so well-attuned to Main Street).<br />  <br />3)  Corporate taxes.  Lew suggested in the hearing that Republicans and Democrats could &#8220;work together&#8221; so that changes in the international tax scheme could lead to lighter burdens on some foreign income of US multinationals.  The Bloomberg report notes that he supported a global minimum tax, but indicated that could be nominally territorial, with limits on offshoring income to tax haven countries. </p>
<p>4) Earned benefit programs.  Lew is one of those Democrats who is more right of center than the party&#8217;s base.  He still mentions the need for &#8220;entitlement&#8221; program changes as well as additional revenue increases as a part of &#8220;balanced&#8221; deficit reduction.</p>
<p>ME:  This is one of the most disturbing aspects of the Lew nomination.  He is pushing the GOP agenda of deficit reduction and &#8220;entitlement&#8221; reform when instead he should be staunchly defending the New Deal against the oligarchs who want to shrink government, diminish the safety net, end any support for innovative environmental and energy progrms, yet continue to reap benefits from the long-term government subsidies for Big Oil&#8230;..We should not tamper with Social Security&#8211;and there is no deficit reason for doing so. </p>
<p>cross posted with <a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2013/02/lews-senate-finance-hearing-as-treasury-nominee.html">ataxingmatter</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/lews-senate-finance-hearing-as-treasury-nominee.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Inequality Gap</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/the-inequality-gap.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/the-inequality-gap.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2013 00:23:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Inequality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linda Beale]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/the-inequality-gap.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Beale The Inequality Gap Robert Reich, former labor secretary, has some worthwhile advice for the President&#8217;s State of the Union address:  he notes that the focus should be the &#8220;central issue you want the nation to help you take action on&#8221;.  That&#8217;s &#8220;not immigration, guns or the environment&#8221; (though &#8220;[a]ll are important&#8221;) but [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Linda Beale</p>
<p>The Inequality Gap</p>
<p>Robert Reich, former labor secretary, has some worthwhile advice for the President&#8217;s <a href="http://www.last.fm/music/David%2BFord/State%2Bof%2Bthe%2BUnion">State of the Union address</a>:  he notes that the focus should be the &#8220;central issue you want the nation to help you take action on&#8221;.  That&#8217;s &#8220;not immigration, guns or the environment&#8221; (though &#8220;[a]ll are important&#8221;) but rather &#8220;joblessness, falling real wages, economic insecurity, and widening inequality&#8221; . See Robert Reich, <a href="http://www.salon.com/2013/02/11/memo_to_obama_focus_on_the_inequality_gap_partner/">Memo to Obama: Focus on the inequality gap</a>, Salon.com (Feb. 11, 2013).</p>
<p>He&#8217;s right.</p>
<p>&#8220;<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/It%27s_the_economy%2C_stupid">It&#8217;s the economy, stupid</a>&#8220;, that old slogan from the Clinton campaign days, goes only so far.  It doesn&#8217;t tell us, for example, what parts of the economy are most important&#8211;is it the stock market&#8217;s well-being, and indirectly the fortunes of the very few at the top of the income distribution who own significant amounts of those items being sold on the market?  Or is it the unemployment data, with its distressing litany of continuing failure of our economy to provide decent jobs for ordinary people?  Is it the way that corporate owners and managers can use the powers of government to make unionization difficult and thereby make it much easier for corporate management and shareholders to retain all the productivity gains while workers wages stagnate (everything from Wal-Mart&#8217;s tendency to tear down union fliers in worker areas (based on my personal observation) to the CEO&#8217;s determination to beat unions down any way possible (see the New York Times story in the 2/12 edition, At Cablevision, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norma_Rae">Norma Rae</a>&#8216;s Been Escorted Outside, New York Times (Feb. 12, 2013), at A23, regarding Cablevision&#8217;s firing of two  dozen employees for being off work,</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>after claiming to have an &#8220;open&#8221; management that invited worker conversations yet allowing those same employees to cool their heels for 40 minutes waiting to talk to him and then walking out and firing them for not being on the job)?  Or is it the general optimism of the upper class, who can pass on untaxed estates to heirs who will get those stocks at stepped up basis and renew the cycle of monetization without taxation for their own account?</p>
<p>Stock market statistics mostly tell us about the upper class, along with the upper part of the middle class that has some share of that bounty:  they don&#8217;t tell us about how well the economy is serving others, unless the general well-being of corporate America spills over to the general well-being of average Americans.  It doesn&#8217;t do that in an era of push-down on unions to ensure that workers have no voice, push-back on taxes to ensure that the wealthy managers and owners not only get all the productivity gains but have to pay too little in taxes to support the system that made those gains possible.  Mostly, stock market statistics tell us about how the privileged are maintaining their privilege, as their ownership of most of the financial assets continues to mean their heightened influence over most laws and their garnering of most of the gains that do take place.</p>
<p>This is well noted in a <a href="http://economistsview.typepad.com/economistsview/2013/02/there-is-nothing-inevitable-about-low-rates-of-economic-mobility.html">post on Economist&#8217;s View </a>(Mark Thoma), embedding a post by Miles Corak on Free Exchange about research on inter-generational social mobility.<br />
<blockquote>The real lesson from the historical research is not that there is anything inevitable about a low degree of inter-generational mobility, or that it signals more persistence than other research. The most privileged will do everything they can to perpetrate their status across generations, and in past eras the structure of labor markets and public policies permitted, and in some measure continue to permit, a non-level playing field.</p></blockquote>
<p>I&#8217;ve long argued that the way to evaluate the economy is in terms of how well it is serving ordinary people who make up the middle class (roughly defined as the middle three quitiles of the income and wealth distribution)  and how adequate is the safety net it provides for those who make up the lower class (the bottom quintile of income and wealth).</p>
<p>What matters is economic sustainability, in terms of  adequacy of those many intangibles by which we measure quality of life&#8211;like accessible quality health care, accessible quality education, accessible quality jobs, decent wages for decent work.  That means that government&#8217;s intervention in the economy will need to be on the side of the little guy, ensuring that resource allocation isn&#8217;t so skewed to the already rich that we become an oligarchy where most of us live off crumbs and a few of us live like kings.  If we want a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sustainability">sustainable economy</a> and sustainable democracy, democratic eqalitarianism demands that governments temper market forces with protections for underdogs, providing counter forces to the redistribution upwards tendency of brute force capitalism.</p>
<p>Today, the rise of the US oligarchy and the frightening power of wealth in determining how laws work have put us in a terrible situation:   &#8220;debtor prisons, once a relic of the 18th century, are making a frightening comeback in the U.S. justice system.&#8221;  Alex Kane, <a href="http://www.salon.com/2013/02/11/miss_a_traffic_ticket_go_to_jail/">Miss a traffic ticket, go to jail?</a>, Salon.com (Feb. 11, 2013).</p>
<p>So an appropriate slogan for progressives today should be something along the lines of &#8220;It&#8217;s the inequality, stupid.&#8221;  And that certainly doesn&#8217;t mean more of the same old failed GOP policies that favor the wealthy, mistakenly labeled &#8220;job creators&#8221; by the GOP in its constant effort to undo unions (witness Michigan&#8217;s disastrous anti-union legislation or Cablevision&#8217;s determination to aid anti-union forces and squelch union activists), favor capital over labor (from the problematic preferential rate for capital gains to the ridiculous &#8220;carried interest&#8221; taxation of the compensation payments to so-called profits partners (a category of &#8220;partner&#8221; for tax purposes not provided for in the tax code but essentially an invention of Wall Street) to the squandering waste of an estate tax and charitable contribution deduction that favor meritless accession to and use of untaxed wealth and pushes the burden for government revenues to laborers instead).  And it certainly doesn&#8217;t mean more of the same &#8220;deficit hawks, austerity mavens, trickle-down charlatans, and government haters who have commanded center stage for too long.&#8221;  <a href="http://www.salon.com/2013/02/11/memo_to_obama_focus_on_the_inequality_gap_partner/">Memo to Obama: Focus on the inqueality gap</a>,</p>
<p>As Reich says:<br />
<blockquote>The President should make it clear that any Republican effort to hold the nation hostage to the GOP&#8217;s ideological fixation on the budget deficit and a smaller government will slow the economy, likely pushing us into another recession.  And that those most imperiled are the middle class and the poor.<br />He should emphasize that the real job creators are not the rich but the vast majority of ordinary Americans whose purchases give businesses reason to add jobs.  And that if most Americans still cannot afford to buy, the government must be the spender of last resort.  Id.</p></blockquote>
<p>Reich goes on to make some specific policy suggestions for acting to reduce inequality.  These include
<ul>
<li>reversing the impact of the reinstatement of the higher Social Security tax rate by exempting the first $20,000 of income from the tax and lifing the ceiling on income subject to it; </li>
<li>reviving government-run work corps, like the WPA and CCC, &#8220;to put the long-term unemployed directly to work&#8221; </li>
<li>raising the minimum wage </li>
<li>imposing a 2% tax surcharge on wealth in excess of $7 billion to be dedicated to education </li>
<li>Cutting corporate and military welfare </li>
<li>not cutting public investments or safety nets </li>
<li>giving tax credits for actual job creation </li>
<li>supporting states that rehire teachers, firefighters police and social workers.  Id. (quoting and paraphrasing).</li>
</ul>
<p>Sounds like a pretty good plan.   As Corak noted (in the <a href="http://economistsview.typepad.com/economistsview/2013/02/there-is-nothing-inevitable-about-low-rates-of-economic-mobility.html">Economist&#8217;s View post </a>cited above):<br />[D]ynamic labor markets offering new opportunities to the population as a whole, progressive public policies of relatively more benefit to the relatively disadvantaged, and strong families with growing incomes and human capital will lead to much more mobility than aristocrats of a pervious era could ever have imagined.</p>
<p>And the Reich plan is certainly better than what most of the GOP-led state experiments like Michigan are coming up with, which read like a plan for even more redistributing upwards to the top few, including:
<ul>
<li>eliminating income taxes in favor of regressive sales taxes, </li>
<li>eliminating business taxes in favor of regressive user fees (a GOP-led Michigan &#8220;upward&#8221; redistribution &#8220;innovation&#8221;), </li>
<li>pushing hard against unions  (a GOP-led Michigan &#8220;innovation&#8221;), </li>
<li>reducing safety net support like Medicaid (being considered in Michigan), </li>
<li>taxing vulnerable seniors on pension income (another of Michigan&#8217;s recent &#8220;innovations&#8221;), </li>
<li>cutting support for state universities while reallocating the support that remains to those that serve the upper class rather than underprivileged who will generally need to borrow more and take longer to succeed (another of Michigan&#8217;s redistributionist efforts).</li>
</ul>
<p>cross posted with <a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/2013/02/the-inequality-gap.html">ataxingmatter</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/the-inequality-gap.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Goggle&#8217;s Bermuda hideaway/HSBC&#8217;s too-big status: time to rein in the corporations!</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/goggles-bermuda-hideawayhsbcs-too-big-status-time-to-rein-in-the-corporations.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/goggles-bermuda-hideawayhsbcs-too-big-status-time-to-rein-in-the-corporations.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 17 Dec 2012 19:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Linda Beale]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[money laundering]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/goggles-bermuda-hideawayhsbcs-too-big-status-time-to-rein-in-the-corporations.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Beale Goggle&#8217;s Bermuda hideaway/HSBC&#8217;s too-big status: time to rein in the corporations! If you are a company that depends on IP for a lot of your revenue, you may be able to avoid considerable taxes by funneling profits from subsidiaries in high-tax countries into a Bermuda shell company.  Google avoided about $2 billion [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Linda Beale</p>
<p>Goggle&#8217;s Bermuda hideaway/HSBC&#8217;s too-big status: time to rein in the corporations!</p>
<p>If you are a company that depends on IP for a lot of your revenue, you may be able to avoid considerable taxes by funneling profits from subsidiaries in high-tax countries into a Bermuda shell company.  Google avoided about $2 billion in worldwide income taxes in 2011 by shifting about 80% of its total pretax profits&#8211; $9.8 billion &#8212; into Bermuda.  See Jesse Drucker, <a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2012-12-10/google-revenues-sheltered-in-no-tax-bermuda-soar-to-10-billion.html">Google Royalties Sheltered in No-Tax Bermuda Soar to Nearly $10 Billion</a>, Bloomberg.com (Dec. 10, 2012).</p>
<p>Meanwhile, the US decided not to take action against HSBC for its fraudulent behavior because it was considered so big that it could damage the financial system (again) to interfere with its continuing corporate existence.  See  Glenn Greenwald,<a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2012/dec/12/hsbc-prosecution-fine-money-laundering">HSBC, too big to jail, is the new poster child for US two-tiered justice system</a>, guaradian.co.uk (Dec. 12, 2012) (noting that <strong>&#8220;one of the world&#8217;s largest banks, HSBC, spent years committing serious crimes, involving money laundering for terrorists; &#8216;facilitating money laundering by Mexican drug cartels&#8217;; and &#8216;moving tainted money for Saudi banks tied to terrorist groups&#8217; &#8221; but US officials decided &#8220;not to prosecute HSBC for accepting the tainted money of rogue states and drug lords on Tuesday, insisting that a $1.9bn fine for a litany of offences was preferable to the &#8216;collateral consequences&#8217; of taking the bank to court&#8221;).</strong><br /><strong></strong><br /><a name="more"></a><strong><br /></strong> Maybe this kind of information will finally incense governments against corporate tax dodging.  What we need are laws that refuse to recognize shell companies set up in tax-haven countries to siphon profits from the countries where they originate.  What we need are fewer possibilities for companies to expand through tax-free mergers and acquisitions that allow them to get so big that they become immune to ruin when they commit major crimes. </p>
<p>cross posted with <a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2012/12/goggles-bermuda-hideawayhsbcs-too-big-status-time-to-rein-in-the-corporations.html">ataxingmatter</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/goggles-bermuda-hideawayhsbcs-too-big-status-time-to-rein-in-the-corporations.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Republican &#034;fiscal cliff&#034; proposal</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/republican-fiscal-cliff-proposal.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/republican-fiscal-cliff-proposal.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 05 Dec 2012 12:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[economic politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fiscal cliff]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linda Beale]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/republican-fiscal-cliff-proposal.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Beale Republican &#8220;fiscal cliff&#8221; proposal House republican leaders have sent a letter to President Obama with their &#8220;fiscal cliff&#8221; proposal, which the Republicans cast as a &#8220;fair middle ground&#8221; and a &#8220;balanced framework for averting the fiscal cliff.&#8221;  Id.  Republicans object that the administrative proposal has is unbalanced, because it has &#8220;four times [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Linda Beale</p>
<p>Republican &#8220;fiscal cliff&#8221; proposal</p>
<p>House republican leaders have sent <a href="http://www.speaker.gov/sites/speaker.house.gov/files/documents/letter_to_wh_121203.pdf">a letter to President Obama </a>with their &#8220;fiscal cliff&#8221; proposal, which the Republicans cast as a &#8220;fair middle ground&#8221; and a &#8220;balanced framework for averting the fiscal cliff.&#8221;  Id.  Republicans object that the administrative proposal has is unbalanced, because it has &#8220;four times as much tax revenue as spending cuts&#8221; (under a Republican claim that the Administration shouldn&#8217;t count already enacted spending cuts that were part of the Administration&#8217;s original proposal as part of the bargain).  And of course the Republicans don&#8217;t like the idea of any stimulus measures being included in the deal or the proposal to finally do away with our arcane and unnecessary debt ceiling mess, which invites games of chicken that have no point.  They claim that they are merely supporting the Bowles-Simpson plan, which of course they are not since they are refusing all tax rate increases.</p>
<p>The letter is written rather confusedly and is therefore somewhat ambiguous on exactly what it is offering as a concrete proposal.  One has to conclude that it isn&#8217;t a concrete proposal but actually merely puffery that restates the position that the GOP wants lots of entitlement cuts, no military cuts, and no tax rate increases (but might go along, maybe, with some unspecified &#8220;loophole eilmination&#8221; for the nonce).  It appears to propose the following:</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<ul>
<li>$900 billion in cuts to mandatory spending including Medicare and Medicaid spending over the next decade 
<ul>
<li>The Republican letter, of course, tries to assume the mantle of &#8220;preserving and protecting&#8221; social welfare programs even while they reach out to reduce, eliminate or privatize them, when it suggests that perhaps the Republicans will return to the Budget Resolution that offered a voucher plan for limiting Medicare benefits (and hoped to buy off current seniors and those nearing retirement by promising them benefits under the current program). The Republican proposal referred to claims to &#8220;reform&#8221; Medicaid by offering &#8220;flexibility&#8221; that cuts $800 billion from the program over 10 years!  Although admitting that the election makes pursuing those kinds of harsh reforms &#8220;counterproductive&#8221;, the Republican leaders promise to &#8220;continue to support and advance them.&#8221; </li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>$300 billion in cuts to other discretionary spending over the next decade </li>
<li>$200 billion in cuts to Social Security benefits (by revising the method of calculating cost of living increases, which would also apply to keep the tax brackets from rising as fast and for adjustments to government pensions) </li>
<li>$800 billion in new revenue&#8211;achieved through &#8220;pro-growth tax reform that closes special-interest loopholes and deductions while lowering rates&#8221; (but of course without mentioning just what loopholes and deductions would be removed).  The letter goes on to declare that the Republican leaders will not agree to higher tax rates, asserting that their position is to &#8220;protect small businesses and our economy&#8221;.</li>
</ul>
<p>Let&#8217;s assess this so-called &#8220;proposal.&#8221; </p>
<p>Lowering rates is absurdity at this point:  no reasonable person should vote for a proposal to lower US tax rates even more than they already are.  Lowering rates while eliminating deductions or loopholes doesn&#8217;t work any better:  immediately after such a bill is passed, the lobbyists will be back on the floor.  First they&#8217;ll demand a temporary extension while markets &#8220;adjust&#8221; (mostly bulls..t).  Then they&#8217;ll demand that the temporary provision be made permanent to provide &#8220;certainty&#8221; to markets and businesses.  Then they&#8217;ll demand enhancement of the loophole to broaden it, since they say such provisions will incentivize job creation. Etc.  This is an old story that never plays out the way the lobbyists promise.  Congress shouldn&#8217;t fall for it again.  Because the next ploy will be&#8211;oh, let&#8217;s broaden the base by removing these new old loopholes and then we can lower rates even more.  The only thing that is likely to happen in this ploy is that the top rates go down for the wealthiest taxpayers, who pay less and less.</p>
<p>Cutting the various safety net programs is equally absurd.  Especially in a time of continuing difficulty, especially for vulnerable populations like the elderly, poor, laborers with inadequate pension and health care possibilities after retirement and other large groups in our population.  There is no reason to cave to the GOP&#8217;s forty-year campaign to reduce, privatize or eliminate social welfare programs:  let the gradual onset of taxes and sequesters take place in January, and then ask them to pass a tax cut to benefit those in the middle and lower-income groups.</p>
<p>The letter ends with an oxymoronic statement that essentially states that if the Obama administration will cave to these GOP demands, they are &#8220;ready and eager to begin discussions about how to stucture these reforms.&#8221;  They go on to suggest that President Obama has taken actions to &#8220;undermine good-fith effrorts to reach a reasonable and equitable agreement.&#8221;</p>
<p>That&#8217;s bunk, boys.  If the GOP is going to play this game this way, the administration should not attempt any kind of short-term resolution.  After the Bush tax cuts are repealed once and for all by operation of existing law as of January 1, it will be much easier to discuss what reasonable tax cuts should be enacted to protect the middle class rather than the wealth of corporate managers and owners.  And once there is a first start on the reduction of the military budget, we can move on to reduce it even more.  Action can be taken to stave off problems that would be caused by any of the provisions in early 2013.</p>
<p>cross posted with <a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2012/12/republican-fiscal-cliff-proposal.html">ataxingmatter</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/republican-fiscal-cliff-proposal.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Links Worth Noting: Stealth (Class) Warfare</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/links-worth-noting-stealth-class-warfare.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/links-worth-noting-stealth-class-warfare.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 02 Dec 2012 14:49:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[economic politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linda Beale]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/links-worth-noting-stealth-class-warfare.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Beale Links Worth Noting: Stealth (Class) Warfare(Op-ed) Paul Krugman, Class Wars of 2012, New York Times (Nov. 30, 2012). When Mitt Romney disparaged ordinary Americans, it was visible, obvious, and clearly an indication of the lack of esteem he held for ordinary Americans. The same arrogance is at work in the class warfare [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Linda Beale</p>
<p>Links Worth Noting: Stealth (Class) Warfare<br />(Op-ed)</p>
<p>Paul Krugman, <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/11/30/opinion/krugman-class-wars-of-2012.html">Class Wars of 2012</a>, New York Times (Nov. 30, 2012).</p>
<p>When Mitt Romney disparaged ordinary Americans, it was visible, obvious, and clearly an indication of the lack of esteem he held for ordinary Americans. The same arrogance is at work in the class warfare that the radical right is waging against the social programs that have been partof the great stabilization of the middle class and a singular pathway to a more sustainable lifestyle for those who are underprivileged in America&#8211;Social Security, Medicare, and Medicaid.</p>
<p>The drumbeat for &#8220;fiscal cliff&#8221; worries continues to build in the media. The right wants us to think that they are worried about future generations facing mountains of debt. They aren&#8217;t. The right wants us to think that they are worried that the only way to combat skyrocketing health care costs is by cutting back on benefits for ordinary Americans. They aren&#8217;t, and it isn&#8217;t. The right wants us to think that the wealthy have sacrificed already and are truly noble if they bear even minimal tax increases from the expiration of the Bush tax cuts. They haven&#8217;t and they aren&#8217;t. The right wants the progressives to roll over and play dead, so they can insist that they have the good of the country at heart when they demand cuts to infrastructure spending and cuts to &#8220;entitlements&#8221; as a condition for petty little increases in the taxes of the ultra rich who have greedily sucked up all the juice in the economy for forty years. We won&#8217;t.</p>
<p>Readers may think this blog has become a broken record of arguments for higher taxes&#8211;at least on the wealthy, at least through the removal of the preferential capital gains rate&#8211;and holding firm on protecting Social Security, Medicare, Medicaid. Maybe so. But we must continue to speak out until those we elected to lead the country act like they heard the prevailing sentiment of the election: we want more taxes on the upper class; we want an economy that is stimulated by government spending when private spending won&#8217;t do it; we want a sustainable economy that distributes resources more equitably and not a winner-take-all economy that allows those with monetary power to dictate the lifestyles of the rest of us.</p>
<p>Krugman is, as usual, correct. What they can&#8217;t get by buying an election the rich will try to get by lobbying and pretending to worry about the fiscal cliff. Let them try. Progressives in Congress should start talking, on any available outlet, about &#8220;going over the cliff&#8221; because it really isn&#8217;t so bad. It will free us once and for all of the ridiculous Bush tax cuts and allow us to undertake thinking about the tax code without that &#8220;status quo&#8221; hanging over our head like the sword of Damocles. And we can pass some really decent tax cuts for the lower income quintiles at the first of the year, without having to deal yet again with the &#8220;extenders&#8221; on the table. We can reform corporate tax&#8211;getting rid of loopholes; getting rid of the transfer pricing games&#8211;without lowering rates. And we can deal with the sequester in reasonable ways. What should we spend on and why. Let the rest go. We would finally begin the process of lowering the expectations of the military-industrial complex.</p>
<p>The following are excerpts from Krugman&#8217;s piece.</p>
<blockquote><p>The important thing to understand now is that while the election is over, the class war isn’t. The same people who bet big on Mr. Romney, and lost, are now trying to win by stealth — in the name of fiscal responsibility — the ground they failed to gain in an open election.<br />***<br />Consider, as a prime example, the push to raise the retirement age, the age of eligibility for Medicare, or both. This is only reasonable, we’re told — after all, life expectancy has risen, so shouldn’t we all retire later? In reality, however, it would be a hugely regressive policy change, imposing severe burdens on lower- and middle-income Americans while barely affecting the wealthy. Why? First of all, the increase in life expectancy is concentrated among the affluent; why should janitors have to retire later because lawyers are living longer? Second, both Social Security and Medicare are much more important, relative to income, to less-affluent Americans, so delaying their availability would be a far more severe hit to ordinary families than to the top 1 percent.<br />***<br />[A]ny proposal to avoid a rate increase is, whatever its proponents may say, a proposal that we let the 1 percent off the hook and shift the burden, one way or another, to the middle class or the poor.<br />***<br />The point is that the class war is still on, this time with an added dose of deception. And this, in turn, means that you need to look very closely at any proposals coming from the usual suspects, even — or rather especially — if the proposal is being represented as a bipartisan, common-sense solution. In particular, whenever some deficit-scold group talks about “shared sacrifice,” you need to ask, sacrifice relative to what?<br />***<br />America’s top-down class warriors lost big in the election, but now they’re trying to use the pretense of concern about the deficit to snatch victory from the jaws of defeat. Let’s not let them pull it off.</p></blockquote>
<p>cross posted with <a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2012/11/113012-links-worth-noting-stealth-class-warfare.html" title="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2012/11/113012-links-worth-noting-stealth-class-warfare.html">ataxingmatter</a>   11/30/12</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/links-worth-noting-stealth-class-warfare.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Media&#8217;s Role in Driving the &#034;Fiscal Cliff&#034; Imagery</title>
		<link>./../../2012/11/the-medias-role-in-driving-the-fiscal-cliff-imagery.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/11/the-medias-role-in-driving-the-fiscal-cliff-imagery.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 26 Nov 2012 11:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[fiscal cliff]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Fiscal policy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Fiscal Responsibility]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linda Beale]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/11/the-medias-role-in-driving-the-fiscal-cliff-imagery.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Beale The Media&#8217;s Role in Driving the &#8220;Fiscal Cliff&#8221; Imagery The mainstream media has been fed a steady diet of releases from interested parties (like right-leaning propaganda tanks) about the need to adopt austerity measures, often cast as needing to save the country from out-of-control spending and unprecedented deficits and debt. At the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Linda Beale</p>
<p>The Media&#8217;s Role in Driving the &#8220;Fiscal Cliff&#8221; Imagery</p>
<p>The mainstream media has been fed a steady diet of releases from interested parties (like right-leaning propaganda tanks) about the need to adopt austerity measures, often cast as needing to save the country from out-of-control spending and unprecedented deficits and debt. </p>
<p>At the same time, the mainstream media has generally given up investigative journalism to engage in sports-like &#8220;he said-she said&#8221; journalism:  it treats most fiscal issues as a contest between left-leaning and right-leaning groups to be described by each side&#8217;s post position&#8211;i.e., as a merit-based race between equally valid positions.  Without the investigative wherewithal for in-depth research, there&#8217;s much less information about whether and how the facts may support one side and not the other. </p>
<p>We see it on climate change, where a scientific consensus is treated as just another opinion contrasted with the wishful opinions of anti-environmental corporatists.  We see it on evolution, where belief-based creationism is taught in schools alongside fact-supported scientific theory, with the two sides reported in the news as though they represent equally valid educational positions.   </p>
<p>It shouldn&#8217;t be surprising, therefore, that this approach surfaces in spades when it comes to the so-called &#8220;fiscal cliff&#8221;. </p>
<p>One is hard pressed to find articles that give credence to the position of progressives on Social Security (it is not bankrupt), Medicare (we can solve the long-term problem of financing of reasonable universal health care without cutting benefits by learning from the facts and experiences about controlling medical care costs through single-payer systems like those adopted in every other advanced nation), or even taxes.  The possibility of using the end-of-year changes as a fresh-start, &#8220;sweep the house clean&#8221; foundation for immediate action early in the new term is often ignored and, if mentioned, is generally given short shrift and inadequate explanation. </p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>It&#8217;s easy, though, to find forecasts of return to recession outcomes if the sequester and end of the Bush tax cuts are allowed to take place as currently enacted.<br />   <br />Take, for example, the rhetoric of Mark Johnson in a KTVB.com report, <a href="http://www.ktvb.com/news/The-Fiscal-Cliff-and-its-potential-effect-on-Idahoans-179899411.html">A Fiscal Cliff primer</a> (Nov. 18, 2012, updated Nov. 19).<br />If Congress cannot come up with an agreement on the Simpson-Bowles ratification, and then cannot come up [with] enough compromises to pass a plan of their own, and the President refuses to extend the current January 1st deadline, it&#8217;s over the cliff for Uncle Sam.<br />And, straight into the tax increases, unemployment jump, deep federal cuts and probable recession; A rough landing for the country and a scenario neither side wants.</p>
<p>The article adds to the crisis drumroll by quoting political scientist David Adler.<br />
<blockquote>&#8220;And all the progress that Idaho families made in getting out of the recession will have gone by the wayside if in fact America&#8217;s politicians in Washington are not able to put our fiscal house in order.&#8221; Id.</p></blockquote>
<p>In a similar vein, <strong>Jonathan Weisman in the New York Times</strong> reports today that &#8220;negotiators&#8221; have agreed on the parameters for a deal in which they will agree on fixed amounts of revenue to be raised (without tax rates increasing) and fixed amounts of cuts to social programs (and other federal programs like farm subsidies).  Jonathan Weisman, Seeking Ways to Raise Taxes but Leave Tax Rate as is: Negotiators Float Ideas to Appease Both Parties, New York Times (Nov. 23, 2012), at A12. </p>
<blockquote><p>The article contains a good bit of information (or speculation, it isn&#8217;t completely clear) about what &#8220;negotiators&#8221; are considering in order to &#8220;pacify&#8221; the Republicans without permitting tax rate increases.  There&#8217;s no specific source attribution other than to &#8220;&#8221;aides involved in the negotiations&#8221; and a &#8220;Republican aide involved in the current talks.&#8221;  Id.  Predictably, it also includes a description of the slated legislative changes as a &#8220;crisis&#8221; when the &#8220;&#8216;fiscal cliff&#8217; would squeeze hundreds of billions of dollars out of the fragile economy next year and, many economists say, send the country back into recession&#8221;.  Id. </p></blockquote>
<p>There&#8217;s not a single hint that it may not really be a &#8220;cliff&#8221;.  That it merely cuts back INCREASES in military spending.  That the sequester, with its cuts to the military, leaves the government with more options for funding NEEDED stimulus spending.  That Congress has all the power it needs to undo any truly harmful components of the sequester.  That Congress can instead consider targeted cuts to lower-income taxpayers to prevent a renewal downward recession trend.  That Congress can instead target spending cuts (and spending) on stimulation of the economy.  That Congress, in other words, has it in its power to help lower-income taxpayers pay for needed consumption and thus to create tax cuts and controlled spending cuts to benefit the lower and lower-middle income classes whose consumption is most needed to drive economic growth.</p>
<p>A little better is Evan Soltas, <a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2012-11-19/a-gentler-slope-for-the-fiscal-cliff.html">A Gentler Slope for the &#8216;Fiscal Cliff&#8217;</a>, Bloomberg.com (Nov. 19, 2012), in which he admits the siren-call of the term to journalists.</p>
<p>The vivid imagery and false urgency of the [fiscal cliff] term transformed budget arcana into a national Wile E. Coyote moment. The words lent themselves to media overexposure and political opportunism. Despite efforts by <a href="http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/45755883/ns/msnbc-the_last_word/#49753971">Chris Hayes</a>, <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/wonkblog/wp/2012/11/13/the-fiscal-cliff-the-austerity-crisis/">Ezra Klein</a> and<a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/wonkblog/wp/2012/11/09/the-fiscal-cliff-is-an-austerity-crisis/"> Suzy Khimm</a> to rebrand it the “fiscal curb” or “austerity crisis” &#8212; either of which would be more consistent with reality &#8212; Bernanke&#8217;s original phrasing has held fast.  Id.<br />Soltas at least explores the benefit of avoiding drastic austerity measures and even considering an &#8220;alternate&#8221; path of increasing the tax take beyond the &#8220;historic&#8221; measures of 18-19% of GDP.  Remember, we are currently at all-time lows in the perecentage of GDP taken in federal taxes, due especially to the enormously preferential rates to the super-elite through taxation of capital gains, dividends and private equity compensation (that is, &#8220;carried interest&#8221;) at less than half the top rate on ordinary compensation.</p>
<p>A reasonable solution might be a combination of spending cuts and revenue increases which stabilizes both at 18 or 19 percent of gross domestic product. That would be in line with their 50-year historical average. Increases or decreases beyond this level demand larger arguments about the proper size and role of government.</p>
<p>Alternatively, one could contend that demographic shifts &#8212; namely, the growing elderly fraction of the population &#8212; or rising health care costs justify greater public resources without any moral claims about government’s proper size. There is merit to this argument, but it neglects the revenue side of the historical consensus on the taxes paid to the federal government.<br />The relevance of any &#8220;historical consensus&#8221; on the percent of GDP that should be paid to the federal government, however, is questionable.  The times are extraordinarily different, with the years of low tax intake from the Reagan tax cuts through the Bush tax cuts, coupled with the unprecedented problem of the Bush preemptive wars being fought without the historical use of wartime increases in tax cuts (especially on the rich) to pay for them.<br />Maybe one of the better articles is a pre-election discussion at Fidelity.com on the &#8220;<a href="https://www.fidelity.com/viewpoints/market-and-economic-insights/fiscal-cliffhanger">Fiscal Cliffhanger</a>&#8220;, Sept. 26, 2012.  Here at least there is a good graphic demonstrating just how significant the Bush-era tax cuts are in our deficit problem ($221 billion) and how little the cut to support for Medicare payments to providers is ($11 billion).  Perhaps this kind of graphic can get the upper-middle class Americans to consider their fair-share obligation. (That means couples, like most professionals such as myself, who make more than $100,000 a year but less than the $250,000 or more a year that Obama has taken as his targeted income level for reintroducting pre-Bush era taxes.)  Further, the article acknowledges that gridlock in the lame duck is quite possible, but goes on to note that there will likely be a resolution&#8211;with compromise on both sides&#8211;early in 2013.<br />Many progressives&#8211;in which group I include myself&#8211; do think that a clean sweep start to the new session could allow Congress to act more reasonably on our long-term fiscal needs without compromising measures needed to continue moving us out of the Bush recession.  <br />Once the Bush tax cuts are gone and the sequester starting to take effect, Congress could  enact piecemeal legislation.  It could pass new, better targeted tax cuts for the lower-middle and lower income distribution.  Hopefully Obama, now in office and not needing to protect his electoral future, will recognize the reasonableness of allowing some tax increases to take place in four-or five- years for those couples in the $100,000 to $250,000 taxable income set.  <br />Once the sequester is starting to roll in, Congress could move to reinstate public pension support.  It could consider long-term support for Medicare through gradual adoption of a single-payer, Medicare-for-all system that meets the real needs of the future rather than using an artificially created fiscal crisis to destroy the New Deal programs.  It could accept the sequester&#8217;s limited spending increases for the military.  It could even finally act to reduce the tax-and-spending subsidies for Big Banks (get rid of the active financing exception to Subpart F), Big Pharmacy and Big IT (legislate new international tax rules that undo the tax evasion that current  &#8220;affiliated sales&#8221; of intellectual property permits while reining in the ability of MNEs to locate their profits in offshore tax havens with sophisticated tax planning like the &#8220;Dutch sandwich&#8221; techniques), and Big Oil and Big Agribusiness (outright subsidies built into well-lobbied tax and spending provisions).   <br /><a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2012/11/media-role-in-driving-the-fiscal-cliff.html" title="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2012/11/media-role-in-driving-the-fiscal-cliff.html">http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2012/11/media-role-in-driving-the-fiscal-cliff.html</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/11/the-medias-role-in-driving-the-fiscal-cliff-imagery.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>1/24/12 Links worth noting: Germany rejects Swiss banking secrecy deal; Labor Devaluation</title>
		<link>./../../2012/11/12412-links-worth-noting-germany-rejects-swiss-banking-secrecy-deal-labor-devaluation.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/11/12412-links-worth-noting-germany-rejects-swiss-banking-secrecy-deal-labor-devaluation.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2012 13:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[labor economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[labor markets]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linda Beale]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[links worth noting]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/11/12412-links-worth-noting-germany-rejects-swiss-banking-secrecy-deal-labor-devaluation.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[1/24/12  Links worth noting by Linda Beale: Germany rejects Swiss banking secrecy deal;   Labor Devaluation  David Jolly, German Lawmakers Reject Swiss Tax Deal, New York Times (Nov. 23, 2012).The US and other countries like Germany have been pressing the Swiss on their bank secrecy, which allows U.S. and other foreign citizens to establish bank accounts without [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>1/24/12  Links worth noting by Linda Beale:</p>
<p> Germany rejects Swiss banking secrecy deal;   Labor Devaluation </p>
<p> David Jolly, <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/11/24/business/global/german-lawmakers-reject-swiss-tax-deal.html">German Lawmakers Reject Swiss Tax Deal</a>, New York Times (Nov. 23, 2012).<br />The US and other countries like Germany have been pressing the Swiss on their bank secrecy, which allows U.S. and other foreign citizens to establish bank accounts without the knowledge of the home country and thus hide assets and income from home-country taxation.  The US passed laws (called by the acronym &#8220;FATCA&#8221;) that require foreign banks to actively report information on US accountholders.   The hope is that every country will recognize the harm done to tax systems by banking secrecy and join in imposing similar information-reporting requirements. </p>
<p>The Swiss, meanwhile, have been trying to circumvent universal adoption of such laws.  See, e.g., Nicholas Shaxson, <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2012/nov/22/scheme-trillions-tax-havens-scuppered">A scheme designed to net trillions from tax haves is being scuppered</a>, Guardian.com (Nov. 22, 2012).   Britain, Luxemburg and Austria are cited as being in the forefront of the scuttling movement:  Britain, for example, has entered into a &#8220;Rubrik Agreement&#8221; with the Swiss.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>The Swiss thought they had a deal with Germany.  This would be a bilateral deal in which the Swiss agree to an upfront payment in lieu of any back taxes on the accounts and then agree to act as tax collector for the foreign government on the accounts, thus maintaining secret the identity of the foreign taxpayers. <br />Such an agreement is problematic for two reasons:  (i) it requires the foreign government to trust the Swiss banks to pay the right amount over in taxes and (ii) it undermines the drive to eliminate offshore banking secrecy as a cover for tax evasion. </p>
<p>Transparency in international banking and taxation matters would require that banks provide information on accounts held by foreigners to the foreigners&#8217; home jurisdictions, without any account-specific or accountholder-specific request required.  The reason for a more transparent rule is that otherwise the home jurisdiction has to have information it does not have (who has an account at a Swiss bank) before it can ask for the information it needs to ferret out who has such an account and may be engaging in tax evasion.  The biggest cracks in banking secrecy have thus come from  whistleblowers and opportunists who sell account-holder information to purchasing jurisdictions. </p>
<p>Friday, the Germans rejected&#8211;for now at least&#8211;a German-Swiss deal supported by Chancellor Merkel that had been two years in the making.  France is apparently also considering rethinking a similar deal.<br />The Swiss leverage was clearly stated by Swiss banking official Mario Tuor, who &#8220;<i>noted that without a deal, the status quo would remain: German officials can seek specific information from the Swiss government on people suspected of tax evasion, or go back to buying data stolen from Swiss banks. &#8216;With an agreement, every German taxpayer in Switzerland would be taxed</i>,&#8217; Mr. Tuor said.&#8221; <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/11/24/business/global/german-lawmakers-reject-swiss-tax-deal.html">German Lawmakers Reject Swiss Tax Deal</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.twohalfhitches.blogspot.com/2012/02/steady-devaluation-of-human-labor.html">The Steady Devaluation of Labor</a>, Two Half Hitches (Feb. 2012).</p>
<p>This is an oldie but goodie, one worth reminding you of (or calling to your attention for the first time).<br />[The] minimum wage, in constant dollars, has had its ups and downs since 1970 but the overall trend indicated by the straight black line is down. The numbers show that the American economy puts less value on the entry level worker than it did in 1970. Why is that? Are minimum wage workers less intelligent now than they were forty years ago? Are they lazier?</p>
<p>The reason probably has a lot to do with the rise of the global economy and cheaper Chinese labor. It may also have to do with basic attitudes toward labor. <a href="http://politicalcorrection.org/blog/201106020015">Some see labor as a commodity</a>, while <a href="http://www.inthesetimes.com/working/entry/7239/labor_is_not_a_commodity/">others believe it is not.  </a></p>
<p>***<br />Representative <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_King">Steve King (R-IA)</a> on the floor of the House of Representatives last year: </p>
<p><strong>&#8220;Labor is a commodity just like corn or beans or oil or gold, and the value of it needs to be determined by the competition, supply and demand in the workplace.&#8221;</strong><br /><strong></strong><br /><strong>***</strong><strong> </strong><br /><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samuel_Gompers">Samuel Gompers</a>, cigar maker-turned-labor organizer and founder of the American Federation of Labor in the early 20th Century, had a different business ethic related to labor and said this:<br /><strong><br /></strong> <strong>“You cannot weigh the human soul in the same scales with a piece of pork.”</strong><br /><strong><br /></strong> Labor advocates actually managed to insert a statement affirming the status of human labor in the 1914 <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clayton_Act">Clayton Antitrust Act</a>:  <strong>“The labor of a human being is not a commodity or article of commerce.”</strong></p>
<p>cross posted with <a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2012/11/112412-links-worth-noting.html">ataxingmatter</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/11/12412-links-worth-noting-germany-rejects-swiss-banking-secrecy-deal-labor-devaluation.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
