<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>chained cpi &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Social Security and the current fad of being balanced and comprehensive</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/social-security-and-the-current-fad-of-being-balanced-and-comprehensive.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/social-security-and-the-current-fad-of-being-balanced-and-comprehensive.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2012 17:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Bruce Webb (Social Security)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[chained cpi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Democratic Party]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fiscal cliff]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Republican Party]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security for the young]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/social-security-and-the-current-fad-of-being-balanced-and-comprehensive.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Salon writer  Natasha Lennard reports that a sticking point around Social Security stalled &#8216;fiscal cliff&#8217; back and forth rejoinders between the two parties, but also points out that the topic continues to be on the table (and has been offered by President Obama before these talks a couple years ago).   Notice both parties using the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.salon.com/2012/12/30/gop_demands_social_security_cuts_setting_back_fiscal_talks/" target="_blank">Salon writer</a>  Natasha Lennard reports that a sticking point around Social Security stalled &#8216;fiscal cliff&#8217; back and forth rejoinders between the two parties, but also points out that the topic continues to be on the table (and has been offered by President Obama before these talks a couple years ago).   Notice both parties using the same language of &#8220;<i>part of a balanced, comprehensive agreement</i>&#8221; as the fix is in without looking at other parts of the budget&#8230;these back and forth sallies are bi-partisan in appearance, but do not address the current version of &#8216;fical cliff&#8217; responsibilities.
<p>A free gift to the political players and the cover of the moment, a matter not even related to current fiscal responsibility, nor to the real world impact it has on poverty and seniors, nor the carefully thought out and responsible plans offered to address real issues.</p>
<blockquote><p>In what Democratic aides told reporters was a “major setback” in fiscal cliff negotiations, Republicans proposed throwing a Social Security cut into the scaled-back deal Congress is attempting to cobble together in advance of the New Year deadline. As things stand at the time of writing, negotiations are close to breakdown.
<p>Aides to Republican Senate Minority Leader Mitch McConnell presented the Social Security proposal, which included a method of calculating benefits with inflation. The plan would lower cost of living increases for Social Security recipients. Democrats were swift to reject the offer.</p>
<p>A Democratic aide told <a href="http://abcnews.go.com/Politics/OTUS/fiscal-cliff-talks-hit-major-setback-social-security/story?id=18095739&#038;page=2#.UOCptLamAeM">ABC News</a> that the proposal was a “poisoned pill” in the current negotiations. However, it should be noted that President Obama has suggested a similar proposal within the context of negotiations on a broad deficit-reduction deal. Such a measure had been taken off the table in discussions over a scaled-back, short-term agreement.</p>
<p>Senate Majority Leader Harry Reid said on the Senate floor Sunday, “We’re willing to make difficult concessions as part of a balanced, comprehensive agreement but we’ll not agree to cut social security benefits as part of a small or short-term agreement, especially if that agreement gives more handouts to the rich.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>How do I know this?  Well, it is worth the time to follow posts at <i>Angry Bear </i> over the next few months, and to compare the analysis to your own understandings.  Bruce Webb will be writing with updated numbers, a must to understand the words others are using, and to gain further understanding of the big numbers used to argue political points of view.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/social-security-and-the-current-fad-of-being-balanced-and-comprehensive.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
