<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>SCOTUSblog &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 15:57:33 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Tom Goldstein of SCOTUSblog tweets, during the short break after the first hour of argument in the California Prop 8 case, that …</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/tom-goldstein-of-scotusblog-tweets-during-the-short-break-after-the-first-hour-of-argument-in-the-california-prop-8-case-that.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/tom-goldstein-of-scotusblog-tweets-during-the-short-break-after-the-first-hour-of-argument-in-the-california-prop-8-case-that.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 15:18:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Defense of Marriage Act (DOMA); California's Proposition 8]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Roberts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lyle Denniston]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Reuters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SCOTUSblog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the Supreme Court; Tom Goldstein]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/tom-goldstein-of-scotusblog-tweets-during-the-short-break-after-the-first-hour-of-argument-in-the-california-prop-8-case-that.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Breaking: 1st update- #prop8 unlikely to be upheld; either struck down or #scotus won’t decide case. More in 30 mins. This is the more important of the two gay-marriage cases.  Tomorrow’s argument will be on the constitutionality of the federal Defense of Marriage Act (DOMA), but almost no one (best as I can tell), thinks [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr"></div>
<div dir="ltr"><a href="https://twitter.com/SCOTUSblog/status/316560034295324672">Breaking</a>: 1st update-<a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23prop8&#038;src=hash"> #prop8</a> unlikely to be upheld; either struck down or<a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23scotus&#038;src=hash"> #scotus</a> won’t decide case. More in 30 mins.</div>
<div dir="ltr">This is the more important of the two gay-marriage cases.  Tomorrow’s argument will be on the constitutionality of the federal Defense of Marriage Act (DOMA), but almost no one (best as I can tell), thinks the Court will uphold the constitutionality of that Act.  The real suspense* is in the Prop 8 case.  So …. </p>
<p>UPDATE: <a href="http://www.scotusblog.com/2013/03/the-proposition-8-oral-argument/">Here&#8217;s</a> Tom Goldstein&#8217;s post-argument report. </p>
<p>SECOND UPDATE:  <a href="http://newsandinsight.thomsonreuters.com/Legal/News/2013/03_-_March/Supreme_Court_raises_doubts_on_California_marriage_case/">This one&#8217;s</a> from Reuters.  It seems to me that the Roberts comment quoted in the article is very significant.  In a good way.</p>
<p>THIRD (and final, for at least a few hours) UPDATE: <a href="http://www.scotusblog.com/2013/03/argument-recap-on-marriage-kennedy-in-control/">Here’s</a> SCOTUSblog’s Lyle Denniston’s take.  He’s my (and many, many others’) go-to guy on all things Supreme. He seems to think that they’ll simply dismiss the Supreme Court case, saying that the petition grant was “improvidently granted,” leaving the Ninth Circuit opinion intact. </p>
<div dir="ltr">That would leave intact the Ninth Circuit ruling&#8211;which was that, because California already had been allowing same-sex marriage before Prop. 8 was approved in 2006, in localities that approved it, the state could not suddenly render those marriages null and void.  Doing so would violate the Fourteenth Amendment’s Due Process clause.  And since some gays already were allowed to be married, and their marriages would continue to be recognized by the state, refusing to allow other gays to marry would violate the Fourteenth Amendment’s Equal Protection clause. That’s the ruling that would remain in effect if the Supreme Court rules that the Prop. 8 petitioners have no legal standing to be a party to the case.  </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">That now seems more likely to me than the other option that would allow them to avoid deciding on whether same-sex marriage is a constitutional right.  That other option would be to rule that “the petitioners”&#8211;the group that earlier asked the Ninth Circuit, and then asked the Supreme Court, to “vacate” the lower-court rulings and uphold the constitutionality of Prop. 8&#8211;don’t have “standing” to be a party to the lawsuit, because they would have no injury from a court ruling striking down Prop. 8 that is sufficiently direct and significant to meet the Article III standing requirement.  </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">If they go the “no standing” route, that would leave intact not the Ninth Circuit ruling based on narrow grounds but instead the lower, trial-court judge’s ruling, which was based on much broader grounds.  The effect would be somewhat, but not entirely the same, whichever of these two options they choose. </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">As I understand it, if they choose the option that leaves the Ninth Circuit opinion in place, that would mean that localities in California would have the option to allow same-sex marriage but would  not be required to allow it, although all government entities throughout the state would have to recognize any same-sex marriage as legal. If they instead choose the option that vacates the Ninth Circuit opinion and restores the lower, trial-court ruling, by ruling that the petitioners have, and had, no legal standing to appeal from the trial-court ruling either in the Ninth Circuit Court of Appeals or in the Supreme Court, that would mean that, for now, in central California, within the trial-court level federal court district where the case was filed and where the trial-court ruling was issued, Prop. 8 would be invalid and all localities within that court district would be required to allow same-sex marriage. </p>
</div>
<p>&#8212;- </p>
<p>*Originally, I used the word &#8220;action,&#8221; but changed it to &#8220;suspense&#8221; because if the Court strikes down DOMA as unconstitutional, that would be big, important action. I really meant &#8220;suspense,&#8221; because I do think the striking of DOMA is highly likely; not much suspense on that.  But tomorrow&#8217;s argument will give some hint about whether I&#8217;m right.</p></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/tom-goldstein-of-scotusblog-tweets-during-the-short-break-after-the-first-hour-of-argument-in-the-california-prop-8-case-that.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Scotusblog&#8217;s Wednesday roundup links Angry Bear</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/scotusblogs-wednesday-roundup-links-angry-bear.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/scotusblogs-wednesday-roundup-links-angry-bear.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 26 Jul 2012 02:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Beverly Mann (Supreme court)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SCOTUSblog]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/scotusblogs-wednesday-roundup-links-angry-bear.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Another recognition for Angry Bear contributors comes in the form of Scotusblog Wednesday roundup: You may have heard of Scotusblog because of the coverage of Supreme Court&#8217;s decision on court challenges to parts of Obamacare. Beverly Mann, having begun to write for Angry Bear as an added subject which I believed to be an increasingly [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Another recognition for Angry Bear contributors comes in the form of Scotusblog Wednesday roundup:</p>
<p>You may have heard of <i>Scotusblog</i> because of the coverage of Supreme Court&#8217;s decision on court challenges to parts of Obamacare. Beverly Mann, having begun to write for <i>Angry Bear</i> as an added subject which I believed to be an increasingly important impact on policy decisions, again makes it to recommended links to read.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.scotusblog.com/2012/07/wednesday-round-up-144/#more-149651" target="_blank">Wed roundup at Scotusblog</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p>Jess Bravin of the Wall Street Journal reviews the latest book by Justice Antonin Scalia and Bryan Garner. Coinciding with the book’s release, Justice Scalia recently sat for interviews with CNN (which Beverly Mann discusses at <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/07/did-scalia-pointedly-hint-at-major.html" target="_blank">the blog Angry Bear</a>) and NPR’s Nina Totenberg.</p></blockquote>
<p>(bolding mine)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/scotusblogs-wednesday-roundup-links-angry-bear.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The difference between Social Security/Medicare and Medicaid under the Spending Clause, in light of the ACA opinion</title>
		<link>./../../2012/06/the-difference-between-social-securitymedicare-and-medicaid-under-the-spending-clause-in-light-of-the-aca-opinion.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/06/the-difference-between-social-securitymedicare-and-medicaid-under-the-spending-clause-in-light-of-the-aca-opinion.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2012 19:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[ACA litigation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lyle Denniston]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obamacare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SCOTUSblog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Supreme court]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tom Goldstein]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/06/the-difference-between-social-securitymedicare-and-medicaid-under-the-spending-clause-in-light-of-the-aca-opinion.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[While the Court’s upholding the mandate is deservedly taking front stage in the media coverage, the Court’s decision to strike down a part of the Medicaid expansion may ultimately have broader jurisdprudential consequence.  That, at least, will be a subject of debate among lawyers and academics in the days and weeks to come.  This is [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>While the Court’s upholding the mandate is deservedly taking front stage in the media coverage, the Court’s decision to strike down a part of the Medicaid expansion may ultimately have broader jurisdprudential consequence.  That, at least, will be a subject of debate among lawyers and academics in the days and weeks to come.  This is the first time (as far as I know) that the Court has actually found a Spending Clause condition unconstitutionally coercive.  Whether it establishes principles that make many other programs vulnerable is a question that will require further analysis and debate.  Lyle Dennisten will start that analysis in an post later today or tomorrow morning.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212; Kevin Russell, <i><a href="http://www.scotusblog.com/2012/06/medicare-holding-may-have-broad-implications/">Medicaid holding may have broadimplications</a></i>, SCOTUSblog
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I one of the many updates to my initial post this morning, mentioned this exchange between Lyle Denniston and Tom Goldstein (SCOTUSblog’s publisher:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Lyle: The rejection of the Commerce Clause and Nec. and Proper Clause should be understood as a major blow to Congress&#8217;s authority to pass social welfare laws. Using the tax code &#8212; especially in the current political environment &#8212; to promote social welfare is going to be a very chancy proposition.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Tom: I dissent from Lyle&#8217;s view that the Commerce Clause ruling is a major blow to social welfare legislation. I think that piece of the decision will be read pretty narrowly.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div> I wrote:
</p>
</div>
<div>I’m almost always in agreement with Lyle’s analyses (as is, I’m sure, Tom Goldstein, who is the blog’s publisher and also a major Supreme Court litigator; Amy Howe, also a lawyer, is Goldstein’s wife).  But, like Goldstein, I disagree with Lyle on this one.  In order for the Court to interpret this opinion as limiting Congress’s authority to enact social welfare legislation, the Court would have to place in question a slew of current, longstanding social welfare programs.  I don’t think that was Roberts’ intent—really, I don’t—and I don’t think the opinion will be viewed that way.  Unless, of course, Romney wins and appoints a wingnut to replace, say, Ginsburg if her health does not hold out.  </p>
</div>
<div>
<div>Here’s what I think will happen: </p>
<p><a name="more"></a>But first, I need to point out that Medicaid, unlike Social Security and Medicare, are programs structured as partnerships between the respective states and the federal government, each paying some portion of the cost, and that Medicaid has always contained a provision that makes state participation voluntary and that allows states to remove themselves from the program if they want to.  Social Security and Medicare, by contrast, are solely federally-funded and federally-run programs. </div>
<div></div>
<div>The 26 states that challenged the ACA’s Medicaid provision argued that a provision in the Medicaid section of the ACA allows the federal government to withdraw all federal funds for a state’s entire Medicaid program—that is, the money it already is receiving—if a state opts out of the Medicaid-expansion part of the ACA.  The states argued that this was too coercive and therefore violates principles of state sovereignty.  Seven justices—the four dissenters, Roberts, Breyer and Kagan—agreed with that claim, and so they ruled that, while the federal government can put conditions on its funding of the new expansion, and can withdraw the money for that expansion if a state doesn’t comply with the conditions, the federal government <i>can’t</i>withdraw funding also for the earlier parts of Medicaid that the state already was receiving.</div>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Sooo …. this ruling certainly (in my opinion) appears to have no effect whatsoever on any program funded entirely through, and administered by, the federal government.  And i tappears to have no effect on any social welfare program that is a partnership between states and the federal government as long as there is no threat by the federal government to withdraw funds already being given to the state for something else, in order to get the state to agree to participate in the new partnership, or in the new part of the part of the partnership.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I just don’t see how this restricts in any significant way Congress’s ability to enact social welfare programs.  I think that ruling is really very narrow.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>As an aside, I want to mention the four dissents who wanted to strike down the entire ACA tried to at least persuade Roberts that the entire Medicaid-expansion part of the statute simply because that one provision in that part of the Act was ruled unconstitutional—even though, as Roberts points out, the Act includes what’s known as a “severability” provision providing that if any particular section of the Act is ruled unconstitutional, the section should be severed from the remainder of the statute, and the remainder should remain in force.  This let’s-see-if-we-can-get-the-tail-to-wag-the-dog-and-win-on-this-part-at-least tack of the minority was so transparently inappropriate that Roberts, in responding to it in his opinion, seems downright offended by it.  Good for him.  
</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/06/the-difference-between-social-securitymedicare-and-medicaid-under-the-spending-clause-in-light-of-the-aca-opinion.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>From SCOTUSblog: The individual mandate survives as a tax. OH. MY. GOD!!!! &#8212; REPEATEDLY UPDATED (seven updates so far)</title>
		<link>./../../2012/06/from-scotusblog-the-individual-mandate-survives-as-a-tax-oh-my-god-repeatedly-updated-seven-updates-so-far.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/06/from-scotusblog-the-individual-mandate-survives-as-a-tax-oh-my-god-repeatedly-updated-seven-updates-so-far.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2012 14:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[ACA litigation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obamacare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SCOTUSblog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Supreme court]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/06/from-scotusblog-the-individual-mandate-survives-as-a-tax-oh-my-god-repeatedly-updated-seven-updates-so-far.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[UPDATE: From SCOTUSblog: &#8220;The bottom line: the entire ACA is upheld, with the exception that the federal government&#8217;s power to terminate states&#8217; Medicaid funds is narrowly read.&#8221; TOTAL, TOTAL VICTORY   !!!! SECOND UPDATE: The opinion is 5-4, with Roberts voting with the Dem appointees and writing the opinion, and Kennedy writing the main dissent. Here’s [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>UPDATE: From SCOTUSblog: &#8220;The bottom line: the entire ACA is upheld, with the exception that the federal government&#8217;s power to terminate states&#8217; Medicaid funds is narrowly read.&#8221;</p>
<p>TOTAL, TOTAL VICTORY   !!!!
<div></div>
<div>SECOND UPDATE: The opinion is 5-4, with Roberts voting with the Dem appointees and writing the opinion, and Kennedy writing the main dissent.
</p>
</div>
<div><a name="more"></a></div>
<div>Here’s more from SCOTUSblog:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The money quote from the section on the mandate: Our precedent demonstrates that Congress had the power to impose the exaction in Section 5000A under the taxing power, and that Section 5000A need not be read to do more than impose a tax. This is sufficient to sustain it.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The court reinforces that individuals can simply refuse to pay the tax and not comply with the mandate.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8220;Nothing in our opinion precludes Congress from offering funds under the ACA to expand the availability of health care, and requiring that states accepting such funds comply with the conditions on their use. What Congress is not free to do is to penalize States that choose not to participate in that new program by taking away their existing Medicaid funding.&#8221; (p. 55)</p>
</div>
<div>
<div>And (added after second update was posted):
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Another way to think about Medicaid: the Constitution requires that states have a choice about whether to participate in the expansion of eligibility; if they decide not to, they can continue to receive funds for the rest of the program.</div>
<p>The most talked-about part surely will be “individuals can simply refuse to pay the tax and not comply with the mandate” part.  Is it really a mandate at all if there’s no penalty for refusal to comply?  So maybe it&#8217;s not a total victory, after all.  But it&#8217;s still a big, big victory.  
</p>
<p>(The Medicaid part of the ruling has no effect on the breadth or implementation of the law at all.)</p>
<div>THIRD UPDATE:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Correction from SCOTUSblog (and HT to buffpilot in the comment to my post):
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Apologies &#8211; you can&#8217;t refuse to pay the tax; typo. The only effect of not complying with the mandate is that you pay the tax.  </p>
<p>Looks like everything revolves on it being a tax.  
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Ah-hah!! It IS a TOTAL, TOTAL victory.  !!!</p>
<div>FOURTH UPDATE:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Again from SCOTUSblog:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>In Plain English: The Affordable Care Act, including its individual mandate that virtually all Americans buy health insurance, is constitutional. There were not five votes to uphold it on the ground that Congress could use its power to regulate commerce between the states to require everyone to buy health insurance. However, five Justices agreed that the penalty that someone must pay if he refuses to buy insurance is a kind of tax that Congress can impose using its taxing power. That is all that matters. Because the mandate survives, the Court did not need to decide what other parts of the statute were constitutional, except for a provision that required states to comply with new eligibility requirements for Medicaid or risk losing their funding. On that question, the Court held that the provision is constitutional as long as states would only lose new funds if they didn&#8217;t comply with the new requirements, rather than all of their funding.  
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>
<p>Yup. Total, total victory.  </p>
</p>
<p>
<div>FIFTH UPDATE:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>From SCOTUSblog:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The Court holds that the mandate violates the Commerce Clause, but that doesn&#8217;t matter b/c there are five votes for the mandate to be constitutional under the taxing power.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Well, kudos, to … um … me.  I called it pretty nearly spot-on.  I began to sort of wonder in the last few days whether in fact I really was onto something, because my post from June 15 laying that out (again) kept getting more and more “hits” as the days went by.  Usually my posts stop getting “hits” a few days after I post them.  I actually began (almost) thinking it was possible that a few people from within the Court itself—i.e., law clerks to the justices—were clicking the post after possibly being told of it by someone who reads, maybe, Business Insider.  If so, that would seem to indicate that I actually had called it right.  But I dared not <i>really</i> think that Supreme Court law clerks were reading my post.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Btw, in a comment to a blog conversation on Slate on Monday, I wrote:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Hmm.  Well, having gone out on a limb 10 days ago on a blog I write for, posting an article that discusses as one of the more likely possible healthcare-case results the tax-law outcome that Savage suggests in his LA Times article today, I’m feeling ever-so-slightly less lonely out on that tree branch.  At least now I’ll have someone to cling to on Thursday as the limb falls to the ground. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The blog conversation is ongoing there.  The current latest entry (from last night) is <a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/the_breakfast_table/features/2012/_supreme_court_year_in_review/supreme_court_year_in_review_who_lost_obamacare_the_leading_suspects_are_the_solicitor_general_the_white_house_liberal_law_professors_and_five_supreme_court_justices_.html">here</a>, should any AB readers be interested. </div>
</div>
<div>SIXTH UPDATE:
</p>
</div>
<div>Salvaging the idea that Congress did have the power to try to expand health care to virtually all Americans, the Supreme Court on Monday upheld the constitutionality of the crucial – and most controversial — feature of the Affordable Care Act.   By a vote of 5-4, however, the Court did not sustain it as a command for Americans to buy insurance, but as a tax if they don’t.  That is the way Chief Justice John G. Roberts, Jr., was willing to vote for it, and his view prevailed.  The other Justices split 4-4, with four wanting to uphold it as a mandate, and four opposed to it in any form.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Since President Obama signed the new law, it has been understood by almost everyone that the expansion of health care coverage to tens of millions of Americans without it could work — economically — only if the health insurance companies were guaranteed a large pool of customers.   The mandate to buy health insurance by 2014 was the method Congress chose to supply that pool.   It is not immediately clear whether the Court’s approach will produce as large a pool of new customers.   The ACA’s key provision now amounts to an invitation to buy insurance, rather than an order to do so, with a not-very-big tax penalty for going without.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212; <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/business/economy/for-scotusblog-one-goal-beat-everybody-and-break-news-of-health-care-ruling/2012/06/27/gJQA1TZp7V_story.html">Lyle Denniston</a>, “<a href="http://www.scotusblog.com/2012/06/dont-call-it-a-mandate-its-a-tax/">Don’t call it a mandate — it’s a tax</a>,” SCOTUSblog
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Those are the first two paragraphs of Lyle’s (I love him, and can refer to him by his first name if I want to) three-paragraph initial article on the regular blog (as opposed to the live blog).  He’s sure to post updates to the article later today.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Earlier, on the live blog, Amy Howe wrote:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Take a quick look at Footnote 11, which is on page 44 of the slip opinion: Those subject to the individual mandate may lawfully forgo health insurance and pay higher taxes, or buy health insurance and pay lower taxes. The only thing that they may not lawfully do is not buy health insurance and not pay the resulting tax.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And for those of you who remember my writing about an obscure court-jurisdiction statute called the Anti-Injunction Act, which was a subject of controversy in the case, Lyle, writing earlier on the live blog, wrote:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Interesting, at least to scholars, that while the mandate and its attached penalty are a tax for purposes of its constitutionality, but not for the Anti-Injunction Act. If it were a tax for AIA purposes, this case would not have been decided re the mandate.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Also on the live blog, Lyle wrote:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The rejection of the Commerce Clause and Nec. and Proper Clause should be understood as a major blow to Congress&#8217;s authority to pass social welfare laws. Using the tax code &#8212; especially in the current political environment &#8212; to promote social welfare is going to be a very chancy proposition.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Tom Goldstein then wrote:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I dissent from Lyle&#8217;s view that the Commerce Clause ruling is a major blow to social welfare legislation. I think that piece of the decision will be read pretty narrowly.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I’m almost always in agreement with Lyle’s analyses (as is, I’m sure, Tom Goldstein, who is the blog’s publisher and also a major Supreme Court litigator; Amy Howe, also a lawyer, is Goldstein’s wife).  But, like Goldstein, I disagree with Lyle on this one.  In order for the Court to interpret this opinion as limiting Congress’s authority to enact social welfare legislation, the Court would have to place in question a slew of current, longstanding social welfare programs.  I don’t think that was Roberts’ intent—really, I don’t—and I don’t think the opinion will be viewed that way.  Unless, of course, Romney wins and appoints a wingnut to replace, say, Ginsburg if her health does not hold out.  
</p>
</div>
<div>SEVENTH (Yikes!) UPDATE:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>This one’s not from SCOTUSblog.  It’s from Ginsburg’s concurrence, joined by Breyer, Sotomayor and Kagan:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>At bottom, THE  CHIEF  JUSTICE’s and the joint dissenters’ “view that an individual cannot be subject to Commerce Clause regulation absent voluntary, affirmative acts that enter him or her into, or affect, the interstate market expresses a concern for individual liberty that [is] more redolent of Due Process Clause arguments.”  SevenSky, 661 F. 3d, at 19.  See also  Troxel v.  Granville, 530 U. S. 57, 65 (2000) (plurality opinion) (“The [Due Process] Clause also includes a substantive component that provides heightened protection against government interference with certain fundamental rights and liberty interests.” (internal quotation marks omitted)).  Plaintiffs have abandoned any argument pinned to substantive due process, however, see 648 F. 3d 1235, 1291, n. 93 (CA11 2011), and now concede that the provisions here at issue do not offend the Due Process Clause.8
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Footnote 8 says:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>8. Some adherents to the joint dissent have questioned the existence of substantive due process rights.  See McDonald v.  Chicago, 561 U. S. ___, ___ (2010) (THOMAS, J., concurring) (slip op., at 7) (The notion that the Due Process Clause “could define the substance of th[e] righ[t to liberty] strains credulity.”); Albright v. Oliver, 510 U. S. 266, 275 (1994) (SCALIA, J., concurring) (“I reject the proposition that the Due Process Clause guarantees certain (unspecified) liberties[.]”).  Given these Justices’ reluctance to interpret the Due Process Clause as guaranteeing liberty interests, their willingness to plant such protections in the Commerce Clause is striking.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The <i>SevenSky</i> opinion, <i>SevenSky v. Holder</i>, that Ginsburg quotes from was written last November by Lawrence Silberman, a Reagan appointee to the federal Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia, and one of the most respected (in conservative legal circles) federal appellate judges, in one of the ACA cases. As for Ginsburg’s footnote 8, she says something I’ve wondered about all along: Substantive due process is legal doctrine under which <i>Roe v. Wade</i>and, before that, the opinion striking down  a Connecticut law that prohibited the sale and use of contraceptives, were based.  <i>Lawrence v. Texas</i>, the 2003 Kennedy opinion invalidating Texas’s sodomy statute also was based on that doctrine.  Thomas and Scalia routinely lambaste the doctrine, as do many other tea partier folks. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>So the question is: Do these people now concede the appropriateness of the legal doctrine underlying those cases they hate so much?
</p>
</div>
<p></div>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/06/from-scotusblog-the-individual-mandate-survives-as-a-tax-oh-my-god-repeatedly-updated-seven-updates-so-far.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>UPDATE On Kiobel v. Royal Dutch Petroleum. And How It Could Impact ‘Court-Stripping’ Jurisprudence.*</title>
		<link>./../../2012/03/update-on-kiobel-v-royal-dutch-petroleum-and-how-it-could-impact-court-stripping-jurisprudence.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/03/update-on-kiobel-v-royal-dutch-petroleum-and-how-it-could-impact-court-stripping-jurisprudence.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 09 Mar 2012 02:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Alien Tort Statute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Beverly Mann]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[court-stripping]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kiobel v. Royal Dutch Petroleum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lyle Denniston]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SCOTUSblog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Supreme court]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/03/update-on-kiobel-v-royal-dutch-petroleum-and-how-it-could-impact-court-stripping-jurisprudence.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Last Wednesday, the day after oral argument at the Supreme Court in a case called Kiobel v. Royal Dutch Petroleum, both Linda and I posted about the case.  Linda’s post I believe was written shortly before the argument although posted afterward.  Mine was written after the argument and discussed news reports about what occurred.  The [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>Last Wednesday, the day after oral argument at the Supreme Court in a case called <i>Kiobel v. Royal Dutch Petroleum</i>, both Linda and I posted about the case.  Linda’s post I believe was written shortly before the argument although posted afterward.  Mine was written after the argument and discussed news reports about what occurred.  The title of Linda’s post was “<a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/02/supreme-court-corporate-monsters-if.html">The Supreme Court&#8217;s corporate monsters&#8211;if money buys them &#8220;free speech&#8221; rights, can it help them avoid giving others human rights?</a>” The title of mine was “<a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/02/international-law-as-established-at.html">International Law, As Established At Nuremberg*: The ACTUAL Grounds On Which the Supreme Court Will Rule For Shell Oil’s Parent Company In<i> Kiobel v. Royal Dutch Petroleum</i></a>.”  (I added the asterisk and the related footnote later that night, to make clear that the part of the title that preceded the colon was intended as a sarcastic reference to a statement made by the oil company’s counsel during oral argument, a statement I discussed in the post.)
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>To refresh your memory—it was barely more than a week ago, but in the intervening time, we’ve all been somewhat distracted by more important things, such as whether slightly-increased private healthcare premiums caused by the inclusion of contraceptives coverage really is public welfare paid by “taxpayers” and therefore women who receive the benefit are prostitutes—my post began by explaining the supposed issue in the case.  I wrote:<br /><a name="more"></a></div>
<div>In her post earlier today on <i>Kiobel v. Royal Dutch Petroleum</i>, the sort-of-<i>Citizens</i>&#8211;<i>United</i>-like case argued yesterday in the Supreme Court, Linda discusses the issue that was supposed to be the one that the Court would decide, because, well, that was the issue that the lower appellate court, the Second Circuit Court of Appeals, decided.  The issue is whether under the Alien Tort Statute, which was enacted in 1789 and allows “aliens” to file civil lawsuits in the U.S. for violations of the “law of nations,” allows aliens to sue <i>corporations</i>, or instead only individuals, for violations of human rights as defined under clearly-established international law.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The Second Circuit court said it doesn’t, and, as the excerpt from that opinion that Linda posts shows, the appellate panel used as its justification the judges’ own moral judgment that since individuals (i.e., the corporation’s top executives) make the corporate decisions to leverage the corporation’s resources to accomplish these heinous acts, only those individuals, and not the ill-used corporation itself, should be suable.  And that therefore, only those individuals, and not the ill-used corporation itself, <i>will</i> be suable in U. S. federal courts under the ATS.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>This notwithstanding that the statute itself says nothing at all about <i>who</i> can be sued under it; it states only what acts the actor can be sued <i>for</i>.  And notwithstanding that the Second Circuit panel’s stated grounds for the ruling, if not necessarily the result (the dismissal of the lawsuit), conflict with the Supreme Court’s ruling two years ago in <i>Citizens United v. FEC</i>.  Which parlayed the First Amendment free-speech right of individuals into a right of corporate CEOs to leverage those rights of its individual human shareholders into a First Amendment speech right of the CEO to use corporate funds to advance his or her political preferences.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I noted that Anthony Kennedy, author of the <i>Citizens United</i> opinion, reportedly indicated that he agreed with the oil company’s statement in its brief that international law does not recognize corporate liability.  Case closed, as far as he was concerned.  But several of the justices disagreed—most emphatically Stephen Breyer and Elena Kagan, but Alito seemed to, too. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>But I went on to say that I expected from what transpired that the Court wouldn’t decide that issue at all and would instead decide the case on entirely separate grounds asserted by Samuel Alito during the argument but not addressed earlier in the case.  Alito questioned whether the statute applies as against <i>anyone</i>, corporation or individual, when, as in that case, the acts alleged occurred outside the United States, by someone or some entity not based in the United States, against people who have no connection to the United States.  I predicted that a majority led by Alito would say it does not.</p>
<p>It now looks like I was right.</p></div>
</p>
<p>
<div>On Monday afternoon, the Court issued a surprise order in the case, asking that the parties brief the following issue:</div>
<div>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Whether and under what circumstances the Alien Tort Statute, 28 U.S.C. § 1350, allows courts to recognize a cause of action for violations of the law of nations occurring within the territory of a sovereign other than the United States.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The briefing won’t be completed until June 29, and so the Court will decide the case next term, not during the term that ends by July 1. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The defendant in <i>Kiobel</i> did not claim that the statute provides federal-court jurisdiction (the legal authority to hear the case) only for cases alleging violations of international law that occurred within the United States—probably because the words of the statute suggest otherwise, and because in a 2004 case filed under that statute, in which the acts at issue occurred outside the United States , the Supreme Court gave no indication that it does.  But as SCOTUSblog’s<a href="http://www.scotusblog.com/2012/03/kiobel-to-be-reargued/"> Lyle Denniston noted</a>, the defendant in another current ATS case does.  That defendant lost in the appellate court, and filed a petition asking the Supreme Court to consider the issue in that case.  The justices considered the petition last Friday and took no action on that petition.  Instead, they inserted the issue into <i>Kiobel</i>, in an order described variously by commenters as surprising, unusual, and <a href="http://newsandinsight.thomsonreuters.com/Legal/News/2012/03_-_March/SCOTUS__Should_U_S__courts_police_international_human_rights_/">stunning</a>. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The injection of this issue into <i>Kiobel</i> enables the justices to avoid ruling on whether the statute, enacted the same year that the Constitution was ratified, applies only to allow suits against individuals and not against violations corporations under whose auspices the human rights violations occurred. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The one-sentence statute says: “The district courts shall have original jurisdiction of any civil action by an alien for a tort only, committed in violation of the law of nations or a treaty of the United States.”  The law of nations does not allow corporations to have atrocities committed under their auspices, whatever yoga-like linguistics contortions Justice Kennedy’s mind or law clerks performed that caused him to suggest otherwise at the argument.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>But neither do the statute’s words suggest that it does not apply to (as the Court put it in its briefing order) violations of the law of nations occurring within the territory of a sovereign other than the United States.  If the statute adopts international law only to identify what <i>torts</i>—what <i>actions</i>—can be the subject of a suit in the country, and not to identify who (or what) can be sued, then it shouldn’t matter that (according to Kennedy at oral argument, quoting from a brief supporting the oil company) this country appears to be the only one in the world to “exercise universal civil jurisdiction over alleged extraterritorial human rights abuses to which the nation has no connection.”  But it will, although possibly circuitously.</div>
<div>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>“What business does a case like this have in the courts of the United States?” Alito asked.  None, a majority of the Court is likely to say, and not because the defendant is a corporation but instead because the atrocities alleged occurred in Nigeria rather than in the United States.  But since the statute itself doesn’t say that, the majority of justices will have to either interpret it as implying that it does or say that the statute must be interpreted in that matter in order to avoid striking it down as unconstitutional, because (they’ll say) Congress lacks the authority to give the federal courts jurisdiction to hear cases about wrongs committed outside the territorial United States. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Which would be a novel ruling, but one that, as Denniston points out, Alito seemed to suggest by asking: “Is there an Article III source of jurisdiction for a lawsuit like this?…What’s the constitutional basis for a lawsuit like this, where an alien is suing an alien?” 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Article III is the section of the Constitution that created the judicial branch.  It’s also the part of the Constitution that says that Congress, which Article I created, has the authority to grant the federal courts jurisdiction (legal authority) to hear certain types of cases.*  In enacting the ATS, Congress granted the federal district courts the authority to hear “any civil action by an alien for a tort only, committed in violation of the law of nations or a treaty of the United States.”
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>But there are other parts of the Constitution—the Bill of Rights; the Fourteenth Amendment (due process, equal protection of the law); the prohibition against suspension of the right to habeas corpus and against <i>ex post facto</i> laws and bills of attainder (protections included in the original Constitution)—that appear to require access to federal court in order to challenge, whether or not Congress provides for it. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>There are other parts of the Constitution, such as Article II, which created the executive branch, that may limit Congress’s authority to create federal-court jurisdiction.  This is what Alito appears to have in mind.*
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And conversely, there are other parts of the Constitution—the Bill of Rights; the Fourteenth Amendment (due process, equal protection of the law); the prohibition against suspension of the right to habeas corpus and against <i>ex post facto</i> laws and bills of attainder (protections included in the original Constitution)—that appear to require access to federal court in order to challenge, whether or not Congress provides for it. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Or at least it would seem so.  The political right is incessantly trying to remove federal-court jurisdiction to hear cases that they claim violate states’ rights to violate individuals’ rights—a tactic called “court-stripping.”  And one that, with the aggressive assistance of the current Supreme Court, has been phenomenally successful in effectively suspending (read: eliminating) the right of federal-court habeas corpus review by persons convicted of crimes in state court. “Phenomenally” is no overstatement, either.  It’s truly a phenomenon, and one that needs its own post.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Court-stripping and the reverse—I’ll call it court-mandating—are issues that the Supreme Court normally avoids like the plague, best as I can tell.  But if nothing else good comes from <i>Kiobel</i>—and it certainly looks like nothing else will—a Supreme Court acknowledgment that there are constitutional limits to Congress’s authority to determine federal-court jurisdiction might be the consolation prize.  But only if that limitation is viewed as a two-way street.
</p>
<p>*<i>This post originally referred to Article I (establishing Congress) as Article II, and referred to Article II (establishing the executive branch) as Article I.  Ooops.</i></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/03/update-on-kiobel-v-royal-dutch-petroleum-and-how-it-could-impact-court-stripping-jurisprudence.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
