<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Koch brothers &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The Road to Serfdom!!</title>
		<link>./../../2011/09/the-road-to-serfdom.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/09/the-road-to-serfdom.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2011 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[hayek]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Koch brothers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[libertarian]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medicare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/09/the-road-to-serfdom.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Brad DeLong points us to a post from The Nation on early Koch brothers and Hayek The Road to Serfdom!! Yasha Levine and Mark Ames: Charles Koch to Friedrich Hayek: Use Social Security!: [I]n early June 1973, weeks after [Charles] Koch was appointed president of the Institute for Humane Studies. Along with his brothers, Koch [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Brad DeLong points us to a post from The Nation on early Koch brothers and Hayek <a target="_blank" href="http://delong.typepad.com/sdj/2011/09/the-road-to-serfdom.html">The Road to Serfdom!!</a></p>
<p><a target="_blank" href="http://www.thenation.com/article/163672/charles-koch-friedrich-hayek-use-social-security?utm_source=dlvr.it&#038;utm_medium=twitter&#038;page=full">Yasha Levine and Mark Ames</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>Charles Koch to Friedrich Hayek: Use Social Security!: [I]n early June 1973, weeks after [Charles] Koch was appointed president of the Institute for Humane Studies. Along with his brothers, Koch inherited his father’s privately held oil company in 1967…. Koch invited Hayek to serve as the institute’s “distinguished senior scholar” in preparation for its first conference on Austrian economics, to be held in June 1974.</p>
<p>Hayek initially declined Koch’s offer. In a letter to IHS secretary Kenneth Templeton Jr., dated June 16, 1973, Hayek explains that he underwent gall bladder surgery in Austria earlier that year, which only heightened his fear of “the problems (and costs) of falling ill away from home.” (Thanks to waves of progressive reforms, postwar Austria had near universal healthcare and robust social insurance plans that Hayek would have been eligible for.)<br /><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>IHS vice president George Pearson (who later became a top Koch Industries executive) responded three weeks later, conceding that it was all but impossible to arrange affordable private medical insurance for Hayek in the United States. However, thanks to research by Yale Brozen, a libertarian economist at the University of Chicago, Pearson happily reported that “social security was passed at the University of Chicago while you [Hayek] were there in 1951. You had an option of being in the program. If you so elected at that time, you may be entitled to coverage now.”</p>
<p>A few weeks later, the institute reported the good news: Professor Hayek had indeed opted into Social Security while he was teaching at Chicago…. He was eligible…. On August 10, 1973, Koch wrote a letter appealing to Hayek to accept a shorter stay at the IHS, hard-selling Hayek on Social Security’s retirement benefits, which Koch encouraged Hayek to draw on even outside America. He also assured Hayek that Medicare, which had been created in 1965 by the Social Security amendments as part of Lyndon Johnson’s Great Society programs, would cover his medical needs…. [T]aking on the unlikely role of Social Security Administration customer service rep, Koch adds, “In order to be eligible for medical coverage you must apply during the registration period which is anytime from January 1 to March 31. For your further information, I am enclosing a pamphlet on Social Security.”</p></blockquote>
<p>(h/t Mike Kimel)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/09/the-road-to-serfdom.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Florida State University and Koch Brothers&#8230;significant or not?</title>
		<link>./../../2011/05/florida-state-university-and-koch-brothers-significant-or-not.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/05/florida-state-university-and-koch-brothers-significant-or-not.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2011 08:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Koch brothers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[public school funding]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/05/florida-state-university-and-koch-brothers-significant-or-not.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Via Alternet and the St. Petersberg Times: A foundation bankrolled by Libertarian businessman Charles G. Koch has pledged $1.5 million for positions in Florida State University&#8217;s economics department. In return, his representatives get to screen and sign off on any hires for a new program promoting &#8220;political economy and free enterprise.&#8221; The agreement is here. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Via <a target="_blank" href="http://www.alternet.org/story/150892/koch_brother_buys_professors_at_public_university_to_spread_free_market_propaganda_--_is_public_education_the_kochs%27_next_front?akid=6947.29972.7TTkss&#038;rd=1&#038;t=12">Alternet</a> and the <a target="_blank" href="http://www.tampabay.com/news/business/billionaires-role-in-hiring-decisions-at-florida-state-university-raises/1168680">St. Petersberg Times</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>A foundation bankrolled by Libertarian businessman Charles G. Koch has pledged $1.5 million for positions in Florida State University&#8217;s economics department. In return, his representatives get to screen and sign off on any hires for a new program promoting &#8220;political economy and free enterprise.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>The agreement is <a target="_blank" href="http://www.tampabay.com/specials/2011/PDFs/fsucontract.pdf">here</a>.</p>
<p><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-bSfk28GxGTo/TcpJ2M5I2NI/AAAAAAAAAnA/BqTKwC6gH7E/s1600/Capture.JPG"><img border="0" alt="" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-bSfk28GxGTo/TcpJ2M5I2NI/AAAAAAAAAnA/BqTKwC6gH7E/s400/Capture.JPG"></a></p>
<p>Since readers include university professors, what is the deal? What is usual or setting a new bar for funding in a public institution?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/05/florida-state-university-and-koch-brothers-significant-or-not.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Wisconsin, fiscal responsibility, and power (plants?)</title>
		<link>./../../2011/02/wisconsin-fiscal-responsibility-and-power-plants.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/02/wisconsin-fiscal-responsibility-and-power-plants.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Feb 2011 13:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Koch brothers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[labor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wisconsin]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/02/wisconsin-fiscal-responsibility-and-power-plants.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Have you heard about 16.896? &#8220;&#8230;with or without solicitation of bids, for any amount that the department determines to be in the best interest of the state.&#8221; Who knew behind the scenes it was also power plants? From rortybomb at the link above: The fight in Wisconsin is over Governor Walker’s 144-page Budget Repair Bill. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a target="_blank" href="http://rortybomb.wordpress.com/2011/02/21/the-less-discussed-part-of-walkers-wisconsin-plan-no-bid-energy-assets-firesales/">Have you heard about 16.896?</a>   <br />&#8220;&#8230;with or without solicitation of bids, for any amount that the department determines to be in the best interest of the state.&#8221;  Who knew behind the scenes it was also power plants? From <strong>rortybomb</strong> at the link above:</p>
<blockquote><p>The fight in Wisconsin is over <a target="_blank" href="http://legis.wisconsin.gov/2011/data/JR1SB-11.pdf">Governor Walker’s 144-page Budget Repair Bill</a>. The parts everyone is focusing on have to do with the right to collectively bargain being stripped from public sector unions (except for the unions that <a target="_blank" href="http://voices.washingtonpost.com/postpartisan/2011/02/scrooge-ism_in_wisconsin_part.html?hpid=opinionsbox1">supported Walker running for Governor</a>). Focusing on this misses a large part of what the bill would do. Check out this language, from the same bill (my bold):</p>
<p><strong>16.896</strong> Sale or contractual operation of state−owned heating, cooling, and power plants. (1) Notwithstanding ss. 13.48 (14) (am) and 16.705 (1), the department may sell any state−owned heating, cooling, and power plant or may contract with a private entity for the operation of any such plant, <strong>with or without solicitation of bids, for any amount that the department determines to be in the best interest of the state</strong>. Notwithstanding ss. 196.49 and 196.80, no approval or certification of the public service commission is necessary for a public utility to purchase, or contract for the operation of, such a plant, and <strong>any such purchase is considered to be in the public interest and to comply with the criteria for certification of a project under s. 196.49 (3) (b).</strong></p></blockquote>
<p>(Update:  Dan here&#8230;see also <a target="_blank" href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2011/02/krugman-on-union-busting.html">Linda Beale&#8217;s post</a> on the same issue via Mark Thoma.  <a target="_blank" href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2011/02/wisconsins-walker-joins-government-asset-giveaway-club-and-is-rahm-soon-to-follow.html">Yves Smith</a> adds her comments.)<br /><a name="more"></a></p>
<blockquote><p>The bill would allow for the selling of state-owned heating/cooling/power plants without bids. This excellent catch is from <a target="_blank" href="http://www.ginandtacos.com/2011/02/21/stand-and-deliver/">Ed at ginandtacos.com</a> (who, speaking of Madison, took me to the Essen Haus on my 21st birthday, where the night began to go sideways). Ed correctly notes:</p>
<p>&#8220;If this isn’t the best summary of the goals of modern conservatism, I don’t know what is. It’s like a highlight reel of all of the tomahawk dunks of neo-Gilded Age corporatism: privatization, no-bid contracts, deregulation, and naked cronyism. Extra bonus points for the explicit effort to <strong>legally redefine </strong>the term “public interest” as “whatever the energy industry lobbyists we appoint to these unelected bureaucratic positions say it is.”</p>
<p><strong>&#8230;</strong></p>
<p>It’s important to think of this battle as a larger one over the role of the state. The attempt to break labor is part of the same continuous motion as saying that the crony, corporatist selling of state utilities to the Koch brothers and other energy interests is the new “public interest.” </p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/02/wisconsin-fiscal-responsibility-and-power-plants.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
