<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>cash for clunkers &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Evaluating Cash for Clunkers: The Case of the Missing Denominator</title>
		<link>./../../2009/11/evaluating-cash-for-clunkers-the-case-of-the-missing-denominator.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/11/evaluating-cash-for-clunkers-the-case-of-the-missing-denominator.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2009 13:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Auto bailout]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cash for clunkers]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/11/evaluating-cash-for-clunkers-the-case-of-the-missing-denominator.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Tom Bozzo An AP story (via Felix Salmon) based on an analysis of &#8220;Cash for Clunkers&#8221; transactions is circulating with the non-news that a number of the transactions involved trades of gas-guzzling trucks for only modestely less gas-guzzling trucks. Here&#8217;s the lede: The most common deals under the government&#8217;s $3 billion Cash for Clunkers [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Tom Bozzo</p>
<p>An AP story (via <a href="http://blogs.reuters.com/felix-salmon/2009/11/09/cash-for-clunkers-datapoint-of-the-day/">Felix Salmon</a>) based on an analysis of &#8220;Cash for Clunkers&#8221; transactions is circulating with the non-news that a number of the transactions involved trades of gas-guzzling trucks for only modestely less gas-guzzling trucks.  Here&#8217;s the lede:<br />
<blockquote>The most common deals under the government&#8217;s $3 billion Cash for Clunkers program, aimed at putting more fuel-efficient cars on the road, replaced old Ford or Chevrolet pickups with new ones that got only marginally better gas mileage, according to an analysis of new federal data by The Associated Press&#8230;</p>
<p>The single most common swap — which occurred more than 8,200 times — involved Ford F-150 pickup owners who&#8230; trade[d] their old trucks for new Ford F-150s. They were 17 times more likely to buy a new F-150 than, say, a Toyota Prius&#8230;.</p></blockquote>
<p>Whoa now.  It isn&#8217;t until the 6th paragraph that readers are told the analysis involves more than 677,000 transactions, so the most common swap accounts for just 1.2 percent of cash-for-clunkers transactions.  The seventh paragraph finally deigns to mention the average fuel economy statistics: 15.8 mpg for the traded clunkers, 24.9 mpg for the purchased vehicles — if you invert the mpgs, that&#8217;s a 36.5% reduction in fuel consumption at the means.</p>
<p>Salmon for whatever reason reckons this makes cash-for-clunkers the administration&#8217;s worst policy initiative yet, which brings a <a href="http://blog.internetnews.com/apatrizio/orly_owl.html">lolcritter</a> to mind.  Even William Buiter granted in an <a href="http://blogs.ft.com/maverecon/2009/03/please-torch-my-car/">otherwise cranky post </a>that, under conditions clearly met by the program (i.e. a temporary incentive that&#8217;s big enough),  the programs  are &#8220;bound to work&#8221; as Keynesian stimulus which arguably the administration hasn&#8217;t pursued in sufficient quantity.  [*]</p>
<p>More below the jump.</p>
<p>None of this is news because the ability to trade old trucks for slightly more fuel-efficient new trucks was a widely reported feature of the enacted program design, which was biased towards the stimulus end of things, given the truck-heavy product lines of the domestic three.  Participants could get $3,500 for a 1 mpg improvement in a light truck-for-light truck trade.   Still, program participants generally used the credits for something better than 2 mpg improvements.  Here&#8217;s the full distribution of differences between the old- and new-vehicle MPGs as reported in the CARS public transaction database:</p>
<p>mileage_diff |      Freq.     Percent        Cum.<br />&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;+&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8211;<br />        -3 |          4        0.00        0.00<br />        -2 |          5        0.00        0.00<br />        -1 |         20        0.00        0.00<br />         0 |        116        0.02        0.02<br />         1 |      9,961        1.49        1.51<br />         2 |     37,486        5.61        7.12<br />         3 |     31,130        4.66       11.78<br />         4 |     36,584        5.47       17.25<br />         5 |     50,526        7.56       24.81<br />         6 |     56,730        8.49       33.30<br />         7 |     50,187        7.51       40.80<br />         8 |     49,397        7.39       48.19<br />         9 |     41,127        6.15       54.35<br />        10 |     62,020        9.28       63.62<br />        11 |     71,757       10.74       74.36<br />        12 |     47,101        7.05       81.41<br />        13 |     38,482        5.76       87.16<br />        14 |     26,377        3.95       91.11<br />        15 |     16,205        2.42       93.53<br />        16 |     10,801        1.62       95.15<br />        17 |      5,433        0.81       95.96<br />        18 |      3,019        0.45       96.41<br />        19 |      1,478        0.22       96.63<br />        20 |        896        0.13       96.77<br />        21 |      1,530        0.23       97.00<br />        22 |        475        0.07       97.07<br />        23 |      1,576        0.24       97.30<br />        24 |      1,016        0.15       97.46<br />        25 |        870        0.13       97.59<br />        26 |        717        0.11       97.69<br />        27 |        361        0.05       97.75<br />        28 |        333        0.05       97.80<br />        29 |        141        0.02       97.82<br />        30 |         95        0.01       97.83<br />        31 |         64        0.01       97.84<br />        32 |      5,504        0.82       98.67<br />        33 |      1,965        0.29       98.96<br />        34 |      2,401        0.36       99.32<br />        35 |      2,276        0.34       99.66<br />        36 |      1,223        0.18       99.84<br />        37 |        680        0.10       99.94<br />        38 |        303        0.05       99.99<br />        39 |         60        0.01      100.00<br />        40 |          7        0.00      100.00<br />&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;+&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8211;<br />     Total |    668,439      100.00</p>
<p>The distribution is a bit bimodal, with peaks at 6 and 11 mpg improvements; the latter is the most common swap in mpg improvement terms, or to borrow the AP article&#8217;s reporting style, that&#8217;s around 9 times more common than F-150 for F-150 trades.  Fuel economy improvements of more than 30 mpg over the trade-in vehicle (roughly, trading a very large truck for a Prius) are more common than F-150 for F-150 trades.  The 1 mpg minimum improvement likewise was not overly common at 1.51 percent of transactions.<br />﻿﻿<br />In addition, fuel consumption reductions and stimulus aren&#8217;t the only potential benefits from the program.  While current emissions regulations hold light trucks to the same standard as cars for regulated pollutants (as of 2009, in fact, though notably not [yet] including carbon dioxide), trucks previously were allowed to meet lower emissions standards.  All cars and light trucks have been held to higher standards since the mid-1990s as <a href="http://www.epa.gov/air/caa/caaa_overview.html#titleII">stricter emissions regulations</a> have phased in.  Indeed, as the following table shows, fully 30 percent of trades predate the 1994 start of the phase-in for the Tier 1 emissions regulations.  New <a href="http://www.epa.gov/tier2/basicinfo.htm">Tier 2</a> vehicles are much cleaner than pre-MY2003 vehicles, which account for 99 percent of Clunkers trades.</p>
<p>Trade_in_Year |      Freq.     Percent        Cum.<br />&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;+&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8211;<br />      1984 |      1,835        0.27        0.27<br />      1985 |      9,703        1.43        1.70<br />      1986 |     10,771        1.59        3.29<br />      1987 |     12,171        1.80        5.09<br />      1988 |     18,537        2.74        7.83<br />      1989 |     23,826        3.52       11.35<br />      1990 |     23,993        3.54       14.89<br />      1991 |     28,036        4.14       19.03<br />      1992 |     32,248        4.76       23.80<br />      1993 |     41,652        6.15       29.95<br />      1994 |     57,145        8.44       38.39<br />      1995 |     66,363        9.80       48.19<br />      1996 |     61,430        9.07       57.26<br />      1997 |     65,955        9.74       67.00<br />      1998 |     65,876        9.73       76.73<br />      1999 |     62,441        9.22       85.95<br />      2000 |     43,758        6.46       92.42<br />      2001 |     29,183        4.31       96.73<br />      2002 |     16,114        2.38       99.11<br />      2003 |      4,472        0.66       99.77<br />      2004 |      1,226        0.18       99.95<br />      2005 |        254        0.04       99.99<br />      2006 |         52        0.01       99.99<br />      2007 |         23        0.00      100.00<br />      2008 |         17        0.00      100.00<br />&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;+&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8211;<br />     Total |    677,081      100.00</p>
<p>There&#8217;s also a cautionary lesson in here investigating large databases.  In a 677,000-record dataset, there will be hundreds or thousands of errors unless the data are meticulously cleaned.  The AP report takes note of the 145 transactions listed above where the mileage of the trade was no worse than that of the new vehicle, which could indicate frauds against the program if correct.  Among the putative horror stories:<br />
<blockquote>A driver in Negaunee, Mich., traded a 1987 Suburban that got 18 mpg for $3,500 toward a new Silverado pickup that got only 15 mpg. An Indianapolis driver traded a 1985 Mercedes 190 that got 27 mpg for $3,500 toward a new Volkswagen Rabbit that got only 24 mpg.</p></blockquote>
<p>The article is correct based on the mpg for the trades as coded in the database.  However, other information in the database suggests that the transactions actually may have involved valid fuel economy improvements.   The database includes the vehicle identification number (VIN) of the trade, which provides important eligibility information on the cars when decoded.</p>
<p>In the case of the 1987 Suburban, to get 18 mpg it would need to be a RWD model equipped with a 6.2-liter diesel engine.  That&#8217;s what the database record says, but according to the VIN, the Suburban was a 13 mpg gas-engined model.  Likewise, the VIN of the 1985 Mercedes is consistent with the car being an eligible 18 mpg gas-engined 190 rather than a 27 mpg diesel 190.  In both cases, the database is ambiguous as to the validity of the transactions; if the VINs are correct, then they were allowable.</p>
<p>The Cash for Clunkers program pretty clearly was not designed as an efficient environmental program, and there have been questions as to its efficiency as stimulus, too.  However, as its costs are spread over aims of stimulus, reducing fuel consumption (which has costs external to car owners), and reducing emissions pollutants other than fuel consumption-related GHGs, it doesn&#8217;t have to be. To call it the Worst Obama Program Ever is to go overboard.</p>
<p>[*] Buiter, who takes the line that it&#8217;s crazy per se to destroy a portion of the capital stock, doesn&#8217;t carefully consider that automobiles don&#8217;t just magically produce transportation services; they consume other inputs and emit various wastes doing so.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/11/evaluating-cash-for-clunkers-the-case-of-the-missing-denominator.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Levitt on Cash for Clunkers</title>
		<link>./../../2009/08/levitt-on-cash-for-clunkers.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/08/levitt-on-cash-for-clunkers.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2009 12:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Auto bailout]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cash for clunkers]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/08/levitt-on-cash-for-clunkers.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Tom Bozzo Steven Levitt wonders aloud at the Freakonomics blog whether it could possibly be true that the CARS a/k/a Cash for Clunkers is about to run out of money, given the level of new vehicle sales in the U.S.: The program went into place on July 24th. One week later, the program was [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Tom Bozzo</p>
<p>Steven Levitt <a href="http://freakonomics.blogs.nytimes.com/2009/08/03/is-somebody-lying-about-cash-for-clunkers/">wonders aloud at the Freakonomics blog</a> whether it could possibly be true that the CARS a/k/a Cash for Clunkers is about to run out of money, given the level of new vehicle sales in the U.S.:<br />
<blockquote>The program went into place on July 24th. One week later, the program was said to be out of money.</p>
<p>In 2006, before the current ills of the automakers, the average number of new cars sold in a week in the United States was 125,000.</p>
<p>So if you believe the numbers, sales involving clunkers as trade-ins last week represented more than two times the weekly sales of new vehicles when the industry was healthy.</p></blockquote>
<p>You have to go well into the comments thread before someone points out that pre-crisis, the number of new automobiles sold in the U.S. was more like 300,000/week — say 16 million sales/year divided by 52 weeks.  As <a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/blogspot/Hzoh/~3/UoRR1CAs2vE/july-auto-sales.html">Spencer showed yesterday</a>, second quarter sales were running around 9.5 million at a seasonally adjusted annual rate; by advanced math, that&#8217;s about 182,500 weekly sales.  The difference in July vs. Q2 sales was about 1.7 million vehicles at SAAR, or 142,000/month.  That would be among the greener shoots were it attributable to general economic conditions.  So CARS actually could fund about two weeks&#8217; worth of the difference between the Q2 sales rate and the pre-crisis rate.  Though maybe given the recent track record of the Chicago school, being off by only a factor of 2.5 is not a bad performance.</p>
<p>A little more below the fold.</p>
<p>Consistent with reports that SUVs and pickups are getting traded in mainly on bread-and-butter cars and small crossovers, a number of high-volume models had very good months.  For instance, Toyota&#8217;s Big Three (Camry, Corolla, and Prius) sold 23,413 more units in <a href="http://pressroom.toyota.com/pr/tms/toyota-reports-july-sales-97581.aspx">July</a> than in <a href="http://pressroom.toyota.com/pr/tms/toyota-reports-june-and-first-95132.aspx">June</a>, a 39.4 percent increase.  Prof. Hamilton&#8217;s <a href="http://www.econbrowser.com/archives/2009/07/no_rebound_for.html">auto-sales graph</a> shows perhaps a modest June-July sales bump in the pre-crisis data.  Honda, Ford, and Hyundai among others also had relatively good months by recent standards.  While one of Levitt&#8217;s commenters boasts of trading a seldom-used pickup on a BMW Z4, lousy sales results from luxury makes suggest this is not a major problem (even though the $45,000 price ceiling is base price and hence relatively permissive); <a href="http://www.autospies.com/news/Mini-Sales-Dip-3-8-In-July-BMW-Fumbles-YTD-Sales-Lead-To-Lexus-After-Dropping-31-5-46600/">BMW&#8217;s sales report</a> affirmatively cited a lack of CARS activity. [1]</p>
<p>So picking over the sales reports, it doesn&#8217;t seem hard to come up with 100,000 sales or thereabouts that could have been juiced by CARS, and the bottom line is that if that&#8217;s the case (and <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/08/04/business/04auto.html?hp">reported</a> fuel economy improvement statistics are based off of the first 80,000 applications), then it&#8217;s perfectly possible that the program could run out of money quickly, or very quickly given a sufficient backlog of unprocessed applications.</p>
<p>Obviously the ordering of the program start and promulgation of the regulations is not a high point in government, but a look at the results suggests that some of the tea-partying reaction is unwarranted.  Based on the reported fuel consumption difference of about 38 percent for the initial wave of applications, savings in fuel and avoided external costs from burning the fuel are on the order of $1200/year if the clunker was driven a typical amount (12,000 miles/year) with fuel at $2.50 and external costs of $1.50/gal.  This is not a bad return on a $4,000 investment.</p>
<p>[1] Moreover, the $45,750 base price of even a &#8220;stripper&#8221; Z4 3.0 renders the model ineligible for CARS.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/08/levitt-on-cash-for-clunkers.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
