<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Peter Dorman &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Reading the story, asking normal business questions</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/reading-the-story-asking-normal-business-questions.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/reading-the-story-asking-normal-business-questions.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2013 12:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[econospeak]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Peter Dorman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[reading the news]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/reading-the-story-asking-normal-business-questions.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Peter Dorman at Econospeak writes a gem of a post asking readers to ask simple questions when offered a morality tale by journalists, or an implied cause and effect tale, and how it takes no special skill to ask simple business questions that the journalist should at least ask, even if not o tanswer all [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://econospeak.blogspot.com/2013/03/the-spin-on-tires.html">Peter Dorman</a> at <i>Econospeak</i> writes a gem of a post asking readers to ask simple questions when offered a morality tale by journalists, or an implied cause and effect tale, and how it takes no special skill to ask simple business questions that the journalist should at least ask, even if not o tanswer all of them.</p>
<p>Peter Dorman writes:</p>
<p>The Spin on Tires</p>
<p>It would be nice to have economic literacy in journalism.  Take <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/03/17/world/europe/fates-of-2-factories-show-social-schisms-in-france.html?ref=todayspaper&#038;pagewanted=print">this morning’s story</a> in the <i>New York Times </i>about a pair of tire factories in Amiens.  One is managed by Dunlop; its workers agreed to a schedule of constantly shifting workweeks and shift work, and it is still operating.  The other is managed by Goodyear.  There the workers rejected the disruptive schedule, and the factory is shutting down.  The comparison is presented as a morality tale, where the responsible workers, recognizing the new demands of productivity and competitiveness in a globalized economy, did the right thing, while their obstinate counterparts, representative of all that’s wrong with France, preferred heroic self-annihilation. </p>
<p>Reading the article, I couldn’t help but think that this analysis of The Real Reason the French Economy is Sputtering was there all along, looking for a story to attach itself to. </p>
<p>But an economist might ask a few simple questions.  First, what is the elasticity of the total production cost of a tire with respect to the changes in work hours?  I realize the reporter wants to emphasize the symbolism, the importance of workers bending to the employer’s will as a virtue in and of itself, but perhaps there is a factual dimension worth looking into.  Just a suggestion.  </p>
<p>Second, what is the market for these tires?  In particular, who if anyone will pick up the market share being abandoned by Goodyear?  Is this about outsourcing of a portion of tire production to lower-cost producers in developing countries?  Or is it about a shrinking domestic market that no longer needs the output of both plants?  Or some combination of the two or something else? </p>
<p>In particular, it is interesting that both factories, despite their different nameplates, are owned by the same company, Goodyear Dunlop.  Thus, this story describes a consolidation.  The very least an enterprising journalist can do is to inquire into the company’s overall capacity.  Is it cutting back elsewhere in Europe?  Are they shifting production geographically?  Is it possible that they might want only one operation in Amiens in any case, and that the only result of the contest over worker concessions is which plant it will be? </p>
<p>All of this is speculative, because I don’t know the tire market in France.  That’s what I would want to learn from a newspaper story, a rather long one at that, on the subject.  This might also help me understand why the US, where few workers are unionized and none have the will or ability to resist whatever schedule is dictated to them, is not blanketed in tire factories.    </p>
<p>Incidentally, there has been a ton of research in the past decade documenting the health effects of exactly the sort of work schedule being imposed at Dunlop.  It is associated with significantly elevated levels of a wide range of diseases; arguably it represents the single greatest occupational safety and health threat experienced in developed countries.  An informed journalist might want to weave that into the story too.</p>
<p>(re-posted with permission of the author)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/reading-the-story-asking-normal-business-questions.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>How to Think About Aggregate Labor Markets</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/how-to-think-about-aggregate-labor-markets.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/how-to-think-about-aggregate-labor-markets.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Feb 2013 13:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[aggregate labor markets]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[labor economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Peter Dorman]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/how-to-think-about-aggregate-labor-markets.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Peter Dorman at Econospeak takes a look at economics and models. (Re-posted with authors consent) How to Think About Aggregate Labor Markets The remarkable Tyler Cowen has me scratching my head again. Here he is at the beginning of a critique of minimum wage laws and sticky-price Keynesianism. (The latter is an oxymoron, as anyone [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://econospeak.blogspot.com/2013/02/how-to-think-about-aggregate-labor.html" target="_blank">Peter Dorman at <i>Econospeak</i></a> takes a look at economics and models. (Re-posted with authors consent)</p>
<p>How to Think About Aggregate Labor Markets</p>
<p>The remarkable Tyler Cowen has me scratching my head again.  Here he is at the beginning of a critique of minimum wage laws and sticky-price Keynesianism.  (The latter is an oxymoron, as anyone who knows the history of Keynes’ dispute with the “Treasury view” knows, but we’ll let it pass.) <br />Let’s say your labor is worth $10 an hour but you won’t go back to work for less than $12, thereby leading to the unemployment of you. <br />In essence you are self-imposing a minimum wage on that market, but the employer is responding by leaving you jobless.<br />You can guess where this is headed.</p>
<p>The interesting thing is that Cowen apparently has no inkling that most people would find his opening sentence insulting.  It implies that some significant portion of the unemployed are simply worth less than they think they are.  Imagine going up to someone who’s been without a job for a while and saying, “I’m sorry, but have you considered the possibility that your abilities are really not very valuable, and your job search has failed because of this delusion?”  If you insist on saying this, I’d advise doing it from a distance.</p>
<p>Now, of course some people have an inflated sense of self-worth, and others are too bashful.  It might be an interesting research project to see whether the distribution of these types is correlated with employment status.  I don’t have any priors about which would predominate where—do you?</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>What makes this interesting to an economist is that the popular perception of unemployment actually fits how we model the aggregate labor market pretty well.  Let me explain.  The view of most unemployed people, according to the interviews I’ve seen, goes something like this: “I’m looking for a job, and I’m willing to take something that’s worse than what I used to have, but I haven’t found anything yet.”  The unemployed person hopes that the job is out there but that the connection hasn’t been made.</p>
<p>This formalizes to the now-standard model of search and matching, for which Peter Diamond and especially Dale Mortensen and Christopher Pissarides split a Nobel.  Equilibrium in such models does not occur where the Beveridge curve crosses the 45-degree line, which it would if the criterion were supply equals demand, but depends on a larger array of factors.  The model is used to explain why the ratio of unemployed workers to vacant jobs is typically greater than one, even in “full employment”.</p>
<p>This is how knowledgeable economists study aggregate labor markets today.  Supply and demand, as deployed by Cowen, is a special and highly unlikely case that assumes away the complications that make the theory empirically relevant.  If you see someone drawing supply and demand curves for labor and trying to explain unemployment as a result of too-high wages, you know they are employing outmoded methods.</p>
<p>What’s striking is that the more high-powered model actually conforms better to popular intuition.  You have to have a rather uncharitable view of human behavior to believe that excess unemployment is due to people overestimating their true worth.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/how-to-think-about-aggregate-labor-markets.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Risk = Freedom?</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/risk-freedom.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/risk-freedom.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2013 16:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[econospeak]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[freedom]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Peter Dorman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[risk]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/risk-freedom.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Peter Dorman at Econospeak speaks to the current selling of big idea models of the world (re-posted with permission from the author): There’s a review on the Dissent website by Steve Randy Waldman of Freaks of Fortune: The Emerging World of Capitalism and Risk in America by Jonathan Levy. The book sounds interesting, but it [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://econospeak.blogspot.com/2013/02/risk-freedom.html">Peter Dorman</a> at Econospeak speaks to the current selling of big idea models of the world (re-posted with permission from the author):</p>
<p>There’s a review on the <a href="http://www.dissentmagazine.org/online_articles/the-risk-ownership-society#prclt-9tUWfN1s"><i>Dissent</i> website</a> by Steve Randy Waldman of <i>Freaks of Fortune: The Emerging World of Capitalism and Risk in America</i> by Jonathan Levy. The book sounds interesting, but it is apparently based on a commonplace but false understanding of the relationship between freedom and risk-taking. </p>
<p>At the individual level it is absolutely true that we face a tradeoff between risk and freedom. You can opt for a secure life, but only at the expense of creativity, individualism, moral courage and all the other Emersonian goodies. Each one of us, every day, faces this choice. Mostly it is just a matter of a tiny bit of risk-taking, but these moments add up, and from time to time there is a fundamental fork in the road. We make our own freedom.</p>
<p>But the social level is another story. Individuals take the array of risks as given; society can choose how much risk its members will face and what their risk-freedom tradeoffs will be, at least up to a point. If the objective is to minimize all risk of any sort, especially all risks to health and income, the result will be stultifying. But that’s not where we are on the Great Risk Curve.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p> Rather, the debates we have are about whether to cut back or extend social insurance programs like Social Security and Medicare, social protections like TANF and Medicaid, and more or less regulation of finance, pollution and such. It seems clear to me that more security of this sort, which limits the downside risk individuals face in their personal lives, reduces the cost of living freely.    </p>
<p>Examples are everywhere. Ample unemployment insurance makes it easier to work for a startup or switch jobs in general rather than being held down by too strong a need for job security. A stronger public pension system encourages entrepreneurship: people can hazard their savings by starting a business rather than hoarding everything for old age. Social guarantees for basic needs make it possible for artists to risk making art their day job. Professors with tenure (big time risk reduction) can take more controversial positions on public issues. (I don’t say they always do this, but they do it more than they would if all professors were temps.) In each case there is a real tradeoff between freedom and security at the individual level, but society can create programs that relax it, so it takes less courage to live freely.  </p>
<p>That’s what I don’t like about the nanny state rhetoric. Yes, of course the state can go too far and overprotect us from risks we would do better to face ourselves. But the state we actually live in goes too far in the other direction. With a stronger safety net we could have less risk and more freedom.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/risk-freedom.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Economics an Almost Social Science</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/economics-an-almost-social-science.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/economics-an-almost-social-science.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 23 Jul 2012 14:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Behavioral Economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[microeconomic theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[neoclassical economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Peter Dorman]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/economics-an-almost-social-science.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Peter Dorman at Econospeak discusses problems with microfoundations, and in a more thorough paper at Association Economique politique explores the Political Econonomic Outlook for Capitalism. Mark Thoma had pointed to this Business/behavioral science can help guide economic-policy view notion of looking at incentives in an empirical way.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Peter Dorman at <a href="http://econospeak.blogspot.com/2012/07/the-problem-with-microfoundations-bad.html" target="_blank">Econospeak</a> discusses problems with microfoundations, and in a more thorough paper at <a href="http://www.assoeconomiepolitique.org/political-economy-outlook-for-capitalism/wp-content/uploads/2012/06/Economics-an-Almost-Social-Science.pdf" target="_blank">Association Economique politique</a> explores the <i>Political Econonomic Outlook for Capitalism.</i></p>
<p>Mark Thoma had pointed to this <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/07/08/business/behavioral-science-can-help-guide-policy-economic-view.html?emc=tnt&#038;tntemail1=y" target="_blank">Business/behavioral science can help guide economic-policy view</a> notion of looking at incentives in an empirical way.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/economics-an-almost-social-science.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Main Point</title>
		<link>./../../2012/05/the-main-point.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/05/the-main-point.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 May 2012 01:36:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[austerity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Fiscal policy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[monetary policy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Peter Dorman]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/05/the-main-point.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Peter Dorman at Econospeak brings us another reminder about policy decisions on the economy.  Reposted from Econospeak: The Main Point Macroeconomics is complicated and political economy is devilish, so it is easy to get lost in the details. From time to time, it’s good to come up for air—to remember what the fundamental issue is. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://econospeak.blogspot.com/2012/05/main-point.html">Peter Dorman</a> at <i>Econospeak</i> brings us another reminder about policy decisions on the economy.  Reposted from Econospeak:</p>
<p><strong>The Main Point</strong></p>
<p>Macroeconomics is complicated and political economy is devilish, so it is easy to get lost in the details.  From time to time, it’s good to come up for air—to remember what the fundamental issue is.  In a way, the debate over structural versus cyclical factors invites us to do just that.  </p>
<p>Suppose the current recession/depression is mainly structural.  Suppose it is due to an immense misallocation of capital and labor, a failure to foresee what our economy would really demand in the years ahead.  According to this story, we have trained too many masons and anthropologists and invested in too many building cranes and liberal arts colleges, and it will take years to shift our human and produced resources to more valuable pursuits.  (Actually, I think there continues to be an enormous misallocation of investment, but this will become apparent only when the threat of global warming is taken seriously.)  If the structuralist story is right, the ongoing slump is necessary and unavoidable and will end only when we have fashioned the resources for producing the right stuff.  </p>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />If the cyclical story is predominately true, however, we have neither the wrong people nor the wrong capital stock.  We have all the ingredients it takes to have a vibrant economy that can fully employ our populations and generate a standard of living that surpasses what we had in the past and that keeps growing further.  But think about it: if we have the wherewithal to resume prosperity, what holds us back?  And why should rational people accept any excuses for policies that delay it?  </p>
<p>Repeat: we have everything we need, right now, to restart our economies.  All the unemployment, the hardship, the lost opportunities are unnecessary.  That’s the main point.  </p>
<p>The secondary point is about the why.  There are ultimately two reasons why economies like ours get stuck in a cyclical rut.  The first is that there is a reinforcing cycle of insufficient demand and insufficient investment.  This is where standard countercyclical policy comes in: through fiscal deficits the government increases demand on its own initiative, and through monetary easing an impetus is added to investment.  We are near the limit of what easing can do (diminishing returns to the QE’s), but not anywhere near the limit of fiscal expansion.  </p>
<p>The second reason arises in balance sheet recessions: too much private borrowing has taken place, debtors find it difficult to sustain debt service, and both debtors and creditors retrench.  In this case, which is ours, the essential problem is that fulfillment of claims on wealth—both credit claims and equity claims on debt-related assets—interferes with the conditions required for restarting growth.  In other words, the shadow of past wealth creation is depriving new wealth creation of sunlight.  While respecting wealth claims is desirable during normal times, since it supports long-term planning, there come episodes in which a choice must be made between the past and the future.  This is such a time.  Wealth claims need to be trimmed, quickly and sufficiently, in order to reduce leverage and permit economies to return to growth.  We shouldn’t forget the main point, which is that economic growth produces the stuff of which real wealth is made, while satisfying the claims inherited from yesterday only allocates this stuff.  (And in a slumping economy the claims can’t be honored anyway.)  </p>
<p>If you accept the cyclical story, and the evidence certainly weighs in its favor, you should not accept another month, much less year after year, of excuses for austerity.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/05/the-main-point.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Bankrupt Rhetoric</title>
		<link>./../../2012/03/bankrupt-rhetoric.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/03/bankrupt-rhetoric.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 24 Mar 2012 13:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2012 elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bankruptcy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Peter Dorman]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/03/bankrupt-rhetoric.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Peter Dorman at Econospeak comments:  Bankrupt Rhetoric  I woke up this morning to Paul Ryan, describing his budget proposal, as quoted in the New York Times: “This is about putting an end to empty promises from a bankrupt government.” Bankrupt government? Let’s consider this more closely. The normal meaning of bankrupt is negative net worth, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://econospeak.blogspot.com/2012/03/bankrupt-rhetoric.html" title="http://econospeak.blogspot.com/2012/03/bankrupt-rhetoric.html?utm_source=feedburner&#038;utm_medium=feed&#038;utm_campaign=Feed%3A+espeak+%28EconoSpeak%29">Peter Dorman</a> at <i>Econospeak</i> comments:</p>
<p> Bankrupt Rhetoric</p>
<p> I woke up this morning to Paul Ryan, describing his budget proposal, <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/03/21/us/politics/house-republicans-release-budget-blueprint.html?ref=todayspaper&#038;pagewanted=print">as quoted in the <i>New York Times</i></a>: “This is about putting an end to empty promises from a bankrupt government.”</p>
<p>Bankrupt government? Let’s consider this more closely. The normal meaning of bankrupt is negative net worth, as when your liabilities exceed your assets. By this standard, the US government is hardly bankrupt, since it has enormous hard assets and an even larger soft one, the legal right to tax the income, transactions and property of all individuals and organizations subject to US law. We should all be so bankrupt!</p>
<p>So I guess Ryan is not using the normal business meaning of the word. Perhaps for him bankrupt means having negative earnings over some period of time. Here is the federal government’s fiscal record since 1929:</p>
<p><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-ZuYwKLFk_Uw/T2mPEe1O_7I/AAAAAAAAA0M/9hYhKBL6jQ8/s1600/Federal+surplus+or+deficit+as+percent+gdp.gif"><img border="0" height="287" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-ZuYwKLFk_Uw/T2mPEe1O_7I/AAAAAAAAA0M/9hYhKBL6jQ8/s400/Federal+surplus+or+deficit+as+percent+gdp.gif" width="400"></a></p>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />So during what periods has the federal government been “bankrupt”? During every year when outlays exceeded revenues? That would include nearly all of modern history since the 1960s. Or when the fiscal deficit exceeded, say, 5% of GDP? That’s a smaller time frame—basically the past few years since the financial crisis hit and WWII. But if the government is bankrupt now, how bankrupt was it in the days of FDR and the struggle against Germany and Japan? And what does it mean to be bankrupt if the US could be really, really bankrupt in the 1940s and then bounce back to fiscal health almost immediately as soon as the troops came home?</p>
<p>And if the US government is bankrupt today, how come it can raise money at approximately a zero real interest rate?</p>
<p>And on a philosophical level, how does Ryan measure the financial health of government when its purpose is not to make itself rich but to support the prosperity of everyone else?<br />My translation of the way Ryan uses the word “bankrupt” would be “I want to scare everyone about the current fiscal deficit, and the best way to do it is to use a business-sounding term that has no meaning at all in this situation and hope that the public, and especially the journalists, are too dumb to notice.”</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/03/bankrupt-rhetoric.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
