<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>RFR &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Economists = Idiots? Part 1829</title>
		<link>./../../2010/07/economists-idiots-part-1829.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/07/economists-idiots-part-1829.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 21 Jul 2010 16:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[economic theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[excess reserves]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[financial institutions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[FRBOperations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[interest rates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[liquidity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[RFR]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[solvency crisis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the fed]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WSJ]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/07/economists-idiots-part-1829.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[It was their idea, so it&#8217;s no surprise they like paying interest on reserves, even excess reserves: For quite a while, the Fed was quite happy to have that money on its books. Indeed, the power to pay interest on reserves was considered a key tool to keep control over all the liquidity the Fed [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It was their idea, so it&#8217;s no surprise they like <a href="http://blogs.wsj.com/economics/2010/07/21/ending-interest-on-reserves-wont-help-economy-much/">paying interest on reserves, even excess reserves</a>:<br />
<blockquote>For quite a while, the Fed was quite happy to have that money on its books. Indeed, the power to pay interest on reserves was considered a key tool to keep control over all the liquidity the Fed pumped into the system during the financial crisis. The Fed wanted to see bank lending increase, but in a controlled fashion, so as not to fan the flames of an inflation surge.</p>
<p>But as worries about the outlook have risen, the game has changed. Some see a move to drive all those reserves into the economy as a key way to produce better economic growth. Markets got to thinking Fed Chairman Ben Bernanke would indicate this as a possible path when he testifies before the Senate Wednesday and the House of Representatives Thursday on the economic and monetary policy outlook.</p>
<p>Economists, however, think ending the interest on reserves policy would be a bad idea.</p></blockquote>
<p>Right, because the $2,534,722.22 a year paid in interest on $1 Billion in excess reserves is a drop in the bucket for the U.S. Federal deficit.</p>
<p>And because the risk-free rate of return that features in so many economic models should be different for intermediaries (financial institutions) than wealth-creators (businesses).</p>
<p>And because &#8220;excess reserves&#8221; are money issued by the government which is inflationary because of the multiplier effect of money—which, of course, assumes the money is being invested. (As this money is, in taxing our tax dollars and giving them to Vikram Pandit, Ken Lewis, Lloyd Blankfein, and Jamie Dimon [in descending order of theft; YMMV].)</p>
<p>And, of course, because that $1 Billion that is not being used in the economy would only produce about $5-8 Billion in GDP, which is roughly, what, 50,000 to 80,000 new jobs?</p>
<p>But, of course, banks have better use for the money than potential workers.<br />
<blockquote>[Barclays Capital’s Joseph Abate] noted much of the money that constitutes this giant pile of reserves is &#8220;precautionary liquidity.&#8221; If banks didn&#8217;t get interest from the Fed they would shift those funds into short-term, low-risk markets such as the repo, Treasury bill and agency discount note markets, where the funds are readily accessible in case of need. Put another way, Abate doesn&#8217;t see this money <em>getting tied up in bank loans or the other activities that would help increase credit, in turn boosting overall economic momentum</em>. [emphasis mine]</p></blockquote>
<p>Oh, well, since they&#8217;re not going to lend the money anyway, we should have no trouble paying them interest on it. What is The Fed other than a mattress stuffed by tax dollars?</p>
<p>The key phrase is &#8220;precautionary liquidity.&#8221; If you assume that the recovery started in June or July of last year,* then you would expect &#8220;excess reserves&#8221; held for &#8220;precautionary liquidity&#8221; to have declined over time, as the need for &#8220;precautions&#8221; is reduced as the economy becomes safer. But that hasn&#8217;t been the case.</p>
<p>Choose one (or both) from: (1) the banks don&#8217;t believe the economy is recovering or (2) the banks are holding assets on their books at higher levels than they know they are worth, and are therefore using &#8220;excess reserves&#8221; to cover real losses until they can&#8217;t any more.</p>
<p>It is unclear whether Abate sees the banks&#8217;s unwillingness to be intermediaries as a feature. But at least he knows not everyone is doing it.<br />
<blockquote>Abate buttressed his argument that banks really just want to stay liquid by noting who is holding reserves at the Fed. He said the 25 largest U.S. banks account for just over half of aggregate reserve levels, with three by themselves making up 21% of the reserves.</p></blockquote>
<p>So the biggest of the Too Big to Fail banks have decided not to act as financial intermediaries, preferring instead to continue feeding from the taxpayer trough (where the $25MM in interest really is a drop in the bucket) and/or pretend that they are more solvent than they really are.</p>
<p>And, according to the Wall Street Journal, economists believe we should continue to <em>pay</em> those banks for misvaluing their assets and refusing to perform their economic function.</p>
<p>The economic theory I learned is that capital is paid its marginal product.  The marginal product of those excess reserves is zero, while the required reserves are intended to explicitly provide &#8220;precautionary liquidity.&#8221;</p>
<p>Unless the TBTF banks are arguing that the Fed&#8217;s current Reserve Requirements are too low—a possibility, perhaps, though <a href="http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/40271298-9428-11df-a3fe-00144feab49a.html">the FT cites evidence contrariwise</a>—the basis of all economic and financial theory indicates that they <em>should</em> receive no interest on those reserves.</p>
<p>An &#8220;economist&#8221; who says otherwise is either lying or selling something.</p>
<p>*I would argue—see <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2010/07/are-you-better-off-than-you-were-year.html">yesterday&#8217;s post</a>—that June 2009 is rather eliminated by the non-recovery of more than half the states&#8217;s job markets a full year later.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/07/economists-idiots-part-1829.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
