<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Daniel Becker &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Business income or personal income</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/business-income-or-personal-income.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/business-income-or-personal-income.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 Dec 2012 04:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Daniel Becker]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[small business]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[taxes and small business]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/business-income-or-personal-income.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In response to Small businesses and tax cuts and reporting by Daniel Becker, reader Betty, a long time small business owner and not a sole proprietor herself in one of the richer towns of MA with a median income over $180,000 , asked: &#8230; I&#8217;ve always been baffled by the Republican complaint that it would [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In response to <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/11/small-businesses-tax-cuts-and-reporting.html" target="_blank">Small businesses and tax cuts and reporting</a> by Daniel Becker, reader Betty, a long time small business owner and not a sole proprietor herself in one of the richer towns of MA with a median income over $180,000 , asked:</p>
<blockquote><p>&#8230; I&#8217;ve always been baffled by the Republican complaint that it would be bad for the BUSINESSES of small business owners with incomes over $250,000 to be lumped with the Rich and have their taxes go up, or not go down, if the Bush tax cuts were not extended for the wealthy.  What I don&#8217;t get is this:  Even if the business earns millions, all business expenses are deductible. What&#8217;s left that&#8217;s taxable (the profit)  is the PERSONAL INCOME of the owner or owners, right?  So how does a higher tax adversely affect the business? Or are these large small businesses just corporations in disguise?</p></blockquote>
<p><i>Dan Becker</i> replied to Betty in two excellent posts from the past:</p>
<p>
<blockquote>I posted back in July of 2008 specifically addressing the <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2008/07/myth-of-argument-is-in-conflation.html" target="_blank">conflation of income and business taxes</a> as Betty is noting.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, too many business people don&#8217;t get it either as I found after having a heated discussion with one of my colleagues.  He insisted I must not be incorporated because I did not know what I was talking about.<br />At the time I posted it, a couple others at AB commented that I was making the issue too complicated and that the average reader did not need to know such details.  Here we are 2012 discussing it again.  We can not expect to solve our problems is we are going to avoid deeper understanding of the words we use and the concepts those word represent.<br />I suggest my posting on the 1936 tax tables is another one of those postings that not enough people have read.  To many people really have little to no idea <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/03/defining-rich-vi-1936-tax-tables.html" target="_blank">just what is being talked about when someone says &#8220;income tax&#8221; or &#8220;marginal rates&#8221;</a><a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/03/defining-rich-vi-1936-tax-tables.html" target="_blank">. </a></p></blockquote>
<p>(Dan C here&#8230;The small businesses many people, in my estimation, generally associate the term &#8216;small business&#8217; are probably &#8216;companies&#8217; under 50 employees but with a variety of legal and IRS oriented classifications.  I may post updated versions of these posts&#8230;people tend to approach taxes with more religious fervor than understanding).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/business-income-or-personal-income.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Small businesses, tax cuts, and reporting</title>
		<link>./../../2012/11/small-businesses-tax-cuts-and-reporting.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/11/small-businesses-tax-cuts-and-reporting.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 29 Nov 2012 13:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Daniel Becker]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economic reporting]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[links worth noting]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[small business]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax cuts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WaPo]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/11/small-businesses-tax-cuts-and-reporting.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[ I sometimes get the &#8216;eyes rolling&#8217; reaction from people in my social sphere when I insist that at least linking to  original documents is important, and that someone needs to follow up on what an author says someone else says (as a way to gain traction and authority status for their own writing, such as [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p> I sometimes get the &#8216;eyes rolling&#8217; reaction from people in my social sphere when I insist that at least linking to  original documents is important, and that someone needs to follow up on what an author says someone else says (as a way to gain traction and authority status for their own writing, such as saying the non-partisan Tax Policy Centers says).  I won&#8217;t go into the idea of spin, which involves figuring out intent.  Mine is a caution for readers:</p>
<p>The post is lifted from a note from Daniel Becker in response to a query I sent to him&#8230;Dan is a small businessman in the way most of us think of as small business.  (The IRS has a different criterion  of ownership that allows a company like <i>Bechtal </i>at $31 billion to be considered a small business).</p>
<p>Dan Becker&#8217;s note:</p>
<p>The Washington Post article is   <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/business/economy/obama-calls-for-small-business-tax-breaks/2012/11/27/83575192-389d-11e2-b01f-5f55b193f58f_story.html"><i>Obama calls for small business tax break</i>s</a>.   The article uses the  <a href="http://www.taxpolicycenter.org/taxtopics/2013-Temporary-Tax-Relief-to-Create-Jobs-and.cfm">Tax Policy Center</a> original under the title <i>Temporary Tax Relief to Create Jobs </i> as the source for the reporting.</p>
<p>The WP article notes:</p>
<p>&#8220;The last time the country had a similar proposal to the tax subsidy was during the Carter administration, according to the Tax Policy Center. Research by the Labor Department found that few firms knew about the tax policy, but those that did increased employment notably.&#8221;    </p>
<p>But from their source it actually notes:    <br />
<blockquote>&#8220;The last experience the United States had with a credit for incremental employment was with the new jobs credit enacted at the beginning of the Carter Administration in 1977. Evaluations of that credit <a href="http://taxvox.taxpolicycenter.org/sunley.pdf">and how it came about</a> found that most firms were either unaware of the credit or did not respond to it. <a href="http://ideas.repec.org/a/aea/aecrev/v69y1979i2p173-79.html">Research based on a Department of Labor survey</a> found that only 6 percent of firms who knew about the credit said that it prompted them to hire more workers. Firms that were aware of the credit, however, increased employment about 3 percent more than other firms. &#8221;   (bolding is Dan B.&#8217;s)</p></blockquote>
<p>WP had another smoothing over (under the fold):<br />      <br /><a name="more"></a><br />&#8220;An incremental jobs credit could be a cost-effective way of raising employment in the short run, the <a href="http://www.taxpolicycenter.org/taxtopics/2013-Temporary-Tax-Relief-to-Create-Jobs-and.cfm">nonpartisan center said in a report</a> this year. The effectiveness of any jobs subsidy depends . . . on how employers perceive its potential benefits when making hiring decisions.&#8221;</p>
<p>The actual statement:     <br />
<blockquote>In summary, the effect of this proposal on employment is very uncertain. In theory, an incremental jobs credit could be a cost-effective way of raising employment in the short run and some research suggests that the 1977 credit did increase jobs, although the evidence on that is far from conclusive.<br />The effectiveness of any jobs subsidy depends greatly on both the details of the proposal, still to be finalized, and on how employers perceive its potential benefits when making hiring decisions.</p></blockquote>
<p><i>Dan B</i></p>
<p>(Editorial comment at end of note from Dan Becker&#8230;.Man! They still want to believe that cutting taxes is actually the same as if the 99% were now getting that $1 trillion of income that is now with the 1%. Just like they believe cutting taxes will increase revenues (sure if you convince the dictator to stop taking a full 90% of all that his people produce, but that&#8217;s not US).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/11/small-businesses-tax-cuts-and-reporting.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
