<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Keynesian economics &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>What Mindless Cliché-Driven Centrism From a High-Profile Pundit Looks Like, in Detail.</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/what-mindless-cliche-driven-centrism-from-a-high-profile-pundit-looks-like-in-detail.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/what-mindless-cliche-driven-centrism-from-a-high-profile-pundit-looks-like-in-detail.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2013 16:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dana Milbank]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Keynesian economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Washington Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/what-mindless-cliche-driven-centrism-from-a-high-profile-pundit-looks-like-in-detail.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The State of the Union ritual is by now familiar to most Americans. President Obama leads the Democratic side of the chamber to a series of standing ovations for proposals that everybody knows won’t become law. Republicans show their seriousness of purpose by smirking or making stony faces — and by inviting as guests to [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">The State of the Union ritual is by now familiar to most Americans. President Obama leads the Democratic side of the chamber to a series of standing ovations for proposals that everybody knows won’t become law. Republicans show their seriousness of purpose by smirking or making stony faces — and by inviting as guests to the speech people such as <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/reliable-source/post/ted-nugent-attending-state-of-the-union-address/2013/02/11/2b868238-749f-11e2-95e4-6148e45d7adb_blog.html">rocker Ted Nugent</a>, who has called the president a “piece of [excrement]” who should “suck on my machine gun.”</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">But this spectacle, unlike [Mardi Gras], is not all harmless fun. Obama made clear that he is not entertaining serious spending cuts or major entitlement reforms. Republicans, in their responses, repeated that they are not budging on taxes. The hard choices will have to wait for another day.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">The standoff gives new meaning to Fat Tuesday: The nation’s finances are a mess, but — what the heck? — let’s have another round. No wonder a new Washington Post poll found that <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/the-fix/wp/2013/02/12/obama-faces-deeply-divided-nation-in-state-of-the-union-address/">56 percent of Americans</a> have a dim view of the country’s political system.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/dana-milbank-state-of-the-union-and-mardi-gras--what-a-coincidence/2013/02/12/105119ee-7560-11e2-aa12-e6cf1d31106b_story.html?hpid=z2">Let the bleak times roll</a>, Dana Milbank, Washington Post, today</div>
<p>Yup.  Fifty-six percent of Americans want another deep recession.  Now!  Our nation’s finances are a mess.  And they want to see them become messier!  And they want a few million hungry or homeless elderly. Not necessarily now.  But soon.</p>
<p>The luxury of being a Centrist, at least one of this particular and common variety, is that you can spout generic truisms without ever actually tying them to specifics.  Much less to basic economics principles. Milbank’s column is so replete with unsupported and in fact completely unexplained inferences&#8211;declaratory clauses and sentences each made in its own little vacuum but offered as though dependent upon one another&#8211;that Milbank’s heard somewhere, that I wondered as I read this thing whether he’d brought his MacBook Air to a <a href="http://www.uline.com/Grp_316/Plastic-Retail-Food-Bags?pricode=WL25&#038;gclid=CPSNs8rBs7UCFZE-MgodmS8Axw">Uline</a> plant to watch the speech last night. I mean, how else to explain this?:</p>
<div dir="ltr">Early in his address, Obama pronounced himself “more than halfway towards the goal of $4 trillion in deficit reduction that economists say we need to stabilize our finances.” He blithely proclaimed that the rest of the job could be done by making “modest reforms” to Medicare and “getting rid of tax loopholes and deductions for the well-off.”</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">He didn’t mention that this would leave the country with a historically high debt level — and would be but a temporary fix before health-care costs explode in a decade. Departing from his prepared text, Obama challenged the idea that “deficit reduction is a big emergency, justifying making cuts in Social Security.” </div>
<p>Oh, horrors. After all, deficit reduction is a big emergency. And a historically high debt level&#8211;irrespective of the specifics, such as how high that debt level is relative to GDP&#8211;will crash the economy.  Just like the historically high debt levels did at the end of World War II. </p>
<p>“Washington’s version of Mardi Gras had begun early in the day, at the Capitol South Metro station, where members of a nonpartisan balanced-budget group, Bankrupting America, offered beads to passersby willing to ‘show us your cuts,’” Milbank writes. “By that standard, few necklaces would be distributed. Democrats and Republicans alike would sooner bare their private parts than come clean about what government programs they would cut.”  True enough.</p>
<p>But then, this:</p>
<div dir="ltr">Even [Paul] Ryan, who is drafting a budget that could slash domestic discretionary spending by 40 percent over a decade, doesn’t like to be specific. </div>
<p>Even Paul Ryan doesn’t like to be specific about cuts that would slash domestic spending by 40 percent over decade?  Even Paul Ryan?  You don’t say!</p>
<p>And then, of course:</p>
<div dir="ltr">And House Democratic leader Nancy Pelosi says, “<a href="http://foxnewsinsider.com/2013/02/10/nancy-pelosi-says-the-spending-problem-is-a-false-argument/">It is almost a false argument to say we have a spending problem</a>.”</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Pelosi’s formulation is just as reckless as the Republicans’ mantra: “We don’t have a revenue problem; we have a spending problem.”</div>
<p>Of course. Which is why, pre-Bush-tax-cuts, and pre-Bush-unfunded-wars, we didn’t have a spending problem. Now we do, so let’s cut Social Security!  Canada, Germany, Australia and Holland must also have spending problems.  After all, they have extensive social safety-net programs, and high standards of living.</p>
<p>Milbank ends by saying, “In reality, we eventually need both spending cuts and tax increases — and lots of them. But sacrifice will have to wait. In Washington, they’re still partying like there’s no tomorrow.”</p>
<p>No, actually, the Democrats are partying like there is a tomorrow.  There&#8217;s real, if unwitting, irony in the headline writer&#8217;s choice of a heading for Milbank&#8217;s column.  Although&#8211;who knows?&#8211;maybe the headline writer actually is familiar with Keynesian economics. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/what-mindless-cliche-driven-centrism-from-a-high-profile-pundit-looks-like-in-detail.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Yup, John Boehner and Paul Ryan Are Right: The economy contracted in the fourth quarter because #spendingstheproblem and Keynesian Economics Doesn’t Work.</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/yup-john-boehner-and-paul-ryan-are-right-the-economy-contracted-in-the-fourth-quarter-because-spendingstheproblem-and-keynesian-economics-doesnt-work.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/yup-john-boehner-and-paul-ryan-are-right-the-economy-contracted-in-the-fourth-quarter-because-spendingstheproblem-and-keynesian-economics-doesnt-work.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2013 17:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[#spendingstheproblem]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Boehner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Keynesian economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/yup-john-boehner-and-paul-ryan-are-right-the-economy-contracted-in-the-fourth-quarter-because-spendingstheproblem-and-keynesian-economics-doesnt-work.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Construction has been one of the more encouraging sectors, adding jobs each of the last four months. The hiring there was probably because of a combination of rebuilding from Hurricane Sandy, unseasonably warm weather that led to fewer work stoppages, and the nascent housing recovery, said Ian Shepherdson, chief economist at Pantheon Macroeconomic Advisors. Retailing, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">Construction has been one of the more encouraging sectors, adding jobs each of the last four months. The hiring there was probably because of a combination of rebuilding from <a href="http://topics.nytimes.com/top/reference/timestopics/subjects/h/hurricanes_and_tropical_storms/index.html?inline=nyt-classifier">Hurricane Sandy</a>, unseasonably warm weather that led to fewer work stoppages, and the nascent housing recovery, said Ian Shepherdson, chief economist at Pantheon Macroeconomic Advisors.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Retailing, health care and the wholesale trade also added positions in January, while the government again shed jobs. Government payrolls have been shrinking most months over the last four years.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/02/business/economy/us-adds-157000-jobs-unemployment-rate-edges-up-to-7-9.html?emc=na&#038;pagewanted=all">Job Growth Is Steady Amid Snags Holding Back Economy</a>, Catherine Rampell, New York Times, today</div>
<p><a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/01/paul-ryan-says-taxes-should-be-raised.html">Bring on</a> <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/01/john-boehner-says-defense-spending-is.html">the sequester</a>, I say!  Let’s get that economy <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/01/opinion/krugman-looking-for-mister-goodpain.html?_r=1&#038;">going again</a>! </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/yup-john-boehner-and-paul-ryan-are-right-the-economy-contracted-in-the-fourth-quarter-because-spendingstheproblem-and-keynesian-economics-doesnt-work.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Brian Williams Thinks Raising the Debt Ceiling Means Increasing BUDGET APPROPRIATIONS. O Peter Jennings, Walter Cronkite, and Edward R. Murrow, Where Art Thou? &#8212; [UPDATED]</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/brian-williams-thinks-raising-the-debt-ceiling-means-increasing-budget-appropriations-o-peter-jennings-walter-cronkite-and-edward-r-murrow-where-art-thou-updated.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/brian-williams-thinks-raising-the-debt-ceiling-means-increasing-budget-appropriations-o-peter-jennings-walter-cronkite-and-edward-r-murrow-where-art-thou-updated.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2013 15:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[austerity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Brian Williams]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Keynesian economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NBC Nightly News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Krugman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the debt ceiling]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The New York Times]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/brian-williams-thinks-raising-the-debt-ceiling-means-increasing-budget-appropriations-o-peter-jennings-walter-cronkite-and-edward-r-murrow-where-art-thou-updated.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I watched NBC Nightly News with Brian Williams last night.  Big Mistake. Big mistake. Because now I’m really confused.  I was pretty darn sure until then that “raising the debt ceiling” meant allowing the Treasury Department to pay financial obligations already incurred, such as interest on bonds, Medicare payments, and contract obligations, and to allow [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I watched NBC Nightly News with Brian Williams last night.  Big Mistake. </p>
<p>Big mistake. </p>
<p>Because now I’m really confused.  I was pretty darn sure until then that “raising the debt ceiling” meant allowing the Treasury Department to pay financial obligations already incurred, such as interest on bonds, Medicare payments, and contract obligations, and to allow continued payments for ongoing financial obligations such as Social Security payments, Veterans’ benefits, and salary payments to federal employees, some of whose jobs are sort of important.  (Think: air traffic controllers.)  I had thought that because I had followed the recurring-crisis news reports about it since 2011, when the first of the crises began.  And because Obama had actually explained it in his Jan. 14 press conference. </p>
<p>But now, well, I think I might have misunderstood, because after Williams reported that the Senate yesterday had approved the House bill to “suspend” the debt ceiling through May 19, he added, shaking his head in disapproval, something like: “This is Washington’s version of kicking the can down the road.  Our debt is now more than a trillion dollars.”</p>
<p>I suggest that next time Williams is onboard one of NBC’s corporate jets, he might read, say, Paul Krugman’s <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/01/opinion/krugman-looking-for-mister-goodpain.html?_r=0">column in today’s New York Times</a>.  It doesn’t explain the difference between the debt ceiling statute and budget-appropriations statutes, so Williams will continue to conflate the two until he digs deeper and reads earlier Krugman columns or other mainstream-media articles that did that.  But it does (yet again)&#8211;<a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/01/paul-ryan-says-taxes-should-be-raised.html">to borrow a phrase from Paul Ryan</a> in his Meet the Press interview aired last Sunday&#8211;debate the efficacy of Keynesian economics, and whether anti-Keynesian “austerity” measures reduce or instead increase national debt in real terms and, more important (although Williams apparently doesn’t know this), decrease or instead increase debt relative to GDP.</p>
<p>But if he is going to wait until he’s up there in the air in that Learjet to read the Krugman column, I hope the trip occurs before May 20.  </p>
<p>&#8212;-</p>
<p>UPDATE: Additional recommended reading for Brian Williams: Joe Scarborough, Paul Krugman and the economist-pundit divide on debt and deficits, Neil Irwin, Washington Post, yesterday. </p>
<p>Scarborough, though, at least knows what the debt ceiling law is, and that it isn’t the same as budget-appropriations legislation.  He does, after all, work for MSNBC, not, say, NBC News. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/brian-williams-thinks-raising-the-debt-ceiling-means-increasing-budget-appropriations-o-peter-jennings-walter-cronkite-and-edward-r-murrow-where-art-thou-updated.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>John Boehner Says Defense Spending Is the Problem with the Economy. Awesome. &#8211; [UPDATED]</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/john-boehner-says-defense-spending-is-the-problem-with-the-economy-awesome-updated.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/john-boehner-says-defense-spending-is-the-problem-with-the-economy-awesome-updated.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 31 Jan 2013 19:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[#spendingistheproblem]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Glenn Thrush]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Greg Sargent]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Boehner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Keynesian economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politico]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Washington Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/john-boehner-says-defense-spending-is-the-problem-with-the-economy-awesome-updated.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Politico’s Glenn Thrush reports this morning that Republicans believe the GDP report showing the economy is shrinking gives them political “leverage” over Obama, since bad economic news is terrible for the President. But Thrush notes that this shouldn’t be the case, since the contraction was the result of spending cuts, which in theory should undermine [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">Politico’s Glenn Thrush <a href="http://www.politico.com/politico44/2013/01/obamas-gdp-nightmare-155645.html?hp=l4">reports this morning</a> that Republicans believe the GDP report showing the economy is shrinking gives them political “leverage” over Obama, since bad economic news is terrible for the President. But Thrush notes that this shouldn’t be the case, since the contraction was the result of spending cuts, which in theory should undermine the GOP argument that we should cut spending as deeply as possible:</div>
<div dir="ltr">The fact that the shock this time came from a plunge in defense/federal spending should, in theory, bolster Obama’s contention that budget-cutting and trimming entitlement spending is the worst thing for the economy right now. It should, in a more Spock-like world, be an argument against the sequester cuts and big changes to Medicare and Social Security. </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Forget about that.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">All nuance is lost in the howling gale of an economic “contraction” — and the advantage, at least in the current news cycle, shifts to a down-in-mouth GOP. It’s not likely to be a major shift in the dynamics of looming fiscal fights, but Republicans, in the words of one senior Hill staffer I spoke to this morning, “will take any leverage we can get.”</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Thrush very well be right that people won’t take the right message from the contraction. But in a rational world, what should be glaringly obvious is that the belief that this gives the party “leverage” highlights how absurdly incoherent the GOP message about the economy has become. (Read S<a href="http://maddowblog.msnbc.com/_news/2013/01/31/16789587-diagnosing-the-gdp-problem?lite">teve Benen for all the other problems here</a>.)</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">The economic contraction was driven largely by a steep drop in defense spending. As <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/wonkblog/wp/2013/01/30/government-is-hurting-the-economy-by-spending-too-little/?wprss=rss_business">Ezra Klein details</a>, this shows that “government is hurting the recovery” by “spending and investing too little.” As Ezra notes, “government spending and investment have, at all levels, been contractionary since 2010.”</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Yet Republicans are responding to the news of the economic contraction by suggesting invalidates their view that we need to further cut spending to help the economy. Hence their claimed “leverage” in the coming battle over the sequestered cuts, half of which is to defense spending. Republicans are actively using the sequester to force Dems to agree to avert it by offsetting it entirely with other deep cuts to social programs, and no new revenues from the wealthy. In response to the contraction, John Boehner <a href="https://twitter.com/johnboehner/status/296647347096674304">tweeted out this hashtag</a>:</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">#spendingistheproblem</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">In other words, the contraction confirms that we need more spending cuts.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/plum-line/wp/2013/01/31/we-all-agree-that-spending-cuts-hurt-the-economy-right-right/">We all agree that spending cuts hurt the economy. Right? Right.</a>, Greg Saregent, Washington Post, today</div>
<p>Okay, look.  If Obama doesn’t now, finally, explain Keynesian economics to the general public, using actual facts&#8211;such as the reason for the economic contraction&#8211;and point out that Boehner &#038; Co. either are ignorant of the facts or are willing to deliberately misinform the public about such a critically important matter, then he should resign and let Joe Biden explain it as president.  </p>
<p>I mean it. </p>
<p>Obama did a stellar job a week before his inaugural address explaining the debt ceiling law and what “raising the debt ceiling” means&#8211;and that ti does not mean what the Republicans’ campaign of disinformation was saying it means.  He should do the same now, on this.  </p>
<p>Presumably, he’ll enlist as his chief speechwriter for his State of the Union address a speechwriter who understands how to easily explain Keynesian economics and the current “contraction” statistics.  But, just as with his inaugural address, he should not wait until that speech to expose the Republican game plan for what it is: a concerted campaign to misinform the public about critical facts, knowing that the public will not know the accurate specifics, and aware that&#8211;as Thrush says, outright&#8211;the mainstream press will not sufficiently (or at all) apprise the public of those fact.  </p>
<p>In other words: that Romneyism&#8211;the flagrant lying, con artistry, as the chief modus operandi&#8211;is now at the very heart of what the Republican Party is.</p>
<p>The public did catch on to Romney by the fall.  And, thanks largely to Obama’s statements at his press conference on Jan. 14 abou the debt ceiling, they caught on to that, as well.  And if Obama makes an effort to explain to the public basic Keynesian economics, and cites actual facts, actual statistics, about the fourth-quarter contraction, they’ll catch on this time, too.  And, maybe, finally, to the fact that the Republicans have decided upon a strategy of fraud in order to disassemble the social safety network, including Social Security and Medicare.  </p>
<p>In his State of the Union address, he’ll have an opportunity to finally educate the public about the actual causes of the Greek meltdown, of the actual effect of Tory austerity in Britain, of the actual cause of economic near-collapse in Spain, in Italy, in Ireland, in Iceland&#8211;and of the actual effect of the safety net in Germany, in Holland, and elsewhere.  And maybe he’ll even take that opportunity.  But the State of the Union address is two weeks away.  And in responding to Boehner’s tweet at #spendingistheproblem, there’s no time like the present.  Or at least like the next few days.  Just as with the fiscal cliff and the debt ceiling, the Republicans’ political leverage, whether real or fanciful, will turn out to be ephemeral.  </p>
<p>Unless Obama remains mute. 
<div></div>
<div>&#8212;-</div>
<div>UPDATE: Wow.  Either Greg Sargent is channeling me, or I’m channeling him.  He posted <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/plum-line/wp/2013/01/31/make-strong-case-that-spending-cuts-hurt-economy-mr-president/">this</a> one minute after I posted my post on AB. </div>
<p>But as I say in my post, Obama shouldn’t wait the two weeks until the State of the Union address to begin making the point.  Just as he didn’t wait a week until his inaugural address to explain to the public what “raising the debt ceiling” actually means&#8211;thus pulling the rug out from under Repubs’ disinformation campaign telling the public that it means increasing spending appropriations.  </p>
<p>Sargent titles his post “Make strong case that spending cuts hurt economy, Mr. President!”  (Amen.)  He points out: that</p>
<div dir="ltr">Unfortunately, at times, Obama has diluted this message. During his 2010 State of the Union speech, for instance, the President proposed a temporary spending freeze, and said:</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">“Families across the country are tightening their belts and making tough decisions. The federal government should do the same.”</div>
<div dir="ltr">  </div>
<p>But I think it’s a mischaracterization to describe that as a dilution of the Keynesian message.  It’s actually an outright misrepresentation of economic fact; that’s why that statement has been so detrimental.  And, if necessary, Obama should expressly acknowledge that this was misleading about economic fact, and then explain exactly why. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/john-boehner-says-defense-spending-is-the-problem-with-the-economy-awesome-updated.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Paul Ryan Says Taxes Should Be Raised to Pre-Bush-Tax-Cut Levels. But the Republicans Will Opt Instead For the “Sequester.” Unless, Of Course, the Koch Brothers Intervene.</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/paul-ryan-says-taxes-should-be-raised-to-pre-bush-tax-cut-levels-but-the-republicans-will-opt-instead-for-the-sequester-unless-of-course-the-koch-brothers-intervene.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/paul-ryan-says-taxes-should-be-raised-to-pre-bush-tax-cut-levels-but-the-republicans-will-opt-instead-for-the-sequester-unless-of-course-the-koch-brothers-intervene.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 31 Jan 2013 17:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[David Gregory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Keynesian economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Meet the Press]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the Koch brothers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the sequester]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/paul-ryan-says-taxes-should-be-raised-to-pre-bush-tax-cut-levels-but-the-republicans-will-opt-instead-for-the-sequester-unless-of-course-the-koch-brothers-intervene.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[There were three big political stories that came out of David Gregory’s fabulously interesting interview of Paul Ryan aired last Sunday on Meet the Press.  One was that Ryan said: Well, we can debate the efficacy of Keynesian economics or not. And I don’t obviously believe– I think the debt is pretty clear it doesn’t [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There were three big political stories that came out of David Gregory’s fabulously interesting interview of Paul Ryan aired last Sunday on Meet the Press.  One was that Ryan said: </p>
<div dir="ltr">Well, we can debate the efficacy of Keynesian economics or not. And I don’t obviously believe– I think the debt is pretty clear it doesn’t work.</div>
<p>Another was that he said that if Bill Clinton were president, we would have solved the budget-deficit problem, a statement that he presumably bases on the fact that when Bill Clinton was president, he solved the budget-deficit problem.</p>
<p>The third headline-grabber from that interview was that the Republicans will allow the “sequester” to take effect, presumably because they think it’s pretty clear that Keynesian economics doesn’t work, and because Bill Clinton is not longer president.  If Bill Clinton were president, the Republicans would allow him to raise tax rates to the level he did in 2001, this time without having to have the vice president cast the 51st vote in the Senate for the tax increase, and with enough Republican votes in the House to allow a vote on the tax increase.  </p>
<p>In other words, if Bill Clinton were president, Ryan and his compadres would not keep refusing to allow the Bush tax cuts on annual incomes of less than $450,000, and tax cuts on corporations, capital gains, and dividends, to expire.  But because Obama, rather than Clinton, is president, they won’t. They should be allowed to expire, Ryan says.  But they won’t be allowed to expire, because Obama is president.</p>
<p>Instead, the Republicans will opt to test out the the efficacy of Keynesian economics, or not&#8211;depending, probably, on whether <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/01/chuck-hagel-is-threat-to-americas.html">the Koch Brothers pick up the phone and disabuse Ryan of his belief that Keynesian economics doesn’t work</a>.  Before Wall Street does.  </p>
<p>Here’s what I obviously don’t believe: That if Ryan actually obviously doesn’t believe&#8211;thinks the debt is pretty clear it doesn’t work&#8211;he has even basic knowledge of past and current economic fact.</p>
<p>I’ll take his word for it that he was being truthful about his belief. But I sort of expect that the Koch brothers <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/business/economy/sequestration-looms-contractors-dont-fret/2013/01/30/3bcf60ea-6b0a-11e2-af53-7b2b2a7510a8_print.html">and others</a> will educate him and other congressional Republicans who hold that belief, very soon. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/paul-ryan-says-taxes-should-be-raised-to-pre-bush-tax-cut-levels-but-the-republicans-will-opt-instead-for-the-sequester-unless-of-course-the-koch-brothers-intervene.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Chuck Hagel Is a Threat to America’s National Security! And to the Koch Brothers’ Financial Interests.</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/chuck-hagel-is-a-threat-to-americas-national-security-and-to-the-koch-brothers-financial-interests.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/chuck-hagel-is-a-threat-to-americas-national-security-and-to-the-koch-brothers-financial-interests.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2013 19:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Chuck Hagel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CNBC]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Keynesian economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Meet the Press]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The American Future Fund]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the Koch brothers]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/chuck-hagel-is-a-threat-to-americas-national-security-and-to-the-koch-brothers-financial-interests.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The American Future Fund is an Iowa based 501(c)(4) tax-exempt organization affiliated with the Center to Protect Patient Rights, which in turn has reported ties to billionaires Charles G. Koch andDavid H. Koch. American Future Fund was founded by individuals who worked for Mitt Romney&#8216;s 2008 bid for the Republican U.S. Presidential nomination. Nick Ryan, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">The American Future Fund is an Iowa based <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/501(c)(4)">501(c)(4)</a> tax-exempt organization affiliated with the Center to Protect Patient Rights, which in turn has reported ties to billionaires <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_G._Koch">Charles G. Koch</a> and<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_H._Koch">David H. Koch</a>.</div>
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Future_Fund#cite_note-7"></a></p>
<div dir="ltr">American Future Fund was founded by individuals who worked for <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mitt_Romney">Mitt Romney</a>&#8216;s 2008 bid for the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republican_Party_(United_States)">Republican</a> U.S. Presidential nomination. Nick Ryan, an adviser to Republican US Representative <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jim_Nussle">Jim Nussle</a>, founded the organization in 2007, with Nicole Schlinger, a GOP leader in Iowa, as its president. Its current president is Iowa Republican state Sen. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sandra_Greiner">Sandra Greiner</a>.</div>
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Future_Fund#cite_note-10"></a>
<div dir="ltr">The fund &#8220;advocates <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conservative">conservative</a> and free-market principles&#8221; and energy positions that include support for drilling offshore and in the Alaska National Wildlife Refuge.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Activities </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">In 2010 the American Future Fund reported over 9 million dollars of independent campaign expenditures to the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal_Election_Commission">FEC</a>, and 100% of its expenditures benefited <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Republican_Party_(United_States)">Republicans</a>.</div>
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Future_Fund#cite_note-WP_Future_Fund_2010_spending-13"></a>
<div dir="ltr">In 2012 the organization funded ads supporting <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mitt_Romney">Mitt Romney</a>&#8216;s bid for the U.S. presidency. In the same year, it also funded ads attacking Missouri Attorney General <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chris_Koster">Chris Koster</a> and in support of California&#8217;s Proposition 32, which would prevent unions from collecting political contributions as paycheck deductions. </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">The organization does not disclose the names of those who have provided its funding.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Future_Fund">Wikipedia</a></div>
<p>Add to the Activities list an anti-Chuck Hagel TV ad. </p>
<p>Okay.  So I happened to catch a segment on CNBC just now (don’t ask; catching segments on CNBC is not quite part of my normal daily routine) that ended with an ad blasting Hagel for … um … a whole lot of stuff geared toward making people think he would have lots of conflicts of interest if confirmed as Secretary of Defense, even if he sells all those financial interests in defense contractor companies that the ad says he has, and in that company that invests in Iran, and stops flying on corporate jets. </p>
<p>At the end of the ad, the viewer is told that it’s sponsored by The American Future Fund.  Which I couldn’t identify from memory, since the names of these organizations all sound alike.  And are all very interested in America’s future.  </p>
<p>But, having seen the ad, I now knew that Hagel would be a very dangerous guy to have as Defense Secretary.  I just didn’t know who exactly he posed a danger to.  But thanks to Wikipedia, I know now.</p>
<p>Sounds to me like Paul Ryan should have consulted the Koch brothers before he declared on Meet the Press last weekend that Keynesian economics has proved to be a failure.  If you get my drift.  Those oil and gas subsidies and defense contracts <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Koch_Industries">that the Koch businesses receive</a> are important to our national defense &#8230; and to the economy.*
<div></div>
<div>*<i>Edited for clarity after initial posting.</i>
<div></div>
<div></div>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/chuck-hagel-is-a-threat-to-americas-national-security-and-to-the-koch-brothers-financial-interests.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
