<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>college &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Updated cost projections for the Pell Grant program</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/updated-cost-projections-for-the-pell-grant-program.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/updated-cost-projections-for-the-pell-grant-program.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 09 Feb 2013 17:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[college]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Pell grants]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[student debt]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[student loans]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/updated-cost-projections-for-the-pell-grant-program.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[New America points us to Pell Grant cost projections: The Congressional Budget Office this week released updated cost projections for the Pell Grant program – and the estimates show an unexpected surplus over the past several years. The figures are much awaited because they dictate what lawmakers must allocate to the program in the upcoming [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://edmoney.newamerica.net/blogposts/2013/new_pell_grant_estimates_buy_time_long_term_fix_still_needed-78890">New America</a> points us to Pell Grant cost projections:</p>
<blockquote><p>The Congressional Budget Office this week released <a href="http://www.cbo.gov/sites/default/files/cbofiles/attachments/43912_PellGrants.pdf">updated cost projections for the Pell Grant program</a> – and the estimates show an unexpected <em>surplus</em> over the past several years. The figures are much awaited because they dictate what lawmakers must allocate to the program in the upcoming fiscal year 2014 appropriations process if they want to keep the program running at its current level of benefits and with existing eligibility rules.<br />In 2010 and 2011, those estimates sparked panic. The program was burning through money faster than anyone expected, prompting Congress and the Obama administration to shift funding from other programs and cut parts of the Pell Grant program itself three separate times.</p>
<p>The funding emergency was exacerbated by the fact that congressional lawmakers and the Obama administration had tried to maintain a large increase in the maximum grant, first funded without any long-term funding plan by the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009. The latest round of temporary funding was set to dry up in 2014, leaving a $5.8 billion hole in the program. In 2015, the number would jump to $8.7 billion, and stay at about that level indefinitely.</p>
<p>Luckily for procrastinators in the White House and on Capitol Hill – and for Pell Grant supporters – the latest <a href="http://www.cbo.gov/sites/default/files/cbofiles/attachments/43912_PellGrants.pdf">Congressional Budget Office estimates</a> have come to their rescue. According to CBO, the program was actually <em>overfunded </em>the past few years, leaving a surplus of $9.2 billion. The CBO doesn’t give much explanation as to what changed. For that we’ll have to wait for the president.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/updated-cost-projections-for-the-pell-grant-program.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>&#034;No payment — no access code — no participation — lower final grade.&#034;</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/no-payment-no-access-code-no-participation-lower-final-grade.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/no-payment-no-access-code-no-participation-lower-final-grade.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Jul 2012 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[college]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[run 75441]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[textbooks]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/no-payment-no-access-code-no-participation-lower-final-grade.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Run 75441 &#8220;No payment — no access code — no participation — lower final grade.&#8221;Illustration by Jake Parker; http://www.agent44.com/http://heyoscarwilde.com/jake-parker-oliver-twist/ Now the use of textbooks and the sharing of a new textbook can be stopped with the sale of a yearly access code to engage in discussion boards by students with instructors. The Publishing Industry with the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Run 75441 <br /><i><br /></i><br /><i>&#8220;No</i> <i>payment — no access code — no participation — lower final grade.&#8221;</i><br /><i><br /></i><br /><a href="http://heyoscarwilde.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/09/jakeparker_olivertwist.jpg"><img alt="clip_image002" border="0" height="244" src="http://lh6.ggpht.com/-ntFggKB2PtI/T_n9Y5s1ZII/AAAAAAAAA5k/J4OuHtfkwok/clip_image002%25255B3%25255D.jpg?imgmax=800" title="clip_image002" width="201"></a><br />Illustration by Jake Parker; http://www.agent44.com/<br />http://heyoscarwilde.com/jake-parker-oliver-twist/</p>
<p>Now the use of textbooks and the sharing of a new textbook can be stopped with the sale of a yearly access code to engage in discussion boards by students with instructors. The Publishing Industry with the help of one Economics Professor has found a way to stop the sharing of text books amongst students and the sales of old text books to the next incoming classes. New students will be forced to buy a new text book or buy a special code allowing them to use the book new or old. The press release describing the new invention put it in this manner:</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p><i>&#8220;In the case of a used book or pirated download, the student pays for the access code,&#8221; according to the press release. &#8220;No payment — no access code — no participation — lower final grade.&#8221; <a href="http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/47969316/ns/technology_and_science-security/"><i>Professor Patents way . ..</i></a></i></p>
<p><i><i><a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/future_tense/2012/06/19/joseph_henry_vogel_s_patent_to_fight_textbook_piracy_.html" target="_blank">Grades of Students Who Pirate Would be Docked Under Prof&#8217;s Plan</a></i></i><br /><i><br /></i><br />Maybe it is just me, but an education which is increasingly  expensive and restrictive as the ways to shave a few dollars off of it are closed to those who only wish to achieve it  from using old text of which more times than naught are out of date after one year. The world and its knowledge turn much faster leaving students to beg for the obsolete education resources paid for by a hefty tuition<i>. </i></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/no-payment-no-access-code-no-participation-lower-final-grade.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
