<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>John McCain &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Apparently, Public Financing has been Very Good to John McCain</title>
		<link>./../../2008/11/apparently-public-financing-has-been-very-good-to-john-mccain.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/11/apparently-public-financing-has-been-very-good-to-john-mccain.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2008 05:43:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2008 presidential]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John McCain]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/11/apparently-public-financing-has-been-very-good-to-john-mccain.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[UPDATE II: An e-mail from Rick Davis clarifies the plans for the last moments of the campaign: On Monday, we will have a 14 state rally with our candidates crisscrossing the country trying to turn out our voters and sway the final undecided voters. Governor Palin will hit Ohio, Missouri, Iowa, Colorado, Nevada and Alaska [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>UPDATE II</strong>: An e-mail from Rick Davis clarifies the plans for the last moments of the campaign:<br />
<blockquote>On Monday, we will have a 14 state rally with our candidates crisscrossing the country trying to turn out our voters and sway the final undecided voters. Governor Palin will hit Ohio, Missouri, Iowa, Colorado, Nevada and Alaska in the final day of campaigning, while Senator McCain will travel from Tampa, Florida, to Virginia, then Pennsylvania, Indiana, New Mexico, Nevada and finish the night in Prescott, Arizona. The enthusiasm and excitement we generate on Monday will be the electricity that powers our &#8220;Get Out the Vote&#8221; efforts on Tuesday.</p></blockquote>
<p><strong>UPDATE</strong>: Via Dr. Black, Oliver Willis notes that the McCain campaign <em>deliberately</em> decided to <a href="http://www.oliverwillis.com/2008/10/31/disaster-looming/">eschew GOTV efforts in favor of spending their monies on television advertising</a>.</p>
<p>We all knew that John McCain doesn&#8217;t operate a computer, but he claims to watch football.  Did not he—or anyone in or, especially, running his campaign—see <a href="http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/6877753/">the dot.com Super Bowl commercials</a>, and wonder what happened to most of those companies?</p>
<p>Contrary to <a href="http://angrybear.blogspot.com/2008/10/best-spam-folder-e-mail-evah.html">previously</a> <a href="http://angrybear.blogspot.com/2008/10/follow-up-to-previous-spam.html">received</a> e-mails—and much recent whining—John McCain is <a href="http://edition.cnn.com/2008/POLITICS/10/31/campaign.wrap/index.html">ready and able to spend</a>:<br />
<blockquote>McCain and the Republican Party expect to outspend his Democratic rival, Sen. Barack Obama, by $10 million in the closing days of the campaign, Davis said. [emphases mine]</p></blockquote>
<p>and he will be traveling, though we&#8217;re not certain where:<br />
<blockquote>Trailing in the polls, Sen. John McCain will travel to seven states in one day as his presidential campaign enters its final hours, the Republican nominee&#8217;s campaign manager announced Friday.</p>
<p>McCain will campaign in seven cities Monday, just one day before Election Day, Rick Davis told reporters in a conference call. The final list of cities has not been finalized, Davis said.</p></blockquote>
<p>And the idea that they are in multiple states may or may not be CNN&#8217;s.  Developing&#8230;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/11/apparently-public-financing-has-been-very-good-to-john-mccain.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Always Tax Cuts for the Rich?</title>
		<link>./../../2008/10/always-tax-cuts-for-the-rich.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/10/always-tax-cuts-for-the-rich.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2008 08:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[economic stimulus]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John McCain]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/10/always-tax-cuts-for-the-rich.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Tom Bozzo The &#8216;McCain Resurgence Plan&#8217; surges on (h/t Creative Destruction): Current rules mandate that investors must begin to sell off their IRAs and 401Ks when they reach age 70 and one half years old. Those rules should be suspended to spare senior citizens from being forced to sell their stock just as the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Tom Bozzo</p>
<p>The &#8216;McCain Resurgence Plan&#8217; surges on (h/t <a href="http://gecon.blogspot.com/2008/10/mccains-economic-plan.html">Creative Destruction</a>):<br />
<blockquote>Current rules mandate that investors must begin to sell off their IRAs and 401Ks when they reach age 70 and one half years old. Those rules should be suspended to spare senior citizens from being forced to sell their stock just as the market is hurting the most. Under the emergency measure I propose, we will also cut the tax rate for withdrawals from tax-preferred retirement accounts to ten percent&#8230;</p>
<p>Fine, but this affects a small slice of the public and not necessarily those who are going to be hurt by the recession.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>&#8220;Small slice of the public&#8221; may be an understatement for the retirement plan changes.  Last time I checked, there was a 10 percent regular income tax bracket, and for 2008 a married couple has to have $16,050 in taxable income to clear it.  The top of the 15% bracket is $65,100.  So lower-income seniors get nothing except the right to defer tax-deferred plan withdrawals that they arguably cannot afford not to take, and most seniors get no more than 5 percent of their withdrawals.  The main beneficiaries are owners of tax-deferred retirement accounts that are so large that they can replace an income in roughly the top 25% (or better).</p>
<p>McCain<a href="http://www.johnmccain.com/Informing/News/Speeches/Read.aspx?guid=d51f366d-a4ba-4d55-99b5-0f1a39a67e20"> goes on</a>&#8230;<br />
<blockquote>It is essential that we avoid an exodus of capital from the market. Senator Obama yesterday offered up a proposal that would have the effect of encouraging early withdrawal of funds from 401(k) accounts, by suspending penalties through 2009. This is an invitation to capital flight, and therefore to continued instability in the market, at a moment when exactly the opposite is needed. Any family that takes part in this will not see the benefits of the market recovery that smart policy can help bring about. In my administration, we will instead revive the market by attracting new investment. I will cut in half the capital gains tax on stocks purchased and held for more than a year &#8212; from a rate of 15 to 7.5 percent.</p></blockquote>
<p>These provisions do not make exactly make Team McCain look in-touch.</p>
<p>First, people are raiding their 401(k)&#8217;s because defined contribution plan balances are often the only significant &#8220;savings&#8221; they have.  &#8220;Joe Sixpack,&#8221; as a certain vice-presidential candidate likes to say, doesn&#8217;t have appreciable amounts of money in assets that are potentially subject to capital gains tax.  (See, e.g., the <a href="http://www.federalreserve.gov/PUBS/oss/oss2/2004/scf2004home.html">Survey of Consumer Finances</a>.  In 2004, the median holdings for working families owning stocks and investment funds were $10,000 and $25,000, respectively.  But only 15 percent of all families owned stocks directly and 40 percent owned mutual funds, so majorities had nada.)  Eating one&#8217;s retirement capital is already a desperation measure, and Obama&#8217;s plan arguably relieves an injury following insults that are done deals.  Plus, Obama would keep in place the loss-of-income-tax-deferral disincentive and limit penalty-free withdrawals, so we aren&#8217;t talking carte blanche here.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, there is a fairness issue here, in that the &#8220;rich&#8221; — i.e. those with substantial financial asset holdings outside of retirement accounts — can dump their assets at will and McCain will if anything make the terms of such transactions more favorable.  It&#8217;s just us chumps with defined contribution plans who are tasked with riding out the crisis in McCain world.</p>
<p>Second, it&#8217;s not at all obvious what McCain could substantively mean by &#8220;capital flight.&#8221;  This, I suppose, is part of what has Brad DeLong <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/BradDelongsSemi-dailyJournal/~3/420662635/is-this-the-wor.html">scratching his head</a>.  Asset sales have to have two parties — the upshot is that someone exchanges money for an asset.  These transactions aren&#8217;t counted as savings in the NIPAs since all that happens is a change in ownership, and the macro statistics don&#8217;t care exactly who holds what.   Capital can&#8217;t be &#8220;fleeing&#8221; the market since someone has to buy in to complete the transaction, and desperate 401(k) raiders likely are not trying to invest their proceeds in foreign assets.  (That would be the rich dumping assets to stuff cash in tax havens.)</p>
<p>Third, if the stated policy aim is to keep people from selling assets, how on earth will reductions in taxes on asset sales — note that another part of the McCain plan is to increase capital losses that can be counted against income — do that?  The naive incentives of the plan make it a bit easier to sell, unless McCain is offering something other than the long-term capital gains rate cut that he seems to be selling.  Rich people who are sitting on long-term gains see their tax rate go, as Maynard of Creative Destruction puts it, from minuscule to infinitesimal.  So maybe that gun is set to run out of ammo anyway.  But when the case is made for capital gains tax cuts raising, or at least not losing, much revenue, the argument always seems to involve an element of capital gains realization timing: people time their asset sales to take advantage of the more favorable tax terms.</p>
<p>In any event, it is maybe not so surprising that a campaign of millionaires and lobbyists can&#8217;t put together a plan that isn&#8217;t a giveaway to themselves.  So the clown show at a train wreck goes on&#8230;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/10/always-tax-cuts-for-the-rich.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mc Cain sinks the Dow!</title>
		<link>./../../2008/10/mc-cain-sinks-the-dow.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/10/mc-cain-sinks-the-dow.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2008 13:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John McCain]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stock Market]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/10/mc-cain-sinks-the-dow.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Divorced one like Bush Concerned about the cause of the Dow? Not to fear. Many have been working on it such as Glenn Greenwald.The market does not like someone who is not like them so goes the Mc Cain clan. It is possible, but then Glenn asks for proof and finds an economist of [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Divorced one like Bush</p>
<p>Concerned about the cause of the Dow?  Not to fear.  Many have been working on it such as <a href="http://www.salon.com/opinion/greenwald/2008/10/13/obama/index.html">Glenn Greenwald</a>.The market does not like someone who is not like them so goes the Mc Cain clan.  It is possible, but then Glenn asks for proof and finds <a href="http://godly-fumigation.blogspot.com/2008/10/lies-damned-lies-and-statistics.html">an economist</a> of his nature who has discovered it is all due to McCain!  He has produced a chart proving it.<br /><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_ea3-LcbrX8A/SPSc1ge7eEI/AAAAAAAAAIk/C6CUaRCh9yY/s1600-h/Fun-with-charts.jpg"><img src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_ea3-LcbrX8A/SPSc1ge7eEI/AAAAAAAAAIk/C6CUaRCh9yY/s400/Fun-with-charts.jpg" border="0" alt=""></a></p>
<p>I&#8217;m convinced.  But, I&#8217;m going to wait for Cactus&#8217; review of this man&#8217;s work.</p>
<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/10/mc-cain-sinks-the-dow.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Guy Who Will Say Anything to Get Elected</title>
		<link>./../../2008/10/the-guy-who-will-say-anything-to-get-elected.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/10/the-guy-who-will-say-anything-to-get-elected.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2008 12:22:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Health Care]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Housing Prices]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John McCain]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/10/the-guy-who-will-say-anything-to-get-elected.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Tom Bozzo Brad DeLong blogs the train wreck at a clown show that is the McCain campaign so I don&#8217;t have to (big report due in a week, sorry ). He has a twofer. First, there&#8217;s the the McCain health plan. Or, rather, the evolution from We&#8217;re phoning it in, to OMG, people are [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Tom Bozzo</p>
<p><a href="http://delong.typepad.com/sdj/2008/10/cant-anybody-pl.html">Brad DeLong blogs</a> the train wreck at a clown show that is the McCain campaign so I don&#8217;t have to (big report due in a week, sorry ).  He has a twofer.</p>
<p>First, there&#8217;s the the McCain health plan.  Or, rather, the evolution from</p>
<p>We&#8217;re phoning it in, to</p>
<p>OMG, people are <a href="http://angrybear.blogspot.com/2008/09/mccains-health-plan-tax-cut-or-tax-hike.html">looking at it and figuring out ways it might suck</a>, so</p>
<p>Sweeten it, but&#8230;</p>
<p>That&#8217;s too expensive for our small-government-conservative narrative, and voila,</p>
<p>Let&#8217;s commit political suicide!!<br />
<blockquote>You know, we have llike seen this before. On health care:</p>
<ul>
<li>McCain started with a tax credit that was equal in aggregate to the additional tax he levied on employer-sponsored health benefits in the first year&#8211;in later years the credit became much smaller than the tax.</li>
<li>Then it was like ooops, that&#8217;s not popular. We know&#8211;we never intended to subject employer-sponsored benefits to the FICA tax, only to the income tax.</li>
<li>Then it was like ooops, now we&#8217;re scared that the plan is fiscally irresponsible and will raise the deficit. We know&#8211;we will cut Medicare!</li>
<li>Then it was like ooops, we have to carry Floria. We know&#8211;have Sarah Palin say that McCain will not cut but will protect your entitlements.</li>
</ul>
<p>Can&#8217;t anybody play this game? If we lose the election to these clowns, I am going to be really embarrassed. It seems as though nothing is competently staffed out&#8211;as if nobody in the McCain campaign cares about actually having policy proposals, but only about having something incoherent that an ignorant and lazy reporter can be deceived into thinking is a policy proposal.</p></blockquote>
<p>Second, on the housing crisis, McCain pulls his new bailout plan out of his behind at the &#8220;debate.&#8221;  However:<br />
<blockquote>But it soon develops that much of Senator McCain&#8217;s proposal is not his but Barney Frank&#8217;s, and that the differences make it not a homeowner relief bill but an imprudent banker profit and rescue bill.</p></blockquote>
<p>And so our so-called conservatives want to nationalize negative home equity (that&#8217;s some concern for the taxpayer, there):<br />
<blockquote>[DeLong quoting the Politco] “Clearly we face the trade off that we would in fact be taking the negative equity position and putting it on the taxpayers books instead of putting it on the private lenders books or the homeowners books,” Holtz-Eakin told Politico. “We think the balance of risk has shifted to the point where this is the way to go.”</p></blockquote>
<p>Does the McCain website say that?  No.<br />
<blockquote>But by the time I got to the website, it read differently:</p>
<blockquote><p>JohnMcCain.com &#8211; McCain-Palin 2008: For those that cannot make payments, mortgages must be re-structured to put losses on the books and put homeowners in manageable mortgages. <s>Lenders in these cases must recognize the loss that they’ve already suffered.</s> [Apparently that last sentence was struck by a panicked editor &#8212; ATB.]</p></blockquote>
<p>Apparently the schmuck who was assigned the job of writing up the web description did not believe the plan could possibly be what he was told it was.</p></blockquote>
<p>Most deliciously, someone couldn&#8217;t stop from thinking out loud in naming the &#8220;program,&#8221; such as it is: it&#8217;s the &#8220;American Homeownership Resurgence Plan (McCain Resurgence Plan).&#8221;  Apparently it&#8217;s change someone can believe in.</p>
<p>(Cross-posted at Marginal Utility.)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/10/the-guy-who-will-say-anything-to-get-elected.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Ms Parker, Mc Cain, Party and Honor</title>
		<link>./../../2008/09/ms-parker-mc-cain-party-and-honor.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/09/ms-parker-mc-cain-party-and-honor.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2008 05:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[honor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John McCain]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Palin]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/09/ms-parker-mc-cain-party-and-honor.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Divorced one like Bush Before we get to excited about Ms. Parker&#8217;s recent calling out, consider her 9/5 opinion in What Sarah Palin brings to the Republican Party: And relief that the first Republican woman on a presidential ticket wasn’t going to let them down. No one was going to be embarrassed by John [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Divorced one like Bush</p>
<p>Before we get to excited about Ms. Parker&#8217;s recent calling out, consider her 9/5 opinion in <a href="http://www.tcpalm.com/news/2008/sep/05/kathleen-parker-what-sarah-palin-brings-republican/">What Sarah Palin brings to the Republican Party</a>:<br />
<blockquote>And relief that the first Republican woman on a presidential ticket wasn’t going to let them down. <strong>No one was going to be embarrassed</strong> by John McCain’s maverick pick.</p></blockquote>
<p> Referring to Palin&#8217;s convention speech:<br />
<blockquote>Palin delivered&#8230;What she showed was strength, conviction, determination, confidence, a willingness to rumble and fearlessness. No caribou caught in the headlights, she.</p></blockquote>
<p>I guess Ms. Parker is referring to herself here:<br />
<blockquote>Whatever conclusions the punditry might draw from Palin’s remarks, we can be fairly certain that Middle America felt nothing but redemption and salvation.</p></blockquote>
<p>Ms. Parker note&#8217;s Palin was the savior to the point of being Democratic like:<br />
<blockquote>Behind closed doors around the Twin Cities, talk focused on the need for new templates, new models. Republicans have to communicate that they, too, care about the issues Democrats have claimed as their own — education, health and the environment. They need new ideas and new — younger — faces to deliver the message.</p>
<p>Voila. Enter Palin.</p>
<p>She has animated voters who had little enthusiasm for the race. She has given them the very thing Democrats have been enjoying the past several months: hope and change.</p></blockquote>
<p>In the end, did Ms. Parker know she was so prophetic?<br />
<blockquote>That’s potent medicine. It also should come with a warning label: “May cause delusions and a false sense of power.”</p></blockquote>
<p>Ironic no?  Of course, maybe Ms. Parker really knew what was real and was hedging her bets.  But that would mean all the good stuff written on 9/5/08 was just BS?    Well by 9/22 she was coming out of the <a href="http://www.news-press.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20080922/OPINION/809220331/1015">delusion and sense of power</a>. </p>
<p>The 9/5/08 opinion and her now calling for Mrs. Palin to step down pretty much confirms that McCain et al&#8217;s campaign has been and is nothing more than one man&#8217;s quest for a trophy to the exclusion of the calling he so desires.  Palin stepping down vs McCain firing her will not change the fact that she was chosen as a coach picks a play and a player.  It&#8217;s all about the trophy.  It&#8217;s just a game, about the win of the contest.  Not about the win of the ideology of governance as Ms. Parker would have us believe. </p>
<p>Face it Ms. Parker, the only way for Mc Cain et al to save face and affirm that his campaign is about the country is to keep Palin.  It is the only way to show conviction of his professed American ideals.  If he looses the election on his ideals, he has no shame.  If Palin goes, he perjures his entire campaign. </p>
<p>I hear Mc Cain is an honorable man.  Is he?  It is his honor, Ms Parker, that you are holding in your hands with this call.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/09/ms-parker-mc-cain-party-and-honor.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Annals of Intellectual Bankruptcy</title>
		<link>./../../2008/09/annals-of-intellectual-bankruptcy.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/09/annals-of-intellectual-bankruptcy.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2008 01:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[bailout]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John McCain]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/09/annals-of-intellectual-bankruptcy.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Tom Bozzo Who&#8217;da thunk: Hank Paulson&#8217;s blank check giveaway plan turns out to be the best answer to the financial crisis the Republicans can come up with: Towards the end, McCain finally spoke up, mentioning a counter-proposal that had been offered by some conservative House Republicans, which would suspend the capital gains tax for [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Tom Bozzo</p>
<p>Who&#8217;da thunk: Hank Paulson&#8217;s blank check giveaway plan turns out to be the best <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2008/09/25/at-white-house-mccain-pla_n_129438.html">answer to the financial crisis the Republicans can come up with</a>:<br />
<blockquote>Towards the end, McCain finally spoke up, mentioning a counter-proposal that had been offered by some conservative House Republicans, which would suspend the capital gains tax for two years and provide tax incentives to encourage firms that buy up bad debt. McCain did not discuss specifics of the plan, though&#8230;</p></blockquote>
<p>I think we know what the &#8216;specifics&#8217; are:</p>
<p>1. Tax cuts for the rich!<br />2. ???<br />3. A chicken in every pot and a horseless carriage in every garage!!11!</p>
<p>Meanwhile, the decisive leader who would never poke a digit into the political wind&#8230;<br />
<blockquote>&#8230;was non-committal about supporting it.</p></blockquote>
<p>And the other Republican excuse for a leader?<br />
<blockquote>At another point in the meeting, President Bush chimed in, &#8220;If money isn&#8217;t loosened, this sucker could go down&#8221; &#8212; and by sucker he meant economy.</p></blockquote>
<p>Looks like I picked the <a href="http://www.ft.com/indepth/global-financial-crisis">wrong</a> <a href="http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/7647d4d4-8b33-11dd-b634-0000779fd18c.html">week</a> to <a href="http://us.imdb.com/title/tt0080339/quotes">stop sniffing glue</a>.</p>
<p>Added: See also <a href="http://time-blog.com/curious_capitalist/2008/09/the_republican_alternatives_to.html">Justin Fox</a> via <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/BradDelongsSemi-dailyJournal/~3/403419091/justin-fox-on-t.html">Brad DeLong</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/09/annals-of-intellectual-bankruptcy.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Now is the time to start worrying</title>
		<link>./../../2008/09/now-is-the-time-to-start-worrying.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/09/now-is-the-time-to-start-worrying.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2008 21:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2008 presidential]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bailout]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John McCain]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/09/now-is-the-time-to-start-worrying.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Remember that plan of Patrick Ruffini&#8217;s, that McCain should run against whatever plan is developed: For McCain and other Republicans, voting &#8220;no&#8221; on Paulson without accepting the consequences of that vote is the political equivalent of a bottomless crack pipe: it will please the conservative &#8220;base,&#8221; distance them from both Bush and &#8220;Washington,&#8221; and let [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Remember that <a href="http://digbysblog.blogspot.com/2008/09/opening-for-maverick-by-digby-ed.html">plan of Patrick Ruffini&#8217;s</a>, that McCain should run against whatever plan is developed:<br />
<blockquote>For McCain and other Republicans, voting &#8220;no&#8221; on Paulson without accepting the consequences of that vote is the political equivalent of a bottomless crack pipe: it will please the conservative &#8220;base,&#8221; distance them from both Bush and &#8220;Washington,&#8221; and let them indulge in both anti-government and anti-corporate demagoguery, even as Democrats bail out their Wall Street friends and big investors generally. You simply can&#8217;t imagine a better way for McCain to decisively reinforce his simultaneous efforts to pander to the &#8220;base&#8221; while posing as a &#8220;maverick.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>Well, that strategy appears to have become about as useful as abstinence training in Alaska.  Taking its place is <a href="http://conservativereader.net/wordpress/2008/09/24/mccain-will-suspend-campaign-requests-postponing-debate/">the &#8220;take-charge, we-don&#8217;t-need-no-stinking-debate&#8221; MAVERICK</a>:<br />
<blockquote> I do not believe that the [ill-considered $700,000,000,000 bailout] plan on the table will pass as it currently stands, and we are running out of time.</p>
<p>Tomorrow morning, I will suspend my campaign and return to Washington after speaking at the Clinton Global Initiative. I have spoken to Senator Obama and informed him of my decision and have asked him to join me.</p>
<p>I am calling on the President to convene a meeting with the leadership from both houses of Congress, including Senator Obama and myself. It is time for both parties to come together to solve this problem.</p>
<p>We must meet as Americans, not as Democrats or Republicans, and we must meet until this crisis is resolved. I am directing my campaign to work with the Obama campaign and the commission on presidential debates to delay Friday night’s debate until we have taken action to address this crisis.</p></blockquote>
<p>But don&#8217;t worry; it won&#8217;t take long:<br />
<blockquote>I am confident that before the markets open on Monday we can achieve consensus on legislation that will stabilize our financial markets, protect taxpayers and homeowners, and earn the confidence of the American people. All we must do to achieve this is temporarily set politics aside, and I am committed to doing so.</p></blockquote>
<p>This is the clearest sign yet that the Administration is about to agree to everything  Senator Dodd requested: John McCain wants to take part of the credit.</p>
<p>Be Afraid.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/09/now-is-the-time-to-start-worrying.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The WSJ editorial page slams&#8230;John McCain</title>
		<link>./../../2008/09/the-wsj-editorial-page-slams-john-mccain.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/09/the-wsj-editorial-page-slams-john-mccain.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2008 16:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[21st Century economic philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John McCain]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[regulation]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/09/the-wsj-editorial-page-slams-john-mccain.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Ken Houghton It was five degrees (C) warmer here this morning than the previous two days of taking the Eldest Daughter to her school bus. Presumably, this is balanced out in part by record-low temperatures in Hell, as the WSJ editorial page (well, Thomas Frank, but still&#8230;) summarizes the McCain Position: Last week, Republican [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Ken Houghton</p>
<p>It was five degrees (C) warmer here this morning than the previous two days of taking the Eldest Daughter to her school bus.</p>
<p>Presumably, this is balanced out in part by record-low temperatures in Hell, as the WSJ editorial page (well, Thomas Frank, but still&#8230;) summarizes <a href="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB122221440058969313.html?mod=djemEditorialPage">the McCain Position</a>:<br />
<blockquote>Last week, Republican presidential candidate John McCain called for a commission to &#8220;find out what went wrong&#8221; on Wall Street. It was an excellent suggestion: Public inquiries into Wall Street practices served the country well in the 1930s.</p>
<p>And Mr. McCain has a special advantage to bring to any such investigation &#8212; many of the relevant witnesses are friends or colleagues of his. In fact, he can probably get to the bottom of the whole mess just by cross-examining the people riding on his campaign bus. So the candidate should take a deep breath, remind himself that the country comes first, pull the Straight Talk Express over at a rest stop, whistle up his media pals, and begin.</p></blockquote>
<p>Go read <a href="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB122221440058969313.html?mod=djemEditorialPage">the whole thing</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/09/the-wsj-editorial-page-slams-john-mccain.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>From the Horse&#8217;s [Mouth]</title>
		<link>./../../2008/09/from-the-horses-mouth.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/09/from-the-horses-mouth.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2008 22:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[credit crisis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John McCain]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[regulation]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/09/from-the-horses-mouth.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[By Steam Fangs Palin (Tom Bozzo) On 60 Minutes, John McCain helped resolve a couple of issues that occupied the comments last week. Q1. Did McCain support Gramm-Leach-Bliley? A: Yes, and he still does! PELLEY: In 1999, you were one of the Senators who helped pass deregulation of Wall Street. Do you regret that now? [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By Steam Fangs Palin  (Tom Bozzo)</p>
<p>On 60 Minutes, John McCain helped resolve a couple of issues that occupied the comments last week.</p>
<p>Q1. Did McCain <a href="http://www.haloscan.com/comments/angrybear/5968654274175468894/#721028">support Gramm-Leach-Bliley</a>?
<p>A: Yes, and he still does!</p>
</p>
<blockquote><p>PELLEY: In 1999, you were one of the Senators who helped pass deregulation of  Wall Street. Do you regret that now?</p>
<p>MCCAIN: No.  I think the deregulation was probably  helpful to the growth of our economy.</p>
</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(Quote via <a href="http://firedoglake.com/2008/09/22/mccain-doesnt-regret-financial-dergulation-says-it-was-helpful/">Firedoglake</a>.)</p>
<p>Q2. Is McCain going to <a href="http://www.haloscan.com/comments/angrybear/5968654274175468894/#721138">outflank Obama with a populist volte-face on the bailout</a>? (See also <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2008/09/21/excess-of-responsibility/">Krugman</a>.)</p>
<p>A: Not as long as reporters can recall their ability to do a Google.  <a href="http://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/20080921/ap_on_el_pr/financial_meltdown_candidates;_ylt=AiyilNMMPbkRo1vD2UBk2EGs0NUE">Via the AP</a>:<br />
<blockquote>In the [60 Minutes] interview, McCain defended the Bush administration&#8217;s proposed bailout of financial firms as necessary, though he acknowledged it could get expensive.</p>
<p>&#8220;We&#8217;re going to take over these bad loans,&#8221; McCain said. &#8220;And we&#8217;re going to have the taxpayer help you out. But when the time comes and the economy recovers, then anything that&#8217;s gained back is going to go to the taxpayers first.</p>
<p>&#8220;I&#8217;m not saying this isn&#8217;t going to be messy. And I&#8217;m not saying it isn&#8217;t going to be expensive. But we have to stop the bleeding,&#8221; McCain said.</p></blockquote>
<p>None of this is to say that McCain won&#8217;t continue his pattern of <a href="http://www.thecarpetbaggerreport.com/flipflops">rampant flip-flopping</a> by at least trying to stake out positions both for and against the bailout — as Obama deftly calls it, an &#8220;<a href="http://tpmelectioncentral.talkingpointsmemo.com/2008/09/obama_on_economy_mccain_has_ha.php">election-time conversion</a>&#8221; — or running against all the fatcats <a href="http://tpmelectioncentral.talkingpointsmemo.com/2008/09/mccain_calls_for_end_to_the_ty.php">except for Carly Fiorina</a> and Phil Gramm (worth every penny!).  And it stands to reason that the Republicans will <a href="http://digbysblog.blogspot.com/2008/09/opening-for-maverick-by-digby-ed.html">run against the &#8220;horrible big-government program&#8221;</a> of the Bush administration, though of course they&#8217;ll also run against the Democrats for obstructing the vital economic recovery program of the Bush administration as the situation presents itself.</p>
<p>PLUS: Mirabile dictu, could it be that congressional Democrats are getting the Administration to<a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=20601087&#038;sid=a4q2..MUPsoA&#038;refer=home"> concede to the major features of the bailout plan a la Dodd and Frank</a>?* With, in particular, equity dilution now part of the deal with Treasury, the revised bailout (Dodd discussion draft <a href="http://www.politico.com/static/PPM41_ayo08b28.html">here</a>) looks to be a huge substantive improvement over the DOA blank-check plan, and has garnered early favorable reviews from <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/CalculatedRisk/~3/399987786/dodd-plan.html">CR</a>, <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2008/09/22/dodd/">Krugman</a>, and (with some more specifics) <a href="http://www.creditslips.org/creditslips/2008/09/the-dodd-bailou.html">Adam Levitin</a> at Credit Slips.  Bloomberg suggests that Republicans may bolt, but they won&#8217;t make things easy for McCain if they end up opposing the plan for being too tough on financial executives and too easy on stressed homeowners.</p>
<p>* From one perspective, this could be terrifying as it may signal that Treasury really sees itself as staring into the abyss.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/09/from-the-horses-mouth.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Dep&#8217;t of WTF (McCain and Economic Crisis Management)</title>
		<link>./../../2008/09/dept-of-wtf-mccain-and-economic-crisis-management.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/09/dept-of-wtf-mccain-and-economic-crisis-management.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2008 15:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[candidate econ advisors]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[credit crisis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John McCain]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/09/dept-of-wtf-mccain-and-economic-crisis-management.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[At Americablog, Robert Arena writes: Watching John McCain&#8217;s economics speech in Wisconsin. It&#8217;s like watching a modern day Herbert Hoover live. He really doesn&#8217;t get it&#8230; &#8211; He went through a castigation of the Fed and basically told them to stay out of this &#8211; I mean, does he really not understand that the Fed [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>At <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/Americablog/~3/397216527/john-mccains-herbert-hoover-speech.html">Americablog</a>, Robert Arena writes:<br />
<blockquote>Watching John McCain&#8217;s  economics speech in Wisconsin. It&#8217;s like watching a modern day <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herbert_Hoover">Herbert Hoover</a> live. He  really doesn&#8217;t get it&#8230;<br />
<blockquote>&#8211; He went through a castigation of the Fed and basically told them to stay out  of this &#8211; I mean, does he really not understand that the Fed was designed to  regulate the financial markets? These investment and insurance companies, given  their enormous size, are effectively a part of the financial services system.  That was the rationale for <a href="http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/405796/nationalization">nationalizing</a>  them instead of letting them fail. The Fed has been doing exactly what they are  supposed to. Now the Treasury Department, that&#8217;s a different question &#8211; does  McCain know the difference? After years on the Commerce Committee one would  expect so, but maybe not.</p></blockquote>
</blockquote>
<p>Exaggeration?  This is the <a href="http://www.johnmccain.com/Informing/News/Speeches/9a604256-0519-46e6-a1ce-e70798b39ec2.htm">text of the Green Bay speech</a> from the McCain website:<br />
<blockquote>Finally, the Federal Reserve should get back to its core business of responsibly managing our money supply and inflation. It needs to get out of the business of bailouts. The Fed needs to return to protecting the purchasing power of the dollar. A strong dollar will reduce energy and food prices. It will stimulate sustainable economic growth and get this economy moving again.</p></blockquote>
<p>Does McCain really think that the economy would be in better shape if Ben Bernanke and company hadn&#8217;t been trying everything in the books to counteract the crisis?  If so, on what basis?  Could he possibly have a clue as to, e.g., what happens to the money supply in a credit crunch?  Whether the Fed&#8217;s crisis management policies have constituted economic stimulus?  (This is not to say that Bernanke and the Fed are infallible by any stretch of the imagination, but as Brad DeLong suggests, we at least want them to avoid the known gross <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/BradDelongsSemi-dailyJournal/~3/396512969/is-2008-our-192.html">mistakes of the past</a>.)</p>
<p>What&#8217;s arguably worse is that this represents some form of his advisers&#8217; &#8220;wisdom.&#8221;  Which is to say, as a big picture matter neither McCain nor his economic advisers deserve to be let anywhere near the tiller of the metaphorical supertanker.</p>
<p>Added: <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/BradDelongsSemi-dailyJournal/~3/397365284/john-mccain--19.html">DeLong concurs</a>&#8230; also <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/espeak/~3/397517157/mccain-on-federal-reserve-policy-dont.html">PGL at EconoSpeak</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/09/dept-of-wtf-mccain-and-economic-crisis-management.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
