<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>media pundits &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>A President Who&#8217;ll Cut Social Security &#8212; And Liberals Who Love Him Too Much</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/a-president-wholl-cut-social-security-and-liberals-who-love-him-too-much.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/a-president-wholl-cut-social-security-and-liberals-who-love-him-too-much.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2013 04:22:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[liberals]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[media pundits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/a-president-wholl-cut-social-security-and-liberals-who-love-him-too-much.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Richard Eskow  points us to a trend with liberals media types and Social Security: A President Who&#8217;ll Cut Social Security &#8212; And Liberals Who Love Him Too Much The spectacle of a supposedly liberal president repeatedly and needlessly trying to cut Social Security is enough to bring a reasonable, economically literate person to the point [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/rj-eskow/a-president-wholl-cut-soc_b_2835274.html%22Richard">Richard Eskow</a>  points us to a trend with liberals media types and Social Security:</p>
<blockquote><p>A President Who&#8217;ll Cut Social Security &#8212; And Liberals Who Love Him Too Much</p>
<p>The spectacle of a supposedly liberal president repeatedly and needlessly trying to cut Social Security is enough to bring a reasonable, economically literate person to the point of existential despair. To see leading liberal lights like Rachel Maddow and Ezra Klein chuckle indulgently at those foolish Republicans in Congress over the subject &#8212; <i>Don&#8217;t they know he&#8217;s already giving them what they want? </i>&#8212; is to risk plunging into the depths of that despair.</p>
<p>This week the president hosted a dinner for Republicans leaders where he worked to sell his budget proposal, including his harmful plan to cut benefits through the &#8220;chained CPI.&#8221; National Security was the main course and Social Security was the dessert. And guess who <i>wasn&#8217;t</i> coming to dinner: The elderly, the disabled, or any policy experts who understand the disastrous implications of the chained CPI.</p>
<p>The Maddow/Klein exchange (which we&#8217;ll bring to you as soon as a transcript is available) is the crest of a building wave in pro-Democratic Party commentary which says, as <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/wonkblog/wp/2013/03/01/what-we-have-here-is-a-failure-to-communicate/">Klein</a> puts it, that &#8220;what we have here is a failure to communicate.&#8221; Klein says that at least &#8220;some of the gridlock (in Washington) is due to poor information.&#8221; Jonathan Chait <a href="http://nymag.com/daily/intelligencer/2013/03/would-teaching-republicans-about-obama-help.html">bemoans</a> the fact that Republicans &#8220;won&#8217;t acknowledge [Obama&#8217;s] actual offer, which includes large cuts to retirement programs.&#8221;</p>
<p>&#8230;</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>But Democrats like Maddow, Klein, and Chait know better. They know exactly what Obama&#8217;s been trying to do.  And their only complaint seems to be that he&#8217;s not doing effectively enough. We&#8217;re not hearing much from the &#8216;left&#8217; side of the debate about the profound flaws, biases, and inherent cynicism behind both the President&#8217;s policy and his rhetoric.</p>
<p>Here are the facts:<br />1.Research suggests that Social Security cost-of-living increases are already inadequate. (See studies on &#8220;CPI-E&#8221; for more details on the best ways to increase them.)</p>
<p>2.Obama&#8217;s proposed chained-CPI cut would typically reduce benefits for 3 percent, and by as much as 6 percent for some recipients.</p>
<p>3.The White House&#8217;s decision to label this cut the &#8220;superlative CPI&#8221; is grotesque. It suggests that elderly women who receive an average of $950 or so per month are receiving &#8220;superlative&#8221; benefit increases each year.</p>
<p>4.The administration&#8217;s insistence on speaking of &#8220;entitlement reform,&#8221; mixing Medicare (which has a real cost problem because of our for-profit health system) with Social Security, is a cheap trick first devised by Republican consultants.</p></blockquote>
<p>(hat tip Nancy Ortiz)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/a-president-wholl-cut-social-security-and-liberals-who-love-him-too-much.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
