<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Pigou club &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The End of the Affair?</title>
		<link>./../../2008/06/the-end-of-the-affair.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/06/the-end-of-the-affair.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2008 20:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Pigou club]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transportation]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/06/the-end-of-the-affair.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In cross-price elasticity of demand news, a story on the AP wire notes that, for the first time in ages, Toyota&#8217;s Camry and Corolla cars both outsold Ford&#8217;s full-size F-150 pickup truck. [*] It&#8217;s arguably worse even than that for Ford&#8217;s truck business, since neither the Corolla (52,826 units sold) nor the Camry (51,291) was [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In cross-price elasticity of demand news, a <a href="http://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/20080603/ap_on_bi_ge/auto_sales">story on the AP wire</a> notes that, for the first time in ages, Toyota&#8217;s Camry and Corolla cars both outsold Ford&#8217;s full-size F-150 pickup truck. [*]</p>
<p>It&#8217;s arguably worse even than that for Ford&#8217;s truck business, since neither the Corolla (<a href="http://www.toyota.com/about/news/corporate/2008/06/03-1-sales.html">52,826 units sold</a>) nor the Camry (51,291) was the top-selling vehicle in the U.S. last month; that award goes to the Honda Civic (<a href="http://www.hondanews.com/categories/1097/releases/4528">53,299</a>).  As Honda also sold 43,728 Accords, that bumps the mighty pickup into 5th and 6th place for Ford and Chevy respectively.</p>
<p>In fact, poring over the gruesome sales numbers from the Domestic Three, it looks like $4 gasoline is enough to undermine the market for larger &#8216;crossover&#8217; SUVs, without which measured truck sales would be even worse.  (Crossovers are trucks partly for regulatory reasons and partly for marketing reasons; the features that let them pass for regulatory trucks put them at a considerable fuel-economy disadvantage compared to the few proper wagons that the auto industry deigns to sell in the U.S.) No surprise, then, that there&#8217;s quite a bit of belated scrambling to &#8220;<a href="http://media.gm.com/servlet/GatewayServlet?target=http://image.emerald.gm.com/gmnews/viewmonthlyreleasedetail.do?domain=74&#038;docid=46161">build on car momentum</a>&#8221; in industry-speak.</p>
<p>And as many of you have seen, that&#8217;s hitting <a href="http://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/20080603/ap_on_bi_ge/gm_factories">the Domestic Three&#8217;s manufacturing employment</a>:<br />
<blockquote>General Motors is closing four truck and SUV plants in the U.S., Canada and Mexico as surging fuel prices is hastening a dramatic shift to smaller vehicles.</p>
<p>CEO Rick Wagoner said Tuesday before the automaker&#8217;s annual meeting the plants to be closed are in Oshawa, Ontario; Moraine, Ohio; Janesville, Wis.; and Toluca, Mexico. He also said the Hummer brand may be discontinued.</p></blockquote>
<p>Janesville is not far from Madison, and it was considered something of a coup at the time when Janesville retained its lines for GM&#8217;s large pickups and SUVs.  However, the truck market had already peaked by the time the current models had reached production a couple years ago.  Unfortunately for the 2000-odd GM employees (and a number of local employees of GM suppliers), GM&#8217;s product planners don&#8217;t have anything more marketable for them to build there.</p>
<p>[*] The story was edited to reflect later-arriving sales figures.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/06/the-end-of-the-affair.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>(Albufeira, Portugal) Congestion Pricing at Work?</title>
		<link>./../../2008/05/albufeira-portugal-congestion-pricing-at-work.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/05/albufeira-portugal-congestion-pricing-at-work.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2008 10:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Pigou club]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transportation]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/05/albufeira-portugal-congestion-pricing-at-work.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Yesterday afternoon, a trio of fellow Conference on Postal and Delivery Economics attendees and I were marveling at the emptiness of the A2 motorway connecting the southern exburbs of Lisbon and the Algarve region. Certainly, there is not a whole lot of stuff en route, but you could say the same thing about a lot [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday afternoon, a trio of fellow <a href="http://crri.rutgers.edu/references/post/index.html">Conference on Postal and Delivery Economics</a> attendees and I were marveling at the emptiness of the A2 motorway connecting the southern exburbs of Lisbon and the Algarve region.  Certainly, there is not a whole lot of stuff en route, but you could say the same thing about a lot of points 250 km apart along the Interstate highway system west of the Mississippi River; those are not that lightly-traveled.</p>
<p>There are income and substitution effects to consider: Portugal&#8217;s per-capita GDP is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Economy_of_the_European_Union#Economic_variation">75% of the EU average</a> (or less than 2/3ds that of Rich Europe), and fuel was dear at around €1.50/liter — though the preponderance of small diesel-powered cars implies a much smaller difference in per-km costs versus the U.S. than you&#8217;d get from the pump price.  But one of the bigger hits was the toll of almost €19.  A 150-km ride on the Pennsylvania Turnpike a couple weeks ago for another conference was $4; the Illinois Northwest Tollway, highly congested in the Chicago suburbs and exurbs, only hits you up for $2 between the Wisconsin state line and the toll-free city Chicago expressways if you use the system enough to shell out for an I-Pass transponder (they price-discriminate by charging twice the I-Pass toll for cash, which for all I know may be going on here, too).</p>
<p>This makes me think that the main concern for the privatization of tollways is less the outsourcing of toll-raising dirty work to the private sector so much as whether the states are adequately compensated for such right to raise the tolls as they sell. (*)</p>
<p>* To possibly forestall certain lines of comments, I don&#8217;t actually support government eating-of-capital as a politically expedient alternative to raising other taxes.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/05/albufeira-portugal-congestion-pricing-at-work.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
