<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>cats &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Stories About Cats</title>
		<link>./../../2008/03/stories-about-cats.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/03/stories-about-cats.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2008 14:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[cats]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/03/stories-about-cats.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Everybody needs a hobby. Long time readers may be aware I feed feral cats. I used to do it every day until I moved&#8230; then I found a nice Israeli lady who took over my route on weekdays, but since she can&#8217;t make it on weekends, I still drive back out there every Saturday and [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Everybody needs a hobby. Long time readers may be aware I feed feral cats. I used to do it every day until I moved&#8230; then I found a nice Israeli lady who took over my route on weekdays, but since she can&#8217;t make it on weekends, I still drive back out there every Saturday and Sunday. I used to have as many as 18, um, customers, scattered in about eight different feeding stations, but construction in the area, plus neutering, have dwindled the numbers down to four cats, who get fed in three different areas.</p>
<p>(The entire area is slated for construction &#8211; an outdoor mini-mall and condos. If/when it happens, I don&#8217;t know what will happen to the remaining cats. There aren&#8217;t places to relocate them and I&#8217;m in position to take in another.)</p>
<p>One of the three feeding stations is in a set of bushes behind a restaurant. This Saturday, the bushes were over-run with rats&#8230; a sign that the resident cat, a handsome black cat, was either dead or (much less likely) had moved on. Sunday, there were no rats. I knew immediately&#8230; another cat had moved in. So I left out a bit of kibble and waited and watched for a bit, and sure enough, a skinny orange cat crept out of the bushes. Later, I left him more kibble and a can &#8211; he clearly needs some meat on those bones. And I guess some time soon I have to make some calls to see if someone who still lives in the area will trap and neuter him.</p>
<p>But here&#8217;s my point&#8230; because of the restaurant&#8217;s waste, the entire area could easily be infested with rats. The presence of a single cat eliminates them all very quickly. The cost to the restaurant of making the environment amenable to a feral cat is very, very small.</p>
<p>Here is another <a href="http://health.usnews.com/usnews/health/healthday/080221/cats-help-shield-owners-from-heart-attack.htm">story about cats</a> (hat tip <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2008/03/links-31108.html">Naked Capitalism</a>):</p>
<blockquote><p>Whether it&#8217;s a frisky kitten or a tubby tabby, a cat at home could cut your heart attack risk by almost a third, a new study suggests.</p>
<p>The finding, from a 10-year study of more than 4,300 Americans, suggests that the stress relief pets provide humans is heart-healthy.</p>
<p>And dog lovers shouldn&#8217;t feel left out: Although the study found no such benefit from &#8220;man&#8217;s best friend,&#8221; that&#8217;s probably because there simply weren&#8217;t enough dog owners in the study to draw firm conclusions, the researchers said.</p>
<p>&#8220;For years we have known that psychological stress and anxiety are related to cardiovascular events, particularly heart attacks,&#8221; noted study senior author Dr. Adnan Qureshi, executive director of the Minnesota Stroke Institute at the University of Minnesota in Minneapolis.</p>
<p>According to Qureshi, the new research shows that &#8220;essentially there is a benefit in relieving those inciting factors from pets.&#8221;</p>
<p>He was slated to present the findings Thursday at the American Stroke Association&#8217;s International Stroke Conference in New Orleans.</p>
<p>The stress-cardiovascular disease link is well-documented in scientific literature, and the affection and pleasure pets give humans is a known stress-buster. In fact, one study presented in 2005 at an American Heart Association meeting found that a single 12-minute visit with a dog improved the heart and lung function of people with heart failure.</p></blockquote>
<p>&#8230;</p>
<blockquote><p>Cat owners &#8220;appeared to have a lower rate of dying from heart attacks&#8221; over 10 years of follow-up compared to feline-free folk, Qureshi said.</p>
<p>The magnitude of the effect &#8212; a 30 percent reduction in heart attack risk &#8212; &#8220;was a little bit surprising,&#8221; he added. &#8220;We certainly expected an effect, because we thought that there was a biologically plausible mechanism at work. But the magnitude of the effect was hard to predict.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/03/stories-about-cats.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Reader Cursed on Ethics, Cats, and Lizard Gods</title>
		<link>./../../2007/08/reader-cursed-on-ethics-cats-and-lizard-gods.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2007/08/reader-cursed-on-ethics-cats-and-lizard-gods.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Aug 2007 02:22:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[cats]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2007/08/reader-cursed-on-ethics-cats-and-lizard-gods.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Regular readers know I feed feral and stray cats. (I love all kinds of animals, but cats tend to be the easiest animal to help in a city.) I&#8217;ve had a few instances where I think: this was an unqualified success, but for the most part, all I&#8217;m doing is keeping some of these animals [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Regular readers know I feed feral and stray cats. (I love all kinds of animals, but cats tend to be the easiest animal to help in a city.) I&#8217;ve had a few instances where I think: <a href="http://angrybear.blogspot.com/2007/03/random-cat-blogging.html">this was an unqualified success</a>, but for the most part, all I&#8217;m doing is keeping some of these animals alive for a little bit of time, until they get hit by a car, die of exposure, or I can do nothing more for them as a result of a move. Such is life.</p>
<p>But there is a calculus of aid&#8230; time, money, and resources are limited. Which leads to this e-mail sent by reader Cursed:</p>
<p>&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
<p>Ethics, cats, and lizard Gods.</p>
<p>A stray cat wondered into my life, and a terrible calamity befell her recently, which eventually cost her a leg. The vet tried. Poor little kitty peed blood for over a week, endured surgery, a cast, a gangrenous foot, amputation, finally she was required to wear a plastic cone around her neck for ten days to prevent her from chewing the stitches. That came off two days ago.</p>
<p>Now she weebles and wobbles and growls a lot. It looks like she will get used to only one rear leg, but she is not very happy.</p>
<p>Kitty&#8217;s great passion in life was hunting and laps. Her little world was filled with blue bellied lizards. They didn&#8217;t have a chance against Kitty. They&#8217;d often seek safety in the oak trees, but kitty was an intrepid climber. Kitty might have got her foot hung up in a tree and struggled. I&#8217;ll never know for sure.</p>
<p>I wonder if I did the right thing. Next door another stray cat just had a litter of kittens. Their fate is mostly likely a short life. My kitty has suffered greatly the last six weeks, now she looks to the future as a cripple. Should I have just put her out of her misery and rescued a kitten?</p>
<p>&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
<p>This one was by reader Cursed.</p>
<p>If I might add something (and I&#8217;m not a poetry kind of guy, but some poems have stuck to me), here&#8217;s <em>The Red Wheelbarrow</em> by The Red Wheelbarrow by William Carlos Williams&#8230;</p>
<blockquote><p>so much depends<br />upon</p>
<p>a red wheel<br />barrow</p>
<p>glazed with rain<br />water</p>
<p>beside the white<br />chickens</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2007/08/reader-cursed-on-ethics-cats-and-lizard-gods.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Liberals, Conservatives, Charity, and a Very, Very Large Cat (free to a good home!)</title>
		<link>./../../2006/12/liberals-conservatives-charity-and-a-very-very-large-cat-free-to-a-good-home.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2006/12/liberals-conservatives-charity-and-a-very-very-large-cat-free-to-a-good-home.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 03 Dec 2006 19:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[cats]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2006/12/liberals-conservatives-charity-and-a-very-very-large-cat-free-to-a-good-home.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Every so often, someone comes up with a study showing that religious conservatives are more generous than secular liberals. Recently, there’s been another one. I haven’t read this book. But I have read excerpts, and unless I’m wrong, the book makes what to me is the same errors that previous efforts to prove the same [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Every so often, someone comes up with a study showing that religious conservatives are more generous than secular liberals. Recently, there’s been <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Who-Really-Cares-Compassionate-Conservatism/dp/0465008216">another one</a>.</p>
<p>I haven’t read this book. But I have read excerpts, and unless I’m wrong, the book makes what to me is the same errors that previous efforts to prove the same thing have made.</p>
<p>The first error is that it assumes that any activity centered around a religious organization is charity.</p>
<p>I lived in the South for a number of years. At the time, I noticed that in much of that region, a lot of a town’s social life revolves around the local Church(es). And its not just Sunday services either.</p>
<p>Consider a typical family living in Searcy, Arkansas. Let’s go further, and assume its the kind of typical family the folks in Searcy would proudly call their own. The kids go to camp run by the Church, and they play basketball every day after school on the courts behind the Church. The mom is a member of a Church book club. The dad goes there to hear lectures on one or another topic. Part of family entertainment includes Church fairs, Church-sponsored trips to Little Rock to watch the Arkansas Travelers minor league ball team or up to Fayetteville to watch of the U of Arkansas Hogs play football, the occasional Church play, and of course, Sunday services.</p>
<p>From what I can tell, when they pony up money to the Church for each of these activities, they’re engaging in tax deductible charity.</p>
<p>Now, consider a family of Godless heathens in pagan Los Angeles. The kids play soccer in some league… league fees are not tax deductible, and not charity. The mom is a member of a book club… none of those costs are considered charity. The dad shows up at the occasional lecture series for one or another local university… nothing charity related here. And going to Disneyland, watching the Galaxy or the Dodgers or the Lakers, or going to the beach are not considered to be Charity.</p>
<p>The second error is that many forms of charity fall below the radar, especially when they are the types of activities more likely to be engaged in by city dwellers. I am kind of reluctant to discuss myself in this context, but here goes… every morning, I spend 30 minutes doing some rounds feeding a few colonies of feral cats. It doesn’t make me Mother Teresa, but I feel good doing it. I’m not sure what it costs me in cat food… some months when the budget is tighter, they only get kibble, other months they get to eat cans more frequently. I’ve come across a lot of other people who do the same.</p>
<p>I mention this for two reasons. As far as the government is concerned, most people who feed stray animals are not engaging in charity… there is no write-off occurring. Its way too much effort to go through the process of setting oneself up as a legitimate charity. (Yes, I know about organizations like Alley Cats and Feral Cat Alliance – those are great organizations, but they’re ways of sending money to other people who are doing their own charity work.) The second reason is that, and this is anecdotal, but it is my experience that city dwellers are more likely to be willing to work with animals than are those in rural areas. In the parts of South where I lived, spending time with animals doesn’t mean feeding feral cats or walking dogs at the shelter, it means shooting deer, and on occasion, bears.</p>
<p>(Two asides. Aside number 1 &#8211; I’m moving in a week, and I’ve found people to take over my route. Aside number 2 – anyone within driving distance of the LA area want a cat? My girlfriend and I found a big one living behind a dumpster that used to belong to someone – obvious signs were that she had been declawed and was more approachable than the ferals. We’ve got her at home now, all cleaned up, but we can’t find her owner and its been a few months. She’s about 4 years old, huge (16 solid pounds (i.e., not fat) when we pulled her off the street, larger now), very sweet, clumsy for a cat, and great with people – she will sleep with you in bed. Unfortunately she is very aggressive toward other cats (my girlfriend and I have 3 so we cannot keep her). Prove to me you’ll give her a good home and she’s yours. I mean the cat, not the girlfriend!)</p>
<p>There is a third error with these types of analyses. I remember reading studies that show that in general, people are more willing to pay taxes when a population is relatively homogenous. In other words, we don’t mind paying taxes if everyone else looks like us because we know then the money the government is taking away from us is not going to go to them. (Because, quite frankly, we don’t like them.) This matters because a) most religious conservatives live in rural areas with homogeneous populations and b) most Churches seem to be quite segregated – I’ve seen plenty of communities with a majority black Church and a majority white Church on the same street; thus, when Churchgoers fund their Church, they are funding “us” but not “them.”</p>
<p>So yes…. there is little doubt that the average conservative Church goer will engage in more charity than the average liberal Godless heathen.</p>
<p>Your thoughts?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2006/12/liberals-conservatives-charity-and-a-very-very-large-cat-free-to-a-good-home.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
