<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>nascar &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>GOP Senators! Why do you hate NASCAR?</title>
		<link>./../../2008/12/gop-senators-why-do-you-hate-nascar.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/12/gop-senators-why-do-you-hate-nascar.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2008 21:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Auto bailout]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bad economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[nascar]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/12/gop-senators-why-do-you-hate-nascar.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Bruce Webb(h/t to Hilzoy commenter nortzax for the idea) I mean it is bad enough that failure of the Big 3 means the loss of maybe 3 million jobs. Why are you trying to put Dale Earnhardt Jr. out of a job? Seriously what would the economic impact be to red states if not [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Bruce Webb<br />(h/t to Hilzoy commenter nortzax for the idea)</p>
<p>I mean it is bad enough that failure of the Big 3 means the loss of maybe 3 million jobs. Why are you trying to put Dale Earnhardt Jr. out of a job? </p>
<p>Seriously what would the economic impact be to red states if not only NASCAR but all the other car and truck racing circuits collapsed? NASCAR made a run at getting Washington State to build a track here at taxpayer expense with the claim that the positive economic impact would dwarf the expenditure. (The Leg didn&#8217;t bite). But you can&#8217;t deny the economic impact of having some hundreds of thousands of fans visiting town for a couple of weekends a year.<br /><a href="http://www.nascar.com/races/cup/2009/data/schedule.html">NASCAR schedule</a> Sure there are some blue states on the list. But this article claims the impact of the Daytona 500 alone is over $1 BILLION <a href="http://www.paddocktalk.com/news/html/modules.php?op=modload&#038;name=News&#038;file=article&#038;sid=73891">Paddocktalk</a> &#8220;Well we stuck it right to the Yankees. Ha Ha! Too bad there won&#8217;t be any races at <a href="http://www.kentuckyspeedway.com/default.aspx">Kentucky Speedway</a> this year. Or ever again.&#8221; Somehow I am not sure Mitch McConnell really thought this one through. How much is he really willing to put on the line to have GM workers take a $3/hr paycut a couple of years earlier?</p>
<p>Plus I hear football is kind of popular in both red and blue states. Who is going to pay for all the truck commercials? I suppose that as long as Americans don&#8217;t give up drinking beer that televised sports will continue. But the economic impact of the Big 3 goes far beyond parts makers and car dealers. The GOP is playing with dynamite here, the political ads practically write themselves.</p>
<p>UPDATE: Skip Sauer of The Sports Economist was also <a href="http://thesportseconomist.com/2008/12/nascar-auto-bailout.htm">all over this one on Tuesday</a>, though somewhat cautious:<br />
<blockquote>My sense is that brand loyalty &#8212; NASCAR is the marketing king of sport &#8212; may be the key factor. It is not uncommon in NASCAR country to see window stickers on a Ford truck that show a punkish-looking boy pissing on the Chevy logo. A strong form of negative brand identity, I submit. If the Ford and Chevy brands are irreparably damaged, will those loyalties transfer to Honda and Toyota?</p></blockquote>
<p>UPDATE TWO: Must have been something in the air. The NYT weighs in: <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/12/14/business/14nascar.html">NASCAR sponsors hit by sticker shock</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/12/gop-senators-why-do-you-hate-nascar.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
