<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Indiana &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>I&#8217;ll Believe in the Tea Baggers if Tamyra Gets the Signatures</title>
		<link>./../../2010/02/ill-believe-in-the-tea-baggers-if-tamyra-gets-the-signatures.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/02/ill-believe-in-the-tea-baggers-if-tamyra-gets-the-signatures.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2010 20:07:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Democratic Party]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Indiana]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/02/ill-believe-in-the-tea-baggers-if-tamyra-gets-the-signatures.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Tamyra d&#8217;Ippolito has suddenly become a Very Important Person. She needs signatures primarily in Indian&#8217;s Eighth District (currently represented by Brad Ellsworth, who would be the Party&#8217;s pick to replace Evan Bayh), Evansville, and Terre Haute. She has a background to make a Tea Partier proud: I was born in Worthington, Indiana and raised in [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://tamyraforsenate.com/">Tamyra d&#8217;Ippolito</a> has suddenly become a Very Important Person.</p>
<p>She needs signatures primarily in Indian&#8217;s Eighth District (currently represented by Brad Ellsworth, who would be the Party&#8217;s pick to replace Evan Bayh), Evansville, and Terre Haute.  She has a background to make a Tea Partier proud:<br />
<blockquote>I was born in Worthington, Indiana and raised in Linton. Currently, I live in Bloomington. I was raised an only child with a single, hard-working mother who &#8220;retired&#8221; from General Electric as a factory worker. </p>
<p>I attended college at Indiana State University in Terre Haute, receiving my degrees in Graphic Design and Photography. The United States government financed my education with federal grants. </p>
<p>In 1981, jobs were limited in Indiana so I moved to Houston, Texas and worked for over 3 years at Foley&#8217;s, an advertising agency, as a Production Artist. At 25, I moved to New York City where I lived for the next 20 years. I worked on Wall Street for Salomon Smith Barney and later for Lehman Brothers. While in NYC I picked up another degree at the New York Film Academy in Filmmaking&#8230;.</p>
<p>When I returned to Indiana, I was chosen by the Linton Rotary to go with a team to the country of Brazil. We were Ambassadors of the USA and traveled to 6 different cities. In Indiana, I became involved with World Learning. I worked as a Regional Director with World Learning in Indiana, Boston, and New York City</p>
<p>However, since moving to Indiana I have had no health insurance. I was diagnosed with colon cancer five years ago giving me a pre-existing condition. Additionally, I own a small business. Those two obstacles make insurance very expensive and unattainable. As a cancer survivor and small business owner, health reform is an issue that directly affects me like many Indiana residents.</p>
<p>I own and operate the Ragazzi Arte Cafe in Bloomington. I also founded the Poor Club, www.thepoorclub.org, after meeting many people who are in need. Our mission is to bring awareness and education to the fact that poverty is prevalent in Indiana and I want to make a change for the better.</p>
<p>I am a past board member of Women Inspire, www.womeninspire.org. I am also a member of PSI XOTA, a philanthropic sorority. Some of my accomplishments are Leadership Bloomington Graduate of 1995 and City of Bloomington Citizens’ Academy Graduate in 2008. I also serve on the Volunteers in Medicine Advisory Board.</p></blockquote>
<p>Right now, the Democratic Party (having been royally screwed by its current Senator) is hoping that Tammy doesn&#8217;t get enough signatures to qualify for the ballot, which would enable them <a href="http://washingtonindependent.com/76604/how-can-democrats-replace-bayh">to pick someone without bothering with a primary</a>.</p>
<p>But here&#8217;s a small business owner, someone who earned things and is quite aware of &#8220;from where it is that I come from.&#8221;</p>
<p>In short, an ideal candidate from outside of the Establishment—but one who comes naturally without having to build a third party. And someone who—as a small-business owner—knows very well what works and what doesn&#8217;t.</p>
<p>If the Tea Party people endorse her, then I&#8217;ll take them seriously.  If they avoid her because she would have to run with a (D) next to her name, then that will tell us everything we need to know about whether they are Astroturf.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/02/ill-believe-in-the-tea-baggers-if-tamyra-gets-the-signatures.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Strangely, CATO missed the AZ, IN, and MS budget crises</title>
		<link>./../../2009/06/strangely-cato-missed-the-az-in-and-ms-budget-crises.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/06/strangely-cato-missed-the-az-in-and-ms-budget-crises.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2009 15:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2012 Presidential]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fiscal responsibility summit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GOP governors]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Indiana]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitch Daniels]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[solvency crisis]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/06/strangely-cato-missed-the-az-in-and-ms-budget-crises.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[CATO was making much hay a few days ago about budget problems in California, New York, and New Jersey, which can be explained, respectively, by the Governor&#8217;s veto of an Assembly-passed budget a few months ago, the decline in tax revenues from financial services firms and continuing loss of upstate industry, and underfunded pension obligations [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>CATO was making much hay a few days ago about budget problems in California, New York, and New Jersey, which can be explained, respectively, by the Governor&#8217;s veto of an Assembly-passed budget a few months ago, the decline in tax revenues from financial services firms and continuing loss of upstate industry, and underfunded pension obligations whose origins date back to Christie&#8217;s cocaine-inspired budgets of the mid-1990s.</p>
<p>Strangely (via Dr. Black), they missed the crises in a few other states, most especially including the state governed by <a target="_blank" href="http://www.latimes.com/news/nationworld/nation/la-na-shutdown30-2009jun30,0,1912245.story">Republic hero Mitch Daniels</a>:<br />
<blockquote>Republican Gov. Mitch Daniels has warned residents that most of the state&#8217;s services &#8212; including its parks, the Bureau of Motor Vehicles and state-regulated casinos &#8212; would be shuttered unless a budget is passed today.</p></blockquote>
<p>Closing down the casinos?  Now that is extreme.</p>
<p>Mitch Daniels, doing for my old home state <a target="_blank" href="http://delong.typepad.com/sdj/2009/06/mitch-daniels-did-not-do-his-job.html">what he did for the country</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/06/strangely-cato-missed-the-az-in-and-ms-budget-crises.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
