<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Olympia Snowe &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The Maine Chance</title>
		<link>./../../2009/10/the-maine-chance.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/10/the-maine-chance.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2009 13:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[constitution]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Healthcare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Maine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Olympia Snowe]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[public option]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/10/the-maine-chance.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Robert Waldmann One strange thing about the health care reform debate is that insurance companies claim to support reform. I have tended to suspect that they are just playing possum. Now I find positive proof that WellPoint is willing to do what it takes to make sure health care reform passes &#8212; they sued the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Robert Waldmann</p>
<p>One strange thing about the health care reform debate is that insurance companies claim to support reform.  I have tended to suspect that they are just playing possum.  </p>
<p>Now I find positive proof that WellPoint is willing to do what it takes to make sure health care reform passes &#8212; <a href="http://digbysblog.blogspot.com/2009/10/socialized-profits-by-dday-wild-story.html">they sued the state of Maine claiming they have a constitutional right to make a profit !?!<br /></a><br />In fact they seem to support a public option.  It will be a bit hard for Sens Snowe and Collins to explain why they think no public option is needed after this.</p>
<p>I have a challenge.  Can anyone think of anything anyone could do which is better for the public option that this ?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/10/the-maine-chance.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Thinking on Health care funding. It&#8217;s getting wacky!</title>
		<link>./../../2009/07/thinking-on-health-care-funding-its-getting-wacky.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/07/thinking-on-health-care-funding-its-getting-wacky.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 02 Jul 2009 15:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Critical Thinking]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health care reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Olympia Snowe]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/07/thinking-on-health-care-funding-its-getting-wacky.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Divorced one like Bush So, American&#8217;s put an intellectual in the president&#8217;s seat. It&#8217;s been called pragmatism. We cheer the return of science and thus critical thinking to our politics. Yet, here we are at the cusp of the next great societal character development issue since we figured out after the depression there was [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Divorced one like Bush</p>
<p>So, American&#8217;s put an intellectual in the president&#8217;s seat.   It&#8217;s been called pragmatism.  We cheer the return of science and thus critical thinking to our politics.  Yet, here we are at the cusp of the next great societal character development issue since we figured out after the depression there was class war in the US and we get this:<br />&#8220;If you establish a public option at the forefront that goes head-to-head and competes with the private health insurance market &#8230; the public option will have significant price advantages,&#8221; she said.<br />Yes, Maine&#8217;s finest: Olympia Snowe as she argues against making the public option available at the get go.  </p>
<p>But, this concept is not new.  It dates back to 2006 when the <a href="http://www.cahi.org/cahi_contents/resources/pdf/CAHI_Medicare_Admin_Final_Publication.pdf">Council for Affordable Health Insurance</a> presented a 17 page report suggesting the same thing.  And!, now we have the <a href="http://www.heritage.org/research/healthcare/wm2505.cfm">Heritage foundation</a> dittoing the same report.  (More on that coming at AB by the other bloggers here.) </p>
<p>But, never fear, Sam&#8217;s got you covered.  He explains the appropriateness of Olympia&#8217;s thinking.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/07/thinking-on-health-care-funding-its-getting-wacky.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
