<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>guns &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>If Guns are Cheap, Criminals Will Have Guns</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/if-guns-are-cheap-criminals-will-have-guns.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/if-guns-are-cheap-criminals-will-have-guns.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2013 03:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[guns]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mike Kimel]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/if-guns-are-cheap-criminals-will-have-guns.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Mike Kimel If Guns are Cheap, Criminals Will Have Guns If guns are outlawed, only outlaws will have guns. We&#8217;ve all heard that many times. But is it true? Well, it is certainly a tautology. But there is another way to ensure that outlaws have guns. Namely, keep them cheap. From the 2009 Firearms Used [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Mike Kimel</p>
<p>If Guns are Cheap, Criminals Will Have Guns</p>
<p>If guns are outlawed, only outlaws will have guns.  We&#8217;ve all heard that many times.  But is it true?  Well, it is certainly a tautology. But there is another way to ensure that outlaws have guns.  Namely, keep them cheap.</p>
<p>From the <a href="http://oag.ca.gov/sites/all/files/pdfs/publications/Firearms_Report_09.pdf">2009 Firearms Used in the Commission of Crimes</a> focusing specifically on guns used in the commission of crimes in rural parts of California:</p>
<blockquote><p>Of the 147 firearms examined, there were 120 (81.6<br />percent) handguns, 13 (8.8 percent) rifles, 11 (7.5 percent) shotguns,<br />and 3 (2 percent) machine guns. </p></blockquote>
<p>The <a href="http://oag.ca.gov/sites/all/files/pdfs/publications/Firearms_Report_10.pdf">2010</a> <a href="http://oag.ca.gov/sites/all/files/pdfs/publications/Firearms_Report_10.pdf">version of the same report</a> paints a similar picture:</p>
<blockquote><p>Of the 175 firearms reported, there were 158 (90.3 percent) handguns, 12 (6.9 percent) rifles, 4 (2.3 percent) shotguns, and 1 (0.6 percent) full-auto firearm.</p></blockquote>
<p>The reason handguns are more often used in the commission of a crime than other types of weapons is not because the typical criminal doesn&#8217;t think it would be tres cool to use a belt fed machine gun or a shoulder launched missile.  Its because those types of weapons are very, very hard to come by.  With some digging, you can get your hands on a belt fed machine gun, but you are very unlikely to do it for less than $10K for a cheapo model.   Instead, what often happens is that armed criminals are most often armed with what one can best be described as lousy guns.  Don&#8217;t believe me?  <a href="http://www.tonyrogers.com/news/top_10_crime_guns.htm">Here</a> is a post from someone who clearly cannot be described as pro-gun control, commenting on the list of top ten guns used in crimes according to the ATF.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Descriptions include:</p>
<blockquote><p>An absolute piece of crap that sells for less than $120 retail. No real shooter would even warrant this &#8220;gun&#8221; as a legitimate target to even shoot at.</p></blockquote>
<p>Here&#8217;s another:</p>
<blockquote><p>Another piece of shit that sells for less than $110 retail, and is worth less than the pipsqueak ammunition you can try to feed it.</p></blockquote>
<p>And another:</p>
<blockquote><p>The cheapest 12-guage on the market, designed for people who cannot afford a real shotgun. Not even close to being considered a &#8220;fighting&#8221; shotgun. No offense to Mossberg, but there is a reason that  these Wal-Mart grade firepoles are given away at Ducks Unlimited as door prizes. Most do (and should) end up being traded up at gun shops for real shotguns.</p></blockquote>
<p>Some of the other descriptions are even more creative.  My favorite is number ten on the list:</p>
<blockquote><p>This one takes the cake as the &#8220;most prone to never fire, ever&#8221; firearm that was ever produced. Apparently they had a street price of $60 in Miami at one point, which would have been better spent on a wristrocket or a billyclub if you planned to actually use one in a legitimate crime. They eventually had to fight lawsuits from prosecutors and criminals at the same time because of their inherent defectiveness.</p></blockquote>
<p>To quote that post further:</p>
<blockquote><p>Though most teenage gangbangers wouldn&#8217;t be caught dead with a Smith and Wesson .38 revolver, an old fashioned six shooter, it nonetheless claims the lead on the top ten list. That&#8217;s because there are literally millions in existence; Smith and Wesson introduced the .38 in 1899, and since then, models have proliferated, transforming the name &#8220;Smith and Wesson .38&#8221; into a generic label for a particular style of gun, even clones that aren&#8217;t made by Smith and Wesson. Similarly, the Smith and Wesson .357 revolver, which was introduced in 1935, and the venerable Mossberg shotgun made the list based on the sheer volume in circulation.</p>
<p>But street criminals are interested almost exclusively in semiautomatics, preferring their superior firepower. (Semiautomatics hold at least seven and often as many as ten or twelve rounds of ammunition. &#8211;Or 18 if you can spend the extra dinero made from a 7-11 heist on a Beretta)</p>
<p>Gun traffickers like to peddle cheap semiautomatics to teenagers because they can tack on a hefty mark-up (of ten bucks) and still offer a weapon that costs less than an upscale gun like a Ruger or Smith and Wesson semiautomatic. That&#8217;s why inexpensive semiautomatics dominate the top ten list. As it happens, many of the companies on that list have links to George Jennings, founder of the now-defunct Raven Arms and his clan. Jennings&#8217; son Bruce founded Bryco in 1992. According to the ATF, Jennings&#8217; son-in-law Jim Davis founded Davis Industries, and Lorcin Engineering was launched by Jim Waldorf, Bruce Jennings&#8217; high school friend. These companies and several others also linked to Jennings are known in the trade as the &#8220;ring of fire.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>The point is, criminals use the guns they do because they&#8217;re available, and the guns that are available are usually available because they&#8217;re cheap.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/if-guns-are-cheap-criminals-will-have-guns.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Bring your gun to work 2005</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/bring-your-gun-to-work-2005.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/bring-your-gun-to-work-2005.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 24 Dec 2012 20:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[guns]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[guns and butter]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/bring-your-gun-to-work-2005.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[NRA campaigns to bring a gun to work should be remembered: Actually, the NRA&#8217;s power has been waning since at least 2005 when it declared a boycott against ConocoPhillips, a major Oklahoma employer with 3,000 workers, for blocking its bring-your-gun-to-work efforts. &#8220;ConocoPhillips went to federal court to attack your freedom,&#8221; thundered Wayne LaPierre, NRA executive [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.alternet.org/speakeasy/martharosenberg/are-nras-horse-head-bed-days-over">NRA campaigns to bring a gun to work</a> should be remembered:</p>
<blockquote><p>Actually, the NRA&#8217;s power has been waning since at least 2005 when it declared a boycott against ConocoPhillips, a major Oklahoma employer with 3,000 workers, for blocking its bring-your-gun-to-work efforts. &#8220;ConocoPhillips went to federal court to attack your freedom,&#8221; thundered Wayne LaPierre, NRA executive vice president and CEO. &#8220;We&#8217;re going to make ConocoPhillips the example of what happens when a corporation takes away your Second Amendment rights. If you are a corporation that&#8217;s anti-gun, anti-gun owner, or anti-Second Amendment, we will spare no effort or expense to work against you, to protect the rights of your law-abiding employees<br />&#8230;</p>
<p>The bring-your-gun-to-work bullying did not even fly in the &#8220;Gunshine State,&#8221; Florida. &#8220;Possession of firearms in the workplace or on company property is strictly prohibited,&#8221; said Bruce Middlebrooks of Blue Cross Blue Shield of Florida, which has 7,500 employees in the Jacksonville area. &#8220;We&#8217;re not against the Second Amendment, but guns are inappropriate in our workplaces and workplaces include parking lots,&#8221; said Randy Miller, a lobbyist for the Florida Retail Federation which represents 12,000 businesses in the state.<br />Bring-your-gun-to-work efforts were so over the top, with hundreds a year already killed in workplace shootings, the American Bar Association challenged its legality.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/bring-your-gun-to-work-2005.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Silencing the Science on Gun Research</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/silencing-the-science-on-gun-research.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/silencing-the-science-on-gun-research.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 24 Dec 2012 19:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[bi-patisan politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[data]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[data science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fire arms]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[guns]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[US data]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/silencing-the-science-on-gun-research.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[There is still a lot of headline material concerning the role of guns in our lives, and a lot of anecdotal material and thoughts abound. Also I seem to note an increase in the reporting of police in Lakewood, Washington and firemen in Webster, NY murders by gun makes the news as well. We are [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There is still a lot of headline material concerning the role of guns in our lives, and a lot of anecdotal material and thoughts abound.  Also I seem to note an increase in the reporting of <a target="_blank" href="http://usnews.nbcnews.com/_news/2012/12/24/16125861-4-volunteer-firefighters-shot-2-killed-in-apparent-trap?lite">police in Lakewood, Washington</a> and <a target="+_blank" href="http://usnews.nbcnews.com/_news/2012/12/24/16125861-4-volunteer-firefighters-shot-2-killed-in-apparent-trap?lite">firemen in Webster, NY</a> murders by gun makes the news as well.  We are a site that also values data to help in policy decisions as we try to govern ourselves. Hence this article from JAMA caught my attention on the apparent lack of more specific data on injuries and deaths from media.</p>
<p><a href="http://jama.jamanetwork.com/article.aspx?articleid=1487470" title="http://jama.jamanetwork.com/article.aspx?articleid=1487470">The Journal of the American Medical Association</a> notes in <i>Silencing the Science on Gun Research</i> that basic gahering and reporting data was defunded and/or forbidden by government agencies including the Center for Disease Control and Prevention, National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism, Hational Institute of Health, and other Department of Health agencies. The following is an excerpt:<br />(hat tip reader Tom B.)</p>
<blockquote><p>The nation might be in a better position to act if medical and public health researchers had continued to study these issues as diligently as some of us did between 1985 and 1997. But in 1996, pro-gun members of Congress mounted an all-out effort to eliminate the National Center for Injury Prevention and Control at the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). Although they failed to defund the center, the House of Representatives removed $2.6 million from the CDC&#8217;s budget—precisely the amount the agency had spent on firearm injury research the previous year. Funding was restored in joint conference committee, but the money was earmarked for traumatic brain injury. The effect was sharply reduced support for firearm injury research.</p>
<p>To ensure that the CDC and its grantees got the message, the following language was added to the final appropriation: “none of the funds made available for injury prevention and control at the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention may be used to advocate or promote gun control.”<sup><a href="http://jama.jamanetwork.com/#ref-jvp120140-4">4</a></sup></p>
<p>Precisely what was or was not permitted under the clause was unclear. But no federal employee was willing to risk his or her career or the agency&#8217;s funding to find out. Extramural support for firearm injury prevention research quickly dried up. Even today, 17 years after this legislative action, the CDC&#8217;s website lacks specific links to information about preventing firearm-related violence.</p>
<p>When other agencies funded high-quality research, similar action was taken. In 2009, Branas et al<sup><a href="http://jama.jamanetwork.com/#ref-jvp120140-5">5</a></sup> published the results of a case-control study that examined whether carrying a gun increases or decreases the risk of firearm assault. In contrast to earlier research, this particular study was funded by the National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism. Two years later, Congress extended the restrictive language it had previously applied to the CDC to all Department of Health and Human Services agencies, including the National Institutes of Health.<sup><a href="http://jama.jamanetwork.com/#ref-jvp120140-6">6</a></sup></p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>The US military is grappling with an increase in suicides within its ranks. Earlier this month, an article by 2 retired generals—a former chief and a vice chief of staff of the US Army— asked Congress to lift a little-noticed provision in the 2011 National Defense Authorization Act that prevents military commanders and noncommissioned officers from being able to talk to service members about their private weapons, even in cases in which a leader believes that a service member may be suicidal.<sup><a href="http://jama.jamanetwork.com/#ref-jvp120140-9">9</a></sup><br /><sup></sup>…<br />Given the chance, could researchers achieve similar progress with firearm violence? It will not be possible to find out unless Congress rescinds its moratorium on firearm injury prevention research. Since Congress took this action in 1997, at least 427 000 people have died of gunshot wounds in the United States, including more than 165 000 who were victims of homicide.<sup><a href="http://jama.jamanetwork.com/#ref-jvp120140-1">1</a></sup> To put these numbers in context, during the same time period, 4586 Americans lost their lives in combat in Iraq and Afghanistan.<sup><a href="http://jama.jamanetwork.com/#ref-jvp120140-10">10</a></sup></p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/silencing-the-science-on-gun-research.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
