<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>medicaid &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Rep Marsha Blackburn&#8217;s snow job. Explains how Social Security money flows</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/rep-marsha-blackburns-snow-job-explains-how-social-security-money-flows.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/rep-marsha-blackburns-snow-job-explains-how-social-security-money-flows.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 16 Feb 2013 04:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[C-span]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[entitlements reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[IOU's]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Marsha Blackburn]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medicaid]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medicare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[trust funds]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/rep-marsha-blackburns-snow-job-explains-how-social-security-money-flows.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[                                                                                                                                                                   I was watching C span Washington Journal this morning.  Rep Marsha Blackburn was the guest.  I got to listen to her explanation of how the Social Security funds flow and just had to post the clip.   Copied from the transcript of the clip: THEIRS MONEY THAT GOES TO MEDICARE AND SOCIAL SECURITY AND I [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>                                                                                                                                                                   I was watching C span Washington Journal this morning.  Rep Marsha Blackburn was the guest.  I got to listen to her explanation of how the Social Security funds flow and just had to post the clip.   Copied from the transcript of the clip:</p>
<blockquote><p>THEIRS MONEY THAT GOES TO MEDICARE AND SOCIAL SECURITY AND I THINK IT IS JUST IS SO  INAPPROPRIATE THAT THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT DOES NOT USE THAT AS A TRUST FUND BUT THEY MOVE  IMMEDIATELY TO THE GENERAL FUND  AND STACK UP IOU&#8217;S THAT ARE  SITTING IN A CABINET IN WEST VIRGINIA. </p></blockquote>
<p>What she says should not be allowed to stand and if C-span were half of what it used to be, she would not have had the following go uncorrected.  Thus I leave it to the Angry Bears to correct her here and thus document her ignorance of the subject.  <br /><a href="http://www.c-spanvideo.org/clip/4360645&#038;newclip" target="_blank"></a></p>
<p>I have not watched this lady before.  I could not help but think she is just a more polished version of Sarah Palin. She is totally capable of pulling off what we used to call a &#8220;snow job&#8221; when writing their essay.  </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/rep-marsha-blackburns-snow-job-explains-how-social-security-money-flows.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The &#034;Fiscal Cliff&#034; and the Coming Retirement Crisis of the Middle Class</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/the-fiscal-cliff-and-the-coming-retirement-crisis-of-the-middle-class.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/the-fiscal-cliff-and-the-coming-retirement-crisis-of-the-middle-class.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2013 21:54:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medicaid]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medicare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tax]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/the-fiscal-cliff-and-the-coming-retirement-crisis-of-the-middle-class.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[On January 1, Congress approved a tax and spending bill to avert the so-called &#8220;fiscal cliff&#8221; combination of tax hikes and spending cuts that would have created deflationary pressure on the United States (though Yglesias questioned the conventional wisdom of whether it would necessarily cause a recession). Let&#8217;s take a look at the deal in [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>On January 1, Congress approved a tax and spending bill to avert the  so-called &#8220;fiscal cliff&#8221; combination of tax hikes and spending cuts that  would have created deflationary pressure on the United States (though <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/moneybox/2012/12/31/fiscal_cliff_recession_would_it_really_happen.html">Yglesias questioned</a>  the conventional wisdom of whether it would necessarily cause a  recession). Let&#8217;s take a look at the deal in some detail, then proceed  to the gruesome details of what will happen around the Ides of March.</p>
<p>From <a href="http://thinkprogress.org/economy/2013/01/02/1384291/the-fiscal-cliff-deal-by-the-numbers/">Think Progress</a>, here are some of the more critical parts of the deal.</p>
<p>1)  The Bush tax cuts expire on only about 0.7% of households, those  earning more than $400,000 per year as an individual or $450,000 for a  couple. This brings in $600 billion over 10 years. Since rich people  don&#8217;t spend as much of their income as the poor and middle class do,  this is less deflationary than a tax increase on the middle class, <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/11/what-fiscal-cliff-means-for-middle-class.html">as I discussed</a> in November.</p>
<p>2)  With the expiration of the temporary 2% payroll tax cut, 77% of  households will see their taxes go up. Indeed, every single income group  will, on average, see their taxes increase, as shown below (via <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/moneybox/2013/01/02/credit_suisse_fiscal_cliff_deal_leaves_income_lower_for_everyone_especially.html">Matt Yglesias</a>): </p>
<div><img alt="1357144024996" src="http://www.slate.com/content/dam/slate/blogs/moneybox/2013/01/02/credit_suisse_fiscal_cliff_deal_leaves_income_lower_for_everyone_especially/1357144024996.jpg.CROP.article568-large.jpg" title="1357144024996" width="568"></div>
<p>Since this hits the middle class more directly,  the deflationary consequences are larger than they would be for an  increase in taxes on the rich. On the other hand, this strengthens the  long-run funding of Social Security, an issue I will return to shortly.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>3)  Unemployment insurance is extended for two million workers. This will  get spent and have a definitive stimulative effect on the economy.</p>
<p>However,  the second shoe of the fiscal cliff, the automatic cutbacks known as  the &#8220;sequester&#8221; was simply postponed for two months, which is the same  time that the Treasury Department will run out of creative ways to keep  the country from exceeding the debt ceiling, <a href="http://money.cnn.com/2012/12/31/news/economy/debt-ceiling/index.html">which it hit</a> on December 31.</p>
<p>Combining  these two negotiations, the debt ceiling and the sequester, will be an  extremely high-stakes battle where the middle class has a lot to lose.  The big problem here is that some Tea Party Republicans really do want  to use the debt ceiling to take the economy hostage and force cutbacks  in Social Security, Medicare, and Medicaid. Despite the fact that  Republicans lost the Presidency as well as both Senate and House seats  (with a majority of the votes cast for the House going to Democrats),  they see their <a href="http://thinkprogress.org/justice/2012/11/07/1159631/americans-voted-for-a-democratic-house-gerrymandering-the-supreme-court-gave-them-speaker-boehner/?mobile=nc">gerrymandered House majority</a> as giving them license to wreak havoc.</p>
<p>The consensus among most commentators (<a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/01/01/perspective-on-the-deal/">Krugman</a>, <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/wonkblog/wp/2013/01/02/calm-down-liberals-the-white-house-got-a-good-deal-on-the-fiscal-cliff/">Klein</a>, and <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/moneybox/2013/01/02/white_house_lost_and_liberals_should_be_happy.html">Yglesias</a>,  for example) is that the fiscal cliff deal will work out okay as long  as the President does not cave in to the Republicans&#8217; threats over the  debt ceiling.  I agree as far as that goes. But, as Yglesias points out,  there is nothing great about what Klein says is the most likely  scenario, where the President gets $1 trillion in new tax revenue for $1  trillion in cuts over 10 years. That is still $2 trillion in austerity  measures at a time when unemployment is barely below 8%!</p>
<p>The  looming problem rarely mentioned, even in the context of the Republican  campaign against Social Security, is that my children&#8217;s generation (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Generation_X">Generation X</a>,  if you will) faces a retirement crisis that many of my generation will  avoid, based on the end of pension plans. According to one <a href="http://www.ssa.gov/policy/docs/ssb/v69n3/v69n3p1.html">Social Security Administration report,</a>  the percentage of private-sector workers with a traditional  defined-benefit pension plan fell from 38% in 1980 to 20% in 2008. Over  the same period, private-sector workers who only received defined  contribution plans rose from 8% to 31%. Note that this means that 49% of  private-sector workers are not covered by any pension plan at all.  Moreover, while governments have more commonly provided defined-benefit  plans than private employers have, they are under attack in many states.</p>
<p>Let&#8217;s  do the math. With 49% of private workers having no pension, and another  31% having an on-average less generous defined contribution pension,  how will seniors support themselves if Social Security is cut? Hint: It  won&#8217;t be pretty.</p>
<p>Get ready for a bumpy March.</p>
<p>Cross-posted from <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/">Middle Class Political Economist</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/the-fiscal-cliff-and-the-coming-retirement-crisis-of-the-middle-class.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Let’s try to stick to the real world when we talk about Medicaid,</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/lets-try-to-stick-to-the-real-world-when-we-talk-about-medicaid.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/lets-try-to-stick-to-the-real-world-when-we-talk-about-medicaid.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 18 Jul 2012 11:23:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[ACA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Incidental Economist]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medicaid]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/lets-try-to-stick-to-the-real-world-when-we-talk-about-medicaid.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The Incidental Economist addresses election snippets that keep on going, just like in the movies.  Read the whole thing: Let’s try to stick to the real world when we talk about Medicaid, by Aaron Carroll: (Note: Paul Krugman cites here. Tyler Cowen responds here. I respond to Cowen’s response here.) Tyler Cowen had a piece [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>The Incidental Economist addresses election snippets that keep on going, just like in the movies.  Read the whole thing:</div>
<blockquote><p><a href="http://theincidentaleconomist.com/wordpress/lets-try-to-stick-to-the-real-world-when-we-talk-about-medicaid/">Let’s try to stick to the real world when we talk about Medicaid, by Aaron Carroll</a>:</p>
<p><em>(Note: Paul Krugman cites <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/07/16/medicaid-zombies/">here</a>. Tyler Cowen responds <a href="http://marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2012/07/aaron-carroll-on-medicaid-wars.html">here</a>. I respond to Cowen’s response <a href="http://theincidentaleconomist.com/wordpress/tyler-cowen-on-me-on-medicaid-wars/">here</a>.)</em></p>
<p>Tyler Cowen <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/07/15/business/medicaids-new-tug-of-war-economic-view.html">had a piece in the NYT</a> this weekend on Medicaid. He doesn’t seem too thrilled with its use in the ACA’s coverage expansion. </p>
<p>&#8230; I have to admit that his article set me off a bit. It could be that he didn’t have space in the NYT for more nuance. Perhaps he’ll provide it on his blog. In particular, I’d love him to address some of the points below…</p>
<p>I get a bit annoyed by blanket claims that doctors won’t accept Medicaid&#8230;.<br />I get a bit annoyed when people just claim government programs are “unpopular”&#8230;<br />I get a bit annoyed at the blanket acceptance of the awesomeness of the free market in health care, when there is no phenomenal evidence of its success&#8230;</p>
<p>&#8230;</p>
<p>Look, I get that people may not like the political implications of those systems. They may not like the governments that produce them. They may not like the <a href="http://theincidentaleconomist.com/wordpress/reduced-spending-is-the-wrong-argument/">lack of choice</a>  inherent in such systems. They may not like the potential  limitations within them for making money, and therefore for innovation. But we need to stop making stuff up about them.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/lets-try-to-stick-to-the-real-world-when-we-talk-about-medicaid.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Health Care Thoughts: Another Major Event</title>
		<link>./../../2012/03/health-care-thoughts-another-major-event.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/03/health-care-thoughts-another-major-event.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 17 Mar 2012 01:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[health care thoughts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medicaid]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/03/health-care-thoughts-another-major-event.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt Health Care Thoughts: Another Major Event On the 23rd the Obama administration will publish the administrative regulations for Medicaid expansion. http://www.medicaid.gov/Federal-Policy-Guidance/Downloads/REG-03-16-12.pdf As reported by Modern Healthcare, eligibility will be simplified to an income test as a percentage of the federal poverty level. This may expand Medicaid by as many as [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt</p>
<p>Health Care Thoughts: Another Major Event</p>
<p>  On the 23rd the Obama administration will publish the administrative regulations for Medicaid expansion.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.medicaid.gov/Federal-Policy-Guidance/Downloads/REG-03-16-12.pdf">http://www.medicaid.gov/Federal-Policy-Guidance/Downloads/REG-03-16-12.pdf</a> </p>
<p>As reported by Modern Healthcare, eligibility will be simplified to an income test as a percentage of the federal poverty level. This may expand Medicaid by as many as 17 million recipients by 2016.  There are a number of administrative issues addressed, many focused on simplifying and streamlining processing.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/03/health-care-thoughts-another-major-event.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Town Hall Meetings on the Ryan Budget Raise Concerns</title>
		<link>./../../2011/04/town-hall-meetings-on-the-ryan-budget-raise-concerns.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/04/town-hall-meetings-on-the-ryan-budget-raise-concerns.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 29 Apr 2011 19:07:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[GOP Budget Proposal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health Care]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[House Budget Proposal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medicaid]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medicare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Medicare vouchers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Renee Ellmers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[State Taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[taxes on pensions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[town hall meetings]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/04/town-hall-meetings-on-the-ryan-budget-raise-concerns.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Various congressional representatives held town hall meetings recently, and the news channels and print media were abuzz with the lively give-and-take, including shouting matches. See, e.g., House G.O.P. Members Face Voter Anger Over Budget, New York Times, Apr. 26, 2011; Republicans facing tough questions over Medicare overhaul in Budget Plan, Washington Post, Apr. 22, 2011. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Various congressional representatives held town hall meetings recently, and the news channels and print media were abuzz with the lively give-and-take, including shouting matches. See, e.g., <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/04/27/us/politics/27congress.html" target="_blank" _mce_href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/04/27/us/politics/27congress.html">House G.O.P. Members Face Voter Anger Over Budget</a>, New York Times, Apr. 26, 2011; <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/republicans-facing-tough-questions-over-medicare-overhaul-in-budget-plan/2011/04/22/AFjSRgRE_story.html" target="_blank" _mce_href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/republicans-facing-tough-questions-over-medicare-overhaul-in-budget-plan/2011/04/22/AFjSRgRE_story.html">Republicans facing tough questions over Medicare overhaul in Budget Plan</a>, Washington Post, Apr. 22, 2011.</p>
<p>The issue&#8211;the House&#8217;s adoption of the Ryan budget proposal and its clear agenda of overturning New Deal safety nets embodied in the current understanding of Medicaid, Social Security and Medicare.</p>
<p>Those at or near retirement are worried that the Ryan proposal will hurt everybody. The Ryan proposal comes with frequent disclaimers about protecting the already older population and needing to act now to protect our grandchildren, a clear effort to massage the message to appeal to current grandparents. See, e.g., <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/04/27/us/politics/27congress.html" target="_blank" _mce_href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/04/27/us/politics/27congress.html">House G.O.P. Members Face Voter Anger Over Budget</a>, New York Times, Apr. 26, 2011 (noting Webster&#8217;s statement that &#8220;not one senior citizen is harmed by this budget&#8221; while implying that it is necessary to prevent grandchildren from &#8220;looking at a bankrupt country&#8221;); <a href="http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2011/04/26/ap/national/main20057685.shtml" target="_blank" _mce_href="http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2011/04/26/ap/national/main20057685.shtml">Congressional Republicans go home to mixed reveiws</a>, CBS.com, Apr. 26, 2011 (noting North Carolina GOP Rep. Renee Ellmers&#8217;claim that &#8220;If you&#8217;re 55 and older, your Medicare and Social Security will not change&#8221;).<br /><a name="more"></a><br />But the Ryan proposal clearly envisions mechanisms that would likely lead to decimation of these programs&#8211;either through turning them into limited vouchers (Medicare proposal); turning the funds over to the states to use as they see fit (Medicaid proposal) or limiting benefits (Social Security proposal) in ways that will &#8211;probably sooner rather than later&#8211; hurt everybody.</p>
<p>
<ul>
<li>These proposals take place in a context of expansive, concerted attacks on these &#8220;entitlement&#8221; programs, often failing to acknowledge the historic support for these programs or their foundation in the recognition that federal support is required to protect against the abject poverty and humiliating degradation that accompanied the Great Depression;</li>
<li>Benefits for elderly and sick Americans are cut to provide savings to offset some of the loss of revenues from tax cuts for Big Business and the wealthy, both of whom already pay relatively low taxes, in what hardly seems a bargain to the working poor, the elderly or in fact the overwhelming majority of Americans who are not in the top 15% income or wealth distribution. (This in spite of Ryan&#8217;s claim that there is no huge tax cut for big corporations and the wealthy&#8211;he asserts that the proposed 25% rate is &#8220;in exchange for losing their tax shelters&#8221;. See, e.g., CBS.com <a href="http://www.cbsnews.com/video/watch/?id=7363939n&#038;tag=related;photovideo" target="_blank" _mce_href="http://www.cbsnews.com/video/watch/?id=7363939n&#038;tag=related;photovideo">Evening News coverage of Paul Ryan holding Wis. town meetings</a>, at <a href="http://www.cbsnews.com/video/watch/?id=7363939n&#038;tag=related;photovideo" _mce_href="http://www.cbsnews.com/video/watch/?id=7363939n&#038;tag=related;photovideo">http://www.cbsnews.com/video/watch/?id=7363939n&#038;tag=related;photovideo</a> )</li>
<li>In spite of the high cost for the vulnerable poor and elderly of these budget proposals, they don&#8217;t appear likely to achieve their proffered rationale of reducing debt and deficits&#8211;in fact, the CBO has said that the Ryan budget proposal will result in higher deficits and bigger debt burdens over the next decade.</li>
<p>
<li>It appears shortsighted to wring one&#8217;s hands about a &#8220;bankrupt country&#8221; while considering only one potential solution, especially when that solution is highly detrimental to the most vulnerable populations, and without considering the full facts regarding the amount of debt, the ability of the U.S. to weaken the dollar further to aid unemployment and debt payment, the ability of the U.S. to raise taxes judiciously rather then merely cutting spending, or the ability of the U.S. to let the tax law play out as it is currently slated to do (with the Bush tax cuts that were extended 2 more years over their originally intended short life due to sunset in 2012). As Jim Johnson, a former Ryan supporter who has &#8220;grown increasingly disgusted&#8221; with Ryan noted, &#8220;[Ryan] says Medicare is unsustainable. I&#8217;m thinking, &#8216;Yeah, it&#8217;s because medical costs are out of control.&#8217; &#8230;Why isn&#8217;t he attacking it at that level?&#8221; <a href="http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2011/04/26/ap/national/main20057685.shtml" target="_blank" _mce_href="http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2011/04/26/ap/national/main20057685.shtml">Congressional Republicans go home to mixed reviews</a>, CBS News.com</li>
<p>
<li>Any voucher system for health care will inevitably fail to cover increasing health care costs, resulting in rationing even the most basic health care by socio-economic class&#8211;the very problem that Medicare, Medicaid, and the limited health care reforms undertaken by the last Congress were intended to address. The Center for Budget and Policy Priorities concluded that <a href="http://www.cbpp.org/cms/index.cfm?fa=view&#038;id=3473">out-of-pocket medical costs would skyrocket for low-income seniors</a>; the Washington Post&#8217;s Fact Checker Glenn Kessler (in <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/fact-checker/post/gop-lawmakers-tout-medicare-reform-by-stretching-a-comparison-to-the-health-benefits-they-receive/2011/04/28/AFrRkM9E_blog.html">GOP Lawmakers tout Medicare reform by stretching a comparison to the health benefits they receive</a>, Apr. 29, 2011) notes that the CBO analysis concluded that the Ryan Medicare system would pay only 32% of health care costs by 2030, compared to 70-75% if traditional Medicare remained in place.</li>
<p>
<li>Addressing the problems in the U.S. health care system solely by market means that put the onus on health care recipients to seek cost-savings has failed miserably over the last forty years and cannot help but fail more spectacularly when the Medicaid backup is weakened and the nature of health care needs is such that one of the best antidotes to market problems (the only one permitted in radical market thinking that objects to regulatory safeguards)&#8211;informed consumers who can review options and select among competing providers&#8211;is simply not applicable. Car accident victims don&#8217;t shop for surgeons; cancer victims don&#8217;t know enough to select based on price; etc.</li>
<li>The Ryan proposal appears one-sided in its decision to cut spending on potentially vulnerable populations rather than to address the means through which health care is provided or to consider ways to control profit-taking in the health care system. The market ideology of the proposers leaves many options that might work better off the table (single payer; tax on excessive compensation; revamping the non-profit hospital system; attaching strings to the R&#038;D and other tax expenditures in the tax code; using the clout of a national system to negotiate better doctor and drug pricing for Medicare and Medicaid, etc.);</li>
<li>Many of those states that would acquire more control over the use of Medicaid funds are controlled now, as is the House, by people who have announced their intent to cut taxes on the wealthy and business while cutting or taxing pensions and health benefits for public employees and cutting funds available for Medicaid and other poverty-directed programs; it is not a difficult leap to see the interrelationship of these trends;</li>
<li>Plans to cut benefits for those who may enjoy them in the future pave the way in at least two ways for decisions shortly thereafter to cut benefits for those who currently enjoy them: first, by creating lowered expectations; second, by creating an unfair disparity that supports an &#8220;us against them&#8221; attitude between the current elderly and those who will get lesser benefits in the future. (Note that this resembles the way the right has encouraged an &#8220;us against them&#8221; attitude of <em>private workers</em>, who have been deprived of union benefits through the harsh anti-union tactics used by Big Business, against <em>public employees</em>, who have generally benefited in the past from more reasonable attitudes towards unions fostered in legislative bodies that have, in the past, understood the nature of the bargain that public employees make (which might be summarized as &#8216;work hard, get paid less than you could in the private sector, and accept later benefits in pensions and health care for lesser salary/percs now).</li>
</ul>
<p>
<p>Is is surprising that left-leaning activist groups like Move-On point to the Ryan budget proposal as a &#8220;naked, unapologetic attack on working Americans for the sake of Big Insurance and the riches of the rich&#8221; (quote from Move-On email on this matter)?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/04/town-hall-meetings-on-the-ryan-budget-raise-concerns.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>What Will We Tell the Doctors?</title>
		<link>./../../2011/04/what-will-we-tell-the-doctors.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/04/what-will-we-tell-the-doctors.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 Apr 2011 22:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[entrepreneurship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health care costs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health care reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medicaid]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/04/what-will-we-tell-the-doctors.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[&#8220;The practice of medicine was accepted to be a chancy way to make a living, and nobody expected a doctor to get rich, least of all the doctors themselves.&#8221;  &#8211; Lewis Thomas, The Youngest Science, p. 4 (Penguin, 1995 edition, quote via Google Books) Lost in the discussion of Paul Ryan’s “plan” is the group [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>&#8220;The practice of medicine was accepted to be a chancy way to make a living, and nobody expected a doctor to get rich, least of all the doctors themselves.&#8221;  &#8211; Lewis Thomas, <em>The Youngest Science, </em>p. 4 (Penguin, 1995 edition, quote via Google Books) </p></blockquote>
<p>Lost in the discussion of Paul Ryan’s “plan” is the group of entrepreneurs that will be most harmed economically by enacting it: doctors—most especially general practitioners.</p>
<p>I was speaking with <a href="http://www.economicprincipals.com/" target="_blank">David Warsh</a> last week at Kauffman, and pointed out what “everyone knows” but no one will say: U.S. doctors net about twice as much money as doctors in the rest of the civilized world. (As a ballpark, $200K in the U.S. and $100K elsewhere.)  And until you can solve some of that, you won’t really make much of a dent in the High Cost of Medicine.  David noted that solving that “isn’t going to happen.”</p>
<p> <a name="more"></a>
<p>Paul Ryan’s plan is a large step toward making it happen—just not in the way David (or I) would have expected it to happen.</p>
<p>Let’s sidebar the usually Capitation v. Fee-for-Service discussion, which will only have an effect at the margin.  Assume that doctors net, say, $25 per patient (net of paying for office staff, supplies, waste disposal, etc.).[1]  If they schedule four patients per hour ($100)[2] for eight hours a day ($800) five days a week ($4,000) for a fifty-week year ($200,000), they make their salary.</p>
<p>Note the assumptions I made: the per-patient return is certainly variable (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marginal_cost">standard MC/MR curve</a>), so the real return is based on volume and where that volume falls on the MC curve.  So long as a doctor can schedule to see 160 people a week—8,000 visits a year—they are continually busy and receive optimal returns.</p>
<p>But the market is not perfect.  I am of an age where a few visits a year is strongly suggested.  Tom or Rebecca, by contrast, go in once (if at all) and otherwise when they are unhealthy.[3]  It seems intuitive that, given search costs (think labor markets), a doctor’s practice is marginally more profitable with more repeat patients. Customer retention is therefore of enhanced value in the current equilibrium.[4]</p>
<p>But shifting the burden of payment while not capping insurance margins is also an easy first-order solution: fewer insured people, certainly; higher margins, probably (positive, maybe not significant), shifting of funds toward the sector that reduce overall consumption, and—inevitably—fewer doctor visits for the older and most likely to need care.</p>
<p>Note [4] above becomes relevant on the supply side; the relationship is weaker if still positive.  But the discretionary spending is reduced; Fee-for-Service fades except in the “concierge” segment of the market.  Capitation becomes the rule, and the model that has become prevalent—insurance companies guaranteeing doctors a salary—become the rule.</p>
<p>But visits to the doctor have declined, due to those most in need having the least ability to pay and therefore dropping off the insurance rolls.</p>
<p>So the insurance company doesn’t expect the doctor to make 8,000 separate treatments a year.  Or they do, but find at the end of the year that they were mistaken. The next year they offer to pay based not on 32 patients a day, but rather 30. And, given the frictions in the market, the majority of doctors agree, preferring the certainty of $187,500 a year to the risk of treating the uninsured, who are now a <em>much </em>riskier group.</p>
<p>And then the multiplier effect comes in.  Recall that there are fixed costs as well; doctors’s returns mirror the standard MC/MR curve.  So the actual loss begins gradually, but becomes steeper as the years go by—convexity effects appear.</p>
<p>Eventually, doctors have to right-size their practice. The current trend toward Vertical Integration may mitigate effects in the short term. But eventually—probably within 15 years, though it may take 20—doctors will find that their salaries (“net capitation fees”) are significantly closer to those of their European and Canadian peers.</p>
<p>Coincident to its effect on the poor and the elderly, Paul Ryan’s plan will speed the convergence of doctors’s salaries in the world.  The aspiring doctor in the Harvard Class of 2037 may well look at Lewis Thomas’s thoughts of one hundred years previous and say, “Nothing ever changes.”</p>
<p>The question that remains today is “What will we tell the doctors?”</p>
<p>[1]When I looked a few years ago, my doctor was paid $41 for my $125 office visit from insurance, and I had a $15 copay.  If you can’t figure out how $56 gross can become $25 net, go into a heavy-service industry, such as restaurants or doctoring, and look at their cash flows.</p>
<p>[2]Note that there is no inherent need to conform to the schedule, assuming the patients are not time-constrained.  That is, one can spend longer with patients—more than eight hours in a day—and maintain quality of care at the expense of leisure time.  This is a fairly simple equation and is left for when this isn’t a blog post.</p>
<p>[3]Again, the equation to show when the marginally-unhealthy choose to visit the doctor is left as an exercise. All we need for blog post purposes is to know that the choice is dependent on several factors, including disposable income and out-of-pocket cost.</p>
<p>[4]This is in no small part, at the margin, due to the support of the current Medicare/Medicaid system.</p>
<p>[5]Contracts still require both parties to consent, and the 6.6% decline is the net result—one might assume that some insurance companies will reduce their margins to pay doctors more.  One might also assume a pony with a pointy thing sticking out of its forehead with equal likelihood. There may well be a chimera of hope—though the scenario only extends the timeframe instead of ending the process—but it will not be sustainable, though it may be iterative (which would further attenuate the process).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/04/what-will-we-tell-the-doctors.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Whatever happened to the Guns or Butter premise</title>
		<link>./../../2010/09/whatever-happened-to-the-guns-or-butter-premise.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/09/whatever-happened-to-the-guns-or-butter-premise.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Sep 2010 12:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[medicaid]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/09/whatever-happened-to-the-guns-or-butter-premise.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Run Whatever happened to the Guns or Butter premise? Naomi Freundlich at Maggie Mahar’s Health Beat Blog discusses the passage of the $26 billion state aid package and why it does not go far enough in securing healthcare for those who qualify for Medicaid. Passage of $26 billion State Aid Package Is Merely a [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Run</p>
<p><strong>Whatever happened to the Guns or Butter premise</strong>?  </p>
<p>Naomi Freundlich at Maggie Mahar’s Health Beat Blog discusses the passage of the $26 billion state aid package and why it does not go far enough in securing healthcare for those who qualify for Medicaid. <a target="_blank" href="http://www.healthbeatblog.com/2010/08/passage-of-26-billion-state-aid-package-is-merely-a-stopgap-measure-for-medicaid-woes.html">Passage of $26 billion State Aid Package Is Merely a Stop-Gap Measure For Medicaid Woes</a>.</p>
<p>To get this past the Senate, the bill was stripped of $12 billion Food Stamp Program and closed loopholes in incentives which encourage employers to move jobs overseas to make it revenue neutral. While it is good to see Congress start to close loop holes for companies and individuals who utilize them to their own benefit and not for what they were intended, you have to wonder what were they thinking when it came to the food stamp program. In the midst of a mediocre job creation economy with no end in the near term, the millionaire Senate balances the budget on the backs of the poor who depend upon Food Stamps . . .  41 million citizens in 2010 . . . to get Senator’s Snowe and Collin’s votes. The kicker here is the Senate playing Education off against healthcare and food stamps. Education, healthcare, or food ???</p>
<p><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_8UVGnCIfOVk/TIeDV0tbPYI/AAAAAAAAAX4/T_aCsKXQbqA/s1600/Uninsured_by_State.jpg"><img src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_8UVGnCIfOVk/TIeDV0tbPYI/AAAAAAAAAX4/T_aCsKXQbqA/s320/Uninsured_by_State.jpg" border="0" alt=""></a><br /><a name="more"></a><br />Even with the adjustments, the always neatly groomed, with the Edwards haircut, and nattily dressed John Boehner calls it a pay off to Union bosses and liberal special interests. Ohio did register its uninsured numbers at 13.9% of the population which many would probably qualify for Medicaid if unemployed long enough. Then there is Joe Barton of Texas complaining about the extension also. Yep that is Texas, the number 1 amongst all of the states with the highest number of uninsured at 26.9%. Hey at > than 1 in 4 residents without healthcare what could John really say other than: </p>
<p>“There is no emergency!”</p>
<p>Maybe there is no emergency for Rep. John Barton who is covered by the congressional healthcare plan and maybe we can blame the number of uninsured in Texas on illegal and legal Hispanic immigrants? Wonder what was he thinking? </p>
<blockquote><p>“80 percent of those the Gallup organization or the Census Bureau would count as uninsured are actually U.S. citizens. “If we took all the immigrants out of Texas—legal and illegal—we would still have the highest uninsured rate in the country,”</p></blockquote>
<p> says Eva DeLuna, a budget analyst at the Center for Public Policy Priorities (CPPP), an Austin-based think tank. <a target="_blank" href="http://www.newsweek.com/blogs/the-human-condition/2009/08/19/texans-are-most-likely-to-be-uninsured-gallup-says-but-don-t-blame-immigrants.html">Texans are Mostly Likely</a></p>
<p><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_8UVGnCIfOVk/TIeDtov3GII/AAAAAAAAAYA/0F4dX2ybMp8/s1600/uninsured2.jpg"><img src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_8UVGnCIfOVk/TIeDtov3GII/AAAAAAAAAYA/0F4dX2ybMp8/s320/uninsured2.jpg" border="0" alt=""></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/09/whatever-happened-to-the-guns-or-butter-premise.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Health Care Reform and Caregivers Refusing Medicare Patients</title>
		<link>./../../2009/11/health-care-reform-and-caregivers-refusing-medicare-patients.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/11/health-care-reform-and-caregivers-refusing-medicare-patients.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2009 23:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[health care reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medicaid]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medicare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[National Health Insurance]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/11/health-care-reform-and-caregivers-refusing-medicare-patients.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Robert goes out on a limb and guesses that Lori Montgomery fell for (or is pushing) Republican spin in this article in the Washington PostReport: Bill would reduce senior careMedicare cuts approved by House may affect access to providers A plan to slash more than $500 billion from future Medicare spending &#8212; one of the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Robert goes out on a limb and guesses that Lori Montgomery fell for (or is pushing) Republican spin in this article in the Washington Post<br /><a target="_blank" href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2009/11/14/AR2009111402597.html?hpid=topnews">Report: Bill would reduce senior care<br />Medicare cuts approved by House may affect access to providers</a></p>
<blockquote><p>A plan to slash more than $500 billion from future Medicare spending &#8212; one of the biggest sources of funding for President Obama&#8217;s proposed overhaul of the nation&#8217;s health-care system &#8212; would sharply reduce benefits for some senior citizens and could jeopardize access to care for millions of others, according to a government evaluation released Saturday.</p>
<p>The report, requested by House Republicans, found that Medicare cuts contained in the health package approved by the House on Nov. 7 are likely to prove so costly to hospitals and nursing homes that they could stop taking Medicare altogether. </p>
<p>Congress could intervene to avoid such an outcome, but &#8220;so doing would likely result in significantly smaller actual savings&#8221; than is currently projected, according to the analysis by the chief actuary for the agency that administers Medicare and Medicaid.</p></blockquote>
<p>I have read <a target="_blank" href="http://republicans.waysandmeans.house.gov/UploadedFiles/OACT_Memorandum_on_Financial_Impact_of_H_R__3962__11-13-09_.pdf">the report </a>(warning pdf) &#8230; well actually up to the passage stressed by Republicans and Montgomery.  Montgomery&#8217;s article focuses on one paragraph deep in the report which begins &#8220;It is important to note that the estimated savings for one category of Medicare proposals may be unrealistic.&#8221;  That&#8217;s some serious digging.  </p>
<p>The paragraph goes on to discuss what seems to be new additional budgetary flimflam which is assuming that productivity in hospitals and nursing homes grows at the national average (measured productivity grows much more slowly and it doesn&#8217;t matter if  this is due to unmeasured improved quality of care).  That would be part of a large savings of $ 282 billion.  The report doesn&#8217;t describe what the savings would be if Medicare rates were adjusted to a reasonable forecast of productivity growth.</p>
<p>Now I had assumed that Medicare cuts other than eliminating the Medicare advantage boondoggle were reductions in money effectively given to hospitals (and nursing homes etc) so they could afford to take care of the uninsured.  Hospitals&#8217; budgets will be affected by increased health insurance coverage, both by the increases in the total fraction of people insured and the fraction of people with pre-existing conditions insured.  This means that the total effect on Hospitals&#8217; budgets can&#8217;t be calculated assuming only Medicare payment rates change.</p>
<p>Importantly, the Foster (the author) assumes that reduced Medicare payments will cause hospitals to choose to refuse Medicare patients and not drive Hospitals bankrupt.  It is true that relatively lower Medicare rates will cause more hospitals to refuse Medicare patients.  How many currently do?  I googled <br /><a target="_blank" href="http://www.google.it/search?hl=en&#038;safe=off&#038;q=%22hospitals+which+refuse+medicare%22&#038;btnG=Search&#038;aq=f&#038;oq=">&#8220;hospitals which refuse medicare&#8221;</a> I got links to articles about physicians who refuse Medicare patients and <a target="_blank" href="http://forums.poz.com/index.php?topic=15113.0;wap2">this link</a> to someone who works at a hospital where they talked about refusing Medicare patients.</p>
<p>Medicare rates are already low.  There sure don&#8217;t seem to be many hospitals which refuse to treat Medicare patients.  </p>
<p>OK so I tried the past tense and googled <a target="_blank" href="http://www.google.it/search?hl=en&#038;source=hp&#038;q=%22hospital+did+not+accept+medicare%22&#038;btnG=Google+Search&#038;aq=f&#038;oq=">&#8220;hospital did not accept medicare&#8221;</a><br /><a target="_blank" href="http://forums.obgyn.net/womens-health/WHF.9808/0665.html">This link to someone who says an anonymous hospital told her in 1998 that they didn&#8217;t accept Medicare patients.</a></p>
<p>Quite frankly this doesn&#8217;t seem to be a huge problem.  The idea that it will get even bigger if Medicare rates fall further below other rates doesn&#8217;t seem to me to merit page 1 treatment.</p>
<p>I think Foster is saying that he believes that the new restrictions on Medicare compensation will be waived just as the existing restrictions are waived.  He can&#8217;t say that Congress is flimflamming so he has to explain how this might be a natural response to unforeseen events in the future. My current guess is that the event will be the perfectly foreseeable complaints from hospitals and nursing homes and that the forecast that Congress will waive the rule is the only forecast a responsible actuary can make.  </p>
<p>The Republican/Montgomery/www.washingtonpost.com headline guy spin that elderly people will be denied care if the bill passes is absurd.  If that&#8217;s the way things worked, the 1997 rule wouldn&#8217;t be waived year after year.</p>
<p>There don&#8217;t seem to be many reports of hospitals refusing Medicaid either.<br />No google hits for &#8220;hospital refuses medicaid&#8221; one for <a target="_blank" href="http://www.google.it/search?hl=en&#038;safe=off&#038;q=%22hospital+refused+medicaid%22&#038;btnG=Search&#038;aq=f&#038;oq=">&#8220;hospital refused medicaid&#8221;</a>  to <a href="http://209.85.135.132/search?q=cache:ERTPt2Vg9R8J:www.ncpa.org/email/State_HC_Reform_6-8-07.pdf+%22hospital+refused+medicaid%22&#038;cd=1&#038;hl=en&#038;ct=clnk&#038;gl=it&#038;lr=lang_en">a publication </a>of the National Center for Policy Analysis. Hmmm, where have I heard of that? <a target="_blank" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/18/politics/18bartlett.html?_r=1"> It&#8217;s the so called think tank which fired Bruce Bartlett for heresy</a>.  </p>
<p>The document to which I link asserts that Veterans care is queue rationed and that the veterans administration does provide as high quality care as that available to people with private insurance.  Non ideological sources rate the veterans administration as the best care provider &#8212; number one.</p>
<p>I think that &#8220;Hospitals will refuse Medicare and/or Medicaid&#8221; is a serious policy concern on a level similar to the &#8220;tax cuts cause increased revenues.&#8221;  And here it is on the front page of www.washingtonpost.com.</p>
<p>Update:  Note I am writing about <strong>hospitals</strong> who refuse Medicare not doctors in private practice who refuse Medicare.  My googling and questions were on <strong>hospitals</strong> which refuse medicare and/or medicaid.  Of the first 7 comments, 5 discussed office based practices which refuse medicare.  By my count letters &#8220;hospital&#8221; appear in that order 18 (eighteen) times in the post (sometimes followed immediately by an s).  Somehow commenters seem to have overlooked all 18 (eighteen) of them.  </p>
<p>This is not a quibble. The provision of the bill which Foster suspects will not be actually applied concerns &#8220;institutional&#8221; providers of health care not physicians in private practice.  I quote from his report </p>
<blockquote><p>H.R. 3962 would introduce permanent annual productivity adjustments to price updates for <strong>institutional</strong> providers (such as acute car <strong>hospitals</strong>, skilled <strong>nursing facilities</strong>, and home health <strong>agencies</strong>) using a 10-year moving average of economy-wide productivity gains.  [skip] end participation in the program (possibly jeopardizing access to care for beneficiaries).  </p></blockquote>
<p>That&#8217;s why I asked about Hospitals refusing medicare patients.  There is a big difference between squeezing the entities which can&#8217;t be squeezed and squeezing those which can be squeezed (provided they are getting a lot more money due to increased insurance coverage so they won&#8217;t go bankrupt).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/11/health-care-reform-and-caregivers-refusing-medicare-patients.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Medicaid Dilemmas – Part 1</title>
		<link>./../../2009/10/medicaid-dilemmas-part-1.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/10/medicaid-dilemmas-part-1.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Oct 2009 12:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[elderly care]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health Care]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health care costs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hospital obligations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medicaid]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[state spending plans]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/10/medicaid-dilemmas-part-1.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt Medicaid Dilemmas – Part 1 Medicaid is a federal/state program covering poor people, with general services for all ages and long-term care (nursing home) services for the indigent elderly. State budgets are extremely tight, and many states are cutting reimbursements, including nursing home reimbursements. The majority of long-term nursing home [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt</p>
<p>Medicaid Dilemmas – Part 1</p>
<p>Medicaid is a federal/state program covering poor people, with general services for all ages and long-term care (nursing home) services for the indigent elderly.</p>
<p>State budgets are extremely tight, and many states are cutting reimbursements, including nursing home reimbursements.</p>
<p>The majority of long-term nursing home residents (as opposed to short stay rehab patients) end up being Medicaid funded. </p>
<p>A typical long-term resident is an 84 year widow, suffering from moderate senile dementia, having ambulation problems and problems with activities of daily living (eating, dressing, bathing), with late onset diabetes symptoms, osteoarthritis and congestive heart failure. So, grandma is not a candidate for home care or assisted living.</p>
<p>Many residents are in much worse health. Some receive joint services from the facility and from hospice.</p>
<p>Nursing homes have the toughest regulatory regimen of any health care providers, including piles and piles of mandatory paperwork by nursing and administrative staff.</p>
<p>So, not much room to cut (the best profit comes from selling the facility later). Now what?</p>
<p>In Part 2 we will discuss the possible next phase for state Medicaid budgets.</p>
<p>(The wife, aka the world’s greatest nurse, works part time in long-term care, and will now do more work and take a pay cut. She understands the deal, but one of these days she is going to hang up her stethoscope, a real tragedy for the elderly. Maybe she will become an investment banker – nah, too honest.)<br />______________________________________<br />Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/10/medicaid-dilemmas-part-1.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Re-tooling the Medicare/medicaid model</title>
		<link>./../../2009/08/re-tooling-the-medicaremedicaid-model.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/08/re-tooling-the-medicaremedicaid-model.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2009 14:46:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Healthcare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medicaid]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medicare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SILO/LILO]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/08/re-tooling-the-medicaremedicaid-model.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[rdan I read the Op-Ed in the Boston Globe and asked Doug to write a piece or pieces in a more detailed fashion. There have been allusions to this issue as a cost factor, but no policy consideration here to date. Post by Doug Brown Due to the complexity of organizations today, there is commonly [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>rdan</p>
<p>I read the Op-Ed in the Boston Globe and asked Doug to write a piece or pieces in a more detailed fashion.  There have been allusions to this issue as a cost factor, but no policy consideration here to date.</p>
<p><strong>Post by Doug Brown</strong></p>
<p>Due to the complexity of organizations today, there is commonly a “silo mentality” that develops where one department often doesn’t know what another is doing.  Employees are good at looking at the “trees” within their silo, but very few are seeing the forest.  We have all seen it.  The result is usually organizational dysfunction.  Nowhere is this more pronounced than at one of our largest government agencies – the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services (CMS).  What’s worse, this dysfunction has enormous consequences for the cost and quality of health care that is delivered in this country.  And yet, as we embark on the most significant reform to our health care system in over forty years, no one is talking about this issue.  </p>
<p>In a July 20 Op Ed in the Boston Globe entitled <a target="_blank" href="http://www.boston.com/bostonglobe/editorial_opinion/oped/articles/2009/07/20/retooling_the_medicaremedicaid_model/">Retooling the Medicare/Medicaid Model</a>, I explored this issue.  Specifically, I highlighted a program in Massachusetts that successfully breaks down the silos between these two programs to do what’s best for patients.  </p>
<p>This care delivery model, called Senior Care Options, pools funding from Medicare and Medicaid to allow private organization to integrate care for dually eligible individuals (those eligible for both Medicare and Medicaid, and some of the most costly individuals on our public programs) to provide truly coordinated care that is patient centered and cost effective.  The model has been very successful in keeping seniors out of expensive nursing homes and making them happy and satisfied.  So the question is: in light of what seems to me to be such an obvious opportunity, why aren’t more states doing something about it and why aren’t more people talking about it?  </p>
<p>I received a number of interesting responses to my Op Ed, some of which speculate on this question.  One was from Renee Markus Hodin of Community Catalyst, a well respected consumer advocacy organization.  She reported that her organization has been trying to make headway on this issue for years.  They even got a provision inserted into the original House health reform bill to specially protect and encourage more SCO programs.  But the provision was eliminated, apparently due to a misunderstanding.  I am told it was opposed by some beneficiary groups “who were wary of the provision being abused by states that want to dump their duals into private plans and/or by plans that were not committed to providing the kind of care delivery system that we see under the SCO program.”  That has not been the experience of SCO at all.  But unfortunately, it seems that some of the new “Special Needs Plans” (SNPs) that were created recently by Congress to try to address dual eligibles are not working as intended and do not fully integrate care like SCO does.  </p>
<p>The beauty of the SCO program is that there is a three-way contract; between the state Medicaid agency, Medicare and the SCO.  This is critical to ensure full integration among both programs.   Renee tells me they are trying again and hoping to garner more support.   </p>
<p>I received another response from Jennifer Baron, a senior researcher at the Harvard Business School.  She too has been working on this issue for a number of years.  Here was her post to the online version of my Op Ed:  </p>
<blockquote><p>In April 2008, Harvard Business School Professor Michael Porter and I published a case study profiling Commonwealth Care Alliance (CCA), one of the three organizations offering a SCO plan. This case is one of the few examples we’ve found of a high-value approach to insurance coupled with an innovative care delivery model. Invariably when the case study is taught, students approach us after class to inquire how they can become involved with CCA or SCO. </p>
<p>We&#8217;ve found it particularly inspiring that under the pooled Medicare/Medicaid payment model, CCA managed to successfully serve one of the most complex and costly patient populations on the planet. In 2006-7, the only patient population for which CCA’s costs exceeded average premiums was the institutionalized population. Average premiums for the frail elderly patients who remained outside of institutional settings all exceeded costs. Talk about aligning financial and patient incentives!</p>
<p>My understanding is that once SCO graduated from a demonstration to a Special Needs Plan in 2009, the single three-way contract with Medicare and Medicaid &#8211; one of the most innovative aspects of the reimbursement model – disappeared. Though both Medicare and Medicaid continue to fund the plan as a SNP, I believe they must now contract separately with participating organizations.</p></blockquote>
<p>For additional information, the CCA case study abstract is posted on the Institute for <a target="_blank" href="websitehttp://www.hbs.edu/rhc/health_care_delivery_curriculum.html">Strategy &#038; Competitiveness website</a>. </p>
<p>My best judgment of why this is not getting better traction is twofold: first, Medicare and Medicaid are incredibly complex and few inside and outside of healthcare really understand either one, let alone the way they intersect (that is why I tried hard to make my Op Ed explain the issue as simply as possible; you can let me know whether I succeeded).  Second, we have lacked leadership and focus at the federal level.  CMS has become such a large bureaucracy that it is overwhelming to even think about how one might reorganize it so that it better serves patients.  But in my view it must be done.  I remain very hopeful that with a new administration and a new focus on health reform, we have a unique opportunity to finally address this issue.  I would love to hear your thoughts and ideas on the subject, including ways we might try to help make this happen.<br />_____________________________________<br />by Doug Brown</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/08/re-tooling-the-medicaremedicaid-model.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
