<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>mortgage regulation &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>New Ruling on Mortgage Putbacks a Potential Huge Win for Banks</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/new-ruling-on-mortgage-putbacks-a-potential-huge-win-for-banks.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/new-ruling-on-mortgage-putbacks-a-potential-huge-win-for-banks.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Jan 2013 13:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[mortgage regulation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Yves Smith]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/new-ruling-on-mortgage-putbacks-a-potential-huge-win-for-banks.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Yves Smith discusses New Ruling on Mortgage Putbacks a Potential Huge Win for Banks Even though, for most people, the housing crisis is a thing of the past, the fight over who should bear the cost of sloppy and openly fraudulent mortgage origination and securities sales continues to grind through the courts. We’ve written now [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Yves Smith discusses <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2013/01/new-ruling-on-mortgage-putbacks-a-potential-huge-win-for-banks.html">New Ruling on Mortgage Putbacks a Potential Huge Win for Banks</a></p>
<blockquote><p>Even though, for most people, the housing crisis is a thing of the past, the fight over who should bear the cost of sloppy and openly fraudulent mortgage origination and securities sales continues to grind through the courts.</p>
<p>We’ve written now and again about mortgage putback cases, which are also called representation and warranty, or “rep and warranty” litigation. Investors in mortgage-backed securities were not quite as dumb as the crisis aftermath had made them look. The sponsors of the securitizations made promises in the offering documents (called representations and warranties) about the quality of the loans. It turns out they lied.</p>
<p>Normally, when a loan is found to be worse than the sponsors promised, the remedy is a putback. The originator is required to take the bad loan back and replace it, either with cash or buy replacing it with a loan that was of the quality that the investors were promised. However, the mortgage securitizations put hurdles in front of the investors: it took a minimum level of investors (usually 25%) to demand putbacks and it was hard for any investor to know who else had bought a particular deal. Even then, the trustee (who was the party who was responsible for putting back the loan) almost always ignored and fought investor putback requests. They have ongoing relationships with the sponsors, so they don’t want to ruffle big meal tickets, plus the margins for acting as a mortgage securitization trustee are thin, so they don’t lift a finger unless they absolutely have to&#8230;</p></blockquote>
<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/new-ruling-on-mortgage-putbacks-a-potential-huge-win-for-banks.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Robosigning and gutter service</title>
		<link>./../../2012/02/robosigning-and-gutter-service.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/02/robosigning-and-gutter-service.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2012 14:46:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[mortgage regulation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mortgage settlement]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/02/robosigning-and-gutter-service.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Matt Taibbi is succinct on the reported but not final agreement among state AG&#8217;s on the mortgage settlement: I think the best summation of the settlement is probably Yves Smith&#8217;s, which can be found here. The piece lists the 12 things that suck the most about the settlement. The most painful is probably #12: 12. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.rollingstone.com/politics/blogs/taibblog/why-the-foreclosure-deal-may-not-be-so-hot-after-all-20120209">Matt Taibbi</a> is succinct on the reported but not final agreement among state AG&#8217;s on the mortgage settlement:<br />
<blockquote>I think the best summation of the settlement is probably Yves Smith&#8217;s,<a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/yves-smith/mortgage-settlement_b_1264806.html"> which can be found here</a>. The piece lists the 12 things that suck the most about the settlement. The most painful is probably #12:<br />
<blockquote>12. We&#8217;ll now have to listen to banks and their sycophant defenders declaring victory despite being wrong on the law and the facts. They will proceed to marginalize and write off criticisms of the servicing practices that hurt homeowners and investors and are devastating communities. But the problems will fester and the housing market will continue to suffer. Investors in mortgage-backed securities, who know that services have been screwing them for years, will be hung out to dry and will likely never return to a private MBS market, since the problems won&#8217;t ever be fixed. This settlement has not only revealed the residential mortgage market to be too big to fail, but puts it on long term, perhaps permanent, government life support.</p></blockquote>
<p>My mistake in looking at this deal a few weeks ago, when details of it first leaked out, was in focusing on how much worse it could have been, instead of thinking about how bad it still is. The only acceptable foreclosure deal had to bring about a complete end to robosigning and the other similar corrupt practices that grew up around it (like for instance <a href="http://www.longislandlawyerblog.com/lawsuit-over-process-server-fraud-seeks-to-vacate-100000-debt-collection-judgments">gutter service</a>, the practice of process servers simply signing affidavits <em>saying </em>they delivered summonses, instead of really doing it).<br />But this deal not only doesn&#8217;t end robosigning, it officially makes getting caught for it inexpensive. Shame on me for ever thinking that might be a good thing.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/02/robosigning-and-gutter-service.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Denial in the Mortgage Industrial Complex</title>
		<link>./../../2011/11/denial-in-the-mortgage-industrial-complex.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/11/denial-in-the-mortgage-industrial-complex.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2011 14:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[mortgage markets]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mortgage regulation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[naked Capitalism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/11/denial-in-the-mortgage-industrial-complex.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Yves Smith provides a snapshot of her perception of at least public thoughts from mortgage industry conference participants. It is worth a read. Denial in the Mortgage Industrial Complex I just came back from the AmeriCatalyst conference in Austin, which was a packed two days focused on the state of the housing and securitization market. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Yves Smith provides a snapshot of her perception of at least public thoughts from mortgage industry conference participants. It is worth a read.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2011/11/denial-in-the-mortgage-industrial-complex.html">Denial in the Mortgage Industrial Complex</a></p>
<blockquote><p>I just came back from the <a href="http://americatalyst.com/americatalyst-2011-home-page/1893-2/">AmeriCatalyst conference in Austin</a>, which was a packed two days focused on the state of the housing and securitization market. The panels were very informative, and it was also good to see some of the people I’ve read or heard about, in particular the leading analyst, Laurie Goodman of Amherst Securities. She gave a talk that where she went through a very persuasive (and conservative) analysis that there are 8.3 to 10.3 million more foreclosures baked give how underwater <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2011/11/#">borrowers</a> are. And she had some striking bits of information. One is if you take out the homes where no one has made a mortgage payment in a year or more, homeownership in the US is 61%. In addition, Judge Annette Rizzo discussed a successful program she had developed in Philadelphia to do remediation. The success rate on modifications that come out of her court is 85% after 18 months. </p>
<p>I had quite a few people come and commend me on my comments. I think the main reason was that the viewpoint presented on this blog, that there are deep seated problems resulting from chain of title issues, and that servicers have engaged in a lot of abuses, was sorely underrepresented. I don’t blame the organizer,</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/11/denial-in-the-mortgage-industrial-complex.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mortgage Mess being re-aired</title>
		<link>./../../2011/03/mortgage-mess-being-re-aired.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/03/mortgage-mess-being-re-aired.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 16:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[mortgage regulation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Yves Smith]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/03/mortgage-mess-being-re-aired.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Yves Smith on the Harry Shearer show concerning the Mortgage Mess is being re-aired this Sunday (see link for times). The transcript for the show is at the link.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a target="_blank" href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2011/03/we-explain-the-mortgage-mess-on-harry-shearers-le-show-on-sunday.html">Yves Smith</a> on the <a target="_blank" href="http://harryshearer.com/news/le_show/">Harry Shearer show</a> concerning the Mortgage Mess is being re-aired this Sunday (see <a target="_blank" href="http://media.harryshearer.com/syndicates.html">link for times</a>).</p>
<p><a target="_blank" href="http://www.harryshearer.com/article/?auid=WmyVa-418-cDmH8">The transcript for the show</a> is at the link.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/03/mortgage-mess-being-re-aired.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>More on the Mortgage Mess</title>
		<link>./../../2011/02/more-on-the-mortgage-mess.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/02/more-on-the-mortgage-mess.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 23 Feb 2011 18:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[mortgage markets]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mortgage regulation]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/02/more-on-the-mortgage-mess.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Beale More on the Mortgage Mess As our banking giants engaged more and more in speculation, and as the shadow banking system saw a way to make money off of people&#8217;s bad financial decisions by betting against subprime loans, the financial crisis took off.  So redressing the problems that caused the crisis shouldn&#8217;t [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by <strong>Linda Beale</strong></p>
<p><a target href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2011/02/more-on-the-mortgage-mess.html">More on the Mortgage Mess</a>
<p>As our banking giants engaged more and more in speculation, and as the shadow banking system saw a way to make money off of people&#8217;s bad financial decisions by betting against subprime loans, the financial crisis took off.  So redressing the problems that caused the crisis shouldn&#8217;t overlook mortgages.</p>
<p>The Treasury has now come out with a &#8220;plan&#8221; for addressing the government sponsored enterprises Fannie and Freddie, which played a role in the crisis though were not the drivers of the subprime origination mess.  The plan, <a href="http://www.treasury.gov/initiatives/Documents/Reforming%20America%27s%20Housing%20Finance%20Market.pdf">Reforming America&#8217;s Housing Finance Market: A Report to Congress</a> (Treasury and Housing and Urban Development, Feb. 2011), claims that it will &#8220;reform America&#8217;s housing finance market to better serve families and function more safely in a world that has changed dramatically.&#8221;  It also claims that it is intended to limit the government&#8217;s primary role to &#8220;robust oversight and consumer protection, targeted assistance for low-and moderate-income homeowners and renters, and carefully designed support for market stability and crisis response.&#8221;</p>
<p> <a name="more"></a>
<p>Both of those claims are worrisome.  First, the alternatives proposed seem better designed to serve the financial services industry than famililes.  Not only is there still no provision for mortgage modification in bankruptcy, but securitization is intended to &#8220;continue to play a major role in housing finance&#8221;, even though the securitization process has brought a nightmare of foreclosure mills and uncertainties about who owns debt and has the right to foreclose.  While the Administration walks the GOP-favored walk of decreasing government/increasing private markets, it nonetheless leaves government as the one that backstops the private mortgage market, retaining the possibility of private gains and social losses.</p>
<p>Second, the statement that government will be limited to &#8220;carefully designed support for market stability and crisis response&#8221; means that the government will continue to backstop the securitization losses, as Yves Smith at Naked Capitalism puts it in <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2011/02/15844.html">The 7 Things Really Wrong with the Treasury&#8217;s GSE Proposal</a>:</p>
<p>Of the Treasury three proposals, the last is the same as one advanced by the big guns, from the<a href="http://www.mortgagebankers.org/files/Advocacy/2009/RecommendationsfortheFutureGovernmentRole.pdf"> Mortgage Bankers Association</a>, the Fed (both the New York Fed and the Board of Governors), the Financial Services Roundtable and <a href="http://www.economy.com/mark-zandi/documents/Mortgage-Finance-Reform-020711.pdf">Mark Zandi of Moodys</a>. This alternative preserves too many bad elements of status quo ante, in particular significant and largely hidden subsidies for banks, for anyone to hail it as reform. Although each proposal has some distinctive wrinkles, all call for the creation of “private” entities that would provide insurance to mortgage backed securities that would then be reinsured by the government, with a full faith and credit guarantee.</p>
<p>What is to prevent huge public losses?  The proposal relies on a guarantee fee and higher bank capital requirements.   This isn&#8217;t good enough because it builds too much on the status quo ante.  Yves Smith provides her list of the Treasury proposal&#8217;s problems:</p>
<ol>
<li>The most pressing problems related to the crisis of abuses in the housing securitization markets outside of Fannie and Freddie are still not addressed </li>
<li>The plan continues to use a poor tool to address housing goals, by focusing on mortgage financing. </li>
<li>Reliance on the old 30-year fixed rate prepayable mortgage is outdated and fails to address today&#8217;s markets. </li>
<li>Continued use of the private (owners of the entities)/public (backers of the entities debts) structure is fated to suffer the same problems with increasing risk and lobbying as Fannie and Freddie </li>
<li>This just props up the housing market; it isn&#8217;t really a help to consumers. </li>
<li>The new entities will continue the conflicting roles of the pre-crash Fannie and Freddie of propping up liquidity and making credit decisions. </li>
<li>There&#8217;s nothing to keep these new entities from being too big to fail.</li>
</ol>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/02/more-on-the-mortgage-mess.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
