<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>free trade &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Latest World Trade Organization Lunacy</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/latest-world-trade-organization-lunacy.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/latest-world-trade-organization-lunacy.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2013 13:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[free trade]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Trans Pacific Partnership]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WTO]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/latest-world-trade-organization-lunacy.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Dan Becker&#8217;s post Trans Pacific Partnership: A new Constitution gained a lot of traction because once again the public media is beginning to pay attention to trade policy. Angry Bear has carried a number of posts on the World Trade Organization intent and structure&#8230;here are several on the particular issue between Antigua and the US. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Dan Becker&#8217;s post <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/03/trans-pacific-partnership-new.html" target="_blank">Trans Pacific Partnership: A new Constitution</a> gained a lot of traction because once again the public media is beginning to pay attention to trade policy.  Angry Bear has carried a number of posts on the World Trade Organization intent and structure&#8230;here are several on the particular issue between Antigua and the US.  The issue is not earthshaking in amounts of money, but offers a look at the potential conflicts that can play out between nations.  Perhaps coming later further exploration of the World Trade Organization (from past Angry Bear posts) will be warranted.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2007/07/johna-on-price-of-free-trade-or-price.html" target="_blank">Price of free trade or the price of protectionism</a>, <br /><a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2007/08/antigua-update-part-i-wto-gats.html" target="_blank">Antigua update Part 1 WTO GATS</a>, <br /><a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2007/12/update-about-antigua-and-wto.html" target="_blank">Update about Antigua</a>, <br /><a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2008/03/wto-and-antigua-follow-up.html" target="_blank">WTO and Antigua follow up</a></p>
<p>From <i>The Huffington Post</i> by Lori Wallach comes this note:</p>
<p><a href="https://www.blogger.com/%3Ca%20href=" http:="" internet-pirates-of-the-c_b_2576198.html="" lori-wallach="" target="_blank" title="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/lori-wallach/internet-pirates-of-the-c_b_2576198.html" www.huffingtonpost.com="">Internet pirates of the Caribbean</a></p>
<blockquote><p>On Monday the World Trade Organization (WTO) officially <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/01/29/business/global/dispute-with-antigua-and-barbuda-threatens-us-copyrights.html?_r=0">authorized</a> Caribbean nation Antigua to sell $21 million in &#8220;pirated&#8221; U.S.-copyrighted music, films and computer programs in retaliation for the United States failing to comply with a <a href="http://www.citizen.org/documents/Gamblingsummary2007.pdf">2005 WTO order</a> to allow online gambling here. Say what? (And, no, this news was not sourced from a parody in <em>The Onion</em>.)</p>
<p>The case is an illustrated guide to much of <a href="http://www.citizen.org/Page.aspx?pid=758">what is wrong with the WTO</a>. And, it should spotlight the lunacy of Obama administration plans to expand this dangerous &#8220;trade&#8221; agreement model via the <a href="http://www.citizen.org/TPP">Trans-Pacific Partnership (TPP) &#8220;free trade&#8221;</a> agreement. More on that later. Let&#8217;s tour what is now a full coop of WTO chickens that have come home to roost on this WTO case.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>First, the backstory: in 2003, Antigua filed a case at the WTO claiming that U.S. laws banning Internet gambling violated WTO rules. The case, which some say was in fact the brainchild of an American attorney, Mark Mandel, who is handling the WTO litigation for Antigua, was joined by the European Union and other countries with major gambling industries. Antigua won a final ruling in 2005 and yesterday&#8217;s &#8220;sanctions&#8221; announcement was retaliation for the United States failing to change its domestic laws to comply with the WTO.</p>
<p>Why does the WTO have <em>anything</em> to say as to whether or not the U.S. Congress can ban Internet gambling, especially when the ban applies to domestic and foreign firms alike? Unlike past <u>trade</u> agreements, which focused on cutting tariffs, the WTO imposes expansive constraints on signatory governments&#8217; <u>non-trade</u> policies and establishes new corporate rights. The WTO&#8217;s General Agreement on Trade in Services (GATS) limits how the U.S. government may regulate foreign service firms operating here and cross-border &#8220;trade&#8221; in services too. The WTO&#8217;s Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights (TRIPS) agreement requires countries to provide expanded monopoly patent and copyright terms. (That&#8217;s how U.S. drug patent monopolies got expanded from 17 to 20 years in 1994 when Congress OK&#8217;d U.S. WTO accession, overruling decades of congressional opposition to such patent extensions and costing us billions in higher drug prices, pocketed by WTO booster Big PhRMA.)</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/latest-world-trade-organization-lunacy.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Copyrights and free market pricing</title>
		<link>./../../2012/11/copyrights-and-free-market-pricing.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/11/copyrights-and-free-market-pricing.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2012 13:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[free market fetishism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[free trade]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/11/copyrights-and-free-market-pricing.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The New York Times points us to one anomaly in the idea of &#8220;free markets&#8221;. Dean Baker (and many others) of course has championed taking a more critical look at this set of issues for years.  But most readers know that &#8220;free market&#8221; is an election slogan and a metaphorical  apocryphal story line rather than  something [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/11/05/opinion/copyright-on-imported-works.html?emc=tnt&#038;tntemail1=y">The New York Times</a> points us to one anomaly in the idea of &#8220;free markets&#8221;. Dean Baker (and many others) of course has championed taking a more critical look at this set of issues for years.  But most readers know that &#8220;free market&#8221; is an election slogan and a <strike>metaphorica</strike>l  apocryphal story line rather than  something real for guiding either private companies or governments policies and rules.  On the other hand, that is the language used and something I hear from people in a non-critical way.</div>
<p>Copyright and patent rights need strong government to enforce the rules, and distort &#8220;pricing&#8221; mechanisms.   Yet it does not seem to be enough to cajole people into making a list of possible exceptions and then applying the rule of  &#8220;free&#8221;&#8230;if open to exception, where does it stop?  Often the question puts people to sleep, but is part of the bread and butter of real multinational companies.  And then enforcement falls to whom?  Who votes based on such details?  Trade policy hasn&#8217;t had traction for years.  </p>
<blockquote><p>&#8230;can sell their copyrighted works abroad at prices different from what they charge in the American market and rely on copyright law to help maintain the separate pricing without having importers profit from the difference. The justices should rule that the Copyright Act and a revision to it that Congress made in 1976 prohibit such resales…..</p></blockquote>
<p>.<br /><a name="more"></a>&#8230; <br />
<blockquote>A federal trial court ordered Mr. Kirtsaeng to pay $600,000 in damages for infringing on the Wiley copyright by reselling more than 600 copies of eight different books that he bought in Thailand. Mr. Kirtsaeng contends that the law allows him to resell the textbooks because he, family members and friends bought them legally and a principle called the first-sale doctrine, announced by the Supreme Court in a 1908 <a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?court=us&#038;vol=210&#038;invol=339">ruling</a> and codified into law by Congress, says copyright owners cannot control the distribution and pricing of works, like books, after the initial sale.</p>
<p>But the Copyright Act <a href="http://www.bloomberglaw.com/public/document/John_Wiley__Sons_v_Kirtsaeng_654_F3d_210_99_USPQ2d_1641_2d_Cir_20">prohibits</a> anyone from importing into the United States copyrighted works without the copyright holder’s approval. That provision would be seriously limited if copies of a work made abroad could be resold by importers in this country without constraint.</p>
<p>This case requires a difficult interpretation of the Copyright Act, but that is made easier by understanding the intent of Congress when it revised the law in 1976. It did so to broaden protection against unauthorized imports of copyrighted works by so-called gray-market sellers, and to make easier the kind of market segmentation by geography and price that Mr. Kirtsaeng’s resales subverted. With segmentation, book publishers can offer cheaper editions of their works in less-developed countries, without concern that those copies will be resold in the United States and unfairly undercut sales here. </p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/11/copyrights-and-free-market-pricing.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Did Romney speak blasphemously?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/did-romney-speak-blasphemously.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/did-romney-speak-blasphemously.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 17 Oct 2012 16:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[free trade]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[global economies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[presidential debate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[protectionism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tariffs]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/did-romney-speak-blasphemously.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Of all the things being deconstructed regarding the debate last night, this is the one that stood out for me: QUESTION: The outsourcing of American jobs overseas has taken a toll on our economy. What plans do you have to put back and keep jobs here in the United States? Romney:&#8230;which will allow me as [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>Of all the things being deconstructed regarding the debate last night, <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/decision2012/2012-presidential-debate-president-obama-and-mitt-romneys-remarks-at-hofstra-university-on-oct-16-running-transcript/2012/10/16/be8bfb9a-17dd-11e2-9855-71f2b202721b_story_4.html" target="_blank">this is the one</a> that stood out for me:</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<blockquote><div>QUESTION: The outsourcing of American jobs overseas has taken a toll on our economy. What plans do you have to put back and keep jobs here in the United States?</div>
<div></div>
<div><i>Romney:&#8230;which will allow me as president to be able to put in place, if necessary, tariffs where I believe that they are taking unfair advantage of our manufacturers.  </i></div>
</blockquote>
<div>So, who is it on Romney&#8217;s team that has decided this is a viable tool regarding the position labor is in?  Is this what would be expected of a Republican presidential candidate?  It just floored me to hear Romney speak the word &#8220;tariff&#8221; when presenting his solution to the question.  What would Uncle Milton think of his school&#8217;s chosen one?</div>
<p>
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/did-romney-speak-blasphemously.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>U.S. Trade Deficit Largely Due to &#034;Intra-Firm&#034; Trade</title>
		<link>./../../2012/08/u-s-trade-deficit-largely-due-to-intra-firm-trade.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/08/u-s-trade-deficit-largely-due-to-intra-firm-trade.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 Aug 2012 03:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[free trade]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[intra-firm trade]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[trade agreements]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[trade balances]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transfer pricing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[US trade deficit]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/08/u-s-trade-deficit-largely-due-to-intra-firm-trade.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Kenneth Thomas U.S. Trade Deficit Largely Due to &#8220;Intra-Firm&#8221; Trade The vast majority of the U.S. $727 billion trade deficit in goods for 2011 is due to &#8220;intra-firm&#8221; or &#8220;related party&#8221; trade, that is, trade between two units of the same corporation, according to the U.S. Census Bureau. This is significant because such trade [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Kenneth Thomas</p>
<p>U.S. Trade Deficit Largely Due to &#8220;Intra-Firm&#8221; Trade</p>
<p> The vast majority of the U.S. $727 billion trade deficit in goods for 2011 is due to &#8220;intra-firm&#8221; or &#8220;related party&#8221; trade, that is, trade between two units of the same corporation, according to the <a href="http://sasweb.ssd.census.gov/relatedparty/">U.S. Census Bureau</a>. This is significant because such trade is the most open to companies manipulating the prices between subsidiaries to minimize tax liabilities, usually known as abusive <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2011/11/how-transfer-pricing-hurts-middle-class.html">transfer pricing</a>. Moreover, as <a href="http://www.spokesmanbooks.com/acatalog/Stuart_Holland.html">Stuart Holland </a>argued in 1987, intra-firm trade is also less responsive to changes in exchange rates than is trade between independent businesses, since within an individual multinational corporation each subsidiary will have a specific role to play in its supply chain, which won&#8217;t be quickly changed.    </p>
<p>U.S. goods trade and related party trade (billions of dollars), world and selected countries, 2011:    <br />Country        Exports from US Imports to US Balance    <br />World            $1480.4     $2707.8          &#8211; $727.4    <br />World (RP)     $ 365.0      $1056.2          &#8211; $691.2    <br />Canada          $ 280.9      $ 315.3            -$  34.5    <br />Canada (RP)   $ 98.1        $ 162.0           &#8211; $ 64.1    <br />Ireland           $ 7.6          $ 39.4             &#8211; $ 31.7    <br />Ireland (RP)    $ 1.5          $ 34.6             &#8211; $ 33.1    <br />Mexico           $ 196.4      $ 262.9            &#8211; $ 64.5    <br />Mexico (RP)    $ 60.5        $ 155.7            &#8211; $ 95.2</p>
<p>Sources: Total trade, U.S. Census, <a href="http://www.census.gov/foreign-trade/balance/c0015.html">Trade in Good with World, Not Seasonally Adjusted</a>; Related party (RP) trade, U.S. Census, <a href="http://sasweb.ssd.census.gov/relatedparty/">NAICS Related-Party</a>, select all NAICS2, 2011, all countries, variables &#8220;imports related trade&#8221; and &#8220;exports related trade&#8221; and layout by country. <a href="http://www.census.gov/foreign-trade/balance/c1220.html">Canada</a>, <a href="http://www.census.gov/foreign-trade/balance/c4190.html">Ireland</a>, and <a href="http://www.census.gov/foreign-trade/balance/c2010.html">Mexico</a> as linked.    </p>
<p>As we can see, related party trade (which can mean trade within either a U.S. or foreign multinational corporation) is 27.6% of goods trade, but it represents a whopping 95.0% of the trade deficit. Moreover, in</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>countries where the U.S. has heavy foreign direct investment, such as Canada, Ireland, and Mexico, the trade deficit for intra-firm trade actually exceeds the country&#8217;s overall trade deficit.<br />In fact, virtually all U.S. imports from Ireland take the form of intra-firm trade. This is no doubt due to Ireland&#8217;s status as a tax haven and low corporate income tax rate of 12.5%.    </p>
<p>These data suggest that much of the U.S. trade deficit is due to U.S. corporations offshoring production and exporting the products back home. As the related-party data does not distinguish between U.S. and foreign multinationals, there is no way to know exactly how big the share of U.S. multinationals is in intra-firm, but is surely much more than half. Moreover, not counted in the data are imports that come from subcontractors (Wal-Mart&#8217;s many suppliers, Foxconn producing Apple products, etc.).    </p>
<p>The bottom line is that we need to reverse the incentives in the tax code that encourage the offshoring of jobs. (Why does <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/03/apple-whines-about-having-to-pay-taxes.html">Apple have $64 billion in cash abroad</a>?) However, to emphasize the point I made<a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/08/it-middle-class-stupid-review.html"> last time</a> about what Americans want out of tax reform and the &#8220;reform&#8221; that has actually happened, it&#8217;s worth pointing out that Robert Gilpin of Princeton University, author of the seminal <i>U.S. Power and the Multinational Corporation</i> (<a href="http://www.amazon.com/U-S-Power-Multinational-Corporation-international/dp/0465089518">1975</a>), made the same policy recommendation almost 40 years ago, and it hasn&#8217;t happened yet. We&#8217;ve got our work cut out for us.</p>
<p>UPDATE: Following the Mitt George Romney rule (&#8220;one year might be a fluke&#8221;), I went back and collected the data for all years back to 2002 (the earliest for which the related party trade info was available). While 2009-11 were all 95%, previous years were generally between 70% and 80%. I&#8217;m not sure yet what to make of that.</p>
<div><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-vlIddA2Zvcw/UCRCwF5Qb7I/AAAAAAAAA9E/1Ycpj4_TMYw/s1600/update.PNG" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="251" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-vlIddA2Zvcw/UCRCwF5Qb7I/AAAAAAAAA9E/1Ycpj4_TMYw/s640/update.PNG" width="640"></a></div>
<p>cross posted with <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766">Middle class Political Economist</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/08/u-s-trade-deficit-largely-due-to-intra-firm-trade.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>&#034;Free trade&#034; and the Tea Party Congress</title>
		<link>./../../2011/10/free-trade-and-the-tea-party-congress.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/10/free-trade-and-the-tea-party-congress.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2011 12:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[free trade]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Occupywallst.]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tea Party]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/10/free-trade-and-the-tea-party-congress.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[An op-ed in the Washington Post points to an idea worth exploring: For all the talk of populist foment – the Tea Party on the right and the new Occupy Wall Street movement on the left – business interests remain firmly in control. Forced to choose between their voters and their donors, lawmakers don’t hesitate [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/the-tea-party-loses-another-round/2011/10/12/gIQAxbU2fL_story.html?hpid=z2">An op-ed</a> in the Washington Post points to an idea worth exploring:<br />
<blockquote>
<p>For all the talk of populist foment – the Tea Party on the right and the new Occupy Wall Street movement on the left – business interests remain firmly in control. Forced to choose between their voters and their donors, lawmakers don’t hesitate before choosing the latter.</p>
<p>There is little doubt about where the Tea Party faithful stands on free trade. A year ago, a <a href="http://online.wsj.com/public/resources/documents/WSJNBCPoll09282010.pdf">Wall Street Journal-NBC News poll</a> found that 61 percent of Tea Party supporters thought free-trade agreements had hurt the country, compared to 53 percent of Americans overall who held that view. Shortly after that, a <a href="http://www.people-press.org/2010/11/09/public-support-for-increased-trade-except-with-south-korea-and-china/">Pew Research Center poll</a> found that only 24 percent of Tea Party supporters thought free-trade agreements were good for America.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/10/free-trade-and-the-tea-party-congress.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Corporations pushing for job-creation tax breaks shield U.S.-vs.-abroad hiring data</title>
		<link>./../../2011/08/corporations-pushing-for-job-creation-tax-breaks-shield-u-s-vs-abroad-hiring-data.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/08/corporations-pushing-for-job-creation-tax-breaks-shield-u-s-vs-abroad-hiring-data.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2011 13:23:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[federal subsidies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[free trade]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[international trade]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax cuts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[taxes. federal deficit]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/08/corporations-pushing-for-job-creation-tax-breaks-shield-u-s-vs-abroad-hiring-data.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The Washington Post points us to a thought that needs to be included in public debate. (h/t Stormy) Corporations pushing for job-creation tax breaks shield U.S.-vs.-abroad hiring data Some of the country’s best-known multi­national corporations closely guard a number they don’t want anyone to know: the breakdown between their jobs here and abroad. So secretive [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/business/economy/corporations-pushing-for-job-creation-tax-breaks-shield-us-vs-abroad-hiring-data/2011/08/12/gIQAZwhqUJ_story.html?hpid=z2%3C/a">The Washington Post</a> points us to a thought that needs to be included in public debate. (h/t Stormy)</p>
<p><strong>Corporations pushing for job-creation tax breaks shield U.S.-vs.-abroad hiring data</strong></p>
<blockquote><p>Some of the country’s best-known multi­national corporations closely guard a number they don’t want anyone to know: the breakdown between their jobs here and abroad.</p>
<p>So secretive are these companies that they hand the figure over to government statisticians on the condition that officials will release only an aggregate number. The latest data show that multinationals cut 2.9 million jobs in the United States and added 2.4 million overseas between 2000 and 2009.</p>
<p>Some of the same companies that do not report their jobs breakdown, including <a href="http://washpost.bloomberg.com/marketnews/stockdetail/?symbol=AAPL">Apple</a> and <a href="http://washpost.bloomberg.com/marketnews/stockdetail/?symbol=PFE">Pfizer</a>, are pushing lawmakers to cut their tax bills in the name of job creation in the United States.</p></blockquote>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />
<br />Apple, by the way, is at the top or close to the top, in recent profits. GE has deceased its per centage of US workers from 54% to 46% in the last decade. Few contenders in the presidentail elections or Congressional elections make this notion a part of their campaigns. The debate in regular media usually stops at words like &#8216;protectionism&#8217;. The next time you read about tax cut money flowing to create jobs, hold in mind global trade demands that companies actually respond to, and do not think US jobs are a priority. The rhetoric merely implies a vague ideal&#8230;not company policies.</p>
<p>Perhaps multi-national companies need to be lean and mean to thrive, and raising the overall living standards of the world has trememdous benefits for people in general, and of course some problems that go with it. Just don&#8217;t think that election political rhetoric has US public benefit in mind overall as a priority high on the list.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/08/corporations-pushing-for-job-creation-tax-breaks-shield-u-s-vs-abroad-hiring-data.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Compensating the Losers from Trade</title>
		<link>./../../2011/02/compensating-the-losers-from-trade.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/02/compensating-the-losers-from-trade.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Feb 2011 14:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[free trade]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[international trade]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/02/compensating-the-losers-from-trade.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Uwe Reinhardt&#8217;s post the other day, &#8220;How Convincing is the Case for Free Trade?&#8220;, helped to kick-start a fair bit of discussion recently about the impact of international trade on the US economy. Mark Thoma and William Polley have shared their thoughts about the importance of compensating the losers from trade, while others (e.g. Tim [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Uwe Reinhardt&#8217;s post the other day, &#8220;<a href="http://economix.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/02/18/how-convincing-is-the-case-for-free-trade/">How Convincing is the Case for Free Trade?</a>&#8220;, helped to kick-start a fair bit of discussion recently about the impact of international trade on the US economy. <a href="http://economistsview.typepad.com/economistsview/2011/02/should-losers-from-free-trade-be-compensated.html">Mark Thoma</a> and <a href="http://www.williampolley.com/blog/archives/2011/02/should-losers-f.html">William Polley </a>have shared their thoughts about the importance of compensating the losers from trade, while others (e.g. <a href="http://timworstall.com/2011/02/19/on-the-distribution-of-the-gains-from-trade/">Tim Worstall</a>) have questioned that need.</p>
<p>I&#8217;d like to add 3 points to this discusssion.</p>
<p>1. International trade is not substantially different from trade between two people within the same country. Both types of trade are voluntary agreements between the two parties to the transaction. And both types of trade may negatively impact other people in the economy who had nothing to do with the transaction. The main difference is simply that with international trade, the transaction happens to cross an international boundary.</p>
<p>2. Just because trade leads to an efficient outcome, that doesn&#8217;t mean it&#8217;s a good outcome. I think that <a href="http://streetlightblog.blogspot.com/2011/02/free-trade-efficiency-and-punch-in-nose.html">a parable about a punch in the nose</a> helps make that point. But even very bright economists often confuse &#8220;efficient&#8221; with &#8220;good&#8221;.</p>
<p>3. I see the problem of adequately compensating the losers from international trade as just a part of the larger question of how we treat people in our society who, through no fault of their own, have fallen on hard times. International trade is just one of the many enormous, inexorable forces that constantly reshape our economy. Technological change, demographic change, or the fluctuations of the macroeconomic business cycle may devastate millions of families each year just as surely as international trade. An important measure (to me) of the type of society we live in is how we treat those individuals who are on the losing end of those impersonal economic forces that, in the long run, often help to make the world a more prosperous place.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/02/compensating-the-losers-from-trade.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Tense Problem</title>
		<link>./../../2011/02/a-tense-problem.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/02/a-tense-problem.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2011 21:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[free trade]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Macroeconomic Theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[microeconomic theory]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/02/a-tense-problem.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Mark Thoma begins with a hilarious typo, but eventually gets to the Quote of the Decade (if not century) from Alan Blinder: If we economists stubbornly insist on chanting &#8216;free trade is good for you&#8217; to people who know that it is not, we will quickly become irrelevant to the public debate. As Rusty can [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Mark Thoma <a href="http://economistsview.typepad.com/economistsview/2011/02/how-convincing-is-the-case-for-free-trade.html">begins with a hilarious typo</a>, but eventually gets to the Quote of the Decade (if not century) from Alan Blinder:<br />
<blockquote>If we economists stubbornly insist on chanting &#8216;free trade is good for you&#8217; to people who know that it is not, we will quickly become irrelevant to the public debate.</p></blockquote>
<p>As Rusty can (and will, at length) tell you, the thing that is wrong with that sentence is the tense.  We have had free trade agreements for decades, China has had MFN status since the 1990s, and permanently since 2000.  The pieces of the former Soviet Union, including the current oligarchy that is called Russia, have had that status since 1992.  NAFTA, including its abhorrent Chapter 11, has been in force since 1994.<br /><a name="more"></a><br />There has been a generation that has lived under &#8220;free trade.&#8221;  While an economist might successfully argue that the overall social benefit has been great—<a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2010/mar/15/china-migrant-workers-children-education">millions of Chinese parents become estranged from their children to make a better life</a>, as it were—the retraining, redevelopment and all of the other assumptions economists make about ameliorating the transition to a new economy have been eschewed.</p>
<p>The example of <a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/69746-hart-smith-on-outsourcing.html">Boeing</a> (h/t <a href="http://blogs.reuters.com/felix-salmon/2011/02/18/learning-from-boeings-outsourcing-disaster/">Felix</a>) bodes large: the valuable work was outsourced, the menial work was kept (or <a href="http://www.visteon.com/index.html">spun off</a> <a href="http://delphi.com/">into bankruptcy</a>), and the new &#8220;higher-value&#8221; jobs and opportunities that were expected by <s>idiots</s> economists <a href="http://chronicle.com/blogs/innovations/why-students-want-to-go-to-harvard/28613#">never materialized</a>, replaced instead by growing income inequality and the retraining money lined the pockets of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack_Welch#Criticism">CEOs who produced (to borrow a phrase used by the brilliant McGarrysGhost on Twitter) &#8220;failure masquerading as vision.&#8221;</a></p>
<p>And any microeconomist worth his paycheck can tell you that increasing inequality leads to suboptimal production.</p>
<p>Blinder is wrong in only one thing: the tense he uses indicates that the results are still, somehow, in doubt.  The ability of Chinese peasants to eat a bit more is nice, but the externalities—<a href="http://atbozzo.blogspot.com/2007/07/if-its-friday-there-must-be-fda-recall.html">poisoned toothpaste</a>, <a href="http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/18400433/ns/health-pet_health/">dog food</a>,* <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/search?q=Chinese+tires">defective tires</a>—make it rather impossible to claim that the &#8220;advantages of free trade&#8221; have trickled down in any way except as a <a href="http://www.csulb.edu/~cohlberg/Songs/urea.mp3">ureotelic</a> (mp3 link).**</p>
<p>The first thing we were told by <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Betsy-Brevitz/e/B001IR1RRY/ref=sr_tc_2_0?qid=1298062118&#038;sr=1-2-ent">our veterinarian</a> about the new puppy is that we need to make certain that any food she eats was made in either Canada or the United States.  Fortunately, pet food—unlike its human equivalent—is <a href="http://www.fda.gov/animalveterinary/resourcesforyou/ucm047113.htm">required to be labeled with origin information</a>.</p>
<p>**You better believe I&#8217;m doing The Snoopy Dance on having discovered <a href="http://www.csulb.edu/~cohlberg/songbook.html">this site</a>, which saves me from trying to find a way to transfer my old cassette to a usable format.  But that&#8217;s fodder for <a href="http://xnerg.blogspot.com/">Skippy</a>, not here.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/02/a-tense-problem.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Trade policy agreements and capital flows</title>
		<link>./../../2011/02/trade-policy-agreements-and-capital-flows.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/02/trade-policy-agreements-and-capital-flows.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2011 13:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[free trade]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[international trade]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[trade policy]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/02/trade-policy-agreements-and-capital-flows.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Yves Smith at Naked Capitalism offers wise words regarding trade policy agreements and capital flows, in addition to pointing us toward a letter signed by several hundreds of economists regarding capital controls and government.: This letter is at odds with a longstanding project of major financial firms: to allow them to move money across borders [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a target="_blank" href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2011/02/a-whole-bunch-of-prominent-economists-backs-the-use-of-capital-controls.html">Yves Smith</a> at Naked Capitalism offers wise words regarding trade policy agreements and capital flows, in addition to pointing us toward a letter signed by several hundreds of economists regarding capital controls and government.:</p>
<blockquote><p>This letter is at odds with a longstanding project of major financial firms: to allow them to move money across borders with no muss or fuss. This was the dream of Citibank’s Walter Wriston, who perversely was not deterred by the large losses his bank incurred in its sovereign lending misadventures of the late 1970s. It became a matter of policy in the Rubin/Summers Treasury Department. </p>
<p>Although the danger of destabilizing “hot money” inflows has been well recognized since the Asian crisis of 1997, the thrust of US policy has been to continue to push for more capital markets liberalization, particularly in emerging economies. Yet the evidence has continues to mount that a high level of international capital movements isn’t merely a potential threat to developing markets, but to economic stability. As we’ve pointed out repeatedly, the Carmen Reinhart/Kenneth Rogoff work on financial crises showed a strong correlation between high levels of international funds flows and banking crises.<br /><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>The odd, and telling bit in the debate is the unwitting concession to financiers embedded in the existing terminology: capital controls. <strong>It incorrectly implies that money is every and always stateless, and any effort to restrict it is unnatural</strong>. But truly stateless commodities are highly transportable, high density stores of value whose content can be readily verified: think diamonds (at least pre the era of synthetic diamonds), gold, platinum. But despite their obvious value, what someone receives in exchange if one transports them across borders is very much in doubt, not just due to price fluctuations but also to the difficulties of finding a trustworthy party who would convert the commodity into local currency at a fair rate. </p>
<p>In other words, we’ve all gotten so used to being able to change money, use credit cards, and suck local currency out of ATMs when traveling abroad that we’ve forgotten that this has been put in place with government support. And it has come more recently in some countries than others. I recall running into a McKinsey colleague in the Hong Kong airport in 1985. He was astonished to see that the foreign exchange booths would exchange Indian rupees. The rupee then was a controlled currency; that sort of operation was in theory impermissible. But Hong Kong was always a bit lawless, and this was probably a small scale enough operation so as to fly under any official radar.</p>
<p>But so far, we have been talking about money, and the conversion of currency in a personal/retail context. By contrast, “capital” carries with it the idea of investment. Money is not being moved simply to get it into another country (well it might be if you are a drug dealer or the leader of a banana republic planning your exit strategy) <strong>but to put it to work. That in turn means you expect some sort of legal protection in the recipient country</strong>, ideally as good as the natives get (again note we accept the idea of equal protection under the law in some contexts and not others, so this is not a given). </p>
<p>But what about movement of funds between countries? How exactly is this a matter of rights? For individuals, as with our drug lord example, the reason for trying to move it abroad is almost certainly not legitimate; it’s to escape prosecution and taxation. The US takes the view that the income of its citizens, no matter where earned, is subject to US taxation. Governments lose significant amounts of money due to corporate gaming of tax regimes. Nicholas Shaxson, in his new book Treasure Islands, argues that poor African nations are actually capital exporters. They lose more in tax revenues via arranging their affairs so as to show income in low tax jurisdictions (often with little in the way of real operations there) than they gain in foreign aid. </p>
<p>Now as the letter above acknowledges, international treaties have effectively given investors the right to move funds without restriction into certain types of instruments. But look at the implicit logic, and it’s one that actually goes back to discussions early in the history of the US over whether Congress should charter a bank (yes, Virginia, pre-revolutionary America thrived without banks). The debate centered around differing ideas of what “freedom” meant. </p>
<p>The opponents of the bank charter were concerned about potential abuses that could result from concentrated power. To them, “freedom” meant the right of citizens to take action and use democratic processes to move their government and society in directions that they could hopefully agree on and would produce better outcomes. </p>
<p>The bank advocates, most notably Robert Morris, took a very revealing position: they argued that the government had the right to grant privileges, but not to take them back. It amounted to arguing that economic interests extended to private actors somehow became their property, and that any reversal of these grants was not simply an act of bad faith, but was despotic theft. </p>
<p>Yet we routinely accept the rescinding of government privileges of various sorts; consider the 1990s “end of welfare as we know it” or the expected reductions in pensions of state employees. But when large commercial interests obtain valuable economic rights, reining them back when they are found to impose undue costs on others is depicted in a completely different light. Restricting them isn’t framed neutrally, as, say, a revision, but as a “control” when the prevailing ideology treats that as a “c” word.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/02/trade-policy-agreements-and-capital-flows.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Confusions and policies&#8230;let&#8217;s keep the players in mind all around</title>
		<link>./../../2010/12/confusions-and-policies-lets-keep-the-players-in-mind-all-around.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/12/confusions-and-policies-lets-keep-the-players-in-mind-all-around.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 18 Dec 2010 17:43:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[China]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[free trade]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[international trade]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/12/confusions-and-policies-lets-keep-the-players-in-mind-all-around.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Chinese Confusions by Paul Krugman These days, China seems to play the same role in much of our discourse that Japan did two decades ago. We look at our own follies — which are immense — and then look at the Chinese, and ascribe to them all the virtues of foresight and determination we lack. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a target="_blank" href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2010/12/17/chinese-confusions/">Chinese Confusions</a>  <br />by Paul Krugman</p>
<blockquote><p>These days, China seems to play the same role in much of our discourse that Japan did two decades ago. We look at our own follies — which are immense — and then look at the Chinese, and ascribe to them all the virtues of foresight and determination we lack.</p>
<p>But just like the Japanese, the Chinese are human, and their policy makers are subject to the same kinds of confusion and inability to make hard choices that are part of the human condition. And Chinese macroeconomic policy is in the process of becoming a cautionary tale.</p>
<p>Basic economics says that by deciding to keep the renminbi undervalued, the Chinese put themselves <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2010/11/17/swan-songs/">under inflationary pressure</a>; and sure enough, inflation is rapidly becoming a serious problem.</p>
<p>But political considerations seem to be <a href="http://curiouscapitalist.blogs.time.com/2010/12/17/china%E2%80%99s-inflation-problem-and-the-perils-of-unconventional-policy/?utm_source=feedburner&#038;utm_medium=feed&#038;utm_campaign=Feed:+timeblogs/curious_capitalist+(TIME:+The+Curious+Capitalist)">ruling out all the reasonable responses</a>. They won’t revalue, because that would hurt politically influential exporters. They’re reluctant to raise interest rates, because that would hurt politically influential real estate developers. They’re trying to impose quantitative limits on credit, but are finding that borrowers have enough influence to circumvent the limits. And now they’re trying price controls — which will inevitably come apart at the seams unless they do something about the underlying pressures.</p>
<p>It’s an edifying spectacle.</p>
<p>Now, <em>schadenfreude</em> should not lead to any complaceny on our part; China may be corrupt and unable to make sensible short-run choices, but in terms of fundamental inability to deal with long-term problems, we still have them beat hands down. Still, it’s worth remembering that all giants have feet of clay.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/12/confusions-and-policies-lets-keep-the-players-in-mind-all-around.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
