<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>boehner &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Second Verse, the Same as The First</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/second-verse-the-same-as-the-first.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/second-verse-the-same-as-the-first.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 16 Jul 2012 12:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2012 Presidential elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[boehner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[run 75441]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/second-verse-the-same-as-the-first.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Run 75441“Second Verse, the Same as The First&#8221;The story never seems to change . . . When you say that the high income earners, the top 20 percent, pay 90 percent of the taxes, what should they pay, 99 percent? These are the people who have enough money to invest in businesses and to [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><i>by Run 75441</i><br /><i><br /></i><br />“Second Verse, the Same as The First&#8221;<br /><i><br /></i><br /><i>The story never seems to change . . .</i><br /><i><br /></i><br />
<blockquote>When you say that the high income earners, the top 20 percent, pay 90 percent of the taxes, what should they pay, 99 percent? These are the people who have enough money to invest in businesses and to create jobs.” The tax increase that Obama is proposing “falls directly on those job creators,” Senator Kyl said.&#8221; <i><a href="http://nbcpolitics.msnbc.msn.com/_news/2012/07/15/12753063-can-us-economy-tolerate-a-tax-increase-in-2013?lite">Can U.S. economy tolerate a tax increase in 2013?</a></i></p></blockquote>
<p>The vast majority of the upper quintile in Household Taxable Income does not make >$250,000 in AGI. Yet since 2001, the Republicans would have us believe that 3% of the taxpayers are the same as 20% of the taxpayers and that quintile makes > than $250,000. It is a lie and Senator Kyl needs to retract his blathering. </p>
<p>What is laughable about Senator Kyl statement is the Speaker of the House repudiates his statement here:<br />BOB SCHIEFFER: Do you quarrel with that figure? Is that a right figure or a wrong figure? </p>
<p>BOEHNER: Well, it may be three percent, but it&#8217;s half of small business income. Because, obviously, the top three percent have half of the gross income for those companies that we would term small businesses. And this is why you don&#8217;t want to punish these people at a time when you have a weak economy. <i></i><a href="http://voices.washingtonpost.com/plum-line/2010/09/boehner_concedes_only_three_pe.html"><i>Boehner concedes only three percent of small businesses affected by extending tax cuts.</i></a></p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>3% = 20%? Not likely and this is another example of the Republicans attempting to confuse the taxpayers. Even &#8220;<i>Joe- The-Plumber</i>&#8221; got it wrong; but then, why would a plumber have any greater knowledge then a Senator? At least there is an excuse for Joe.</p>
<p>So would taxing the upper 3% of the Taxable Household Incomes more hurt the economy? Not likely and it would correct the 2001/2003 skewing of taxes to this income group by President George Bush. What Bush did is without precedent in political history and is something not even Hoover attempted.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/second-verse-the-same-as-the-first.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>CBO Scores Boehner Amendment to HR3962</title>
		<link>./../../2009/11/cbo-scores-boehner-amendment-to-hr3962.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/11/cbo-scores-boehner-amendment-to-hr3962.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 05 Nov 2009 15:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[boehner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cbo projections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hr3962]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/11/cbo-scores-boehner-amendment-to-hr3962.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Bruce Webb Last evening the CBO Director Blog announced the release of a score of the Boehner amendment: A Preliminary Analysis of a Substitute Amendment to H.R. 3962, the Affordable Health Care for America Act. The results are not impressive: (as always click to enlarge)The amendment is scored at reducing the deficit by $68 [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Bruce Webb</p>
<p>Last evening the <a target="_blanks" href="http://cboblog.cbo.gov/?p=414">CBO Director Blog</a> announced the release of a score of the Boehner amendment: <a target="_blank" href="http://www.cbo.gov/ftpdocs/107xx/doc10705/hr3962amendmentBoehner.pdf">A Preliminary Analysis of a Substitute Amendment to H.R. 3962, the Affordable Health Care for America Act</a>. The results are not impressive: (as always click to enlarge)<br /><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fjW71B3WLTQ/SvLsmiuzmBI/AAAAAAAAAVM/lr71klquZjg/s1600-h/Boehner-dollars.jpg"><img src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fjW71B3WLTQ/SvLsmiuzmBI/AAAAAAAAAVM/lr71klquZjg/s400/Boehner-dollars.jpg" border="0" alt=""></a><br /><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fjW71B3WLTQ/SvLsmBBmA_I/AAAAAAAAAVE/08X3_2AgUss/s1600-h/Boehner-coverage.jpg"><img src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fjW71B3WLTQ/SvLsmBBmA_I/AAAAAAAAAVE/08X3_2AgUss/s400/Boehner-coverage.jpg" border="0" alt=""></a><br />The amendment is scored at reducing the deficit by $68 billion over ten years. I can&#8217;t get the breakdown to add up (see page 4) but most of the savings is in the form of malpractice reform at $54 billion with further savings from some administrative changes relating to electronic transfers and adoption of the Eschoo Biologics Amendment all of which offsets a whopping $8 billion net actually spent to expand coverage. So what do we get from spending an average of just around $800 million a year? Essentially nothing, CBO projects that the percentage of the legal non-elderly population without health insurance will stay right at 83%.</p>
<p>I suggest the words &#8216;Epic fail&#8217; apply here. Heckuva job Johnnie!<br />____________________________________<br />Update: Lifted from comments on last post. <a target="_blank" href="http://www.zacks.com/stock/news/26896/The+GOP%27s+Health+Care+Plan">The GOP&#8217;s Health Care Plan<br />By: Dirk van Dijk, CFA</a> Dirk provides a nice analysis of the other provisions of the bill beyond the cost and coverage numbers.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/11/cbo-scores-boehner-amendment-to-hr3962.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
