<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>hope &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>A Caesura in Canadian Opposition</title>
		<link>./../../2011/08/a-caesura-in-canadian-opposition.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/08/a-caesura-in-canadian-opposition.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2011 19:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Canada]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hope]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[human capital]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/08/a-caesura-in-canadian-opposition.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[[Expletive Deleted]. It will be interesting to see whether the Libya of Brad DeLong and Juan Cole&#8217;s beliefs produces a respectable opposition leader—one of the surer signs of rule by the people—before Canada does.* UPDATE: Via Amy Wilkins Twitter feed, Layton&#8217;s final words. Can anyone imagine the 2011 Obama** being able to say this: You [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.cbc.ca/news/politics/story/2011/08/22/layton-obituary.html">[Expletive Deleted]</a>.</p>
<p>It will be interesting to see whether the Libya of <a href="http://delong.typepad.com/sdj/2011/08/very-good-news-from-libya.html">Brad DeLong</a> and <a href="http://www.juancole.com/2011/08/top-ten-myths-about-the-libya-war.html">Juan Cole&#8217;s beliefs</a> produces a respectable opposition leader—one of the surer signs of rule by the people—before Canada does.*</p>
<p>UPDATE: Via Amy Wilkins Twitter feed,  <a href="http://www.blogto.com/news_flash/2011/08/open_letter_from_jack_layton_to_canadians/">Layton&#8217;s final words</a>.  Can anyone imagine the 2011 Obama** being able to say this:<br />
<br />
<blockquote>You decided that the way to replace Canada&#8217;s Conservative federal government with something better was by working together in partnership with progressive-minded Canadians across the country. You made the right decision then; it is still the right decision today; and it will be the right decision right through to the next election, when we will succeed, together&#8230;</p>
<p>All my life I have worked to make things better. Hope and optimism have defined my political career, and I continue to be hopeful and optimistic about Canada&#8230;.More and more, you are engaging in politics because you want to change things for the better. Many of you have placed your trust in our party. As my time in political life draws to a close I want to share with you my belief in your power to change this country and this world. There are great challenges before you, from the overwhelming nature of climate change to the unfairness of an economy that excludes so many from our collective wealth, and the changes necessary to build a more inclusive and generous Canada. I believe in you. Your energy, your vision, your passion for justice are exactly what this country needs today. You need to be at the heart of our economy, our political life, and our plans for the present and the future. [emphasis mine]</p></blockquote>
<p>*I said &#8220;respectable.&#8221;  This does not include the Liberal Party for as long as they are led by Michael Ignatieff, to whom <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2011/04/hoocoodanode-great-white-north-edition.html">this post</a> was Far Too Nice.</p>
<p>**I&#8217;ll be nice to those of you who thought that Obama was anything other than a Corporatist from the start.<br /></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/08/a-caesura-in-canadian-opposition.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
