<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>opportunity costs &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>America is an Opportunity Society (Rep Paul Ryan WI)</title>
		<link>./../../2012/06/america-is-an-opportunity-society-rep-paul-ryan-wi.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/06/america-is-an-opportunity-society-rep-paul-ryan-wi.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Jun 2012 14:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[guns and butter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[opportunity costs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/06/america-is-an-opportunity-society-rep-paul-ryan-wi.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Run 75441 America is an Opportunity Society (Rep Paul Ryan WI) “I’m personally offended that they’re playing a high-stakes game of chicken with our national defense,” fumed Weston Newton, chairman of the Beaufort County Council, after hearing Senator Graham’s dire warnings. . Lawmakers look for way out as defense cuts near. After agreeing to [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Run 75441</p>
<p>America is an Opportunity Society (Rep Paul Ryan WI)</p>
<p>“<i>I’m personally offended that they’re playing a high-stakes game of chicken with our national defense</i>,” fumed Weston Newton, chairman of the Beaufort County Council, after hearing Senator Graham’s dire warnings. . <a href="http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/47669971/ns/politics-the_new_york_times/" target="_blank">Lawmakers look for way out as defense cuts near</a>.</p>
<p>After agreeing to automatic cuts if a resolution to the deficit could not be agreed upon in the budgeting process, some members of the Senate now what a redo. Senator Graham goes to great lengths to stir the guns and/or butter pot of fear.</p>
<blockquote><p>· <i>The law exempts war costs and allows the administration to wall off personnel levels and military pay, about a third of the Pentagon budget. That means everything else — operations and maintenance, research and development, procurement, fuel, military construction — would face immediate cuts as deep as 13 percent,&#8221;</i> Mr. Harrison said.<br />· <i>&#8220;&#8216;</i>Our <i>ability to modernize will be basically gutted,&#8217; Senator Graham told National Guard officers in Greenville. &#8216;The Marine Corps will have to choose between its giant training camps in San Diego or Parris Island, he told community leaders in Beaufort, a stone’s throw from Parris Island.&#8221;</i><br />· &#8220;<i>&#8216;The C-17 fleet at Joint Base Charleston would be &#8216;devastated,&#8217; Senator Graham warned city leaders at the Charleston Chamber of Commerce. The cuts to the soldiers and airmen at Shaw Air Force Base would leave behind a &#8216;hollow force,&#8217; he intoned in a windowless room at the Quality Inn in Sumter.'&#8221;</i> </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>During the month of May, a House majority voted to shift the automatic cuts for Defense (resulting from the failure to approve a budget) to cuts of Domestic programs. The National Defense Authorization Act passed the House 218 to 199 in Reconciliation with Wisconsin Representative Paul Ryan (strictly a guns guy) sponsoring cuts in Medicaid ($50 billion), food programs for the poor ($36 billion), federal retirement funds ($80 billion), and capping malpractice lawsuits to save $49 billion. The Act also proposes to increase Defense spending $8 billion (enough to fix 40,000 $200,000 flawed mortgages</p></blockquote>
<p>  <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/05/10/paul-ryan-budget-house-defense-food-stamps_n_1506454.html" target="_blank">Paul Ryan Budget: House Passes Bill To Spare Defense, Cut Food Aid, Health Care</a></p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>While sequestered an agreement was not reached by the handpicked members of Congress who would never reach an agreement in a decade, the Budget Control Act with its default cuts now adds another $500 billion in cuts (over the next decade) on top of the agreed upon $487 billion in Defense spending cuts agreed to last Summer. In a &#8220;<i>Quelle Surprise</i>&#8221; moment, the DEMs appear to be showing some backbone and the Republicans are finding the Dems are serious about the burden of program cuts falling equally over all programs. </p>
<blockquote><p>&#8220;<i>We will sit and stagnate with banks and use rockets, To oversee that it&#8217;s our bottom line that gets carried to the high seas.&#8221; </i>Shikari. Norquist would be proud of these pseudo budget cutters.<br />Falling back on the rhetoric of a built-in culture of dependency, Ryan fights back on the proposed cuts in domestic programs; &#8220;<i>Here&#8217;s the problem: These efforts aren&#8217;t working. One in six Americans today are in poverty</i>, <i>let&#8217;s get back to the idea of America as an opportunity society.&#8221; </i>It is not the two recessions in a decade, the cutting of jobs or globalization at issue, or the stagnation of income, which has led to an increasing portion of the Non-Institutional Civilian Population to reside in Not In Labor Force nor is it reductions in tax revenue; it is a culture of dependency as created by domestic programs. Another &#8220;<i>Quelle Surprise</i>&#8220;</p></blockquote>
<p>moment in politics! Moreover, if we cut food and healthcare we can force them to work. When did healthcare become that cheap and affordable while earning a minimum wage? Which do you do, cast the bones of the future, gamble with your health, and forgo healthcare to buy food or the alternative is to diet? Investing more money in the military, expanding our military presence, and cutting domestic programs; Rep. Paul Ryan believes will solve the economic problem much of the population faces today. </p>
<p>Maybe in the past, the US in its early product life cycle of growth had the resource and the potential to expand the military and invest in the domestic economy; but today, the resources are limited and continuing to invest so heavily in the military could result in an erosion of global economic position. In &#8220;<i>The Rise and Fall of the Great Powers</i>;&#8221; Paul Kennedy examines the growth of Defense (guns),<br /><a href="http://lh4.ggpht.com/-TyZcQk4kveg/T86__wwmNDI/AAAAAAAAA3A/lEogAUpNDlY/s1600-h/clip_image001%25255B3%25255D.gif"><img alt="clip_image001" border="0" height="59" hspace="12" src="http://lh3.ggpht.com/-v03Wx7qxpno/T87AAc6vy_I/AAAAAAAAA3I/iTvmWuv1Gds/clip_image001_thumb.gif?imgmax=800" title="clip_image001" width="233"></a><a href="http://lh5.ggpht.com/-4ih_qZU4AGk/T87AA_mzqiI/AAAAAAAAA3Q/Ztta36rsniU/s1600-h/clip_image003%25255B3%25255D.jpg"><img alt="clip_image003" border="0" height="244" hspace="12" src="http://lh4.ggpht.com/-AEWnM2RBdno/T87ACFepajI/AAAAAAAAA3Y/v0uSnKwmj68/clip_image003_thumb.jpg?imgmax=800" title="clip_image003" width="224">Rise and Fall</a></p>
<p>armaments, global commitments, etc. without an increasing and sustaining Domestic economy and Economic Investment (butter) concluding it has been a greater contributor to a nation&#8217;s demise as a world power and relegated to second or third tier status. Kennedy does so by reviewing the nations, which have been world powers since the 16th Century and compares those former world powers and circumstance in the end with the US. He analyzes the ability to engage in conflict(s) sustained or otherwise and increased military expenditures without adequate or increasing resource of energy, other natural resource, and domestic productivity. The US with a faltering economy, an unproductive large labor pool, and an emphasis on financial and Wall Street gambling may be no longer able to sustain the military and the military complex it has today. </p>
<blockquote><p>As Paul Kennedy suggests a continuation of such policy could &#8220;<i>lead to the downward spiral of slower growth, heavier taxes, deepening domestic splits over spending priorities, and weakening capacity to bear the burdens of defense</i></p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p><i> </i>Hmmmmm, does it sound familar?<i> </i>and adds<i>:</i></p></blockquote>
<p><i></i><br />
<blockquote><i>The task facing American statesmen over the next decades, therefore, is to recognize that broad trends are under way, and that there is a need to “manage” affairs so that the relative erosion of the United States’ position takes place slowly and smoothly, and is not accelerated by policies which bring merely short-term advantage but longer-term disadvantage.</i> <a href="http://www.facebook.com/pages/The-Rise-and-Fall-of-the-Great-Powers/105706569463774#!/pages/" target="_blank">The-Rise-and-Fall-of-the-Great-Powers</a></p></blockquote>
<p>It may be time to rethink our present stance on military expenditures and focus on domestic investments which will revitalize the country and bring more of those people Paul Ryan targets back into the Civilian Work Force. When the automatic cuts go into play; they will not go realign military policy favoring domestic policy; but, the Paul Ryan&#8217;s of Congress would go a long way towards providing the &#8220;Opportunity Society&#8221; he is calling for by doing so. It is an opportunity much of Congress seems to be blind too in their quest to unseat Obama and follow the pledges to Norquist.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/06/america-is-an-opportunity-society-rep-paul-ryan-wi.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>What is meritocracy?</title>
		<link>./../../2011/12/what-is-meritocracy.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/12/what-is-meritocracy.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2011 15:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2012 Presidential elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[meritocracy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[opportunity costs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[winners and losers]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/12/what-is-meritocracy.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Andrew Gelman points to our confusions regarding merit in our social perceptions of winners and losers. I might make a list of naughty and nice sayings for another post. Tyler Cowen pointed to an article by business-school professor Luigi Zingales about meritocracy. I’d expect a b-school prof to support the idea of meritocracy, and Zingales [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a target="_blank" href="http://andrewgelman.com/2011/12/lamentably-common-misunderstanding-of-meritocracy/?">Andrew Gelman</a> points to our confusions regarding merit in our social perceptions of winners and losers.  I might make a list of naughty and nice sayings for another post.<br />
<blockquote>
<p>Tyler Cowen <a href="http://marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2011/10/assorted-links-267.html">pointed</a> to <a href="http://www.city-journal.org/2011/21_4_meritocracy.html">an article</a> by business-school professor Luigi Zingales about meritocracy. I’d expect a b-school prof to support the idea of meritocracy, and Zingales does not disappoint.</p>
<p>But he says a bunch of other things that to me represent a confused conflation of ideas. Here’s Zingales:</p>
<blockquote><p>America became known as a land of opportunity—a place whose capitalist system benefited <em>the hardworking and the virtuous</em> [emphasis added]. In a word, it was a meritocracy.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That’s interesting—and revealing. Here’s what I get when I look up “meritocracy” in the <a href="http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/meritocracy">dictionary</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>1 : a system in which the talented are chosen and moved ahead on the basis of their achievement     <br />2 : leadership selected on the basis of intellectual criteria</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Nothing here about “hardworking” or “virtuous.” In a meritocracy, you can be as hardworking as John Kruk or as virtuous as Kobe Bryant and you’ll still get ahead—if you have the talent and achievement. Throwing in “hardworking” and “virtuous” seems to me to an attempt (unconscious, I expect) to retroactively assign <em>moral</em> standing to the winners in an economic race.    <br />Later, Zingales writes:</p>
<blockquote><p>The fundamental role of an economic system, even an extremely primitive one, is to assign responsibility and reward.</p>
<p> <a name="more"></a> </p></blockquote>
<p>Huh? Again he seems to be conflating economics with morality, in a similar way as when economists Mankiw and Weinzierl implied that the state only has a right to tax things that are “unjustly wrestled from someone else.” Zingales in the above quote is taking the economic functions of prices, wages, supply, and demand and transmuting them into to the morally-loaded terms “responsibility” and “reward.”</p>
<p>Finally, in his praise of meritocracy, Zingales doesn’t seem to be aware of the concept’s self-contradicting nature. As James “Effect” Flynn has <a href="http://andrewgelman.com/2007/12/meritocracy_won/">pointed out</a>,</p>
<blockquote><p>The case against meritocracy can be put psychologically: (a) The abolition of materialist-elitist values is a prerequisite for the abolition of inequality and privilege; (b) the persistence of materialist-elitist values is a prerequisite for class stratification based on wealth and status; (c) therefore, a class-stratified meritocracy is impossible.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>To put it another way, Zingales talks a lot about the threat to meritocracy from business capturing government regulation or from pitchfork-wielding hordes raising the marginal tax rate, but he doesn’t consider some much more direct effects of meritocracy such as <a href="http://andrewgelman.com/2011/06/how_to_party_yo/">this</a>.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>More can be read at Andrew&#8217;s place. (link is at beginning)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/12/what-is-meritocracy.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The National Health</title>
		<link>./../../2011/02/the-national-health.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/02/the-national-health.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2011 19:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[asymmetrical information]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health care costs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health care reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Inequality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[just life]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[opportunity costs]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/02/the-national-health.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I wasn&#8217;t going to mention Melissa Mia Hall&#8217;s death here—this is economics and politics, not sf—but now it is clear that, as usual, there is an overlap: If she had seen the doctor, most likely he would have suspected more than a pulled muscle and would have ordered a life-saving EKG. As Texas lawyer, writer [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I wasn&#8217;t going to mention Melissa Mia Hall&#8217;s death here—this is economics and politics, not sf—but now it is clear that, as usual, <a href="http://thelipstickchronicles.typepad.com/the_lipstick_chronicles/2011/02/the-least-of-us.html">there is an overlap</a>:<br />
<blockquote>If she had seen the doctor, most likely he would have suspected more than a pulled muscle and would have ordered a life-saving EKG.</p>
<p>As Texas lawyer, writer and Melissa&#8217;s friend, Laurie Moore, wrote to me, &#8220;She would&#8217;ve had a huge doctor bill she couldn&#8217;t pay, and would probably have lost her house over it, but she would be alive instead of taking pain pills and dying in the night. &#8220;</p>
<p>In the end, Melissa didn&#8217;t die from an overdose, not even an accidental one; Melissa died of the very heart attack she feared&#8230;.</p>
<p>Melissa worked hard. She owned a home. She paid her taxes. She was trying to live a dream &#8211; the American Dream &#8211; that supposedly we as citizens are promised &#8211; the right to pursue life, liberty and happiness. For her, that couldn&#8217;t be achieved in a traditional job that came with the perks of health care.</p></blockquote>
<p>This is the quintessential &#8220;hard-working American&#8221; who gets talked about by The Teabaggers as if nothing ever goes wrong and <a href="http://slog.thestranger.com/slog/archives/2011/01/31/and-here-i-thought-the-purpose-of-the-oped-page-was-to-promote-debate-not-crush-it">they never need &#8220;government help</a>.&#8221; (link h/t <a href="http://www.eschatonblog.com/2011/01/rural-counties-are-sucking-us-dry.html">Dr. Black</a>) This is <a href="http://blogs.publishersweekly.com/blogs/genreville/?p=978">the woman of whom Peter Cannon (via Rose Fox)* said</a>:<br />
<blockquote>Melissa contributed hundreds of reviews to PW, in all different genres, as well as dozens of Q&#038;As. In recent years, ever reliable and diligent, she was reviewing three books a week for me&#8230;</p></blockquote>
<p>This isn&#8217;t someone who was getting &#8220;fails to perform&#8221; ratings or &#8220;stealing&#8221; a house. This is someone whose every effort was aimed at making money and paying bills to keep what little she had gained. She used her skills—human capital, painfully developed—and made rational decisions.</p>
<p>And the rational <em>ex ante</em> decision not to use the medicines she needed or to have to pay out of pocket for an exam that may well lead to more expenses that are beyond her liquidity constraints are, well, exactly what we teach as &#8220;correct&#8221; in Ph.D. micro- and macro- Economics courses.</p>
<p>So this isn&#8217;t a science fiction post, because no one who reads and writes science fiction would believe that a hard-working, conscientious person with great skills, a positive personality, and diligent attention to opportunities would die because they couldn&#8217;t afford to live.</p>
<p>It&#8217;s an economics and politics post, one I wish I hadn&#8217;t had to write.</p>
<p>*Full disclosure: I&#8217;ve known Peter Cannon for years; he edited both myself and my wife at PW. (Full, full disclosure: he fired me, after having previously turned down my request to quit for a while. Both were good decisions on his part.) I&#8217;ve met Rose Fox several times and she edited my wife for a while when PW still paid something resembling minimum wage for the effort required.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/02/the-national-health.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>How Much Should I Spend to See a Movie? (In which I channel McMegan)</title>
		<link>./../../2008/12/how-much-should-i-spend-to-see-a-movie-in-which-i-channel-mcmegan.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/12/how-much-should-i-spend-to-see-a-movie-in-which-i-channel-mcmegan.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2008 19:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[movies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[opportunity costs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rationality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[TCO]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/12/how-much-should-i-spend-to-see-a-movie-in-which-i-channel-mcmegan.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[While the brood was at Mary Poppins, I took advantage of the Academy Awards rules and went to see Revolutionary Road. The incremental cost was subway fare (arguably a sunk cost, since I have old Metro cards) and the $12.50 NYC film ticket price. So that was quite rationalisable; met up with an old friend [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>While the brood was <a href="http://angrybear.blogspot.com/2008/12/whence-fall-banks-of-england-england.html">at <em>Mary Poppins</em></a>, I took advantage of the Academy Awards rules and went to see <em>Revolutionary Road</em>.  The incremental cost was subway fare (arguably a sunk cost, since I have old Metro cards) and the $12.50 NYC film ticket price.</p>
<p>So that was quite rationalisable; met up with an old friend and spent a relatively pleasant couple of hours. (Saw the movie too.)</p>
<p>On the other hand, <em><a href="http://www.moviefone.com/movie/defiance/30166/main">Defiance</a></em> opens December 31st.  At the Ziegfeld.  And that one I can&#8217;t not take Shira to see.</p>
<p>So it&#8217;s either: spend US$18 for train fare (two r-t) and US$8 possible subway fare (walk slightly over a mile, with timming issues), and ticket price (presumably US$25), <em>and</em> get a babysitter to cover the minimum five hours (and probably more) this hegira would take.</p>
<p>Not to mention how one values ten to twelve person-hours of time with much to get done.</p>
<p>Or wait until it opens on 16 January, and be able to pay C$ (which <em>might</em> still be an advantage then), but not get to see it at The Ziegfeld.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/12/how-much-should-i-spend-to-see-a-movie-in-which-i-channel-mcmegan.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
