<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Dow &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The disconnect of my economy with the money economy</title>
		<link>./../../2009/04/the-disconnect-of-my-economy-with-the-money-economy.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/04/the-disconnect-of-my-economy-with-the-money-economy.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2009 22:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[crisis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dow]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economic decline]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stock Market]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/04/the-disconnect-of-my-economy-with-the-money-economy.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Divorced one like Bush The Yahoo Financial page has had this headline from the AP up for a while today:Top StoriesInvestors are cautious as swine flu cases increase- APThis is the first line: The swine flu gave Wall Street a reason to turn cautious. The Dow Jones industrial average gave up a midday recovery [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Divorced one like Bush</p>
<p>The Yahoo Financial page has had this headline from the AP up for a while today:<br />Top Stories<br /><strong>Investors are cautious as swine flu cases increase- AP</strong><br />This is the first line:<br />
<blockquote>The swine flu gave Wall Street a reason to turn cautious.  The Dow Jones industrial average gave up a midday recovery and retreated about 0.6 percent Monday as the swine flu&#8217;s death count in Mexico grew to about 150 people from 100.</p></blockquote>
<p> Really?  Swine flu is the reason one should be getting out of the market.  Not any of these:<br /><strong>Whirlpool 1Q profit drops on weakening demand</strong>  &#8211; 1 hour, 4 minutes ago<br />&#8211; AP<br />
<blockquote>Whirlpool Corp., the world&#8217;s largest maker of stoves, refrigerators and other major home appliances, said Monday its <strong>first-quarter profit fell 28 percent</strong> on slumping sales, softening consumer demand and the stronger dollar. </p></blockquote>
<p><strong>Boeing CEO calls slump &#8216;once-in-a-lifetime&#8217; event</strong> &#8211; AP &#8211; 1 hour, 5 minutes ago<br />
<blockquote>Boeing Co. Chairman and Chief Executive Jim McNerney assured shareholders Monday that the company is in strong shape to ride out the &#8220;once-in-a-lifetime&#8221; <strong>downturn that has walloped its profits</strong>, jetliner orders and stock price.</p></blockquote>
<p><strong>GM to cut 21,000 US factory jobs, shed Pontiac</strong> &#8211; AP &#8211; 2 hours, 39 minutes ago<br />
<blockquote>General Motors Corp. could be majority owned by the federal government under a massive restructuring plan laid out Monday that <strong>will cut 21,000 U.S. factory jobs</strong> by next year and phase out the storied Pontiac brand.</p></blockquote>
<p>Or this from a few days ago:<br /><strong><a href="http://www.progressiverailroading.com/news/article.asp?id=20192">Retail import volume at U.S. container ports </a>to decline at least through summer, report says</strong><br />
<blockquote>Import cargo volume at major U.S. retail container ports fell again in March after dropping below the 1 million twenty-foot-equivalent (TEU) mark in February, <strong>the first time in seven years the total had fallen that low</strong>. And the volume declines should continue for at least a few more months, according to an IHS Global Insight-National Retail Federation (NRF) report issued Wednesday.</p>
<p>U.S. ports will handle an estimated 987,371 TEUs in April, <strong>which would represent a 22 percent drop compared with the same 2008 period</strong>, after handling an estimated 930,142 TEUs in March, a 19.7 percent decline compared with March 2008’s total, according to the IHS Global Insight-NRF monthly Port Tracker report.</p></blockquote>
<p>Swine flue is what&#8217;s doing it for you hey?  Not that workers are being shed, profits are down, container traffic is down.  I mean come-on, what could a company not making a profit or selling less stuff while shedding jobs in a down economy that was 70% consumer driven have to do with you making money off of their stock.  Nothing I guess.</p>
<p>Nothing has changed.  There are still two economies and only one of them is a concern.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/04/the-disconnect-of-my-economy-with-the-money-economy.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
