<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Egypt &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>More on the Middle East</title>
		<link>./../../2011/02/more-on-the-middle-east.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/02/more-on-the-middle-east.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2011 14:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Egypt]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[food prices]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income inequality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[middle class]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/02/more-on-the-middle-east.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The NYT reports today of further developments in the Middle East. Jordan&#8217;s Royal Palace says the king has sacked his government in the wake of street protests and has asked an ex-army general to form a new Cabinet. King Abdullah&#8217;s move comes after thousands of Jordanians took to the streets — inspired by the regime [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a target="_blank" href="http://www.nytimes.com/aponline/2011/02/01/world/middleeast/AP-ML-Jordan-Cabinet.html">The NYT</a> reports today of further developments in the Middle East.</p>
<blockquote><p>Jordan&#8217;s Royal Palace says the king has sacked his government in the wake of street protests and has asked an ex-army general to form a new Cabinet. </p>
<p>King Abdullah&#8217;s move comes after thousands of Jordanians took to the streets — inspired by the regime ouster in Tunisia and the turmoil in Egypt — and called for the resignation of Prime Minister Samir Rifai who is blamed for a rise in fuel and <a target="_blank" href="http://topics.nytimes.com/top/reference/timestopics/subjects/f/food_prices/index.html?inline=nyt-classifier">food prices</a> and slowed political reforms. </p>
<p>The Royal Palace says Rifai&#8217;s Cabinet resigned on Tuesday. </p></blockquote>
<p><a target="_blank" href="http://econospeak.blogspot.com/2011/01/whither-egypt.html">Barkley Rosser</a> offers a take off point for the international aspects of the Egyptian turmoil, and a <a target="_blank" href="http://econospeak.blogspot.com/2011/01/political-economic-basis-of-egyptian.html">beginning look</a> at the history of the politics/economics of the nation.</p>
<blockquote><p>Yesterday, Juan Cole posted on  <a target="_blank" href="http://www.juancole.com/2011/01/egypts-class-conflict.html">Class Conflict in Egypt</a>. As usual, very insightful on the poltical economic foundations of this uprising. He argues that the original base of support for the Nasserist regime that took over in a coup in 1952 was rural land reform, with the rural middle class that got land still the base of the regime. However, over time with urbanization and slow growth and the rise of corruption since Mubarak took over, that base has eroded. <br /><a name="more"></a><br />Nasser also gained credibility for throwing out the British and standing up to other outsiders (with the US and Soviets ironically siding with him in the 1956 Suez Crisis against the UK, France, and Israel).</p>
<p>Real wages doubled between 1960 and 1970, when Nasser died, but stagnated after that until 2000, with nearly zero real per capita income growth and a worsening income distribution. Neo-liberal policies, including relaxation of food price controls in the 1990s, did not produce much, although growth did increase after 2000, running at a 5-6% rate. But it has not been enough to provide jobs for the many urban youth, particularly the better educated ones.</p>
<p>Also, since 1980 the regime has been seen as supported by outsiders, particularly the US, Israel, Britain, and France, in contrast to the Nasser period. As economic problems surged with the food price spikes in 2008 and the subsequent Great Recession in the world economy, this made for a weak foundation of support for the regime. We should expect any successor to take a more independent line, especially the moderate El-Baradei who was so badly treated by the US previously. </p>
<p>I must note, however, that while inequality has increased, it is not all that bad compared to many other countries, with Egypt&#8217;s current Gini coefficient of 34.0 putting it in 90th place in terms of inequality in the world.</p>
<p>Finally, I note that the chances for Mohamed El-Baradei succeeding Mubarak (eventually anyway) have increased with him receiving the support of the Ikhwan, the Muslim Brotherhood. However, there are other more radical Islamist groups in Egypt calling for an Islamist state with Shari&#8217;a imposed as law, although they appear to be a minority on that side, even though they are more moderate than the expelled Egyptian Islamic Jihad, whose leaders include the #2 and #3 figures in al-Qaeda.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/02/more-on-the-middle-east.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Egyptian CDS in line with Portuguese CDS</title>
		<link>./../../2011/01/egyptian-cds-in-line-with-portuguese-cds.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/01/egyptian-cds-in-line-with-portuguese-cds.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 30 Jan 2011 14:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[CDS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Egypt]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Portugal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rebecca Wilder]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/01/egyptian-cds-in-line-with-portuguese-cds.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[It occurred to me that some Angry Bear readers may be interested in a short analysis of the Egyptian bond market. Professionally, I&#8217;m a macroeconomic analyst and portfolio manager on a global fixed income team. Since we do trade emerging market debt, of which Egyptian debt is categorized, I&#8217;ll be happy to comment. The gist [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It occurred to me that some Angry Bear readers may be interested in a short analysis of the Egyptian bond market. Professionally, I&#8217;m a macroeconomic analyst and portfolio manager on a global fixed income team. Since we do trade emerging market debt, of which Egyptian debt is categorized, I&#8217;ll be happy to comment.</p>
<p>The gist of the article is this: markets are pricing the probability of default in Portugal and Egypt similarly &#8211; I&#8217;d sell protection on the Egyptian debt. At this point, I should state the following disclaimer: this is not a trade recommendation, nor does this represent my firm&#8217;s views on Egypt or Portugal.</p>
<p>Some bond market developments of late:
<ol>
<li>Egypt holds a BBB- rating on its local currency debt by Fitch and S&#038;P (BB+ on its foreign currency debt). The local currency debt in Egypt is at the lowest of the investment-grade ratings, while on January 20, 2011, <a href="http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=133307715">Fitch put Egypt on credit-watch negative</a>.</li>
<li>The Egyptian pound is heavily managed. Over the last week, the USD gained just 0.9% against the pound. Maintaining a stronger nominal currency is common in developing economies to temper the effects of import prices (in this case, food).</li>
<li>The 5.75% 10-yr Egyptian international bond, which is denominated in USD, sold off 7% over the last week. According to JP Morgan, Egypt is well underperforming the index (Egpyt is roughly 0.5% of the index): the year to date total return on the Egyptian international bonds is -10%, while that of the  JP Morgan Emerging Market Bond Index Global (EMBIG) is -0.7%.</li>
<li>Credit default swap spreads jumped 50% over the last week to 454 basis points (bps), according to one Bloomberg source (no link, subscription required). CDS are bilateral contracts between two parties, so pricing varies somewhat &#8211; but the trend is the same among all sources: up. This means that it&#8217;s becoming increasingly expensive to buy protection against Egyptian sovereign default.</li>
</ol>
<p>If you want to know more about CDS, please see a <a href="http://www.dbresearch.com/PROD/DBR_INTERNET_EN-PROD/PROD0000000000252032.pdf">helpful 2009 publication by Deutsche Bank.</a></p>
<p>And this is where it gets interesting: it currently costs the same to buy 5-yr protection on Egyptian bonds (454 bps) as on Portuguese bonds (456 bps). And Portugal is rated A- (negative outlook).</p>
<p><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_Et4TQ-a0gGU/TUVhBPk6BsI/AAAAAAAADcw/L3Cb1VPwO28/s1600/CDS_chart.jpg"><img src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_Et4TQ-a0gGU/TUVhBPk6BsI/AAAAAAAADcw/L3Cb1VPwO28/s400/CDS_chart.jpg" alt="" border="0"></a> (more after the jump)<br /><a name="more"></a>The chart above illustrates a panel of CDS data for countries with similar market risk, where S&#038;P&#8217;s local currency rating is listed in the legend. The CDS quoted above are priced in USD, rather than the local currency; but the spreads do quantify the market&#8217;s assigned probability of default : 29.3% for Egypt vs. 29% for Portugal (with a 30% recovery rate on both).</p>
<p>Generally the decision to default comes in two flavors: the &#8216;willingness&#8217; and &#8216;ability&#8217; to pay. Also, default can take many forms, like missed coupon payments, terming out debt liabilities, or bankruptcy (corporate).</p>
<p>Willingess. A quick analysis of &#8216;governance&#8217; indicators at the World Bank says that on the face of it, Portugal is probably more willing to pay its debts. The governance measures are corruption, government effectiveness, political stability, regulatory quality, rule of law, and voice and accountability. Read about the methodology of the governance indicators <a href="http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1682130">here</a> and get the data <a href="http://info.worldbank.org/governance/wgi/index.asp">here</a>.</p>
<p>In sum, Portugal ranks much higher on the total of the World Bank governance indicators, 6.4, compared to -2.6 for Egypt (I use a strict sum of the 6 components).</p>
<p>Ability. According to the IMF&#8217;s most recent World Economic Outlook (<a href="http://www.imf.org/external/ns/cs.aspx?id=28">October 2010 database</a>), Egypt is expected to grow an average 13.9% per year in nominal terms over the next three years (2010-2013). In contrast, Portugal is expected to grow just 1.7% on average for the next three years.</p>
<p>According to Bloomberg, on January 27, 2011, the yield on a Portuguese 1-year local bond is 3.42%, while that for a local Egyptian bond is 10.99%. I&#8217;ll take odds of payment on the one with nominal growth that exceeds the payment &#8211; Egypt.</p>
<p>A quick look at the WEI shows the following statistics for 2011:<br />
<table border="0" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="438">
<col width="64">
<col width="310">
<col width="64">
<tbody>
<tr height="20">
<td width="64" height="20">Country</td>
<td width="310">Subject Descriptor</td>
<td align="right" width="64">2011</td>
</tr>
<tr height="20">
<td height="20">Egypt</td>
<td>General government net lending/borrowing</td>
<td align="right">-7.622</td>
</tr>
<tr height="20">
<td height="20">Portugal</td>
<td>General government net lending/borrowing</td>
<td align="right">-5.232</td>
</tr>
<tr height="20">
<td height="20">Egypt</td>
<td>General government net debt</td>
<td align="right">60.993</td>
</tr>
<tr height="20">
<td height="20">Portugal</td>
<td>General government net debt</td>
<td align="right">82.864</td>
</tr>
<tr height="20">
<td height="20">Egypt</td>
<td>General government gross debt</td>
<td align="right">71.725</td>
</tr>
<tr height="20">
<td height="20">Portugal</td>
<td>General government gross debt</td>
<td align="right">87.086</td>
</tr>
<tr height="20">
<td height="20">Egypt</td>
<td>Current account balance</td>
<td align="right">-1.605</td>
</tr>
<tr height="20">
<td height="20">Portugal</td>
<td>Current account balance</td>
<td align="right">-9.171</td>
</tr>
<tr height="20">
<td height="20"></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr height="20">
<td colspan="9" height="20">International   Monetary Fund, World Economic Outlook Database, October 2010</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>The 2011 outlook demonstrates the following: government deficits are similar in Portugal and Egypt; government debt is higher in Portugal, a country that has no monetary sovereignty; Portugal has relatively fewer reserves (comparing gross debt to net debt); and the current account deficit in Portugal dwarfs that of Egypt.</p>
<p>If I was an investment bank, I&#8217;d rather sell protection on Egypt than Portugal at these prices.</p>
<p>Rebecca Wilder</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/01/egyptian-cds-in-line-with-portuguese-cds.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
