<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>competitive advantage &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Happy 56th Anniversary</title>
		<link>./../../2011/12/happy-56th-anniversary.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/12/happy-56th-anniversary.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2011 20:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[competitive advantage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[history]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[race]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/12/happy-56th-anniversary.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Not a very long time, even if there were full and complete co-operation. Or, as LBJ said, Source (cross-posted from Skippy, the Bush Kangaroo)]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<p>Not a very long time, even if there were full and complete co-operation. Or, as LBJ said,</p>
<p><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-K95_o-4jxRs/Tte0fRl-omI/AAAAAAAAAsA/InSaLuLuucc/s1600/LBJ%2Bshackles.PNG"><img src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-K95_o-4jxRs/Tte0fRl-omI/AAAAAAAAAsA/InSaLuLuucc/s400/LBJ%2Bshackles.PNG" border="0" alt=""></a></p>
<p><a href="http://books.google.com/books?id=pQMAsT7HlEsC&#038;lpg=PA90&#038;ots=Z-ptvTet88&#038;dq=LBJ%20unshackle%20fair%20race&#038;pg=PA90#v=onepage&#038;q&#038;f=false">Source</a></p>
<p>(cross-posted from <a href="http://xnerg.blogspot.com/">Skippy, the Bush Kangaroo</a>)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/12/happy-56th-anniversary.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>You Want to Invest in This?</title>
		<link>./../../2011/07/you-want-to-invest-in-this.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/07/you-want-to-invest-in-this.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2011 11:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[competitive advantage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[investments]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[IPO]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stock Market]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/07/you-want-to-invest-in-this.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[So I use Pandora on my Droid, and it&#8217;s pretty reasonable. I haven&#8217;t done anything complicated, or even created any mixes. And when I pick Bruce Cockburn Radio or Stevie Wonder Radio or Don Henley Radio or any of the other stations that are perfectly safe to play while at work, there will occasionally be [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>So I use Pandora on my Droid, and it&#8217;s pretty reasonable. I haven&#8217;t done anything complicated, or even created any mixes.  And when I pick Bruce Cockburn Radio or Stevie Wonder Radio or Don Henley Radio or any of the other stations that are perfectly safe to play while at work, there will occasionally be tracks by other artists, but they&#8217;re fairly similar: Stevie gets followed by Aretha, Cockburn gets followed by an instrumentalist or a McGarrigle sister, Henley gets followed by mellow Genesis or Peter Gabriel (&#8220;In Your Eyes&#8221;) or Phil Collins solo.*</p>
<p>So I was very surprised when I launched Pandora from my laptop&#8217;s browser today, still on the Don Henley station.  Here are the first four songs it chose:
<ol>
<li>Led Balloon, &#8220;Stairway to Heaven&#8221; (live, no less)</li>
<li>Bon Jovi, &#8220;Wanted Dead or Alive&#8221;</li>
<li>Lynyrd Skynyrd, &#8220;Sweet Home Alabama,&#8221; and</li>
<li>Queen, &#8220;We Will Rock You&#8221;</li>
</ol>
<p>If I wanted to listen to a set list like that, I would just tune in <a href="http://www.q1043.com/main.html">one of the local mediocre commercial stations</a>. At least their commercials are more interesting.</p>
<p>(Hint to investors: if a company only has one advert that it uses when the app is first used—even after the user clicked through and signed up—they have more of a problem with their business model than <a href="http://www.judysims.com/simsblog/2011/06/its-time-we-talked-about-patch.html">Patch</a>.)</p>
<p>From what I can tell, we&#8217;re back in the <a href="http://www.fastcompany.com/magazine/32/flipdia.html">Built-to-Flip model</a> of Internet investing.</p>
<p>The &#8220;Don Henley&#8221; station is now playing The Rolling Stones&#8217;s &#8220;Paint It Black.&#8221; Love the song, own the Decca collection they&#8217;re linking it to.  Not what I would expect to hear between Coldplay and Steeler&#8217;s Wheel, though.</p>
<p>Paying $36/year to upgrade my account seems much more unlikely than it did even this morning.  The next two songs were &#8220;Another One Bites the Dust&#8221; and this:<br />

</p>
<p>which was the second track by that band in an hour—matching the actual number of Henley/Eagles tracks played.</p>
<p>Either their algorithm is really dumb, or they assume all their listeners obsess over Axl&#8217;s vocals on &#8220;I Will Not Go Quietly.&#8221;  Not the way to bet in the mass market.</p>
<p>*I have some standards: the latter would be an immediate thumb down, but I know why I&#8217;m getting it: after you let the Genesis-recorded Ode to Adultery [&#8220;In Too Deep&#8221;] play, Collins&#8217;s sententious solve-hunger song [&#8220;Another Day in Paradise&#8217;] or the insufferable &#8220;Take Me Home&#8221; probably will be suggested sooner rather than later.)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/07/you-want-to-invest-in-this.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Beating The New Republic by Seven Days, or Does Jonathan Cohn Read AB?</title>
		<link>./../../2011/06/beating-the-new-republic-by-seven-days-or-does-jonathan-cohn-read-ab.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/06/beating-the-new-republic-by-seven-days-or-does-jonathan-cohn-read-ab.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2011 15:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Brad DeLong]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[competitive advantage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economic history]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health care reform]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/06/beating-the-new-republic-by-seven-days-or-does-jonathan-cohn-read-ab.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Yes, it&#8217;s another &#8220;AB was right&#8221; post. Detractors of this blog in general and me in particular could stop reading now. But they shouldn&#8217;t. Anyone who thought through the economics could have pointed out what I did on the 17th: From [Republican Congressman John] Boehner&#8217;s site: At least 30 percent of employers would gain economically [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Yes, it&#8217;s another &#8220;AB was right&#8221; post. Detractors of this blog in general and me in particular <em>could</em> stop reading now.</p>
<p>But they shouldn&#8217;t. Anyone who thought through the economics could have pointed out <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2011/06/mckinsey-thought-experiment-what-if.html">what I did on the 17th</a>:<br />
<blockquote>From [Republican Congressman John] Boehner&#8217;s site:<br />
<blockquote>At least 30 percent of employers would gain economically from dropping coverage even if they completely compensated employees for the change through other benefit offerings or higher salaries.</p></blockquote>
<p>This should be intuitive. If the company is paying $1,000 a month for my family&#8217;s health care along with my $800 a month, it can raise my paycheck by $1,000 a month—employee compensation is employee compensation—and cut back on its health care administration. If I&#8217;m not a health-care administrator, it&#8217;s win-win.</p>
<p>Any economist worth her salt should know that lower costs of employment increase overall employment (assuming there is not a demand-side problem).</p>
<p>If the McKinsey &#8220;study&#8221; were accurate—again, not the way to bet—we should expect overall employment to <em>increase</em>&#8230;.</p>
<p>The follow-on effects in that universe: more people joining the HIEs than expected, improvements in the measurement of &#8220;real&#8221; wage growth, greater transparency in the current health-insurance system, and arguably a larger contingency of workers demanding something closer to a single-payer solution, all improve efficiency and provide opportunity for economic expansion.</p></blockquote>
<p>Or what Jonathan Cohn <a href="http://www.tnr.com/blog/jonathan-cohn/90696/healthcare-mckinsey-obama">wrote for the Kaiser Health Network and <em>The New Republic</em> a week later</a>:<br />
<blockquote>But here’s the irony: Most people like the insurance they get from their employers, which is why you hear politicians from both parties constantly promising to keep that coverage in place. In the long run, though, workplace-based insurance is probably not an arrangement worth preserving&#8230;.</p>
<p>An ideal health care system would&#8230;liberate employers from the responsibility of administering health benefits for workers, allowing them to concentrate on other, more productive activities. Let the car companies make cars and the grocery stores sell groceries and the software firms design software. They don’t need to be running health insurance plans, too.</p></blockquote>
<p>I&#8217;ve left out Cohn&#8217;s historically-illiterate paragraph about the groups of private health insurance, since he omits the main reason it developed: wage controls during wartime left employers looking for other ways to attract and keep workers.* At least he comes to the correct conclusion:<br />
<blockquote>A single-payer system, with a combination of basic government insurance and private supplemental coverage, would be a much better alternative. So would a “competition” system that looks like what is currently in place in the Netherlands or Switzerland, or what Senator Ron Wyden, D-Ore., first proposed back in 2007. The Affordable Care Act could evolve into such a system, particularly if the new insurance exchanges work well and workers feel comfortable the insurance available there is as good as what they’d get from employers. But that transition would probably take a lot of time, no matter what corporate officials were telling the survey-takers at McKinsey.</p></blockquote>
<p>It&#8217;s not just a lot of time. It&#8217;s a lot of opportunity cost and underutilized human capital. And we <a href="http://delong.typepad.com/sdj/2011/06/how-much-human-capital-are-we-pissing-away.html">have enough of that already</a>,** no?</p>
<p>Good to see the Mainstream catching up with AB.</p>
<p>*As an alternative history, consider that, if that industry hadn&#8217;t begun to develop during <a href="http://delong.typepad.com/sdj/2011/06/eleanor-roosevelt-liveblogs-world-war-ii-june-28-1941.html">the War After the War to End All Wars</a>, the U.S. might have followed the same path as the United Kingdom and <a href="http://www.nhs.uk/Pages/HomePage.aspx">founded the National Health Service</a>, instead of leaving the country, almost sixty-five years later, trying to pretend that Barack Obama is <a href="http://www.nupge.ca/news_2004/n30no04c.htm">Tommy Douglas</a>.</p>
<p>**Yes, I would have found a way to link to this piece just for the title. When Brad DeLong is starting to entitle his pieces as if he were <a href="http://www.rudepundit.blogspot.com/">Lee Papa</a> (or at least me; see the following link), the Sensible Centrists are once again signaling that <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2011/06/spot-effing-on-as-mainstreamers-edge.html">their imminent move into the Activist camp</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/06/beating-the-new-republic-by-seven-days-or-does-jonathan-cohn-read-ab.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
