<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>religious wars &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Reasons Market Share Declines</title>
		<link>./../../2010/02/reasons-market-share-declines.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/02/reasons-market-share-declines.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2010 14:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[AAPL]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[monopoly]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MSFT]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[religious wars]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[reputational risk]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/02/reasons-market-share-declines.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Michael Swanwick explains how a monopoly can destroy itself: Nowadays, times are much easier but a lot scammier. Last week I had to buy a new palmbook/laptop. Which, I discovered on my first and only day of possession, was preloaded with Windows 7 Starter, a not-fully-functional OS. When I tried to change the image on [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Michael Swanwick explains <a href="http://floggingbabel.blogspot.com/2010/02/boskone.html">how a monopoly can destroy itself</a>:<br />
<blockquote>Nowadays, times are much easier but a lot scammier.  Last week I had to buy a new palmbook/laptop.  Which, I discovered on my first and only day of possession, was preloaded with Windows 7 Starter, a not-fully-functional OS.  When I tried to change the image on my desktop, I learned that doing so required that I go online and buy Windows 7 Home Premier.  After getting my refund, I talked to salesfolk at various stores and learned that all the new palmtops have the cut-down version because they don&#8217;t have memory enough to run W7HP. </p>
<p>Well, each new version of Windows is written far too memory-hoggish for the current hardware.  So it only makes sense that the new OS would have fewer features.  Still, it was pretty cheeky of them to have it automatically try to sell me an OS that my device couldn&#8217;t run.</p>
<p>Apple doesn&#8217;t play that kind of game, so if I&#8217;d been willing to wait for the iPad to come available, I probably would&#8217;ve spent the extra money for it.  But I have work to do, so I scrounged around until I found one of the dwindling number of netbooks still running on XP.</p></blockquote>
<p>As I&#8217;ve noted before, they did this on laptops with Vista as well.  There is no better way to destroy your reputation that to put out something that doesn&#8217;t work.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/02/reasons-market-share-declines.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Buy on the Rumor, Sell on the Fact</title>
		<link>./../../2010/01/buy-on-the-rumor-sell-on-the-fact.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/01/buy-on-the-rumor-sell-on-the-fact.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 27 Jan 2010 22:17:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[AAPL]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[religious wars]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[technology]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/01/buy-on-the-rumor-sell-on-the-fact.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[UPDATE: datacharmer at Bluematter thinks visually. Bruce, yesterday: Unless you have had the experience of using an advanced smartphone it is hard to explain how transforming it is to have the Internet in your pocket, if I have a question about anything it is mostly as close as my left pocket. But like the iPhone [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>UPDATE: datacharmer at Bluematter <a href="http://bluematter.blogspot.com/2010/01/world-reacts-to-apple-ipad.html">thinks visually</a>.</p>
<p>Bruce, <a href="http://angrybear.blogspot.com/2010/01/why-apple-tablet-and-clones-will-change.html">yesterday</a>:<br />
<blockquote>Unless you have had the experience of using an advanced smartphone it is hard to explain how transforming it is to have the Internet in your pocket, if I have a question about anything it is mostly as close as my left pocket. But like the iPhone the Tablet is a lot more than a combined phone/usable web browser, it is a host for Apps, millions of them. And it is the Apps that are the game changer. Because the possibilities are quite literally endless.</p></blockquote>
<p>Sarah, <a href="http://www.smartbitchestrashybooks.com/index.php/weblog/comments/my-initial-reaction-to-the-ipad">today</a>:<br />
<blockquote>iPad?! Really?! REALLY? Gosh, I’m sorry I no longer have a Nook now. They would have been great partners.</p>
<p>The iPad, now available in Light, Maxi, and Super (8Gb, 16Gb 64Gb)? As Tessa Dare said, are there NO women at Apple who could have given them the heads up (HA) that this is a BAD NAME?&#8230;</p>
<p>This isn’t “standing on the shoulders of Kindle.” It’s giving the Kindle half a nod from across a ballroom full of other people you’d rather talk to&#8230;.</p>
<p>What about onboard social networks, email functionality, or notation from inside iBooks? Wouldn’t that be a key feature to intregrate with the endless onward wanking about Pages? For example: writing a report… and easily with a single gesture including both the source material and the citation using iBooks and Pages?</p>
<p>I realize that reading isn’t the utmost important thing for everyone else, but come on now! Productivity in all forms includes printed material. The lack of interaction demonstrated in iBook makes me hope for other reading alternatives on the iPad (DEAR GOD THE NAME). Color me underwhelmed in a big, big way.</p></blockquote>
<p>UPDATE II:  Brad <a href="http://firemeganmcardle.blogspot.com/2010/01/idontgetit.html">piles on</a>:<br />
<blockquote>But ffs, it can&#8217;t handle flash, and it doesn&#8217;t have any way to access media not on its own HD, no disc drive, no usb port in. That&#8217;s fine for a phone but not for a potential media player. Apple has finally made something I have no interest in owning.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/01/buy-on-the-rumor-sell-on-the-fact.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Charlie Stross Explains It All to You</title>
		<link>./../../2010/01/charlie-stross-explains-it-all-to-you.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/01/charlie-stross-explains-it-all-to-you.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 17 Jan 2010 21:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[AAPL]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MSFT]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[religious wars]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sf]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/01/charlie-stross-explains-it-all-to-you.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The rest is details: The reason I choose to pay through the nose for my computers is very simple: unlike just about every other manufacturer in the business, Apple appreciate the importance of good industrial design. but they&#8217;re nice details. (posted from my daughters&#8217;s &#8220;new&#8221; G4, which needs a new keyboard, but has a right [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The rest is <a href="http://www.antipope.org/charlie/blog-static/2010/01/more-flame-bait.html">details</a>:<br />
<blockquote>The reason I choose to pay through the nose for my computers is very simple: unlike just about every other manufacturer in the business, Apple appreciate the importance of good industrial design.</p></blockquote>
<p>but they&#8217;re nice details.</p>
<p>(posted from my daughters&#8217;s &#8220;new&#8221; G4, which needs a new keyboard, but has a right shift key)</p>
<p>[Apple ticker symbol corrected in tags.  Thank you.]</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/01/charlie-stross-explains-it-all-to-you.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>4</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
