<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Megan McArdle &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Cactus and his merry band of madmen&#8230;and Megan McArdle</title>
		<link>./../../2012/09/cactus-and-his-merry-band-of-madmen-and-megan-mcardle.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/09/cactus-and-his-merry-band-of-madmen-and-megan-mcardle.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 21 Sep 2012 15:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Megan McArdle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Presimetrics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/09/cactus-and-his-merry-band-of-madmen-and-megan-mcardle.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I googled the title phrase and &#8216;Behold!&#8217;, here are the three links.  Mike also sent them. Cactus and his merry band of madmen and Megan McArdle Megan McArdle has a question Megan McArdle has a question: What happens to the cottage industry among Democratic-leaning armchair economists grinding out analyses proving that Democratic presidents are, like, totally [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I googled the title phrase and &#8216;Behold!&#8217;, here are the three links.  Mike also sent them. </p>
<p>Cactus and his merry band of madmen and Megan McArdle</p>
<p><a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2009/07/megan-mcardle-has-question.html" target="_blank">Megan McArdle has a question</a></p>
<p>
<div>Megan McArdle <a href="http://meganmcardle.theatlantic.com/archives/2009/07/question_of_the_day_9.php">has a question</a>:</div>
<blockquote><p>What happens to the cottage industry among Democratic-leaning armchair economists grinding out analyses proving that Democratic presidents are, like, totally awesome for the economy? Presuming that we&#8217;re stuck&#8211;as seem very likely&#8211;in at least a couple of years of really grinding low-to-no growth, Obama is going to destroy their figures. Are we in for a resurgence of belief in exogenous growth factors?</p></blockquote>
<p><a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/business/archive/2009/07/question-answered/20847/" target="_blank">Question answered</a></p>
<blockquote><p>Now, of course, it may be that the economy starts growing like gangbusters in the next year.  In which case I expect that Cactus and his merry band of madmen will continue with their arguments.  But if, as most people expect, growth continues to stall for the next few years,  it seems I can look forward to more explanations of why Democrats&#8211;and only Democrats&#8211;can be thrown out of the sample if they have low growth and betray The Faith; and why the economic results of Democratic presidential administrations&#8211;and only Democratic presidential administrations&#8211;are sensitive to exogenous starting conditions.</p></blockquote>
<p><a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2009/07/response-to-megan-mcardle-again-by.html" target="_blank">Response to Megan McArdle again</a></p>
<blockquote><p>&#8220;Going back to 1952 at least, every Democrat, every single one, has increased the tax burden. Every single Republican lowered them.&#8221;-McArdle</p>
<p>I had some posts after that, perhaps time to revisit them, that showed that not only did the change in the tax burden correlate with growth, the change in the tax burden in the first two years of an administration&#8217;s term correlated with the growth rate in the final six years. And not in the direction McMegan likes to see. Sure, correlation does not imply causality, but it just so happens that Presidents under whom growth in years 2 &#8211; 8 was fastest also were the Presidents who found a way to go back in time to years 1 &#038; 2 and raise the tax burden. Or something like that. Go figure.   </p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/09/cactus-and-his-merry-band-of-madmen-and-megan-mcardle.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Project S.H.A.M.E. on Megan McArdle&#8230;</title>
		<link>./../../2012/09/project-s-h-a-m-e-on-megan-mcardle.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/09/project-s-h-a-m-e-on-megan-mcardle.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2012 17:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Megan McArdle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Yves Smith]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/09/project-s-h-a-m-e-on-megan-mcardle.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Angry Bear has had a history of disagreement with Megan McArdle via her Atlantic magazine posts (starting in 2007), at one point being called Mike and his merry madmen in print by Megan McArdle (in exasperation?). Still. the madmen included Mike, Dan Crawford, Spencer England, Ken Houghton, Robert Waldmann, and other notables brought in to [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Angry Bear has had a history of disagreement with Megan McArdle via her Atlantic magazine posts (starting in 2007), at one point being called <i>Mike and his merry madmen</i> in print by Megan McArdle (in exasperation?).  Still. the madmen included Mike, Dan Crawford, Spencer England, Ken Houghton, Robert Waldmann, and other notables brought in to help.  I will have a history up later when I can sort them out.  </p>
<p>It is with feeling some real vindication publicly when I saw <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/09/project-s-h-a-m-e-on-megan-mcardle-portrait-of-a-taxpayer-subsidized-libertarian.html" target="_blank">Yves Smith</a> post an entire column from <a href="http://shameproject.com/" target="_blank">Project Shame</a> on Megan McArdle well worth reading.  It begins:<br />
<blockquote>Megan McArdle is a Koch-trained conservative activist working as a business journalist and pundit. She earned her MBA from the University of Chicago, received journalism training at the Kochs’ flagship libertarian think-tank, the Institute for Humane Studies, and has used her position at The Atlantic and, most recently, Newsweek/The Daily Beast, to run cover for and promote Koch interests and the Republican Party agenda. In early 2009, a GOP outfit backed by the Kochs hailed McArdle for her “leadership role in … re-branding the Republican party.” McArdle continues to conceal the extent of her deeply conflicted relationships with the Koch influence-peddling machine.</p></blockquote>
<p>Read more at <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/09/project-s-h-a-m-e-on-megan-mcardle-portrait-of-a-taxpayer-subsidized-libertarian.html#VokgGsGRrcmriKJU.99" target="_blank">Naked Capitalism</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/09/project-s-h-a-m-e-on-megan-mcardle.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
