<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>climate change &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Updates on atmospheric methane and volume measurements of Arctic sea ice</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/updates-on-atmospheric-methane-and-volume-measurements-of-arctic-sea-ice.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/updates-on-atmospheric-methane-and-volume-measurements-of-arctic-sea-ice.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 19 Feb 2013 04:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[climate change]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rjs (links)]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/updates-on-atmospheric-methane-and-volume-measurements-of-arctic-sea-ice.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Here is a link filled update on the rise of atmospheric methane and a decrease in volume of Arctic sea ice from reader rjs. Today we’d like to make note of an interesting development in the arctic during January. Below we have 3 images of methane concentrations above the Arctic Ocean from 3 ten day [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Here is a link filled update on the rise of atmospheric methane and a decrease in volume of Arctic sea ice from<u> reader rjs.</u></p>
<p>Today we’d like to make note of an interesting development in the arctic during January. Below we have <a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-OTfGBMswYDs/UQyPQJI8UXI/AAAAAAAAJKQ/zFrPQUexXaY/s1600/8453866348957.jpg">3 images of methane concentrations above the Arctic Ocean from 3 ten day periods in january</a> (January 1-10, January 11-20, and January 21-31) from Russian physicist Dr. Leonid Yurganov.. The methane concentration scale, with darker reds being the highest, can be viewed by <a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-OTfGBMswYDs/UQyPQJI8UXI/AAAAAAAAJKQ/zFrPQUexXaY/s1600/8453866348957.jpg">clicking on the image to enlarge it</a>.</p>
<p><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-OTfGBMswYDs/UQyPQJI8UXI/AAAAAAAAJKQ/zFrPQUexXaY/s1600/8453866348957.jpg"><img border="0" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-OTfGBMswYDs/UQyPQJI8UXI/AAAAAAAAJKQ/zFrPQUexXaY/s640/8453866348957.jpg" height="145" width="400"></a></p>
<p>Quite obviously, there&#8217;s been a sudden increase in atmospheric methane in an area of the arctic ocean north of eastern Europe and western Asia. <a href="http://arctic-news.blogspot.com/2013/02/dramatic-increase-in-methane-in-the-arctic-in-january-2013.html">As shown in the post about this at Arctic News</a>, that <a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-cytwgPSpkDE/UQyQDPryYBI/AAAAAAAAJKc/IXsj2KBw-l0/s1600/4537458256.jpg">area where the methane concentrations are highest coincides with the area of the arctic ocean that is still relatively ice-free</a>. <br />This dramatic increase in atmospheric methane seems to be similar to <a href="http://marketwatch666.blogspot.com/2012/01/notes-on-dec-unemployment-lpss-mortgage.html">an arctic event that we covered a little over a year ago</a> that occurred in November 2011. At that time <a href="http://www.independent.co.uk/news/science/vast-methane-plumes-seen-in-arctic-ocean-as-sea-ice-retreats-6276278.html">Russian scientists had observed vast plumes of methane bubbling to the surface of the arctic ocean</a> off the coast of eastern Siberia, which they described as &#8220;powerful and impressive seeping structures more than 1,000 metres in diameter&#8221;.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Back then we figured that since that eastern Siberian area was one of the shallowest areas of the arctic, it had warmed enough during a period of unusual atmospheric circulation that fall to thaw the extensive amounts of frozen methane hydrates known to be locked up by high pressure and cold temperatures on the ocean floor, and they were melting and rising to the surface. In this case it appears that a branch of the warm gulf stream current is causing enough warming to destabilize the frozen methane on the ocean floor in the areas between Norway and Svalbard and points east. This is similar to a <a href="http://www.carbonbrief.org/blog/2012/10/gulf-stream-unlocking-frozen-methane">scenario that was warned about in a study in the journal Nature in October</a>.</p>
<p>What happens next is anyone&#8217;s guess, but Dr Yurganov&#8217;s records indicate that <a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-KFB9QRidvSM/UQ8bQZJv8OI/AAAAAAAAJNo/tRmzygYW278/s1600/Methane-Jan21-31.jpg">higher levels of arctic methane emissions have been increasing over time</a>. (US scientists must now rely on Canadian &#038; European monitoring of greenhouse gas emissions because <a href="http://climatechangepsychology.blogspot.com/2013/02/noaa-monitoring-of-arctic-methane-and.html">NOAA’s monitoring of Arctic methane and CO2 was halted last week by budget cuts</a>). <a href="http://marketwatch666.blogspot.com/2012/11/unemployment-by-state-housing-starts.html">We&#8217;ve pointed out before </a>that atmospheric<a href="http://www.google.com/url?sa=t&#038;rct=j&#038;q=&#038;esrc=s&#038;frm=1&#038;source=web&#038;cd=2&#038;cad=rja&#038;ved=0CDkQFjAB&#038;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.cnn.com%2F2012%2F11%2F20%2Fworld%2Feurope%2Fgreenhouse-gases-record-high%2Findex.html&#038;ei=FN2wULzkG6WOyAGN_oCYBg&#038;usg=AFQjCNHzsggL2vVDdBWfchF6zfQ-lS-EHw"> methane hit a new high of about 1813 parts per billion (ppb) in 2011, which was at 259% of the pre-industrial level</a>, and that<a href="http://www.wmo.int/pages/mediacentre/press_releases/pr_965_en.html"> 40% of the increase was coming from natural sources such as this</a>. Methane is 25 times as potent a heat-trapping gas as CO2 over a 100 year time horizon, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Global_warming_potential">but 72 times as potent over 20 years</a>, and <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2013/01/links-11213.html#comment-1020851">methane&#8217;s global heat trapping effect is now roughly one-third that of CO2</a>. Further <a href="http://arcticmethane.blogspot.com/2012/05/potential-impact-of-large-abrupt.html">thoughts on the potential impact of large abrupt release of methane in the Arctic are here</a>. Suffice it to say that <a href="http://climatechangepsychology.blogspot.com/2013/02/thawing-permafrost-may-be-huge-factor.html">if all the ancient carbon were to be released from the arctic it would be enough to raise global temperatures 3C</a> on top of <a href="http://marketwatch666.blogspot.com/2012/11/unemployment-by-state-housing-starts.html">the 4C temperature rise from human activities predicted by the recent World Bank study</a>…</p>
<p>Our awareness of this comes the same week that <a href="http://thinkprogress.org.feedsportal.com/c/34726/f/638933/s/2894c394/l/0Lthinkprogress0Borg0Cclimate0C20A130C0A20C140C15942110Cdeath0Espiral0Ebombshell0Ecryosat0E20Econfirms0Earctic0Esea0Eice0Evolume0Ehas0Ecollapsed0C/story01.htm">the European Space Agency’s CryoSat-2 probe has confirmed the conclusion of the Pan-Arctic Ice Ocean Modeling and Assimilation System (PIOMAS) at the University of Washington’s Polar Science Cente</a><a href="http://psc.apl.washington.edu/wordpress/research/projects/arctic-sea-ice-volume-anomaly/">r</a> that not only is <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/09/ice-melting-takes-some-thought.html">the extent of the arctic ice receding</a>, but it&#8217;s thickness has diminished considerably as well. <a href="http://thinkprogress.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/02/arctic-sea-ice-min-volume-comparison-1979-2012-v21.png">The combined result has been a collapse in total arctic ice volume to one fifth of what was the minimum ice volume as recently as 1980</a>. With the associated warming in the arctic, we can only expect the frequency and range of such arctic methane releases to increase, from both the seabed and the permafrost.</p>
<p><a href="http://thinkprogress.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/02/arctic-sea-ice-min-volume-comparison-1979-2012-v21.png"><img alt="" src="http://thinkprogress.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/02/arctic-sea-ice-min-volume-comparison-1979-2012-v21.png" height="367" title="arctic-sea-ice-min-volume-comparison-1979-2012-v2" width="540"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/updates-on-atmospheric-methane-and-volume-measurements-of-arctic-sea-ice.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Barry Ritholz names names</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/barry-ritholz-names-names.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/barry-ritholz-names-names.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Jan 2013 13:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Barry Ritholtz]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[climate change]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/barry-ritholz-names-names.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Barry Ritholz offers a chart on &#8220;the who is debating&#8221; climate change. Personally I am amazed how in December, after Hurricane Sandy, the media reporting seemed to confirm climate change was real and a given fact&#8230;after reporting the &#8216;debate&#8217; so glibly prior to December.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a blank="blank" href="http://www.ritholtz.com/blog/2013/01/global-warming-debate-is-no-debate-at-all/" target="target">Barry Ritholz</a> offers a chart on &#8220;the who is debating&#8221; climate change. Personally I am amazed how in December, after Hurricane Sandy, the media reporting seemed to confirm climate change was real and a given fact&#8230;after reporting the &#8216;debate&#8217; so glibly prior to December. </p>
<div><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-2VPwyH6-sGU/UPi9ehcLGtI/AAAAAAAABZI/uURMoFaiDnM/s1600/climate.PNG" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="241" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-2VPwyH6-sGU/UPi9ehcLGtI/AAAAAAAABZI/uURMoFaiDnM/s320/climate.PNG" width="320"></a></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/barry-ritholz-names-names.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Coastal damage to be more common and extensive?</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/coastal-damage-to-be-more-common-and-extensive.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/coastal-damage-to-be-more-common-and-extensive.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Jan 2013 18:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[climate change]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/coastal-damage-to-be-more-common-and-extensive.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[From The Guardian comes this news: Marcia McNutt, who last week announced her resignation as director of the US Geological Survey, told a conference that Sandy had left coastal communities dangerously exposed to future storms of any size. &#8220;Superstorm Sandy was a threshold for the north-east and we have already crossed it,&#8221; McNutt told the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>From <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/environment/2013/jan/15/east-coast-sandy-storms-obama-scientist">The Guardian</a> comes this news:</p>
<blockquote><p>Marcia McNutt, who last week announced her resignation as director of the US Geological Survey, told a conference that Sandy had left coastal communities dangerously exposed to future storms of any size.</p>
<p>&#8220;Superstorm Sandy was a threshold for the north-east and we have already crossed it,&#8221; McNutt told the National Council for Science and the Environment conference in Washington. &#8220;For the next storm, not even a super storm, even a run-of-the-mill nor&#8217;easter, the amount of breaches and the amount of coastal flooding will be widespread.&#8221;</p>
<p>McNutt, a professor of marine geophysics, was careful to preface her public remarks by saying she spoke as a scientist and not an Obama Administration official. But the unusually stark warning from a departing Obama official indicates the challenges ahead in protecting American population centres from the extreme storms of a changing climate.</p>
<p>&#8220;Before Sandy, someone asked me what my <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/science/scienceofclimatechange">climate change</a> nightmare was. Before Sandy, I said it was that with the extra energy in the atmosphere-ocean system it feeds super storms that intersect mega-cities left rendered defenceless by rising seas,&#8221; McNutt said in a brief interview following her public remarks. &#8220;That is where we now are.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/coastal-damage-to-be-more-common-and-extensive.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>What natural disasters like Sandy teach us about taxes and government</title>
		<link>./../../2012/11/what-natural-disasters-like-sandy-teach-us-about-taxes-and-government.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/11/what-natural-disasters-like-sandy-teach-us-about-taxes-and-government.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2012 13:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[climate change]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linda Beale]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/11/what-natural-disasters-like-sandy-teach-us-about-taxes-and-government.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Left out in the wake of the election and material, Linda&#8217;s post is still relevant as we continue to clean up, repair and replace damage done by Hurricane Sandy and the Nor-easter.. I would like to see more information on plans for future &#8216;unique&#8217; storms and ways to handle some of the unique problems encountered [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Left out in the wake of the election and material, Linda&#8217;s post is still relevant as we continue to clean up, repair and replace damage done by Hurricane Sandy and the Nor-easter..  I would like to see more information on plans for future &#8216;unique&#8217; storms and ways to handle some of the unique problems encountered by rescue teams, firemen, and aid workers.</p>
<p>Bloomberg, the Financial Times, the New York Times and other editorials wanted &#8216;to join the band climbing back on the wagon&#8217; so to speak along with some politicians.</p>
<p>by Linda Beale</p>
<p> What natural disasters like Sandy teach us about taxes and government, and why NY City Mayor Bloomberg endorsed Obama</p>
<p> Bloomberg announced <strike>today (</strike>a week ago<strike>)</strike> that President Obama would be the best candidate to lead the nation over the next four years.  See <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/11/02/nyregion/bloomberg-endorses-obama-saying-hurricane-sandy-affected-decision.html?emc=na">Bloomberg Endorses Obama, Citing Climate Change</a>, New York Times (Nov. 1, 2012).  Bloomberg made the decision in part because of Hurricane Sandy, which wreaked havoc on the east coast, costing many lives and much financial distress.  Obama&#8217;s leadership and willingness to commit federal agencies to aid municipalities and people recover from the devastation was a marked contrast to the Bush Administration&#8217;s handling of Katrina and the utter disregard shown by Bush&#8217;s FEMA executives for prudent planning and quick response. </p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>There is a clear consensus among reputable scientists that global warming is underway and that superstorms like Sandy are one of the likely results.  In that context, a vibrant and efficient emergency response organization is terribly important.  Obama has shown that he recognizes this, in the way that he has handled the preparations for, and implementation of plans after, Hurricane Sandy. </p>
<p>Romney has amply demonstrated that he does not recognize the importance of government action to deal with natural disasters and similar emergencies.  Instead, he has suggested that &#8220;private organizations&#8221; should replace FEMA and that many other similar federal agencies should be squeezed down or even squeezed out.  Even in the lead-up to Sandy&#8217;s east coast strike, Romney was assisting with a gathering of canned goods and praising private charitable responses to emergencies, even though such action is not a very effective way to mobilize emergency aid. Further, as Bloomberg noted in his endorsement of Romney, Romney&#8217;s positions on many issues have shifted radically to the right in his attempt to win the election:  “ &#8216;In the past [Romney] has taken sensible positions on immigration, illegal guns, abortion rights and health care – but he has reversed course on all of them, and is even running against the very health care model he signed into law in Massachusetts,&#8217; Bloomberg said.&#8221;  Id.</p>
<p>Anyone who knows anything about public infrastructure and natural disaster knows that charitable groups and money-making enterprises cannot possibly substitute for good government action.  That is the reason that so many in Haiti are still living in improvized dwellings and so many in Somalia still suffer from chaotic lives with anarchy rather than government as their norm. </p>
<p>Obama&#8217;s course is the right one.  He hasn&#8217;t been willing to speak as strongly about issues like the environment and global warming as I would like, because he is at heart a centrist.  But at least he knows that government can and must act in ways that private organizations cannot act, a truth that Romney seems incapable of acknowledging.  That is the reason that taxation needs to be increased rather than merely &#8220;starving the beast&#8221; to reduce the size of government.  Government is just &#8220;we the people&#8221; acting to do things that are needed that we cannot do individually or even through a business enterprise.  Government acting in those ways requires taxes to provide the revenues to support the activities.  And those things are not inherent evils, as the radical right today paints them.  Quite the contrary.  Taxation and government activity in support of the public good are vitally important parts of a sustainable democracy<br />.<br />cross posted and lightly edited <a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2012/11/what-natural-disasters-like-sandy-teach-us-about-taxes-and-government-and-why-ny-city-mayor-bloomber.html">ataxingmatter</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/11/what-natural-disasters-like-sandy-teach-us-about-taxes-and-government.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Hurricane Sandy and choices for the future</title>
		<link>./../../2012/11/hurricane-sandy-and-choices-for-the-future.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/11/hurricane-sandy-and-choices-for-the-future.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 09 Nov 2012 15:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[climate change]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[David Zetland]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[early warning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[water]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/11/hurricane-sandy-and-choices-for-the-future.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by David Zetland   David Zetland is a senior water economist at Wageningen University in the Netherlands and maintains a blog on water issues at Aguanomics Hurricane Sandy and choices for the future I live in the Netherlands, where living below sea level for many years has driven the Dutch to take flooding and storm surges [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by David Zetland   David Zetland is a senior water economist at Wageningen University in the Netherlands and maintains a blog on water issues at <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/11/hurricane-sandy-and-choices-for-future.html">Aguanomics</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/11/hurricane-sandy-and-choices-for-future.html">Hurricane Sandy and choices for the future</a></p>
<p>I live in the Netherlands, where living below sea level for many years has driven the Dutch to take flooding and storm surges very seriously.*<br />    <br />It&#8217;s therefore interesting to compare the damage from the storm to the <a href="http://www.reuters.com/article/2012/11/03/us-storm-sandy-infrastructure-idUSBRE8A203G20121103">early warnings</a> that Americans had from the Dutch and scientists. Were the Americans right to have ignored those warnings? After all&#8230; &#8220;<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/11/03/opinion/our-latest-high-water-mark.html">Hurricane Sandy was a fluke, right?</a> A storm surged from 90-mile-per-hour winds of a hurricane colliding with a northeaster, perfectly timed with a maximum full-moon high tide. The statistical likelihood of this is once in every 500 to 1,000 years.&#8221;<br />    <br />Huh. I guess the 2010 book on my table [pp 51-52 of Book II <a href="http://www.rotterdamclimateinitiative.nl/nl/delta_cities_website/documents">here</a>] is about 497 years early:<br />
<blockquote>Storm surges along the eastern seaboard of the US are associated with either late summer-autumn hurricanes or extra-tropical cyclones in the winter period, so called nor&#8217;easters&#8230; the height of the hurricane surge is amplified if it coincides with the astronomical high time and additionally occurs at the time of new and full moon&#8230; hurricanes have struck the coastal New York area six times in 1900-1990, resulting in severe coastal flooding, damage and destruction of beachfront property, severe beach erosion, downed power lines, power outages and disruption of normal transportation.</p></blockquote>
<p>When I visited with Piet Dircke in Rotterdam (the center of Dutch vulnerability to floods) two years ago, we discussed the problem of flooding, and he gave me his book (<a href="http://www.rotterdamclimateinitiative.nl/nl/delta_cities_website/documents">free to download</a>, by the way). He was also disappointed that New Yorkers were not interested in investing the time and money necessary for protecting their city from surges and floods. How was that possible when the CEO of New York was saying this?  </p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-SP6gT6XXB-E/UJuyoDAJIiI/AAAAAAAAEGg/dKYxGBgkNi8/s1600/Bloom.PNG"><img border="0" height="255" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-SP6gT6XXB-E/UJuyoDAJIiI/AAAAAAAAEGg/dKYxGBgkNi8/s640/Bloom.PNG" width="640"></a><br />Well, it&#8217;s possible because they were trying to avoid relocating people and neighborhoods or paying $20-30 billion for a real (i.e., Dutch-quality) system for protecting the area that would [p. 59]:** <br />
<blockquote>&#8230; stretch across from Sandy Hook, N.J. to Far Rockaway, Long Island&#8230; providing protection to the outer boroughs of Brooklyn and Queens, additional northern NJ communities, Jamaica Bay and JFK Airport.</p></blockquote>
<p>Now it would probably have been impossible for New Yorkers and others in the region to build such a system in time for the (unexpected) arrival of Sandy, but was there any plan in the works? Not that I know of. That&#8217;s unfortunate, as the storm caused <a href="http://www.reuters.com/article/2012/11/03/us-storm-sandy-infrastructure-idUSBRE8A203G20121103">$20 billion in damages</a> to New York alone.***  <br />So what will happen next? The Dutch would engage in a ruthless triage &#8212; moving people away from vulnerable but poor areas while building up 1-in-10,000 year defenses for places that are too valuable to abandon (e.g., Rotterdam).  </p>
<p>Will the People of Sandy engage in the same ruthless triage, or will they make the same mistake as we&#8217;ve seen with the rebuilding of the Ninth Ward in New Orleans? That political decision to rebuild is a costly and populist gesture that is likely to end when the returnees are flooded again in the future.  </p>
<p>Although that mistake is possible, I am hoping the Bloomberg and others take the time to read this book (and all the other warnings and studies) and make the <a href="http://www.env-econ.net/2012/11/oh-sandy-the-aurora-is-risin-behind-us-1.html">right decision</a> to rebuild in safer places while leaving those who want to stay in unsafe places to pay for their own foolishness.   </p>
<p>Bottom Line: Climate change means that the environment is not going to be reliable and business as usual is going to get more costly. We need to learn a few things from the Dutch: (1) Be realistic; (2) Plan seriously; and (3) Spend seriously. Anything less is not just going to be tragic, but criminally incompetent.  <br />
<hr>* You may want to read my posts on the <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/08/dutch-deltaworks.html">Delta Works</a> and <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2011/01/learning-from-dutch.html">Delta Commission</a>, which addressed these dangers in the past and for the future, respectively. Read <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/05/dutch-water-expertise-does-not-apply.html">this post</a> on why it&#8217;s difficult for the Dutch to export their water &#8220;expertise&#8221; &#8212; mostly because the rest of the world faces water shortage rather than water superabundance.  <br />** They were paying more attention to redeveloping New York, since valuable real estate generates property taxes and flood barriers cost money. I just saw <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Urbanized">Urbanized (2011)</a>, which has an extensive narrative on The High Line and other cool projects but nothing about urban defenses.  <br />*** As well as causing vast grief and inconvenience. People unable to use the flooded subways or tunnels <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/video/2012/11/02/nyregion/100000001880180/after-sandy-two-wheeled-commute.html">took to bikes</a> to avoid horrible traffic jams (as well as the need to buy gasoline, which was <a href="http://www.buzzfeed.com/annanorth/13-people-trying-to-trade-sex-for-gas-on-craigslis">available for sex</a>). It&#8217;s a gratuitous tragedy that so many politicians have embraced &#8220;anti-gouging laws&#8221; that prevent prices from rising to balance supply and demand. Some gas stations stayed closed to avoid angry customers (or offer fuel for sex!); others stayed open but had cars waiting for hours to fill up. Read more on how these laws are counter-productive <a href="http://www.env-econ.net/2012/11/this-just-in-new-yorks-attorney-general-prefers-shortages-to-price-rationing.html">here</a> and <a href="http://knowledgeproblem.com/tag/price-gouging/">here</a>.  <br /><i>H/Ts to MR, MS and MV</i>  <br /><a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/11/hurricane-sandy-and-choices-for-future.html" title="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/11/hurricane-sandy-and-choices-for-future.html">http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/11/hurricane-sandy-and-choices-for-future.html</a><br />Labels:<a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/search/label/climate%20change">climate change</a>,<a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/search/label/floods">floods</a>,<a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/search/label/infrastructure">infrastructure</a>,<a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/search/label/institutions">institutions</a>,<a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/search/label/NL">NL</a>,<a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/search/label/oceans">oceans</a>,<a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/search/label/OPM">OPM</a>,<a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/search/label/politics">politics</a>,<a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/search/label/sustainability">sustainability</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/11/hurricane-sandy-and-choices-for-the-future.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Hurricane Sandy and climate change</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/hurricane-sandy-and-climate-change.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/hurricane-sandy-and-climate-change.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 31 Oct 2012 10:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Andrew Revkin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[climate change]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jan Galkowski]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/hurricane-sandy-and-climate-change.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Reader Jan Galkowski sends this caution about promoting Hurricane Sandy as the result of climate change.  The following is taken from an e-mail to me yesterday: There&#8217;s a lot being written about Hurricane Sandy in connection with climate change. It is likely that this hurricane was exacerbated by human induced climate change, notably the excessively [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>Reader Jan Galkowski sends this caution about promoting Hurricane Sandy as the result of climate change.  The following is taken from an e-mail to me yesterday:</div>
<p>
<blockquote>There&#8217;s a lot being written about Hurricane Sandy in connection with climate change. It is likely that this hurricane was exacerbated by human induced climate change, notably the excessively warm waters off New England, but it is not scientifically correct to say the hurricane or its merging to become a nor&#8217;easter were caused by climate change. It is possible that the blocking high over Greenland contributed to that, however the attribution is dilute, if present.</p>
<p><a href="http://dotearth.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/10/28/the-frankenstorm-in-climate-context/" target="_blank">Andy Revkin in the <em>New York Times</em></a> has a nice summary of the current science.</p>
<p>Although we know all is affected by greater energy on the planet, the fraction of Sandy&#8217;s fury attributable is perhaps 10%. Thus, comments like the following from <a href="http://350.org/en/about/blogs/hurricane-sandy">350.org</a> are simply incorrect, and are misleading:</p>
<blockquote><p>It&#8217;s as out of kilter as the melting Arctic or the acidifying ocean. And if there were any poetic justice, it would be named Hurricane Chevron or Hurricane Exxon, not Hurricane Sandy.</p></blockquote>
<p>The ends do not justify the means.<br />If there&#8217;s something to be learned by this experience, it is that climate change is expanding and enlarging the oceans by thermal effects, and eventually by ice mass melting, both through displacement and gravitational effects. Eventually, common nor&#8217;easters will suffice to breach Battery Park walls and drown barrier islands. And there may be surprises in store as well. <br /><a name="more"></a><br />As some of you have seen, I myself have done a calculation showing that the frequency of out of season hurricanes has increased since the late 19th century. That increase is statistically significant, although it may not be enough for everyone to notice.</p>
<p>Despite the great need to move policy towards a global economy that grows without more material consumption, which I very much agree with, distorting the facts destroys trust and disturbs the healthy ecosystem of scientific funding and research. It is also unethical.</p>
<p>It may be inconvenient that people are not moved by reason as much as by fear. But that is their choice, even if they suffer the consequences. It&#8217;s the responsibility of science to educate and be principled, even if we know that delay implies additional cost, additional deaths. It will also be the responsibility of science to tell policymakers and people that certain aspects of climate change <em>are no longer reversible</em> in any time frame that makes political or economic sense, and the longer we wait, the more of that kind of thing there will be.<br />I ask your collective understanding of this matter, and draw your attention to what will be the increasing problem of <em>mitigating</em> rather than preventing climate-related risks, as they are described in the <a href="http://ipcc-wg2.gov/SREX/images/uploads/SREX-SPMbrochure_FINAL.pdf" taget="_blank">SREX report from the IPCC</a>. (Revkin alludes to this at his page.) </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Thanks. Hope everyone&#8217;s healthy and safe.<br />&#8211; Jan</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/hurricane-sandy-and-climate-change.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Ice melting takes some thought…</title>
		<link>./../../2012/09/ice-melting-takes-some-thought.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/09/ice-melting-takes-some-thought.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 08 Sep 2012 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Arctic sea ice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[climate change]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/09/ice-melting-takes-some-thought.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[From reader rjs comes this list of links in paragraph form on records being passed over time on Arctic sea ice and Greenland glaciers melting.  New radar allows for a variety of measurements, one being a way to measure ice thickness in the Arctic.  Edited lightly for readability: It has been an exciting week for [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>From reader rjs comes this list of links in paragraph form on records being passed over time on Arctic sea ice and Greenland glaciers melting.  New radar allows for a variety of measurements, one being a way to measure ice thickness in the Arctic.  Edited lightly for readability:</p>
<p>It has been an exciting week for those among us who have dedicated their lives to watching ice melt, since <a href="http://www.google.com/url?sa=t&#038;rct=j&#038;q=&#038;esrc=s&#038;frm=1&#038;source=web&#038;cd=4&#038;cad=rja&#038;ved=0CDgQFjAD&#038;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.realscience.us%2F2012%2F08%2F29%2Farctic-sea-ice-reaches-record-low-with-weeks-to-go-in-melting-season%2F&#038;ei=GctDUNClNMPOqgHhg4CYBg&#038;usg=AFQjCNEHy9iHo2AwE57B9p0qgzfbp4RtLw">every day this past week has set a new record low for the amount of arctic ice remaining</a>&#8230;arguably, the old 2007 record may have fallen on <a href="http://climatechangepsychology.blogspot.com/2012/08/arctic-sea-ice-melt-record-smashed.html">August 24th, when the japanese aerospace agency&#8217;s arctic sea ice monitor recorded their new low sea-ice extent of 4,189,375 square kilometers,</a><u> </u>but <a href="http://thinkprogress.org.feedsportal.com/c/34726/f/638933/s/22ca7148/l/0Lthinkprogress0Borg0Cclimate0C20A120C0A80C270C7517810Carctic0Esea0Eice0Ereaches0Elowest0Eextent0Eever0Emeasured0Ereports0Enational0Esnow0Eand0Eice0Edata0Ecenter0C/story01.htm">August 26th marks the date the record was broken according to our National Snow and Ice Data Center</a>, when the <a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=arctic+sea+ice+extent+fell+to+1.58+million+square+miles,+or+4.10+million+square+kilometers&#038;hl=en&#038;rls=com.microsoft:en-us:IE-Address&#038;rlz=1I7ADFA_enUS372&#038;prmd=imvnsu&#038;source=univ&#038;tbm=nws&#038;tbo=u&#038;sa=X&#038;ei=c8tDUJWHLMfMqgGI9YCYCA&#038;ved=0CCEQqAI">arctic sea ice extent fell to 1.58 million square miles, or 4.10 million square kilometers</a>, which was 70,000 square kilometers below the previous record low daily sea ice extent set on September 18 of 2007..</p>
<p>To put those numbers in perspective, t<a href="http://thinkprogress.org.feedsportal.com/c/34726/f/638933/s/22ca7148/l/0Lthinkprogress0Borg0Cclimate0C20A120C0A80C270C7517810Carctic0Esea0Eice0Ereaches0Elowest0Eextent0Eever0Emeasured0Ereports0Enational0Esnow0Eand0Eice0Edata0Ecenter0C/story01.htm">hat is about a million more square miles of the arctic now open than was during the 1979-2000 average,</a> or about an area as large as texas and alaska combined&#8230;this is remarkable in that <a href="http://www.google.com/url?sa=t&#038;rct=j&#038;q=&#038;esrc=s&#038;frm=1&#038;source=web&#038;cd=6&#038;cad=rja&#038;ved=0CD0QtwIwBQ&#038;url=http%3A%2F%2Fcleantechnica.com%2F2012%2F08%2F29%2Fmore-reasons-why-we-do-what-we-do-arctic-sea-ice-drops-off-a-cliff-worldwide-drought-overview%2F&#038;ei=EsxDUJ2NBoWRrAHT9YEw&#038;usg=AFQjCNHEW7a4jzxIRgs1OQzfo8hbbMKynQ">the record was broken so early in the arctic ice melt season</a>, and that <a href="http://www.google.com/url?sa=t&#038;rct=j&#038;q=&#038;esrc=s&#038;frm=1&#038;source=web&#038;cd=1&#038;cad=rja&#038;ved=0CCMQFjAA&#038;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.colorado.edu%2Fnews%2Freleases%2F2012%2F08%2F27%2Farctic-sea-ice-reaches-lowest-extent-ever-recorded-says-cu-boulder-research&#038;ei=VcxDUJu-GMn0qAGTrIHACQ&#038;usg=AFQjCNHficIao4V6AwArtkxMYXcneBTJTw">ice will continue to melt and set new low extents every day at least till mid september</a>, also remarkable in that <a href="http://climatechangepsychology.blogspot.com/2012/08/arctic-sea-ice-extent-accelerates.html">the melting is accelerating this late in the season</a>, ie, more ice has been melting each day than the day before, rather than slowing down as it usually would in late august, with<a href="http://climatechangepsychology.blogspot.com/2012/08/george-monbiot-heat-of-moment.html"> a daily rate of loss 50% higher than it was in 2007</a>.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>The year the old record was set; normally, at this time of year, we&#8217;re losing about 15,000 sq miles of ice a day; <a href="http://nsidc.org/arcticseaicenews/">this year the rate of ice loss continues at 29,000 a day, nearly twice the average</a>&#8230;of course, these newly <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.co.uk/rod-downie/arctic-sea-ice-breaks-rec_b_1838583.html?utm_hp_ref=uk">opened areas in the arctic sea will absorb even more heat than iced over areas</a> that would reflect the sun&#8217;s rays back into the atmosphere&#8230; <a href="http://nsidc.org/arcticseaicenews/2012/08/arctic-sea-ice-breaks-2007-record-extent/">the adjacent illustration from the NSIDC graphs the ice extent during the melt seasons since 1979</a>, the beginning of the satellite record, on the date the new record was set; this year to that date is in dark blue, the previous record year 2007 is a green dash, 1980 is orange, the average of all data is in light blue, with the 1979-2000 average as a solid black line, and the gray area indicating the two standard deviation range of the data.</p>
<p> <a href="http://nsidc.org/arcticseaicenews/">NSIDC also data shows that all 6 lowest ice extents in the satellite record have occurred over the past 6 years</a>. P<a href="http://earlywarn.blogspot.com/2012/08/arctic-sea-ice-volume.html">hysicist Stuart Staniford, observing that the annual   change in arctic sea ice was not linear, fitted a quadratic equation to the rate of loss, which shows the arctic would hit zero ice in 2017</a> and  his <a href="http://earlywarn.blogspot.com/2012/08/more-on-arctic-sea-ice-volume.html">further extrapolations show the Arctic ice free for six months out of the year by 2025</a>…</p>
<p><a href="http://climatechangepsychology.blogspot.com/2012/08/peter-wadhams-arctic-sea-ice-gone-in-3.html">Peter Wadhams, professor of ocean physics at Cambridge, believes arctic ice is on the brink of collapse and that it will be gone in 3 years</a>&#8230;.you may recall that <a href="http://marketwatch666.blogspot.com/2011/02/notes-on-week-ended-jan-29th.html">we discussed one of the effects of a warmer arctic sea on methane release this past winter</a>; that the arctic contains copious amounts of methane-hydrates frozen at high pressure on the seabed, and that as the ocean warmed, <a href="http://www.independent.co.uk/news/science/vast-methane-plumes-seen-in-arctic-ocean-as-sea-ice-retreats-6276278.html">russian scientists observed massive plumes of methane bubbling to the surface of the arctic ocean</a>, some as large as 1000 meters in diameter&#8230;<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atmospheric_methane">methane is known to be a potent greenhouse gas</a>, considered 25 times as potent a heat-trapping gas as CO2 over a 100 year time horizon, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Global_warming_potential">but 72 times as potent over 20 years</a>, so the release of methane enhances the warming feedback, accelerating the process&#8230;.to see this visually, <a href="http://marketwatch666.blogspot.com/2012/01/notes-on-dec-unemployment-lpss-mortgage.html">we have 3 arctic projections showing methane releases from 2002, 2010 and 2011 at the end of our January 8th blog post</a>; the change over just a few years is really quite stunning&#8230; </p>
<p>It&#8217;s not just the ice in the arctic ocean that&#8217;s been melting&#8230;last week, <a href="http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2012/08/120815121318.htm">analysis of satellite photographs confirmed that greenland had already also exceeded it&#8217;s one season melt record on August 8th</a>, almost a full month before the normal end of the melt season on that large island&#8230;the record ice loss had been anticipated after <a href="http://phys.org/news262352789.html#nRlv">an unprecedented 4 day thaw over 97% of the ice sheet in mid-july</a>; also, a nearly obscure <a href="http://nsidc.org/arcticseaicenews/2012/07/">last item in the NSIDC&#8217;s first July Arctic Sea Ice News &#038; Analysis bulletin</a> noted that the<a href="http://climatechangepsychology.blogspot.com/2012/08/northern-hemisphere-land-snow-cover.html"> snow cover in the northern hemisphere in June had melted to such an extent that it beat the 45 year record low a month early</a>, breaking the 2010 record by 1 million square kilometers&#8230;<a href="http://thewe.cc/weplanet/news/glaciers_melting.htm">much of this snowpack loss is from higher elevations, where downstream cities depend on a continuous release of ice-melt for their water supply</a>&#8230;</p>
<p>Arguably, the loss of seasonal of snow &#038; ice on land masses is a more serious problem than over the arctic sea, because it adds to sea level rise, and most of the world&#8217;s major port cities are built at sea level; you might recall the illustration we used <a href="http://marketwatch666.blogspot.com/2011/02/notes-on-week-ended-jan-29th.html">when discussing greenland&#8217;s ice-loss in 2010:</a> if all the snow pack loss from greenland that year were to be dumped at once on low lying new jersey, <a href="http://www.climatecentral.org/gallery/maps/envisioning_ice_loss/#/NJ">it would cover new jersey with 257 feet of snow</a> &#8230; <a href="http://energybulletin.net/stories/2012-01-03/hansen-still-argues-5m-21st-c-sea-level-rise-possible">James Hansen, the head of NASA&#8217;s goddard institute, believes that a 5 meter sea level rise is possible this century</a> as the Greenland antarctic ice sheets rapidly melt&#8230;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/09/ice-melting-takes-some-thought.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sea ice in the Arctic and new data from Cryo-Sat-2</title>
		<link>./../../2012/08/sea-ice-in-the-arctic-and-new-data-from-cryo-sat-2.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/08/sea-ice-in-the-arctic-and-new-data-from-cryo-sat-2.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Aug 2012 21:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Arctic sea ice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[climate change]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cryo-Sat-2]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/08/sea-ice-in-the-arctic-and-new-data-from-cryo-sat-2.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Hi folks&#8230;coming back on line from experiences in hospital services (not mine) and found this Guardian article on something we haven&#8217;t followed closely in posts.   From the Guardian comes this note on the preliminary data of the new Cryo-Sat-2 probe on Arctic ice volumes: Sea ice in the Arctic is disappearing at a far [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>Hi folks&#8230;coming back on line from experiences in hospital services (not mine) and found this Guardian article on something we haven&#8217;t followed closely in posts.  </div>
<div></div>
<div>From the Guardian comes this note on the preliminary data of the new Cryo-Sat-2 probe on Arctic ice volumes:</div>
<p>
<blockquote><a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/environment/sea-ice">Sea ice</a> in the <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/arctic">Arctic</a> is disappearing at a far greater rate than previously expected, according to data from the first purpose-built satellite launched to study the thickness of the Earth&#8217;s polar caps.<br />Preliminary results from the <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/science/european-space-agency">European Space Agency</a>&#8216;s CryoSat-2 probe indicate that 900 cubic kilometres of <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/environment/summer">summer</a> sea ice has disappeared from the Arctic ocean over the past year.<br />…<br /><a href="http://www.ucl.ac.uk/news/news-articles/1004/10040804">CryoSat-2 is the world&#8217;s first satellite to be built specifically to study sea-ice thickness</a> and was launched on a Dniepr rocket from Baikonur cosmodrome, Kazakhstan, on 8 April, 2010. Previous Earth monitoring satellites had mapped the extent of sea-ice coverage in the Arctic. However, the thickness of that ice proved more difficult to measure.<a name="more"></a><br />The US probe ICESat made some important measurements of ice thickness but operated intermittently in only a few regions before it stopped working completely in 2009. CryoSat was designed specifically to tackle the issue of ice thickness, both in the Arctic and the Antarctic. It was fitted with radar that can see through clouds. (ICESat&#8217;s lasers could not penetrate clouds.) CryoSat&#8217;s orbit was also designed to give better coverage of the Arctic sea.<br />…<br />&#8220;Before CryoSat, we could see summer ice coverage was dropping markedly in the Arctic,&#8221; said Rapley. &#8220;But we only had glimpses of what was happening to ice thickness. Obviously if it was dropping as well, the loss of summer ice was even more significant. We needed to know what was happening – and now CryoSat has given us the answer. It has shown that the Arctic sea cap is not only shrinking in area but is also thinning dramatically.&#8221;<br /><a href="http://image.guardian.co.uk/sys-images/Observer/Pix/pictures/2012/08/11/gu_ice_extension-01.jpg">Graphic: shrinking ice caps</a></p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/08/sea-ice-in-the-arctic-and-new-data-from-cryo-sat-2.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Extraordinarily warm tempratures</title>
		<link>./../../2012/04/extraordinarily-warm-tempratures.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/04/extraordinarily-warm-tempratures.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 05 Apr 2012 13:23:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[climate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[climate change]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/04/extraordinarily-warm-tempratures.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This post is not very economic oriented except indirectly, but I felt a need to mark the extraordinary temperatures of high and some low 100 year records.  Lifted and edited for readability in blog format from an e-mail newsletter sent by reader rjs come examples and links for both record setting high temperatures and consecutive days of high temperatures this March. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This post is not very economic oriented except indirectly, but I felt a need to mark the extraordinary temperatures of high and some low 100 year records.  Lifted and edited for readability in blog format from an e-mail newsletter sent by reader <strong>rjs</strong> come examples and links for both record setting high temperatures and consecutive days of high temperatures this March.</p>
<p>I watched in March my daylilies at 6&#8243; plus preceding peones, real azaleas flowering the same time as mongolian azaleas,  and trees <em>flowering</em> a month early simultaneous to blue squill.     <strong>rjs</strong> provides  links.  Dr. Masters website would not allow links to specific posts for me, so go to March archives for material.</p>
<div><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-wybqPZRCl-g/T32bSVVX22I/AAAAAAAAA1Q/uSXBA-vg4-A/s1600/namericalsta_tmo_2012068.jpg" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="214" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-wybqPZRCl-g/T32bSVVX22I/AAAAAAAAA1Q/uSXBA-vg4-A/s320/namericalsta_tmo_2012068.jpg" width="320"></a></div>
<p>  </p>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />
<blockquote>&#8230;Meteorologist <a href="http://www.wunderground.com/blog/JeffMasters/show.html">Dr Jeff Masters of the popular wunderblog</a>, writing from Michigan, probably expressed it best; &#8220;this March started with 12 days of April weather, followed by 10 days of June and July weather, with 9 days of May weather predicted to round out the month&#8221;. </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>   One example is <a href="http://www.google.com/url?sa=t&#038;rct=j&#038;q=&#038;esrc=s&#038;frm=1&#038;source=web&#038;cd=2&#038;ved=0CCwQFjAB&#038;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.emptywheel.net%2F2012%2F03%2F20%2Fwhy-does-fat-al-gore-hate-flower-festivals%2F&#038;ei=UmxuT6OnPIfwggeb1Y1s&#038;usg=AFQjCNFhAYfAX7fzHNF2lQ_yROv6iFk4Bw">Holland, Michigan was planning a tulip festival for May, but saw their blooms last week</a>. Of course, it wasnt just Michigan as <a href="http://www.wunderground.com/blog/weatherhistorian/show.html">temperatures in the 80s were reached in every border state from North Dakota to Maine</a>, as well as <a href="http://climatechangepsychology.blogspot.com/2012/03/jeff-masters-summer-in-march-2012-heat.html">from Manitoba to Nova Scotia in Canada</a>.  <a href="http://climatechangepsychology.blogspot.com/2012/03/march-16-2012-1587-record-breaking-high.html">2023 record-breaking high temperatures were set in the US, while a low was breached only 58 times</a>&#8230; </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>there are a handful of links immediately below which will lead you to all the details, but the highlights include 4 locations (one ea in NH, MI &#038; 2 in MN) where the overnight low in a location eclipsed the previous daytime record high (in locations with 100 years of records), and several locations where the previous record high temperature for the date was exceeded by more than 30°F.  Several locations in the US and Canada also experienced record high temperatures for April,  <a href="http://www.google.com/url?sa=t&#038;rct=j&#038;q=&#038;esrc=s&#038;frm=1&#038;source=web&#038;cd=1&#038;ved=0CCUQFjAA&#038;url=http%3A%2F%2Fi.wund.com%2Fauto%2Fiphone%2Fblog%2FJeffMasters%2Fshow.html&#038;ei=UmxuT6OnPIfwggeb1Y1s&#038;usg=AFQjCNH6Qo9Lgssj0VnrFISSDm-ksQDN4g">ten record high days in a row at International Falls, MN, the most consecutive records ever set anywhere</a>, (and many cities where a new record was set 9 days in a row, including chicago, when observing 7 consecutive record temps at a location is a once in a meteorological blue moon experience… )  </p>
<p>While most everyone experiencing this heat wave probably perferred it to the normal frigid and windy march in this part of the country, there are a few caveats; first, fruit crops are at least a month ahead of schedule over most of the area noted, and damaging frosts are still likely into May.    </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Secondly, a lot of the western areas that would normally have a snow cover are already starting to dry out, raising the potential for drought during the planting season,    </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Lastly, anecdotal reports from the region indicated that with the entire winter being mild, the ground did not freeze deeply, so the normal winter kill of damaging insects didnt occur; so we can expect a bad year for plant pests and ticks, &#038; the mosquitoes are already flying&#8230;</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/04/extraordinarily-warm-tempratures.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Corporate/shareholder value, energy market and global warming</title>
		<link>./../../2012/02/corporateshareholder-value-energy-market-and-global-warming.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/02/corporateshareholder-value-energy-market-and-global-warming.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Feb 2012 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[alternative energy investment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[climate change]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[competition]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economic fundamentals]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economic ideology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[energy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[free markets]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[global warming]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/02/corporateshareholder-value-energy-market-and-global-warming.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Updated: Renewable Germany bailing out Nuclear France   I just read the following in an article by a Mr. Bill McKibben and thought it to be an interesting perspective on why climate change/global warming is being so vigorously denied. If we spew 565 gigatons more carbon into the atmosphere, we’ll quite possibly go right past [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<div>Updated: Renewable Germany bailing out Nuclear France</div>
<p>  <br />I just read the following in an <a href="http://www.commondreams.org/view/2012/02/07-2">article by a Mr. Bill McKibben</a> and thought it to be an interesting perspective on why climate change/global warming is being so vigorously denied.   </div>
<blockquote><div>If we spew 565 gigatons more carbon into the atmosphere, we’ll quite possibly go right past that reddest of red lines. But the oil companies, private and state-owned, have current reserves on the books equivalent to 2,795 gigatons &#8212; five times more than we can ever safely burn. It has to stay in the ground.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Put another way, in ecological terms it would be extremely prudent to write off $20 trillion worth of those reserves. In economic terms, of course, it would be a disaster, first and foremost for shareholders and executives of companies like ExxonMobil (and people in places like Venezuela).</div>
<div></div>
<div><i>If you run an oil company, this sort of write-off is the disastrous future staring you in the face as soon as climate change is taken as seriously as it should be, and that’s far scarier than drought and flood. It’s why you’ll do anything &#8212; including fund an endless campaigns of lies &#8212; to avoid coming to terms with its reality.</i></div>
</blockquote>
<div>Never thought of the resistance to moving away from carbon fuels as an issue of having to write off company value in order to save the planet.  As shown with the housing bubble, writing off inflated value (inflated for what ever reason) is a rather difficult thing to do.  I mean, when you have so much down stream of that artificial value dependent on it (think currency based on oil), the engineering challenge is like playing Jenga only no one will be laughing if you fail and the tower falls.  Also, you have a timer running in this version of Jenga.</div>
<div></div>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<div>I believe Mr. McKibben refers to the issue as a bubble in that the current price of raw carbon fuel is based on the idea that fuel in general is becoming less available.  But fuel or energy is not less available. It is only one source of fuel that is becoming less in quantity.  The only means to keep this conflation of less carbon based energy means less energy fuel in total is to deny the application of science in the energy market place as it relates to a competitor product.   It is artificial price manipulation via psych-ops.</div>
<div></div>
<div>In other words, the only way to keep the carbon energy market alive is to not have a free energy market.  Part of assuring not having a free energy market is to deny the need for a free energy market, thus, deny climate change do to human extraction of carbon from the ground and it&#8217;s ever increasing rate of conversion to a gas of CO2.  It is artificial price manipulation via psych-ops.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Let&#8217;s take the write off issue one step further.  How does the value of a company such as Exxon/Mobil which is based on ever rising price do to ever declining product with ever increasing demand keep this model for valuing the company if the product becomes essentially limitless?  Now we&#8217;re up against our entire paradigm as to how we understand free market value and thus construct value.   </div>
<div></div>
<div>Carbon based energy is currently view as land.  No new land is being made and demand is rising thus ever increasing value.  The proper model for carbon fuel is that of a market where over time the product becomes obsolete.  This I think is the fault in thinking that has created the aberrant paradigm which lead to the bubble Mr. McKibben sees. Our entire energy market, viewed in this way is a complete illusion as seen from the owners side of the energy equation and a complete delusion as seen from the market economist side of the energy equation, though I would say the economist delusion has lead the owners to create their illusion.   </div>
<div></div>
<div>Just one more problem with running an economy based on the efficiency of money as oppose to the efficiency of people.</p>
<p>Update:</p>
<div>From <a href="http://real-economics.blogspot.com/2012/02/cold-snap-triggers-renewables-milestone.html">Real Economics</a> I read an article from Der Spiegel regarding France struggling with electricity shortages do to the cold spell.  Seem France, not normally experiencing cold winters uses electricity for heating homes.  This year they needed 7000 megawatts per hour more power.  100 gigawatts one evening was need, the equivalent of 80 nuclear power plants.  Germany was sending them a net 3000 megawatts/hour because:   </div>
<blockquote><div>It is interesting, said the federal environment minister, that Germany, especially in these days with a very high demand, can even export power—thanks to photovoltaic and wind energy. &#8220;We had in the last days a capacity of up to 10,000 megawatts of solar power, which corresponds to the output of ten nuclear power plants, and up to 11,000 megawatts of wind power,&#8221; said Röttgen.</div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div>Read another take here at <a href="http://k.lenz.name/LB/?p=6144">Lenz Blog</a>.</div>
<div></div>
<div>This is significant, because back in May of 2011 all the rage was how France was bailing out Germany after Germany announced its nuclear generation shut down.  As with Jonathan Larson at Real Economics, no one is saying this means we can scrap all other power generation tomorrow as <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/germany/0,1518,809439,00.html">this Spiegel article</a> notes the lack of solar generated power in Germany during a spell this winter and the need to import electricity. </div>
<div></div>
<div>The January article (not pro solar at all) notes:</div>
<blockquote><div>Until now, Merkel had consistently touted the environmental sector&#8217;s &#8220;opportunities for exports, development, technology and jobs.&#8221; But now even members of her own staff are calling it a massive money pit.</div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<p>How quickly fortunes can change. All the more reason to view carbon based energy in the energy market as a product that can be made obsolescent.  You know, a true free market with competition which purpose is to serves the efficiency of people and not money. Maybe then even Germany would not be so reactionary when their plan stumbles.  Heck, it took the Wright Brothers over a 1000 flights, just to learn how to fly!  Over 200 wings and airfoils!  They did not concern themselves with the issue of scaling it up for use by a planet of 6 billion people.</p></div>
<div> </div>
<div>Stick to your plan Germany because you have the correct intention. </div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/02/corporateshareholder-value-energy-market-and-global-warming.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
