<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Trade Balance &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>How do you get it right?…</title>
		<link>./../../2011/12/how-do-you-get-it-right.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/12/how-do-you-get-it-right.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2011 15:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Brazil]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[international trade]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Trade Balance]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/12/how-do-you-get-it-right.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Mike&#8217;s response to a short note from me I lifted and summarized from an advertisement/advice for investors on Brazil. Mike&#8217;s response below the fold: Today, Brazil moved aggressively to ensure that the widening global financial crisis will not reach its shores, taking several measures to stimulate consumption and investment in the world&#8217;s seventh largest economy. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Mike&#8217;s response to a short note from me I lifted and summarized from an advertisement/advice for investors on Brazil.  Mike&#8217;s response below the fold:<br />
<blockquote>
<p>Today, Brazil moved aggressively to ensure that the widening global financial crisis will not reach its shores, taking several measures to stimulate consumption and investment in the world&#8217;s seventh largest economy. Finance Minister Guido Mantega estimates that the moves will help Brazil&#8217;s GDP reach 5 percent next year.</p>
<p>The following will take effect immediately: <a name="more"></a> </p>
<p>&#8211; Producers of 8,500 manufactured products will receive tax credits of up to 3% for sales abroad</p>
<p>&#8211; The IOF transaction tax will be eliminated on foreign purchases of Brazilian stocks (previously 2%) and on corporate bonds with maturities of more than four years (previously 6%)</p>
<p>&#8211; Stock receipts of Brazilian companies traded abroad, such as American Depositary Receipts (ADRs), will be cancelled</p>
</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In fairness, Brazilian trade policy has often been poorly designed and managed even worse.  When I was growing up there were 500% tariffs on imported electronic goods, the idea being to protect the burgeoning Brazilian electronics and computer industries.  (Needless to say, it didn&#8217;t work.)  </p>
<p>On the flip side, protection of aircraft has led to Embraer making some pretty good planes. Similarly, as I noted before (this isn&#8217;t exactly trade policy, but it is economic policy) actions by the Brazilian government in the late 1970s, 1980s and 1990s are responsible for the fact that a Brazilian can walk into a car dealership today and buy a tri-flex vehicle that runs on any combination of gasoline, ethanol or natural gas.   I doubt Americans will be able to do the same thing before my 17 month old son is able to drive, and perhaps not for decades later.</p>
</p>
<p>The trick, I guess, is&#8230;  how do you get it right?  To come back to the US, how do you increase the ratio of Arpanets to Solyndras?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/12/how-do-you-get-it-right.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Global slowdown underway &#8211; it&#8217;s more than the Japanese supply chain disruptions</title>
		<link>./../../2011/08/global-slowdown-underway-its-more-than-the-japanese-supply-chain-disruptions.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/08/global-slowdown-underway-its-more-than-the-japanese-supply-chain-disruptions.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Aug 2011 18:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Eurozone]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Global Exports]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Global Growth]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Trade Balance]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/08/global-slowdown-underway-its-more-than-the-japanese-supply-chain-disruptions.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Rebecca Wilder Global slowdown underway &#8211; it&#8217;s more than the Japanese supply chain disruptions The global economic rebound is slowing markedly. With a tightening bias in emerging markets and a US recovery that continues to disappoint, external demand for any country that &#8216;needs it&#8217; &#8211; those countries mired in fiscal austerity without monetary autonomy, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by <strong>Rebecca Wilder</strong></p>
<p><strong>Global slowdown underway &#8211; it&#8217;s more than the Japanese supply chain disruptions </strong> </p>
<p>The global economic rebound is slowing markedly. With a tightening bias in emerging markets and a <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2011/07/q2-us-gdp-report-just-terrible.html">US recovery</a> that continues to disappoint, external demand for any country that &#8216;needs it&#8217; &#8211; those countries mired in fiscal austerity without monetary autonomy, i.e. euro area countries &#8211; is decelerating precipitously.</p>
<p>Exhibit 1: import demand for manufactured goods from 22.5% of the world (see chart at the end of this post) is slowing quickly, even contracting.</p>
<p><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-0nyBUYTeqWM/TkkNnat18zI/AAAAAAAAD4A/X5DPfyLkCy0/s1600/import_uschina_chart.jpg"><img src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-0nyBUYTeqWM/TkkNnat18zI/AAAAAAAAD4A/X5DPfyLkCy0/s400/import_uschina_chart.jpg" border="0" alt=""></a><br />
<br />The chart illustrates the growth of import demand for manufactured goods from the US (12.8% of world import demand in 2011) and China (9.7% of world import demand in 2011) on a 3-month over 3-month annualized and seasonally adjusted basis. Spanning April through June 2011 compared to January through March 2011, US imports for manufactured goods slowed to a 4.9% annualized clip, while Chinese manufacturing imports contracted at a 22.9% annualized pace. US import demand growth peaked at 36.9% in March 2011 (again, on the same 3M/3M SAAR basis), while Chinese import demand growth peaked a bit earlier at 108.2% in January 2011.<br />
<br /><a name="more"></a><br />
<br />One may argue that the sharp slowdown (US) and deceleration (China) of manufacturing imports is a product of supply chain disruptions stemming from the Japanese earthquake and ensuing tsunami. Let&#8217;s take a look.</p>
<p>Exhibit 2: Japanese distortions started to ease in April and May, leading global imports by roughly 1 month.</p>
<p><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-RQU3vSPM6EM/TkkNngO4OWI/AAAAAAAAD4I/21GXBKBejgk/s1600/japan_ip.jpg"><img src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-RQU3vSPM6EM/TkkNngO4OWI/AAAAAAAAD4I/21GXBKBejgk/s400/japan_ip.jpg" border="0" alt=""></a><br />
<br />The chart above illustrates the dynamics of the Japanese industrial sector before and after the earthquake. Industrial production started to recover in April 2011 and hit a month/month peak of +6.2% growth in May. The sector has all but recovered, and should have been reflected in the US and Chinese import data as positive momentum by June- it hasn&#8217;t. In June, the seasonally adjusted import demand decelerated to a 0.6% pace in the US, while that in China contracted 4.3%.</p>
<p>In contrast, we saw the easing of supply chain disruptions in the US domestic industrial production stats. In the US (not shown, but you can get the <a href="http://federalreserve.gov/releases/g17/current/">IP data here</a>), production of motor vehicles and parts fell 6.6% in April, which has improved sequentially through June (-2% M/M). This should be reflected in import demand (first chart), but the opposite&#8217;s occurred. In fact, import demand has worsened, while the supply chain disruptions improved. Better put: there&#8217;s weakness in global demand that is unrelated to Japanese supply chain disruptions.</p>
<p>Global growth is slowing &#8211; according to import demand of manufactured goods by the US and China, it&#8217;s slowing rather quickly. Where will this be felt? In Europe, of course. Germany derives near 50% of GDP from export demand, and imports roughly 45% of its goods and services from within the euro area (data <a href="http://epp.eurostat.ec.europa.eu/portal/page/portal/statistics/search_database#">here</a>). The PIIGS countries &#8211; Portugal, Ireland, Italy, Greece, and Spain &#8211; necessitate strong external demand from the core countries (Germany and France) and from outside the euro area in order to successfully deleverage amid sharp fiscal retrenchment. Unless the <a href="http://www.newsneconomics.com/2010/11/eurozone-rebalancing-depends-on-german.html">German consumer</a> really starts spending, the global industrial sector is unlikely to drive demand sufficiently enough in Europe.</p>
<p>Rebecca Wilder</p>
<p>Reference: dynamics of US and Chinese shares of world import demand</p>
<p><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-4Obw0nLPS5M/TkkNn5rL8dI/AAAAAAAAD4Q/ErrW49voG8U/s1600/share_imports.jpg"><img src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-4Obw0nLPS5M/TkkNn5rL8dI/AAAAAAAAD4Q/ErrW49voG8U/s400/share_imports.jpg" border="0" alt=""></a></p>
<p>&#8230;.</p>
<p>Crossposted at <a target="_blank" href="http://www.newsneconomics.com/2011/08/global-slowdown-underway-its-more-than.html">Newsneconomics</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/08/global-slowdown-underway-its-more-than-the-japanese-supply-chain-disruptions.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
