<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>tax tips &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>It&#8217;s Almost April so Tax Tips Are Flowering</title>
		<link>./../../2012/03/its-almost-april-so-tax-tips-are-flowering.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/03/its-almost-april-so-tax-tips-are-flowering.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 04 Mar 2012 14:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Linda Beale (Tax law)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax tips]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/03/its-almost-april-so-tax-tips-are-flowering.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Beale It&#8217;s Almost April so Tax Tips Are Flowering You can tell when it is getting close to the April filing deadline for individual calendar-year taxpayers. All of the major tax firms release their &#8220;handy tax tips&#8221; to entice new clients for this tax season.The American Institute of CPA&#8217;s handy tips (released Mar.1, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Linda Beale</p>
<p>It&#8217;s Almost April so Tax Tips Are Flowering</p>
<p>You can tell when it is getting close to the April filing deadline for individual calendar-year taxpayers. All of the major tax firms release their &#8220;handy tax tips&#8221; to entice new clients for this tax season.<br />The <a href="http://www.aicpa.org/Pages/Default.aspx">American Institute of CPA&#8217;s</a> handy tips (released Mar.1, 2012) include some helpful reminders that taxpayers should claim deductions they are entitled too but shouldn&#8217;t be piggy and claim deductions&#8211;like the home office deduction&#8211;that they aren&#8217;t entitled to.
<ol>
<li>Expenses. &#8220;Keep a daily diary.&#8221; </li>
<li>Deductions. Take advantage of all of the deductions to which you are legally entitled. &#8220;The most common deductions for small business owners include entertainment, travel, meals, capital assets, home office and health insurance. Travel miles, meals and entertainment deductions require that you maintain a diary with daily entries that tie into receipts and other records.&#8221; </li>
<li>Traps. &#8220;[C]laiming deductions that exceed your income for more than one year is a definite red flag. The home office deduction, which is allowable only under specific circumstances, may be another red flag.&#8221; </li>
<li>Retirement. &#8220;income each tax year to qualify for a tax-deductible retirement plan.&#8221; </li>
<p><a name="more"></a>
<li>Equipment. &#8220;For tax years beginning in 2011, a small business may deduct up to $500,000 in equipment purchases as long as the business spends $2 million or less for equipment for the year.&#8221; </li>
<li>Payroll. &#8220;One of the most common and costly tax-related problems for small business owners is that they use the payroll taxes withheld from employees to finance business operations. Not only does the IRS often go after a small business owner’s personal assets to collect the unpaid payroll taxes, but also it may attempt to assess significant penalties.&#8221; In other words, those taxes you&#8217;ve withheld aren&#8217;t your money to spend&#8211;you are collecting on behalf of the government and must turn them over.</li>
<li>Insurance. &#8220;If you have health insurance coverage for your employees, check to see if you are eligible for the small business health care tax credit. The <a href="http://www.irs.gov/newsroom/article/0,,id=223666,00.html">IRS website</a> has a page describing the credit, eligibility requirements and how to claim it. &#8221; </li>
<li>Veterans. There&#8217;s a credit for employers who hire veterans. The <a href="http://www.irs.gov/businesses/small/article/0,,id=253949,00.html">IRS website</a> has details. </li>
<li>Contributions. &#8220;Be sure to get a valuation for any non-cash items your business donates to charity&#8221; </li>
<li>Help. &#8220;If you are unsure about anything related to your tax obligations under the law, you should seek professional help &#8220;</li>
</ol>
<p>crossposted with <a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2012/03/its-almost-april-so-tax-tips-are-flowing.html" target="_blank">ataxingmatter</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/03/its-almost-april-so-tax-tips-are-flowering.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
