<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>TIC release &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>According to the Setser Test, it&#8217;s unlikely that China reduced its Treasury holdings in November</title>
		<link>./../../2011/01/according-to-the-setser-test-its-unlikely-that-china-reduced-its-treasury-holdings-in-november.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/01/according-to-the-setser-test-its-unlikely-that-china-reduced-its-treasury-holdings-in-november.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Jan 2011 20:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[China]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rebecca Wilder]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[TIC release]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/01/according-to-the-setser-test-its-unlikely-that-china-reduced-its-treasury-holdings-in-november.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[According to the Treasury International Capital System (TIC) release, foreigners were net buyers of US securities in November, +$39 billion over the month. Of the $61.7 billion in long-term Treasuries net purchased (notes and bonds), private investors claimed $50.6, while official investors (central banks, sovereign wealth funds, etc.) accrued a smaller $11.1 billion. Over the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_Et4TQ-a0gGU/TTY0hkgsvaI/AAAAAAAADcA/66WykKjfwt0/s1600/CA_TIC_chart.jpg"><img alt="" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_Et4TQ-a0gGU/TTY0hkgsvaI/AAAAAAAADcA/66WykKjfwt0/s320/CA_TIC_chart.jpg" border="0"></a>According to the <a href="http://www.treasury.gov/resource-center/data-chart-center/tic/Pages/index.aspx">Treasury International Capital System</a> (TIC) release, foreigners were net buyers of US securities in November, +$39 billion over the month. Of the $61.7 billion in long-term Treasuries net purchased (notes and bonds), private investors claimed $50.6, while official investors (central banks, sovereign wealth funds, etc.) accrued a smaller $11.1 billion. Over the last twelve months, foreign investors amassed $571 billion of the high-quality US securities: Treasury notes and bonds, agencies, and stocks, which includes the -$12 billion net sale of corporate bonds. Overall, it was a reasonably positive report, indicating that long-term asset sales are roughly in line with the current account deficit (chart to the upper left).</p>
<p>But the pundits follow <a href="http://www.treasury.gov/resource-center/data-chart-center/tic/Documents/mfh.txt">the table on</a> major foreign holders of US Treasuries. <a href="http://www.zerohedge.com/article/november-tic-data-update-china-treasury-holdings-decline-112-billion">They note</a> that the number 1 holder, China, reduced its holdings of Treasuries in November from just over $900 billion to just under. For some reason, investors and critics of the deficit alike are worried that when China is no longer named the US&#8217; biggest stockpiler of Treasury securities, Treasury rates will skyrocket. Oh, the bond vigilantes.</p>
<p>And this is when I really miss Brad Setser&#8217;s commentary (he is now at the National Economic Council). He noted time and time again, that the monthly TIC data tend to under-report the Chinese holdings, especially when they are shifting their portfolio holdings of US Treasuries up the curve. Well, that&#8217;s what the Chinese did in November: holdings of US Tbills dropped $21 billion, while longer-term note holdings increased a net $9.9 billion. (more after the jump)<br /><a name="more"></a></p>
<p><a href="http://blogs.cfr.org/setser/2009/06/19/i-am-pretty-sure-china-didnt-sell-treasuries-in-april-or-may-for-that-matter/">According to Brad Setser</a>, only in the annual <a href="http://www.treasury.gov/resource-center/data-chart-center/tic/Pages/fpis.aspx">survey of US portfolio holdings</a> are China&#8217;s measured holdings of US Treasuries accurate:<br />
<blockquote>This is actually a well established pattern. The past five surveys of foreign portfolio investment in the US have all revised China’s long-term Treasury holdings up (in some cases quite significantly) even as they revised the UK’s holdings down. The following graph shows the gap between Chinese long-term Treasury purchases in the TIC data and China’s actual purchases of long-term Treasuries– as revealed in the survey.</p></blockquote>
<p>Brad Setser&#8217;s quote was from 2009, but the story hasn&#8217;t changed since. In the 2010 report for 2009 foreign holdings, the level of Chinese Treasury holdings was revised up from the TIC-implied level by near $140 billion, while that of the UK was revised down (by over 100 billion, I might add). Clockwork.</p>
<p>So let&#8217;s apply Brad&#8217;s test, <strong>I&#8217;ll call it the Setser Test</strong>, to see if China actually reduced US Treasury holdings in November, as the November TIC release suggests. (I highlighted Brad&#8217;s test in bold italics, RW is me). <a href="http://blogs.cfr.org/setser/2009/06/19/i-am-pretty-sure-china-didnt-sell-treasuries-in-april-or-may-for-that-matter/">The test is listed in the middle of this post.<br /></a><br /><strong>Brad: First, the TIC data should show a fall in China’s holdings, i.e. net sales of Treasuries.</strong></p>
<p>RW: Yes.</p>
<p><strong>Second, the TIC data should also show limited purchases of Treasuries through the UK.</p>
<p></strong><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_Et4TQ-a0gGU/TTc4p5bSryI/AAAAAAAADcQ/ylPhU_-gc6I/s1600/treasury_country.JPG"><strong><img alt="" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_Et4TQ-a0gGU/TTc4p5bSryI/AAAAAAAADcQ/ylPhU_-gc6I/s320/treasury_country.JPG" border="0"></strong></a>RW: No. The UK bought near $25 billion in Treasury notes and bonds, which more than offset the drop in Chinese Treasury buying. In fact, if the TIC data is accurate, the UK is amassing a rather large stockpile of US Treasuries. This would be in sharp contrast with the average $48 billion balance of Treasury holdings since 2006 (<a href="http://www.treasury.gov/resource-center/data-chart-center/tic/Pages/ticsec.aspx">Table 4 or 5 depending on the year</a>)!</p>
<p><strong>Third, the Fed’s custodial holdings should not be rising at a strong clip — as, given China’s size, it is hard to see how China doesn’t make up a large fraction of all custodial holdings.</p>
<p></strong>RW: <a href="http://federalreserve.gov/releases/h41/Current/">The Fed&#8217;s custodial holdings</a> increased by a sizable $39 billion. More likely than not, this was due in part to Chinese activity.</p>
<p>So according to the Setser Test, it&#8217;s very unlikely that China reduced its Treasury holdings in November. In fact they probably increased their Treasury holdings, given the magnitude of the Fed&#8217;s custodial balance.</p>
<p>Rebecca Wilder</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/01/according-to-the-setser-test-its-unlikely-that-china-reduced-its-treasury-holdings-in-november.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>TIC tock; TIC tock; TIC tock</title>
		<link>./../../2010/02/tic-tock-tic-tock-tic-tock.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/02/tic-tock-tic-tock-tic-tock.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2010 00:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[China]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[TIC release]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/02/tic-tock-tic-tock-tic-tock.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[No, the US Treasury&#8217;s time is not running out. Where&#8217;s Brad Setser when you need him &#8211; and the media definitely needed him in reference to the December TIC report. Okay, okay, we know: China dropped its share of Treasury holdings in December by $US 34.2 bn. China now holds just 20.9% of the total [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>No, the US Treasury&#8217;s time is not running out. Where&#8217;s <a href="http://blogs.cfr.org/setser/">Brad Setser </a>when you need him &#8211; and the media definitely needed him in reference to the <a href="http://www.ustreas.gov/press/releases/tg548.htm">December TIC report</a>.</p>
<p>Okay, okay, we know: China dropped its share of Treasury holdings in December by $US 34.2 bn. China now holds just 20.9% of the total foreign-owned stock of Treasuries, second only to Japan (21.3%).</p>
<p>But China’s share is closer to its average, while Japan’s share is way off – there may be a reversion here, i.e., Japan will grow its stock of Treasuries relative to China (Please see <a href="http://www.newsneconomics.com/2010/02/foreign-holdings-of-foreign-holdings-of.html">my post yesterday</a>). Except for the period of September 2008 through November 2009, Japan held a much larger share of Treasuries than did China for every month since 2000.</p>
<p>Is <a href="http://www.zerohedge.com/article/china-dumping-begins-reserve-managers-notified-any-non-usg-guaranteed-securities-must-be-div">there a sinister plot developing</a>? Is China selling off S-T T bills to retaliate against the Obama administration’s push on the renminbi? Or is China simply reallocating its portfolio toward risk?</p>
<p>Perhaps there is a (partial) retaliation scheme underway, as suggested by the 3-month accumulation of short-term US assets (mostly T bills agencies with a maturity of less than 1 year).</p>
<p><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_Et4TQ-a0gGU/S3x-nqY6v2I/AAAAAAAAC3E/z4Xndnjsglc/s1600-h/china_st.PNG"><img src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_Et4TQ-a0gGU/S3x-nqY6v2I/AAAAAAAAC3E/z4Xndnjsglc/s320/china_st.PNG" alt="" border="0"></a>But isn’t it just slightly more plausible that the Chinese are – official + private – selling off zero-yielding (practically) Treasuries in exchange for longer-duration, higher-yielding, and riskier assets.</p>
<p>The first bit of the story is this: one should take care in not reading too much into the TIC report. It’s just one month’s worth of data; but more importantly, the data miss a critical component of the capital account, foreign direct investment.<a name="more"></a></p>
<p><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_Et4TQ-a0gGU/S3x-8xO7DZI/AAAAAAAAC3M/RaETJKJSnpU/s1600-h/china_lt.PNG"><img src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_Et4TQ-a0gGU/S3x-8xO7DZI/AAAAAAAAC3M/RaETJKJSnpU/s320/china_lt.PNG" alt="" border="0"></a>The chart above illustrates China&#8217;s one-year rolling monthly flows of long-term, high quality asset purchases &#8211; Treasuries bonds/notes, agencies, stocks, and corporate bonds. The Chinese are accumulating stocks, primarily through private investors, but through official channels as well (see <a href="http://www.ustreas.gov/press/releases/tg548.htm">press release</a>, lines 8 and 13). This suggests an increasing interest in equity, which could signal growing foreign direct investment flows (not shown in TIC).</p>
<p>Furthermore, the entire year’s shift in assets, long-term Treasury purchases, +$US 98.8 bn fully offsets the drop in short-term Treasuries, -$US 98.8. This suggests diversification.</p>
<p>Finally, everybody’s doing it, not just China &#8211; diversifying away from T bills, that is!</p>
<p><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_Et4TQ-a0gGU/S3x_1Z2Rm8I/AAAAAAAAC3U/tVtngEuC2Qk/s1600-h/total_st.PNG"><img src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_Et4TQ-a0gGU/S3x_1Z2Rm8I/AAAAAAAAC3U/tVtngEuC2Qk/s320/total_st.PNG" alt="" border="0"></a>The chart above illustrates the 3-month rolling sum of all foreign net flows of ST US assets (mostly T bills). If you invest $US 1 million dollars today in a bill expiring in August 2010, you make about 900 bucks. Man, doesn’t that sound like a wonderful investment?</p>
<p>So the next question is: why do the Chinese care about return on their F/X holdings? Because they have a peg! <a href="http://www.brookings.edu/articles/2009/0721_chinas_reserve_prasad.aspx">Here is a great article</a> for all of you who wanted to know about the costs of maintaining a peg. Accumulating FX reserves is a costly business, and T bills are unlikely to finance the type of sterilization that is needed by the PBoC.</p>
<p>Rebecca Wilder</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/02/tic-tock-tic-tock-tic-tock.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
