<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>naked Capitalism &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Jamie Galbraith on inequality and macroeconomics</title>
		<link>./../../2012/05/jamie-galbraith-on-inequality-and-macroeconomics.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/05/jamie-galbraith-on-inequality-and-macroeconomics.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 16 May 2012 10:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Inequality of wealth or income]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jamie Galbraith]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Macroeconomic Theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[naked Capitalism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/05/jamie-galbraith-on-inequality-and-macroeconomics.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Via Naked Capitalism comes this youtube video from Jamie Galbraith on inequality and macroeconomics, a speech delivered at the INET talks in Berlin: Galbraith has marshaled a great deal of cross country data over time, and shows how changes in equality happened in a very large number of economies in parallel. He explains, persuasively, that the most [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Via <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/04/jamie-galbraith-on-changes-in-finance-as-the-driver-of-inequality.html" target="_blank">Naked Capitalism</a> comes this youtube video from Jamie Galbraith on inequality and macroeconomics, a speech delivered at the INET talks in Berlin:</p>
<blockquote><p>Galbraith has marshaled a <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/04/jamie-galbraith-on-changes-in-finance-as-the-driver-of-inequality.html#" rel="nofollow">great <nobr>deal<img src="http://images.intellitxt.com/ast/adTypes/mag-glass_10x10.gif"></nobr></a> of cross country data over time, and shows how changes in equality happened in a very large number of economies in parallel. He explains, persuasively, that the most plausible culprit is changes in the financial regime.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/05/jamie-galbraith-on-inequality-and-macroeconomics.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>More Caution and Skepticism About Federal Mortgage “Investigation”</title>
		<link>./../../2012/01/more-caution-and-skepticism-about-federal-mortgage-investigation.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/01/more-caution-and-skepticism-about-federal-mortgage-investigation.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2012 16:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[AG investigations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[federal regulation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mortgages]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[naked Capitalism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/01/more-caution-and-skepticism-about-federal-mortgage-investigation.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Yves Smith continues to follow the progress of investigations in  More Caution and Skepticism About Federal Mortgage “Investigation” While a large number of “liberal” groups, ranging from the official Democratic party outlets (the Center for American Progress) to ones that sometimes cross swords with the Administration (MoveOn, the Working Families Party) praised the Tuesday evening [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Yves Smith continues to follow the progress of investigations in    <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/01/more-caution-and-skepticism-about-federal-mortgage-investigation.html">More Caution and Skepticism About Federal Mortgage “Investigation”</a>  <br />
<blockquote>While a large number of “liberal” groups, ranging from the official Democratic party outlets (the Center for American Progress) to ones that sometimes cross swords with the Administration (MoveOn, the Working Families Party) praised the Tuesday evening announcement of mortgage “investigations” with Schneiderman co-chairing the effort, others who have been watching the mortgage legal fight closely were far more ambivalent about the creation of a new unit in <a href="http://rushprnews.com/2009/11/17/president-obama-establishes-interagency-financial-fraud-enforcement-task-force">an initiative </a>…which has done pretty much nothing since its creation in 2009 (boldface mine):</p>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />Attorney General Eric Holder, Treasury Secretary Tim Geithner, Housing and Urban Development (HUD) Secretary Shaun Donovan, and Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) Chairwoman Mary Schapiro today announced that President Barack Obama has established by Executive Order an interagency Financial Fraud Enforcement Task Force to strengthen efforts to combat financial crime. The Department of Justice will lead the task force and the Department of Treasury, HUD and the SEC will serve on the steering committee. The task force’s leadership, along with representatives from a broad range of federal agencies, regulatory authorities and inspectors general, <strong>will work with state and local partners</strong> to <strong>investigate and prosecute significant financial crimes</strong>, <strong>ensure just and effective punishment for those who perpetrate financial crimes</strong>, address discrimination in the lending and financial markets and <strong>recover proceeds for victims</strong>.<br /> …<br /> The Times identified the two red flags. First, why are the settlement talks still proceeding? This is ridiculous if the plan is to do investigations. The fact that they have not been halted calls this exercise into question. Second, if this is supposed to be a heavyweight investigation, why hasn’t Obama set up an independent prosecutor, a role much more likely to attract the sort of kick-ass litigator that the Times correctly thinks is necessary for the job? </p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/01/more-caution-and-skepticism-about-federal-mortgage-investigation.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Comments on Inequality, Leverage, and Crises</title>
		<link>./../../2011/11/comments-on-inequality-leverage-and-crises.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/11/comments-on-inequality-leverage-and-crises.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2011 15:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Lane Kenworthy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[naked Capitalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[private debt]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Robert Waldmann]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Steve Keen]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/11/comments-on-inequality-leverage-and-crises.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Clifford Clark&#8217;s post at ataxingmatter* is worth a more complete look. This also brings to mind Steve Keen&#8217;s work on private debt and the economy on his blog Debt Watch as well as Lane Kenworthy&#8217;s exploration of poverty and severe poverty at Consider the Evidence, and Angry Bear Robert Waldmann&#8217;s recent posts here and here. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a target="_blank" href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2011/11/comments-on-inequality-leverage-and-crises-kumhof-ranciere-nov-2010-imf-working-paper.html">Clifford Clark&#8217;s post at ataxingmatter*</a> is worth a more complete look.  This also brings to mind Steve Keen&#8217;s work on private debt and the economy on his blog <a target="_blank" href="http://www.debtdeflation.com/blogs/">Debt Watch</a>  as well as Lane Kenworthy&#8217;s exploration of poverty and severe poverty at <a target="_blank" href="http://lanekenworthy.net/">Consider the Evidence</a>, and Angry Bear Robert Waldmann&#8217;s recent posts <a target="_blank" href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2011/09/record-severe-poverty-ii.html">here</a> and <a target="_blank" href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2010/09/blog-post.html">here</a>.</p>
<p>
<blockquote>Comments on Inequality, Leverage, and Crises&#8211;Kumhof &#038; Ranciere Nov 2010 IMF working paper
<p>[guest post by Clifford D. Clark]</p>
<p>Michael Kumhof&#8217;s and Romain Ranciere&#8217;s November 2010 paper relates income inequality to national economic crises, particularly those experienced as the Great Depression and the Great Recession.  They conclude that increases in income inequality &#8211;comparing the top 5% of households to the bottom 95%&#8211;in the years leading up to the two crises exerted a determining influence on the economy.</p>
<p> &#8230;
<p>First, income inequality grew in similar ways in the years before the depression and the recent deep recession. &#8230;.  The authors find a link between the two phenomena:  income inequality increased at a greater rate than consumption expenditures in the years before the two crises. The public was spending at rates greater than increases in their income.</p>
<p> &#8230;
<p>Second, in the years before the recent downturn the growth in household debt  was due almost entirely to the bottom 95%. Real hourly wages of the top 10% of households increased by an accumulated 70% between 1967 and 2003, while the median households decreased by 5% and wages at the bottom 10% decreased by about 25%.  &#8230;   That represents a clear switch:  whereas in 1983 the top wealth group was more indebted than the bottom 95%, by 2007 the reverse was true. By then the bottom 95% had debts equal to 140 % of income, nearly twice that of the top 5%. They conclude that almost all of the change in the debt to income ratio in aggregate was due to the bottom 95%.</p>
<p> &#8230;
<p>Third, an increase in debt requires and increased need for financial intermediation:  accordingly, the size of the financial sector between 1980 and 2007 increased considerably. Measured by the ratio of private credit of deposit banks and other financial institutions to GDP, that quantity increased from 90% in 1981 to 210% in 2007&#8230;</p>
</blockquote>
<p> <a name="more"></a>
<p> Their conclusion is succinctly stated.</p>
<blockquote><p>“<em>The key mechanism, reflected in a rapid growth in the size of the financial sector, is the recycling of part of the additional income gained by high income households back to the rest of the population by way of loans, thereby allowing the latter to sustain consumption levels, at least for a while. But without the prospect of a recovery in the incomes of poor and middle income households over a reasonable time horizon, the inevitable result is that loans keep growing, and therefore so does leverage and the probability of a major crisis that, in the real world, typically also has severe implications for the real economy.</em>” Id. at 22.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>* correction of source</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/11/comments-on-inequality-leverage-and-crises.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Denial in the Mortgage Industrial Complex</title>
		<link>./../../2011/11/denial-in-the-mortgage-industrial-complex.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/11/denial-in-the-mortgage-industrial-complex.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2011 14:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[mortgage markets]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mortgage regulation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[naked Capitalism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/11/denial-in-the-mortgage-industrial-complex.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Yves Smith provides a snapshot of her perception of at least public thoughts from mortgage industry conference participants. It is worth a read. Denial in the Mortgage Industrial Complex I just came back from the AmeriCatalyst conference in Austin, which was a packed two days focused on the state of the housing and securitization market. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Yves Smith provides a snapshot of her perception of at least public thoughts from mortgage industry conference participants. It is worth a read.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2011/11/denial-in-the-mortgage-industrial-complex.html">Denial in the Mortgage Industrial Complex</a></p>
<blockquote><p>I just came back from the <a href="http://americatalyst.com/americatalyst-2011-home-page/1893-2/">AmeriCatalyst conference in Austin</a>, which was a packed two days focused on the state of the housing and securitization market. The panels were very informative, and it was also good to see some of the people I’ve read or heard about, in particular the leading analyst, Laurie Goodman of Amherst Securities. She gave a talk that where she went through a very persuasive (and conservative) analysis that there are 8.3 to 10.3 million more foreclosures baked give how underwater <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2011/11/#">borrowers</a> are. And she had some striking bits of information. One is if you take out the homes where no one has made a mortgage payment in a year or more, homeownership in the US is 61%. In addition, Judge Annette Rizzo discussed a successful program she had developed in Philadelphia to do remediation. The success rate on modifications that come out of her court is 85% after 18 months. </p>
<p>I had quite a few people come and commend me on my comments. I think the main reason was that the viewpoint presented on this blog, that there are deep seated problems resulting from chain of title issues, and that servicers have engaged in a lot of abuses, was sorely underrepresented. I don’t blame the organizer,</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/11/denial-in-the-mortgage-industrial-complex.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Naked Capitalism&#8217;s Yves Smith is on fire&#8230;</title>
		<link>./../../2011/11/naked-capitalisms-yves-smith-is-on-fire.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/11/naked-capitalisms-yves-smith-is-on-fire.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 06 Nov 2011 15:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[naked Capitalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[offshoring]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[robosigning]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/11/naked-capitalisms-yves-smith-is-on-fire.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Yves Smith has been on fire lately. Here&#8217;s an article on when offshoring fails. &#8230;As these industry examples illustrate, the tradeoff between cost and flexibility can be quite involved and difficult to evaluate. It now appears that the labour-cost benefits gained from offshoring might not be sufficient to cover the lost flexibility under many circumstances. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Yves Smith has been on fire lately.  Here&#8217;s <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2011/11/when-offshoring-backfires.html">an article</a> on when offshoring fails.</p>
<blockquote><p>&#8230;As these industry examples illustrate, the tradeoff between cost and flexibility can be quite involved and difficult to evaluate. It now appears that the labour-cost benefits gained from offshoring might not be sufficient to cover the lost flexibility under many circumstances.</p></blockquote>
<p><a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2011/11/banks-lying-when-they-say-theyve-stopped-robosiging.html">Here</a> she discusses the continuing robosigning.</p>
<p>And <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2011/11/hubris-watch-us-bank-ceo-sniffs-about-breaking-rules-when-his-bank-has-huge-trustee-liability.html">here</a> is the view from within a bank.</p>
<blockquote><p>A writer for the Minneapolis CityPages managed to worm his way into a presentation to the annual meeting of the Minnesota Chamber of Commerce by US Bank’s CEO, Richard Davis&#8230;</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/11/naked-capitalisms-yves-smith-is-on-fire.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Brad DeLong (Desperately?) Tries to Rationalise the Giveaway</title>
		<link>./../../2009/03/brad-delong-desperately-tries-to-rationalise-the-giveaway.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/03/brad-delong-desperately-tries-to-rationalise-the-giveaway.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 22 Mar 2009 14:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Brad DeLong]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bubbles]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mark Thoma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[market-clearing prices]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[markets]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[naked Capitalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[risk management]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[solvency crisis]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/03/brad-delong-desperately-tries-to-rationalise-the-giveaway.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[UPDATE: Dr. Black twists the knife. The Geithner Plan FAQ is worth reading; it&#8217;s a classic example of treating an incomplete market as if it were the entire market. And note that &#8220;skin in the game&#8221; is limited to a part of the local pool. Unfortunately, while Treasury plays in the wading pool, hedge funds [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>UPDATE:  Dr. Black <a href="http://www.eschatonblog.com/2009/03/uh-brad.html">twists the knife</a>.</p>
<p><a target="_blank" href="http://delong.typepad.com/sdj/2009/03/the-geithner-plan-faq.html">The Geithner Plan FAQ</a> is worth reading; it&#8217;s a classic example of treating an incomplete market as if it were the entire market.  And note that &#8220;skin in the game&#8221; is limited to a part of the local pool.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, while Treasury plays in the wading pool, hedge funds have The Whole Wide World in which to romp. <a target="_blank" href="http://economistsview.typepad.com/economistsview/2009/03/despair-over-financial-policy.html">Yves</a> (h/t <a target="_blank" href="http://economistsview.typepad.com/economistsview/2009/03/despair-over-financial-policy.html">Mark Thoma</a>) <a target="_blank" href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2009/03/investor-on-private-public-partnership.html">has a commenter who explains</a>:<br />
<blockquote>Say I am SAC Capital. I get to be one of the bidders on bank assets covered by the program</p>
<p>Citi holds $100mm of face-value securities, carried at $80mm.</p>
<p>The market bid on these securities is $30mm. Say with perfect foresight the value of all cash flows is $50mm.</p>
<p>I bid Citi $75mm. I put up $2.25mm or 3%, Treasury funds the rest.</p>
<p>I then buy $10mm in CDS directly from Citi [or another participant (BOA, GS, etc)] on the bonds for a premium of $1mm.</p>
<p>In the fullness of time, we get the final outcome, the bonds are worth $50mm</p>
<p>SAC loses $2.25mm of principal, but gets $9mm net in CDS proceeds, so recovers $6.75mm on a $2.25mm investment. Profit is $4.5mm</p>
<p>Citi writes down $5mm from the initial sale of the securities, and a $9mm CDS loss. Total loss, $14mm (against a potential $30mm loss without the program)</p>
<p>U.S. Treasury loses $22.75mm.</p></blockquote>
<p>I would have thought by now that economists would know what happens when you create bubbles in a market.  That doesn&#8217;t change just because you use the U.S. Treasury as a Fluffer.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/03/brad-delong-desperately-tries-to-rationalise-the-giveaway.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Grass is Green, Sky is Blue, The WSJ Lies to You</title>
		<link>./../../2008/12/grass-is-green-sky-is-blue-the-wsj-lies-to-you.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/12/grass-is-green-sky-is-blue-the-wsj-lies-to-you.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2008 15:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[bailout]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[credit crisis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jourmalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[naked Capitalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the fed]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Old Firm]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WSJ]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/12/grass-is-green-sky-is-blue-the-wsj-lies-to-you.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Among their editorial suggestions for replacing Tim Geither as head of the New York FRB: Better choices would include &#8230;David Malpass, an economist who worked at the Reagan Treasury and long predicted the credit bubble&#8230;. Yes, you saw that correctly. David Malpass. Strangely, they don&#8217;t describe him as &#8220;David Malpass, former Chief Economist for Bear [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Among their <a href="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB122843659214281369.html?mod=djemEditorialPage">editorial suggestions for replacing Tim Geither as head of the New York FRB</a>:<br />
<blockquote>Better choices would include &#8230;David Malpass, an economist who worked at the Reagan Treasury and long predicted the credit bubble&#8230;.</p></blockquote>
<p>Yes, you saw that correctly.</p>
<p>David Malpass.</p>
<p>Strangely, they don&#8217;t describe him as &#8220;David Malpass, <a href="http://bigpicture.typepad.com/comments/2008/03/malpass-ass.html">former Chief Economist for Bear Stearns</a>, who long advocated taking monies out of your house because appreciation in housing prices changed &#8220;<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/05/22/business/yourmoney/22view.html?_r=1&#038;adxnnl=1&#038;adxnnlx=1228489230-pp+qqFkPTCIa3fCQpbK8Iw">the structure of the household portfolio</a>.&#8221;</p>
<p>And that &#8220;long predicted the credit bubble&#8221;?  This is a family blog, so I can&#8217;t call that horseshit.  So let&#8217;s look at what Malpass said in August of 2007—the point at which his firm was issuing bonds at what were essentially junk levels—<a href="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB118645120890190059.html">about the bubble, in the very pages of the WSJ</a>:<br />
<blockquote>Another aspect of the market disruption is a dramatic stand-off between bond buyers and sellers: Buyers in both housing and debt markets are using the market discontinuity to claw prices and terms back to Earth. The slowdown talk weighing on equities also reflects the Wall Street view that debt, mortgage and takeover businesses have replaced General Motors as the economy&#8217;s bellwether. According to the bears: As goes the credit market, so goes the economy.</p>
<p>Fortunately, Main Street is not that fickle. Housing and debt markets are not that big a part of the U.S. economy, or of job creation. It&#8217;s more likely the economy is sturdy and will grow solidly in coming months, and perhaps years.</p>
<p>Unlike the 1998 seizure in credit markets to which many are now drawing comparisons, reservoirs of global liquidity are full to overflowing, not empty as they were that year. The deep 1997-1998 Asian crisis has been replaced with an all-cylinder boom. Unemployment rates are falling all around the world, while China&#8217;s equities have continued hitting new highs. [emphases mine]</p></blockquote>
<p>The other nominees are little better, including the <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2007/11/feds-gary-stern-makes-lame-arguments.html">Gary Stern</a>, current head of the Minneapolis Fed of &#8220;<a href="http://www.portfolio.com/views/blogs/market-movers/2008/10/22/the-credit-crunch-isnt-a-myth?tid=true">Credit Crisis? What crisis?</a>&#8221; fame. (At least Stern <a href="http://blogs.wsj.com/economics/2008/03/27/minneapolis-fed-president-keeps-eye-on-the-ball/">admits he doesn&#8217;t care about finance as much as some other things</a>.)  But Malpass—and the lies told in support of him—should be beyond the pale even by WSJ standards.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/12/grass-is-green-sky-is-blue-the-wsj-lies-to-you.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
