<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Obamacare &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>John Roberts’ Curious Voting-Statistics Sophism Misconstrues The Census Report’s Statistics by Failing to Consider Key Statistical Deviation Facts and Fails To Consider WHY Massachusetts Blacks Might Be Voting In Lower Percentages Than Mississippi Blacks Are, Even IF They Are. [UPDATED]</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/john-roberts-curious-voting-statistics-sophism-misconstrues-the-census-reports-statistics-by-failing-to-consider-key-statistical-deviation-facts-and-fails-to-consider-why-massachuset.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/john-roberts-curious-voting-statistics-sophism-misconstrues-the-census-reports-statistics-by-failing-to-consider-key-statistical-deviation-facts-and-fails-to-consider-why-massachuset.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 02 Mar 2013 18:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[John Roberts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nate Silver]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nina Totenberg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NPR]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obamacare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politico]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the ACA litigation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Supreme Court]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Voting Rights Act of 1965; Antonin Scalia; the Supreme Court]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[William Galvin]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/john-roberts-curious-voting-statistics-sophism-misconstrues-the-census-reports-statistics-by-failing-to-consider-key-statistical-deviation-facts-and-fails-to-consider-why-massachuset.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In a blog post titled “In Voting Rights Arguments, Chief Justice Misconstrued Census Data” on NPR’s website, veteran NPR Supreme Court correspondent Nina Totenberg deconstructs a sophism offered by John Roberts at the oral argument on Wednesday on the continued constitutionality of a key section of the Voting Rights Act of 1965, which Congress has [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In a blog post titled “<a href="http://www.npr.org/blogs/itsallpolitics/2013/03/01/173276943/in-voting-rights-arguments-chief-justice-may-have-misconstrued-census-data">In Voting Rights Arguments, Chief Justice Misconstrued Census Data</a>” on NPR’s website, veteran NPR Supreme Court correspondent Nina Totenberg deconstructs a sophism offered by John Roberts at the oral argument on Wednesday on the continued constitutionality of a key section of the Voting Rights Act of 1965, which Congress has extended several times, the last time, overwhelmingly, in 2006.  Totenberg writes:
<div dir="ltr">At the <a href="http://www.npr.org/2013/02/27/173086612/conservative-justices-doubt-ongoing-validity-of-1965-voting-rights-act">voting rights argument</a> in the Supreme Court on Wednesday, Chief Justice John Roberts tore into Solicitor General Donald Verrilli, grilling him on his knowledge of voting statistics.</div>
<div dir="ltr">The point the chief justice was trying to make was that Massachusetts, which is not covered by the preclearance section of the Voting Rights Act, has a far worse record in black voter registration and turnout than Mississippi, which is covered by Section 5 of the act.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">But a close look at census statistics indicates the chief justice was wrong, or at least that he did not look at the totality of the numbers.</div>
<p>Totenberg goes on to say that the statistics Roberts used were taken from a lower-court dissenting opinion, statistics that in turn were taken from a 2010 census report.  “But,” Totenberg says, “upon close examination, the numbers are less than reliable, according to the Census Bureau itself.”  She explains:</p>
<div dir="ltr">Here&#8217;s the deal. The Census Bureau does voting surveys to look at voting patterns nationwide, but the survey is based on a very small sample. Most recently, in 2010, the survey looked at 94,208 voters nationwide. Break that up into roughly proportional samples in each state, Census officials say, and it is really not possible to compare states because those with relatively low minority populations have a much higher margin of error.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">The number of black citizens eligible to vote in Massachusetts is 236,000, while it is 721,000 in Mississippi, more than three times that number. Therefore, according to Census officials, when looking at the estimated turnout rate in Massachusetts, the voting percentage for African-Americans at first blush is estimated at 39.3 percent. But the margin of error is 11.5 percentage points, meaning that the black voter turnout actually could be as high as 50.8 percent (or, conversely, as low as 27.8 percent). </p>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />Now, look at Mississippi, where black turnout is listed at 48.7 percent. But because of the large size of the African-American population that was sampled, the margin of error is only 5.4 percentage points.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">That means that factoring in the margin of error, the black turnout rate in Mississippi could be as high as 54.1 percent, or as low as 43.3 percent.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">So, if you factor in the margins of error at their extremes — with Mississippi at the low end and Massachusetts at the high end — Mississippi could have had a black voter turnout rate that was 7.5 percentage points lower than Massachusetts.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Bottom line, as Census officials told me, these numbers are simply not reliable for state-by-state comparisons because of the high margins of error in some states.</div>
<p>Yep, John Roberts, it turns out, is no statistician.  But neither is he, well, a social scientist. Or even a moderately sharp observer of politics.  At least, not of Massachusetts politics. Where, y’know, Democrats usually win with lopsided victories in, say, House races in predominantly black Congressional and state-legislative districts; where the outcome of the state’s electoral college presence in presidential elections has not been in doubt for decades; and where neither Ted Kennedy’s nor John Kerry’s reelection was even remotely in doubt since, I guess, the 1994 Ted Kennedy/Mitt Romney campaign. Totenberg’s report makes clear that voting in the hotly-contested statewide race to replace Kennedy, who died in office&#8211;a special election in late 2009&#8211;was not part of the census report, which measures voting only in national elections.  </p>
<p>So, might not the question of <i>what’s at stake</i> in a particular election <i>matter</i>, even when you’re a Supreme Court justice who’s spent decades wanting to see the Voting Rights Act’s demise and will not be fussy about the grounds you state for your decision?  I mean, just to make it look sorta rational? </p>
<p>Most of the media attention concerning that oral argument focused on what were truly shocking <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/02/racial-entitlements-such-as-right-to.html">comments by Scalia</a> in which he said both that voting rights are a racial entitlement and, equally stunningly, although gaining less attention, that the motive of members of Congress in voting to “perpetuate” that “racial entitlement” in extending the Voting Rights Act&#8211;political reasons, he said&#8211;is appropriate reason for the Supreme Court to refuse to give the usual “deference” (here, legalese for benefit of the doubt) to Congress’s legislative decision after weighing extensive evidence, even if the motive was itself not unconstitutional.  </p>
<p>This latter&#8211;that the motive of members of Congress, which in this case no one claims was an unconstitutional motive (e.g., a racist motive or a religious-discrimination motive)&#8211;purports to give the Court the constitutional authority to reject Congress’s legislative choices&#8211;is so obviously bizarre and dangerous that, in this case, it likely won’t garner agreement by any other justice. But that oral argument was the second time in less than a year that Scalia offered this argument, and the first time he did so, he was joined by three other justices.</p>
<p>The case in which this occurred was the ACA (Obamacare) case.  In his dissenting opinion, he claimed that because a majority of the Court was voting to strike down as unconstitutional one section of the statute&#8211;the section concerning the consequences to states of refusing to agree to accept the expansion of Medicaid&#8211;the Court must strike down the rest of the statute, not because a majority thought the rest of the statute also was unconstitutional (a majority did not), but because a few members of Congress who voted for the statute might not have voted for the statute if that Medicaid-expansion part was not part of it.  The ACA passed the Senate with no votes to spare, see, so, well, I mean, who’s to say that without the Medicaid-expansion part, the statute would have passed at all?!</p>
<p>Rest assured, though, that this, like sooooo many other movement-conservative gimmicks, would be entirely discretionary with the justices, or lower-court judges, case by case.  A budget bill that conservatives favor, and that’s enacted in a close vote, would not be strikeable in its entirely even if it contained some part that a majority of the Court thinks is unconstitutional.  But a budget bill that disfavored by conservatives, and enacted in a close vote, might be strikeable in its entirety if one part is deemed unconstitutional, since ya never know whether it was that log-rolling of the sort that Scalia, Kennedy, Alito and Thomas objected to in the ACA, and that involved the unconstitutional provision, that enabled the passage of the budget bill.</p>
<p>This, by the way, apparently was the bridge-too-far that began Roberts on the road to a change of heart, and change of vote, on the constitutionality of the individual-mandate provision. Reportedly, it really offended and scared him.  But it got the votes of four of the nine justices. </p>
<p>This time around, though&#8211;in the Voting Rights Act case&#8211;Scalia’s apparently trying only to use this motive-matters argument to strike down a key section of the Act, not the whole thing. Which makes sense, since log-rolling wasn’t the reason for the 2006 reenactment of the law, and, as I said, the law was reenacted by overwhelming votes in each house; 98-0 in the Senate. But luckily for Scalia and friends, among them Roberts this time, there is that census report.  </p>
<p>And <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nate_Silver">Nate Silver</a> hasn&#8217;t been asked to analyze it.  And he probably won&#8217;t be.</p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />UPDATE: OH. WOW.  Politico reported last night, in an article titled <a href="http://www.politico.com/blogs/under-the-radar/2013/03/massachusetts-official-slams-chief-justices-comments-158275.html">Massachusetts official slams chief justice&#8217;s comments on Voting Rights Act</a>:</p>
<div dir="ltr">The problem, Massachusetts Secretary of State William Galvin says, is that the data does not back up Roberts’s claim.</p>
</div>
<div dir="ltr">“It’s just disturbing that the chief justice of the United States would spew this kind of misinformation,” Galvin told POLITICO.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Galvin’s office assumes that Roberts was going off <a href="http://www.census.gov/hhes/www/socdemo/voting/publications/p20/2010/tables.html">U.S. Census Bureau data</a>, which is one of the only national datasets on voter turnout by race, but they say the 2010 numbers don’t support what Roberts is saying.</p>
</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">“He’s wrong, and in fact what’s truly disturbing is not just the doctrinaire way he presented by the assertion, but when we went searching for an data that could substantiate what he was saying, the only thing we could find was a census survey pulled from 2010 … which speaks of noncitizen blacks,” Galvin said. “We have an immigrant population of black folks and many other folks. Mississippi has no noncitizen blacks, so to reach his conclusion, you have to rely on clearly flawed information.”</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">The 2010 tables show that Massachusetts does have a high discrepancy between turnout of white and black voters, but is in line with several other states, including Minnesota, Kansas and Washington, which actually has a wider ratio. The states are also similar on registration numbers. Additionally, the margin of error on each of these states’ data is over 10 percentage points, and many states on the list had populations of blacks so small, data wasn’t even available.</div>
<div dir="ltr">“We reached out to academics at many institutions … and they could find no record either, they were puzzled by [Roberts’s] reference,” Galvin said.</div>
<p>So Roberts was gamed by an incompetent or intellectually dishonest lower-court judge, from whose dissenting opinion Roberts took the bait, the hook, the line&#8211;and the sinker. It’s fairly commonplace for lower-court judges to misstate or omit key evidence.  Sometimes, it’s because the law clerk they’ve assigned to do their work for them doesn&#8217;t bother to actually nail down or verify facts put into briefs, and sometimes it’s just that they know how they want to rule, and just cherry-pick truncated statements of fact to support their chosen conclusion.  And sometimes&#8211;and believe me; this is true&#8211;they just fabricate a fact out of nowhere. </p>
<p>But, really&#8211;the chief justice of the U.S. Supreme Court using a statistic on voting that includes non-citizens as eligible to vote, because he just lifted a surprising statistic from a lower-court judge’s dissenting opinion, without first looking into its plausibility, much less its actual accuracy? </p>
<p>What’s next? The chief justice relying unquestioningly on a Bob Woodward report? </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/john-roberts-curious-voting-statistics-sophism-misconstrues-the-census-reports-statistics-by-failing-to-consider-key-statistical-deviation-facts-and-fails-to-consider-why-massachuset.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Hobby Lobby’s Religion Lobby &#8211; [Appended]</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/hobby-lobbys-religion-lobby-appended.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/hobby-lobbys-religion-lobby-appended.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2013 17:17:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[ACA litigation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bill Keller]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ethan Bronner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hobby Lobby]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obamacare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The New York Times]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/hobby-lobbys-religion-lobby-appended.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[About two weeks ago, Dan emailed me with a link to a New York Times article titled “A Flood of Suits Fights Coverage of Birth Control,” by Times reporter Ethan Bronner, published that day. The article began: In a flood of lawsuits, Roman Catholics, evangelicals and Mennonites are challenging a provision in the new health [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>About two weeks ago, Dan emailed me with a link to a New York Times article titled “<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/01/27/health/religious-groups-and-employers-battle-contraception-mandate.html?emc=tnt&#038;tntemail1=y&#038;_r=1&#038;pagewanted=print&#038;">A Flood of Suits Fights Coverage of Birth Control</a>,” by Times reporter Ethan Bronner, published that day. The article began:</p>
<div dir="ltr">In a flood of lawsuits, Roman Catholics, evangelicals and Mennonites are challenging a provision in the new health care law that requires employers to cover birth control in employee health plans — a high-stakes clash between religious freedom and health care access that appears headed to the Supreme Court. </div>
<div dir="ltr">In recent months, federal courts have seen dozens of lawsuits brought not only by religious institutions like Catholic dioceses but also by private employers ranging from a pizza mogul to produce transporters who say the government is forcing them to violate core tenets of their faith. Some have been turned away by judges convinced that access to contraception is a vital health need and a compelling state interest. Others have been told that their beliefs appear to outweigh any state interest and that they may hold off complying with the law until their cases have been judged. New suits are filed nearly weekly.</div>
<p>Dan asked me if I could put the article’s contents into perspective.  I could, and I did.  I responded:</p>
<div dir="ltr">Yeah, this is part and parcel of the Liberty U.-type ACA litigation <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/11/religious-freedom-contraception-and-law.html">that we exchanged emails about back in late Nov.</a> &#8230;</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">The new NYT article discusses the Hobby Lobby case, which is different than the Liberty U. case in an important respect: Hobby Lobby is a for-profit corporation, albeit a closely-held one.  </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">The bottom line is that I expect that for-profit corporations, even small, closely-held ones like Hobby Lobby, will not be allowed an exemption from compliance with parts of the ACA on religious grounds.  The purpose of for-profit corporations is, well, profit, not the advancement of a religious cause or the practice of religion.  And corporations are people only for monetary purposes&#8211;accepting money and spending money.  At least as of now. </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">The two stated grounds for the corporations-are-people-too-my-friend right to First Amendment free-speech rights in Citizens United were (1) that the members of a corporation or union are united by a common political, ideological or monetary goal that is central to the existence of the nonprofit or for-profit corporation or union, and which the money&#8211;er, speech&#8211;addresses; and (2) that the general public has an interest in hearing more political speech, not less.  (At least as long as the speech is what the CEO, if not necessarily a majority of the shareholders, wants to say, and the spending balance&#8211;corporate vs. union&#8211;favors the Republican Party.  </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Unless Justice Kennedy &#038; Co. think more religion on the part of for-profit corporations that sell housewares and crafts is in the public interest, <a href="http://shop.hobbylobby.com/home-decor-and-framing/lamps-and-accessories/">because lamps</a>, picture frames and art supplies are people too, my friend, and because more religion by lamps, picture frames and art supplies is in the public, then Hobby Lobby probably will end up having to comply with the parts of the ACA that violate the lamps&#8217;, picture frames&#8217;, and art supplies&#8217; religious beliefs.  But, who knows? </div>
<p>I thought of that email exchange this morning after reading Bill Keller’s opinion piece about Hobby Lobby case in today’s NYT.  The title: <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/11/opinion/keller-the-conscience-of-a-corporation.html?pagewanted=all">The Conscience of a Corporation</a>.</p>
<p>Kudos to the Times’ headline writer. </p>
<p>Hobby Lobby&#8217;s lobbyists, referenced in the title of <i>this</i> post, are, of course, the company&#8217;s lawyers.</p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />UPDATE: Reader J.Goodwin wrote in the Comments thread:</p>
<div dir="ltr">Hobby Lobby is relatively well-known (at least in Oklahoma) for their religious persuasion. They are closed on religious holidays and Sundays, etc.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">I don&#8217;t think that matters, but it&#8217;s not like this is a company that has never held itself off as having religious owners or religious anything.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">It&#8217;s not a straight up cash grab, it&#8217;s at least based on a history of some sort of religious values.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Obama never should have offered any exemption on this stuff. It&#8217;s time for religions to be treated like the corporations they are.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">I responded:</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">One of the articles I read about the lawsuit said that Hobby Lobby reportedly treats its employees well, paying the lowest-level ones twice the minimum wage.  I had never heard of Hobby Lobby until the fall of 2011, when I was shopping in a strip mall where one was located and decided to stop in.  I didn’t even know it was a chain until last month when I read about the lawsuit, and I knew nothing at all about its owners before that.  </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">But I do know now that it’s a closely-held corporation, the shareholders all members of one family, and that the family is genuinely religious and also apparently generous.  There’s really no question but that their position on the contraceptives insurance matter is entirely and genuinely based on their deep and longstanding religious beliefs; they are not using their beliefs as a pretext. </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">But running a business is not practicing religion. And the law at issue concerns running a business, not practicing religion.  </div>
<p>That said, I didn’t intend by the title of this post to be snide or nasty, but instead to make a point. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/hobby-lobbys-religion-lobby-appended.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Whole Foods, Half-Wit</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/whole-foods-half-wit.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/whole-foods-half-wit.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Jan 2013 01:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[fascism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Mackey Thom Hartmann]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obamacare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sam Sacks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[socialism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Whole Foods]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/whole-foods-half-wit.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[What a spot-on article Run 75441’s piece, “Healthcare Reform; Socialism or Fascism?” is. And what an informative Comments thread.  (Wow, Cynthia, who knew? I sure didn’t.) And, folks, don’t miss this takedown of Mackey, called “Dear Whole Foods CEO, This Is What a Fascist Looks Like,” by Thom Hartmann and Sam Sacks, via ReaderSupportedNews.   [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">What a spot-on article Run 75441’s piece, “<a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/01/healthcare-reform-socialism-or-fascism.html">Healthcare Reform; Socialism or Fascism?</a>” is. And what an informative Comments thread.  (Wow, Cynthia, who knew? I sure didn’t.) </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">And, folks, don’t miss<a href="http://readersupportednews.org/opinion2/277-75/15632-focus-dear-whole-foods-ceo-this-is-what-a-fascist-looks-like"> this</a> takedown of Mackey, called “Dear Whole Foods CEO, This Is What a Fascist Looks Like,” by Thom Hartmann and Sam Sacks, via ReaderSupportedNews.  </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">But I have my own suggestion to Mackey: Consider expanding your company to other countries. Australia, maybe.  Germany.  Canada.  Sweden. France. Britain.  Norway.  Holland.  Maybe even Israel and Poland, both of them countries whose healthcare system Mitt Romney praised last summer.  </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Or maybe Switzerland, where&#8211;as another reader commented in the earlier thread, in noting your praise of the Swiss health system, Mr. Mackey&#8211;you can see a fascist (or is it a socialist?) system at work, while admiring the beautiful mountainscape and maybe even skiing in it.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">And while you’re there, break a leg.</div>
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/whole-foods-half-wit.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Raising the Price of Pizza 10 to 14 cents. . .</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/raising-the-price-of-pizza-10-to-14-cents.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/raising-the-price-of-pizza-10-to-14-cents.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 02 Dec 2012 21:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Health care costs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health care reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Maggie Mahar]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obamacare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[run 75441]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/raising-the-price-of-pizza-10-to-14-cents.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Bill aka run75441 Raising the Price of Pizza 10 to 14 cents. . . Will pizza and food prices really have to increase to cover healthcare costs for the mostly young employees of the Olive Garden&#8217;s, Denny&#8217;s, and Papa John&#8217;s restaurants? A 10 to 14 cents increase per pizza is being proposed by Papa [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by <strong>Bill aka run75441</strong><a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766" name="_top"></a></p>
<p>Raising the Price of Pizza 10 to 14 cents. . .</p>
<p> Will pizza and food prices really have to increase to cover healthcare costs for the mostly young employees of the Olive Garden&#8217;s, Denny&#8217;s, and Papa John&#8217;s restaurants? </p>
<p>A 10 to 14 cents increase per pizza is being proposed by Papa Johns&#8217; to pay for the PPACA. At the same time, Papa John&#8217;s is advertising a 2 million-pizza giveaway with the help of Peyton Manning <a href="file:///C:/Users/Owner/AppData/Local/Microsoft/Windows/Temporary%20Internet%20Files/Content.IE5/XVMSONN6/#_top"><i>&#8220;Two Million Free Pizzas&#8221;</i></a> (must be a freebie?). Not sure myself how I might decide to account for the cost; but, here is a try; free pizza for 2 million NFL fans to increase sales, . . . cut employee hours to avoid the PPACA and keep the price, . . . raise prices 10 to 14 cents per pizza to have healthcare insurance for the restaurant staff, . . . or maybe a kind of half cheese/half sausage combo. . . healthcare and free pizzas with Peyton Manning promoting the social responsibility of Papa John&#8217;s? </p>
<p>Maggie Mahar at The Health Beat Blog <a href="http://www.healthbeatblog.com/2012/11/can-u-s-businesses-afford-obamacare-2/"><i>&#8220;Can US Businesses Afford Obamacare?&#8221;</i></a> points to an interesting article by John Padua of <i>Managed Care Matters </i>discussing who bears the healthcare reform cost if restaurant owners opt out<i> </i>while Forbes Caleb Melby runs the numbers and questions the increased costs suggested by Papa&#8217;s John&#8217;s CEO<i> </i><a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/calebmelby/2012/11/12/breaking-down-centi-millionaire-papa-john-schnatters-obamacare-math/"><i>&#8220;Papa John&#8217;s Obamacare Math&#8221;</i></a><i> .</i><br /><i><br /></i> The issue(s): <i>The Affordable Care Act dictates that full-time employees (30 hours or more per week) at companies with more than 50 workers need to be provided health insurance. CEO John Schnatter has further claimed that some employers will cut employee hours to avoid providing them with healthcare. </i><br /><i></i><br />The Cost: <i>John Schnatter estimates that Obamacare will end up costing his company $5-8 million annually.</i><br /><i></i><br />The Price Increase: <i>10 to 14 cents per pizza</i><br /><strong><br /></strong> <strong>Checking John Schnatter’s Math: </strong><i>Last year, Papa John’s International captured $1.218 billion in revenue. Total operating expenses were $1.131 billion. If Schnatter’s math is accurate (Obamacare will cost his company $5-8 million more annually), then new regulation translates into a .4% to .7% expense increase. It is difficult to set that ratio against the proposed pie increase and across all sizes given size and topping differentials, but many of their large specialty pizzas run for $16. Remarkably, a 10-14 cent increase on a $16 pizza falls in a comparable range of .6% to .9%; but, the cost transference becomes less equitable if you are looking at medium pizzas which run closer to $12, meaning a .8% to 1.15% price increase.</i><br /><i><br /></i> <i>Lets say that Papa John’s sells exactly half medium/half large specialty pizzas. Averaging the ranges for both sizes, then averaging that product yields a .86% price increase — well outside the range of what Schnatter says Obamacare will cost him.</i><br /><i><br /></i> <i>So how much would prices go up, under these 50/50 conditions, if they were to fairly reflect the increased cost of doing business onset by Obamacare? Roughly 3.4 to 4.6 cents a pie.</i><br /><i></i></p>
<p>3.4 to 4.6 cents does not seem like such a huge increase to bear by either customer or the business and if the advertising is done right; it might prove more positive than giving away 2 million freebie pizzas during the NFL season . . . a little like Schooner Tuna in the movie &#8220;<i>Mr. Mom,</i>&#8216;<i>we are in this together for the long haul.'&#8221;</i> What customer would not buy into this?</p>
<p>The Issue(s): From the annals of I made this;<i> &#8220;Everyone is looking for a way &#8216;</i>not<i>&#8216; to provide insurance for their employees. It is essentially a huge tax on all us business people,&#8221; </i>declares <a href="http://thinkprogress.org/health/2012/11/15/1197431/dennys-obamacare/?mobile=nc"><i>Denny&#8217;s RREMC Franchise Owner CEO John Metz</i></a><i> </i>on Fox News. To offset costs further, John adds; &#8220;<strong><i>he also will slash most of the </i></strong><strong><i>staff’s time to fewer than 30 hours per week</i></strong>&#8221; to start January 2014.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Talk about giving a long notice for plant closures to employees. What happens if franchise owner sidesteps the insurance provision of the PPACA and cuts hours to fewer than 30? John Padua of <i>Managed Care Matters </i>says the cost falls back on the US citizenry, employees, and customers of these restaurants. </p>
<p><strong>&#8220;<i>If companies do not provide insurance for low-paid workers, we taxpayers have to.</i></strong><i> That is the way Obamacare works; folks with incomes below 400% of the FPL can get subsidized coverage. If restaurants cut workers’ hours so as not to insure employees, all of us taxpayers get to pay for their health insurance. These companies are avoiding their responsibility and increasing our tax burden. </i><i><a href="http://www.joepaduda.com/2012/11/the-cost-obamacare-14-cents-per-pizza/">&#8220;The Cost of Obamacare -14 cents per pizza&#8221;</a></i><i></i></p>
<p>The Cost: Maggie Mahar raises the question in her <i>&#8220;Can They Afford It???&#8221;</i> post. Metz employs 1,200 associates at his Denny&#8217;s RREMC franchise. Taking the extreme case of all 1200 employees going into the state exchange and being subsidized up to 400% of FPL; by slashing everyone&#8217;s hours to 28, Metz avoids the $2,000 penalty (~$2.34 million in total) for those going into the state exchange.</p>
<p>The Price Increase: 5% surcharge to all meals in 40 Denny&#8217;s in Georgia, Florida and Virginia. (note: I wonder how that will appear on the bill?)</p>
<p>Checking The Math: The CBO (which forever appears to be anti-healthcare reform) found in a recent study, 2014 comprehensive healthcare insurance could be had at $3,400 for an employee up to 30 years of age and single. Understanding we are not talking about writing off Metz&#8217;s employee expenses from his corporate income tax yet and knowing the PPACA requires an employer to pay 65% of the employee&#8217;s healthcare insurance, the $3,400 per person (down from a projected $6,700 without the PPACA) now becomes $2,210 per person. </p>
<p>Denny&#8217;s franchise owner Metz is angry with Obama, the PPACA, and his employees. Granted, the example is as much an extreme as Metz&#8217;s knee jerk reactions and posturing; but, it points to the overall fallacy in the too-much-healthcare- cost is a drag on my business argument. Both of these entrepreneurs did take grief for their stances. Denny&#8217;s CEO John Miller did call john Metz to discuss his stance and John Schnatter has been called out in various blogs and is the subject of multiple boycotts.</p>
<p>Much of this sounds like sour grapes starting with SCOTUS affirming the PPACA and is carryover from the re-election of Barack Obama to the Presidency. Some have protested the validity of the PPACA claiming it was immoral to force business owners to pay for employee healthcare insurance. In an email exchange, John Paduca answers:</p>
<p><i>&#8220;In response to your query as to when it became an employers’ responsibility to provide health insurance, that would have occurred when PPACA was passed, signed into law, and upheld by the Supreme Court. Laws run this country, not morals. If &#8216;morals&#8217; did, we never would have invaded Iraq or water-boarded prisoners or interned Japanese Americans or overturned legitimate governments in Africa and Central America or supported the Shah of Iran. &#8216;Morals&#8217; are personal; laws are societal.&#8221;</i><br /><i><br /></i> Maybe it is just Republicans having to cancel their airline tickets to Boston for the celebration on November 7th which has placed both Johns in a bad mood. Or could it be pent up anger with the very people who elected Barack to The White House for a second term? You know, those 47 percenters who might make up the bulk of the restaurant workers. </p>
<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/raising-the-price-of-pizza-10-to-14-cents.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Binders That Bind</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/the-binders-that-bind.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/the-binders-that-bind.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 17 Oct 2012 17:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Andrea Mitchell]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[binders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obamacare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[oil drilling leases and permits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Romneycare]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/the-binders-that-bind.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The most revealing moment last night came as Ann Romney walked toward her husband onstage at the end.  That expression on her face.  I thought she looked like a woman in a binder. It is, I suppose, poetic justice for Romney that an obviously misspoken phrase of that sort is the catch phrase from last [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div></div>
<div>The most revealing moment last night came as Ann Romney walked toward her husband onstage at the end.  That expression on her face.  I thought she looked like a woman in a binder.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>It is, I suppose, poetic justice for Romney that an obviously misspoken phrase of that sort is the catch phrase from last night.  But the phrase, while generating <a href="http://www.politico.com/politico44/sidecar/2012/10/nkingofdc-138734.html">hilarious witticisms</a>, is not the reason why Romney won’t recover.  Instead, it is the binders that Romney has placed <i>himself</i> in that surely became clear to many of his new-found fans of the last two weeks—the binders that underlie his entire campaign. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Most significantly, in my opinion, that his tax plan is, rather than the new math—as he’s been claiming—actually is <i>no</i> math. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And that he takes contradictory positions at the same time—starkly, last night, for example, that he’s proud that because of him, virtually everyone in Massachusetts has healthcare insurance, yet Obamacare must be repealed because it’s keeping employers from hiring.  (There were others that surely became clear to a lot of people, but this one just bowled me over, because he said these two things within a few minutes of each other.)
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And—yes; finally!—that he habitually plucks statistics out of their context and misrepresents their meaning, although the most clearly illustrative one was one that Obama wasn’t able to make fully clear last night because of time constraints on his reply to Romney’s allegation.  It will be easy for him to do so now, though.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>That statistic: Romney’s claim that Obama has reduced oil production from drilling on federal lands by 14% by denying drilling permits and leases.  Romney first claimed, falsely, that there has been a 14% reduction in oil production from drilling on federal lands <i>since Obama took office</i>.  After Obama repeatedly interjected that that was false and that the level of that oil production actually had <i>increased</i> during his administration, Romney finally qualified his claim; production had decreased by 14% <i>over the past year</i>.
</p>
</div>
<div><a name="more"></a></div>
<div>I loved it that Obama stepped forward—literally—and explained that the leases and permits that his administration had revoked were ones that the leaseholders and permit holders <i>had not been using</i>, and that <i>that was the reason</i> for the revocations; he wanted the leases and permits to be reissued to others, who would <i>use</i> them.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>That was a great moment, albeit one that probably won’t get much attention.  But even more important is that, as Andrea Mitchell explained during the NBC recap and analysis, the 14% reduction occurred (as Romney finally acknowledged) only in the last year—and that the <i>reason</i> for the drop was … a fire at, and consequent shutdown, of a major refinery in Texas!  And, even with that 14% drop in the last year, production from drilling on federal lands <i>has increased more than 10% since Obama took office. </i>
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I think the Obama campaign should do an ad on this, saying that apparently Romney <i>thought it was Obama administration policy to have a fire at a major refinery</i>.  And that Romney’s so inept at math that he doesn’t know the difference between a 10% increase and a 14% decrease.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The public will get the point.  Romney is trying to game them. Not a particularly attractive trait in a presidential candidate.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>But one misuse of a statistic by Romney came earlier in the debate, and it downright <i>shouted</i> sophistry, thanks to Obama’s unmasking of it: Romney’s comparison of gas prices in January 2009 and gas prices now.  When Obama pointed out why gas prices were so low when he assumed office—and why they’ve doubled since then—I <i>knew</i> Obama would win the debate.  And when, later, during the discussion of the policy similarities between G.W. Bush’s policies and Romney’s proposed ones, Obama cleverly said Romney probably would send gas prices falling, by crashing the economy and thus lowering demand for oil, I thought then that Obama won the election last night.  </div>
<div></div>
<div>And in the light of today, I’m pretty sure of it.</div>
<div>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Binders.  Indeed.
</p>
</div>
<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/the-binders-that-bind.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Conservative roots of Obamacare</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/conservative-roots-of-obamacare.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/conservative-roots-of-obamacare.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2012 10:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[ACA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kenneth Thomas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obamacare]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/conservative-roots-of-obamacare.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Kenneth Thomas  Conservative roots of Obamacare The pile-on continues. As I discussed in February, Stuart Butler of the Heritage Foundation wrote a breath-taking op-ed in USA Today (via Don Taylor) denying that he fathered the individual mandate. In fact, his revised 140-page research paper was published January 2, 1989, before President George HW Bush [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Kenneth Thomas<br />  <br />Conservative roots of Obamacare</p>
<p> The pile-on continues. As <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2012/02/heritage-doubles-down-on-individual.html">I discussed in February</a>, Stuart Butler of the Heritage Foundation <a href="http://usatoday30.usatoday.com/news/opinion/forum/story/2012-02-03/health-individual-mandate-reform-heritage/52951140/1">wrote a breath-taking op-ed</a> in <i>USA Today</i> (via <a href="http://theincidentaleconomist.com/wordpress/stuart-butlers-change-of-mind/">Don Taylor</a>) denying that he fathered the individual mandate. In fact, his <i>revised</i> 140-page <a href="http://www.heritage.org/research/reports/1989/a-national-health-system-for-america">research paper</a> was <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2012/02/conservatives-refute-butlerheritage.html">published January 2, 1989</a>, before President George HW Bush came into office, let alone President Clinton, whose proposals Butler says his research was directed against. Two conservatives, <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/aroy/2012/02/07/the-tortuous-conservative-history-of-the-individual-mandate/">Avik Roy</a> of <i>Forbes</i> and <a href="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052970204369404577211161144786448.html">James Taranto</a> of the <i>Wall Street Journal</i>, played strong roles in locking down the point that Butler was the first to propose the mandate.<br />    <br />Today, J.D. Kleinke of the American Enterprise Institute goes straight to that 1989 report in a <i>New York Times</i> <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/09/30/opinion/sunday/why-obamacare-is-a-conservatives-dream.html?pagewanted=1&#038;partner=rss&#038;emc=rss">opinion piece</a> to once again lay the mandate at the feet of Heritage. And why not? According to him, the Affordable Care Act is a conservative&#8217;s dream.<br />
<blockquote>The rationalization and extension of the current market is financed by the other linchpin of the law: the mandate that we all carry health insurance, an <a href="http://www.heritage.org/research/reports/1989/a-national-health-system-for-america">idea</a> forged not by liberal social engineers at the Brookings Institution but by conservative economists at the Heritage Foundation. The individual mandate recognizes that millions of Americans who could buy health insurance choose not to, because it requires trading away today’s wants for tomorrow’s needs. The mandate is about personal responsibility — a hallmark of conservative thought. </p></blockquote>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Kleinke argues that Romney&#8217;s incoherence on health care stems precisely from rejecting his accomplishment in Massachusetts. Romney can&#8217;t offer anything better than the ACA because it is the <i>only</i> conservative way to overcome the problems of the health care market while remaining based on the market and individual responsibility. With no single payer and no public option, it is not surprising that, as he puts it, &#8220;the health insurance industry has been quietly supporting the plan all along.&#8221;<br />    <br />Aside from his odd notion that single payer represents a &#8220;government takeover of health care&#8221; (Canada&#8217;s Medicare is not the United Kingdom&#8217;s National Health Service), Kleinke&#8217;s column is on the money: historically, the mandate <i>was</i> developed by Heritage economists, the ACA more broadly relies on conservative rather than liberal principles, and many liberals have been unenthusiastic for just that reason.</p>
<p>Heck, I&#8217;m unenthusiastic (single payer!). But it&#8217;s a big improvement over the status quo that is already providing benefits to millions of people, whether for <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2011/09/aca-works-for-young-adults-as-planned.html">young adults</a>, the millions of consumers getting <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/07/guest-post-health-insurance-rebates.html">rebates</a> due to the medical loss ratio rule, or for seniors getting rid of the donut hole and gaining free preventive care.</p>
<p>crossposted with <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2012/10/conservative-refutation-of.html">Middle Class Political Economist </a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/conservative-roots-of-obamacare.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Why Doesn’t Rachel Zubay Know That Most Provisions of Obamacare Won’t Start Until 2014?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/09/why-doesnt-rachel-zubay-know-that-most-provisions-of-obamacare-wont-start-until-2014.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/09/why-doesnt-rachel-zubay-know-that-most-provisions-of-obamacare-wont-start-until-2014.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 23 Sep 2012 15:17:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Canadian healthcare system]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Joel Auchenbach]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Michelle Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obamacare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rachel Zubay]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Washington Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/09/why-doesnt-rachel-zubay-know-that-most-provisions-of-obamacare-wont-start-until-2014.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Rachel Zubay, 32, works as a waitress at Abdalla’s Steak House, in the shadow of a recently idled coal-fired power plant. She’s got two kids, is in the middle of a divorce, has no medical insurance and is paying $50 a month on a $15,000 surgical bill after she injured her ankle and foot in [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>Rachel Zubay, 32, works as a waitress at Abdalla’s Steak House, in the shadow of a recently idled coal-fired power plant. She’s got two kids, is in the middle of a divorce, has no medical insurance and is paying $50 a month on a $15,000 surgical bill after she injured her ankle and foot in a nasty fall. She figures she’ll have it paid off in five or 10 years.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>She’ll probably vote for Romney. What about the president’s health-care plan, which is supposed to help people afford medical insurance? “Obviously it hasn’t helped me at all,” Zubay says. “I’d be better off moving to Canada.”
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212; <i><a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/national/health-science/in-ohio-county-electorate-is-hardened-and-fractured/2012/09/22/3a848108-03da-11e2-91e7-2962c74e7738_print.html">In Ohio county, electorate is hardened and fractured</a></i>, <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/joel-achenbach/2011/02/24/AB5edOJ_page.html">Joel Achenbach</a>, Washington Post, today
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Michelle Obama gave a lovely, effective speech earlier this month at the Democratic convention.  But in my opinion, her best moment came two days later, while making a particular comment during a taped clip that was part of the little film played before her husband delivered his acceptance speech.  In one seemingly unscripted moment, at the end of brief comments about Obamacare, she said something about hospitals and physicians sending bills for hundreds of thousands of dollars to, say, a single mothers with hourly-wage jobs—and doing so “with a straight face.”  What was most effective were not even her words but the spontaneous, pained, incredulous look on her face as she said “with a straight face.”
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I’d love to see the Obama campaign use that clip in an ad that also makes clear that the part of Obamacare that will help Ms. Zubay by the time she’s 34, and her young children, and millions of others too, won’t start until 2014.  If it starts at all.  Which, Romney/Ryan, if elected, will do their best to keep it from doing.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Seriously.  It probably didn’t occur to Obama that some people think that Obamacare’s main provisions have started but have just failed to help <i>them</i>.  But now, he knows.  And Ms. Zubay probably isn’t the only one who’s planning to vote for Romney, in part because of that evil Obamacare, who recognizes the benefits, healthcare-wise, of living in Canada.  Or Germany.  Or Taiwan.  Or Israel. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>What some of them don’t recognize, I guess, is that if they injure a foot two years from now, they won’t have to pay $50 a month for the next several decades.  They’ll be able instead to use that $50 a month for other things.</div>
<div>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/09/why-doesnt-rachel-zubay-know-that-most-provisions-of-obamacare-wont-start-until-2014.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>About Ann Romney’s—And Other MS Victims’—Darkest Hour (those who have healthcare insurance, those who have very high deductibles, and those who may lose their jobs and be unable to get new healthcare insurance. Or a dressage horse.)</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/about-ann-romneys-and-other-ms-victims-darkest-hour-those-who-have-healthcare-insurance-those-who-have-very-high-deductibles-and-those-who-may-lose-their-jobs-and.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/about-ann-romneys-and-other-ms-victims-darkest-hour-those-who-have-healthcare-insurance-those-who-have-very-high-deductibles-and-those-who-may-lose-their-jobs-and.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 19 Jul 2012 18:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[ABC News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ACA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ann Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[DNC ad]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[dressage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mandy Clive]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Multiple Sclerosis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obamacare]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/about-ann-romneys-and-other-ms-victims-darkest-hour-those-who-have-healthcare-insurance-those-who-have-very-high-deductibles-and-those-who-may-lose-their-jobs-and.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The DNC has apologized for using Ann Romney&#8217;s London Olympics-bound horse in an attack targetting her husband. The Hill explains that Democrats had used the dressage horse to illustrate its claim that the presumptive GOP nominee was &#8220;dancing around the issue&#8221; of his decision not to release his tax returns. (Dressage is a dance-like sport, but on [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>The DNC has apologized for using Ann Romney&#8217;s London Olympics-bound horse in an attack targetting her husband.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The <em><a href="http://thehill.com/blogs/blog-briefing-room/news/238879-dnc-backs-off-dressage-romney-attack-ads" target="_blank">Hill</a></em> explains that Democrats had used the dressage horse to illustrate its claim that the presumptive GOP nominee was &#8220;dancing around the issue&#8221; of his decision not to release his tax returns. (Dressage is a dance-like sport, but on a horse. Get it?)
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The problem? The horse is used by Ann Romney for therapy related to her multiple sclerosis.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>DNC spokesperson Brad Woodhouse told ABC News that the decision to use footage of the horse &#8220;was not meant to offend Mrs. Romney in any way, and we regret it if it did.&#8221; Woodhouse added that the group won&#8217;t &#8220;invoke the horse any further to avoid misinterpretation.” 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>For what it&#8217;s worth, the dressage horse, named Rafalca, apparently gets the Romneys a rather hefty tax credit. (Literally, fwiw: <a href="http://jezebel.com/5919987/mitt-romneys-fancy-horse-is-worth-more-than-your-entire-family" target="_blank">$77,000</a> a year.)
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212; <i><a href="http://slatest.slate.com/posts/2012/07/19/ann_romney_s_horse_dnc_says_they_won_t_use_it_anymore_in_campaign_ads_.html#comments">DNC Sorry for Using AnnRomney&#8217;s Horse in Attack Ad: TheDemocrats say they won&#8217;t use the Olympic-bound animal in future campaign spots</a></i>, Abby Ohlheiser, Slate, today
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>A headline today on ABC News’ website, about an interview there today with Ann Romney, is “<a href="http://abcnewsradioonline.com/politics-news/ann-romney-opens-up-about-illness-calls-ms-diagnosis-my-dark.html">Mitt Romney&#8217;s Wife, Ann, Calls MS Diagnosis &#8216;MyDarkest Hour&#8217;</a>.”  Unquestionably, that was a dark hour for her, and one that anyone can empathize with.  And, yes, it’s great that dressage helps her regain some of the ability to balance she lost due to her MS. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>But here’s my question to Ann Romney and her husband: How much darker an hour does she think it is for someone who’s given that diagnosis and either has no healthcare insurance or has a very high deductible, or who now dearly fears the loss of his or her job, either because of the health problem or for other reasons, and who, for resulting financial reasons or preexisting-condition reasons—or both—may never again have health insurance if the ACA is repealed? Or be able to get a dressage horse.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I don’t think Obama or the DNC should shy away from asking this question.  Or from doing an ad in which someone in exactly that position asks it. 
</p>
</div>
<p>&#8212;-</p>
<p>UPDATE: Because of the emotional impact of this particular issue, I want post as part of the main post a Comments Section exchange between reader Mandy Clive and me.  Here it is:</p>
<p>
<div>Mandy Clive: I&#8217;m confused. Does owning horses or houses somehow make you a bad presidential candidate? And therapeutic horse riding is used for all sorts of medical conditions, so this is not unusual. Regardless of who I think should win the election, Ann Romney is drawing alot of attention to multiple sclerosis, which is a largely unknowable disease at this point. I have it. Its ruining my life. We need more awareness and research so we can actually understand what causes this disease and how to treat it with something better than a 33% success rate. I&#8217;m all for candidates hashing out their issues, but I agree with those who are calling for a cease fire when it comes to involving Ann and her illness. MS needs positive attention and deserves respect.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Me: Does owning horses or houses somehow make you a bad presidential candidate? That depends on how you got the money to buy the several dressage horses, each worth several hundred thousand dollars, and to buy the several houses, each worth several million dollars.  And on such things as whether or not you paid the full amount of taxes you owed, or instead hid or misrepresented the value of the assets in offshore accounts, including offshore IRA accounts, in order to evade taxes or even to avoid taxes using legal means available only to the very wealthy.  And whether your proposed tax policies, such as reducing yet again taxes on the wealthy, would benefit you (the candidate) extensively, to the detriment of a large percentage of the public. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And, of course, on what you (the voter, rather than the candidate) thinks is a bad presidential candidate. My view is different than yours, obviously.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>As for Ann Romney’s MS and dressage therapy, it was Romney herself, not the DNC, that raised the issue, by going on television this morning and responding to the DNC ad by telling everyone that she uses the Olympic horse for therapy.  (She has several substitute horses when that horse is training or in, say, London for a competition.  She didn’t mention that, though, I guess.)  She also said that the MS diagnosis was her darkest hour. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Her husband is running for president partly on a platform of repealing the ACA, including the provision that requires insurance companies to accept everyone regardless of preexisting medical conditions, and, of course, the provisions that provide for expansion of Medicaid and for subsidies for premiums for some others.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>You say that we need more awareness and research so we can actually understand what causes this disease and how to treat it with something better than a 33% success rate.  So true.  It’s true for so many other very series diseases, as well, that effect young people and middle-aged people.  ([Muscular dystrophy] comes quickly to my mind; someone dear to me died of it two years ago after having lived most of his life in a motorized wheelchair.)  But in this country, unlike in every other advanced industrialized democracy in the world, medical advances can be made use of here only by those who have access to employee-benefit medical insurance.  You’re obviously among them.  But not everyone else with MS or another debilitating chronic illness is.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>
<div>Although I didn&#8217;t put this in my Comment response, I&#8217;d also like to note that under Romney&#8217;s proposed tax and budget cuts, which are extreme, there would be virtually no federal funds for medical research, either to the universities or to the NIH. So if you&#8217;re someone who places a high value on medical research—and I suspect that most people do—this is no small matter to consider when deciding whether Romney is a bad candidate or not.</div>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/about-ann-romneys-and-other-ms-victims-darkest-hour-those-who-have-healthcare-insurance-those-who-have-very-high-deductibles-and-those-who-may-lose-their-jobs-and.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>John Roberts and Elena Kagan: Mirror Images of Each Other</title>
		<link>./../../2012/06/john-roberts-and-elena-kagan-mirror-images-of-each-other.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/06/john-roberts-and-elena-kagan-mirror-images-of-each-other.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2012 14:16:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[ACA litigation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Elena Kagan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jeff Shesol]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Roberts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ken Houghton]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linda Greenhouse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obamacare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/06/john-roberts-and-elena-kagan-mirror-images-of-each-other.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The second biggest surprise of the day, after the survival of the Affordable Care Act, is that we’ve never really gotten over our collective crush on John Roberts. How else to explain today’s outpouring of praise, not merely for the decision but for the man himself, for his statesmanship and judicial modesty? All these years, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>The second biggest surprise of the day, after the survival of the Affordable Care Act, is that we’ve never really gotten over our collective crush on John Roberts. How else to explain today’s outpouring of praise, not merely for the decision but for the man himself, for his statesmanship and judicial modesty? All these years, it now appears, we’ve held it in our hearts; we’ve written it in our diaries, remembering every one of those sweet nothings he once whispered about “common ground” and “humility.” No, we never really gave up on Roberts. Not during that long judicial bender he took with the boys—Nino, Clarence, Tony, and Sam; not during the <em>Citizens United</em> argument, when he called the government “big brother”; not when he swept away a century’s worth of campaign finance regulations. So complete is our swoon, in the afterglow of the ACA ruling, that <a href="http://www.thedailybeast.com/articles/2012/06/28/obamacare-supreme-court-ruling-john-roberts-changes-his-legacy.html" target="_blank">Bob Shrum has written</a> that if Roberts had been Chief Justice in 2000, <em>Bush v. Gore</em> might have gone the other way.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212; <a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/jurisprudence/2012/06/john_roberts_is_hardly_the_hero_and_judicial_statesman_people_make_him_out_to_be_.html#comments">John Roberts Is No Hero: Why ourcrush on the chief justice is silly—and undeserved</a>, Jeff Shesol, Slate, Jun. 28
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>To which I posted the following comment:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I write on legal and political issue issues for a left-of-center blog and have indicated there that I detest and really fear John Roberts because of his deeply diabolical nature and his checklist of ‘80s-era Federalist Society things-to-do.   Linda Greenhouse has written several columns, two or three of them within the last few months, highlighting those two quintessential John Roberts traits.  But Greenhouse, and I, predicted that Roberts would save the ACA because the case is so high-profile and the grounds for striking down the statute so utterly artificial that it would place more public scrutiny on the types of things he and his cadre normally get away with with virtually no public awareness.  I don’t think he did what he did out of a sense of statesmanship, nor in order to gut the Commerce Clause; I think the Commerce Clause ruling will have almost no practical effect, and he could have done the same thing with it simply by joining the other four conservatives in a 5-4 ruling striking down the ACA. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I think he’s, in a way, the mirror image of Elena Kagan, who in high-profile cases usually votes liberal but who, best as I can tell, almost never goes out on a limb for the “nobody” “cert” petitioner and actually fights to get a “cert grant,” as Sotomayor does, and who I’d bet doesn’t even vote very often to hear such cases.  Her priorities seem to be her own public image and being buddies with the “in” crowd on the Court, whereas Roberts’ priority is making as many dramatic changes to the law as he can, but doing so as much under the public’s radar as possible.  (I also think Kagan is a bit naïve on some issues because of her unfamiliarity with them—see, e.g.: federal habeas review of state-court convictions—and fairly easily snowed.)
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>So I agree with Ken Houghton in his post below that John Roberts is not the friend of progressives.  I disagree with Ken, though, that Roberts has set up some trap through which he will later orchestrate the striking down of the ACA as a violation of equal protection because of the way in which the Medicaid expansion is administered (if I understand Ken correctly) is nil.  Roberts ended his opinion with a statement saying that the proper manner in which to determine the ultimate fate of the ACA is through the political process, not the judicial process—and I think he means it.  There are two parts of Roberts’ opinion—the part concerning Congress’s regulatory powers under the Commerce Clause and the part concerning Congress’s power to enact federal-state partnership legislation <i>a la </i>Medicaid—that raise serious concerns about the impact on <i>other</i>legislation.  I wrote separate posts yesterday about each of these, and I’ll be writing another one on Medicaid issue later today. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>But any lawsuits concerning some aspect of how the law is working in practice, once it gets underway, would result in the possible tweaking of an HHS regulation or in the manner in which a particular state is implementing the Act, but I just don’t foresee a successful attack on the constitutionality of some provision in the Act itself. 
</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/06/john-roberts-and-elena-kagan-mirror-images-of-each-other.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Thank you, Judge Posner</title>
		<link>./../../2012/06/thank-you-judge-posner.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/06/thank-you-judge-posner.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2012 23:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[ACA litigation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Commerce Clause]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Fifth Amendment due process clause]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obamacare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard A. Posner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/06/thank-you-judge-posner.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The chief justice, echoing Justice Scalia&#8217;s &#8220;broccoli&#8221; comment at the oral argument, rejected (as did the four dissenters, and so that is now the view of a majority of the justices) the Commerce Clause ground for the mandate, saying that to accept that ground would mean that &#8220;Congress could address the diet problem by ordering [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>The chief justice, echoing Justice Scalia&#8217;s &#8220;broccoli&#8221; comment at the oral argument, rejected (as did the four dissenters, and so that is now the view of a majority of the justices) the Commerce Clause ground for the mandate, saying that to accept that ground would mean that &#8220;Congress could address the diet problem by ordering everyone to buy vegetables.&#8221; This argument, reassuring though it is to our obese population, confuses separate constitutional provisions. The Commerce Clause would empower Congress to order everyone to buy vegetables, because the market for most vegetables is interstate, but the &#8220;liberty&#8221; protected against the federal government by the Fifth Amendment would doubtless be interpreted to forbid such an imposition, just as it would be interpreted to forbid a federal law requiring everyone to be in bed with the lights out by 10 p.m. in order to economize on the use of electricity and, by doing so, reduce carbon emissions from electrical generating plants.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212; Judge <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Posner">Richard A. Posner</a>, on Slate, <a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/the_breakfast_table/features/2012/_supreme_court_year_in_review/affordable_care_act_upheld_why_the_commerce_clause_should_have_been_enough_.html#comments">5:38 p.m. today</a>
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Amen. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Justices Ginsburg, Breyer, Sotomayor and Kagan also made that point, in their concurrence today.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<p>I’m thrilled to be in such exalted company.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/06/thank-you-judge-posner.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
