<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>social security &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Who is not retiring, and why?</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/who-is-not-retiring-and-why.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/who-is-not-retiring-and-why.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2013 10:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[income distribution]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Inequality of wealth or income]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lump of labor fallacy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security for the young]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/who-is-not-retiring-and-why.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Via Bloomberg comes this note on demographics and the work force, and continues a conversation about how that impacts all of us. Probably not in the way most often provided in punditry&#8230;such as taking jobs away from the millenium generation, wealthy old geezers stereotypes, or alarms sounded about who is to pay for services we [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Via <a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2013-03-14/why-grandpa-hasn-t-retired.html#disqus_thread">Bloomberg</a> comes this note on demographics and the work force, and continues a conversation about how that impacts all of us.  Probably not in the way most often provided in punditry&#8230;such as taking jobs away from the millenium generation, wealthy old geezers stereotypes, or alarms sounded about who is to pay for services we want, etc.  </p>
<p>It&#8217;s well known that the U.S. is turning gray. It&#8217;s less well known that the workforce is turning gray as well. The percentage of Americans who are 65 and older will rise from <a href="http://economix.blogs.nytimes.com/2008/12/05/why-does-us-health-care-cost-so-much-part-iii-an-aging-population-isnt-the-reason/">13 percent in 2010 to 20 percent by 2030</a> &#8212; and, if the recent trend continues, a growing share of those elderly Americans will carry on working past the normal retirement age.</p>
<p><img alt="Source: Bureau of Labor Statistics" src="http://www.bloomberg.com/image/iZomGtINy47A.jpg"><br />Source: Bureau of Labor Statistics</p>
<p>In 1990, 11.8 percent of those 65 and older worked. In 2010 the figure was 17.4 percent. By 2020, the <a href="http://www.bls.gov/emp/ep_table_303.htm">Bureau of Labor Statistics</a> expects it to be 22.6 percent. The numbers are even more surprising for Americans older than 75. Less than 5 percent of them worked in 1990. In 2010, it was 7.4 percent. By 2020, according to the BLS, 10 percent of them will still be toiling away.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/who-is-not-retiring-and-why.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Worms, Pond Scum and Economists</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/worms-pond-scum-and-economists.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/worms-pond-scum-and-economists.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2013 10:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dean Baker]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security for the young]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/worms-pond-scum-and-economists.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Dean Baker writes Worms, Pond Scum and Economists The effort to blame the awful plight of the young on Social Security and Medicare is picking up steam.In the last week, there were several pieces in The Washington Post and The New York Times that either implicitly or explicitly blamed older workers and retirees for the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://truth-out.org/news/item/15167-worms-pond-scum-and-economists" title="http://truth-out.org/news/item/15167-worms-pond-scum-and-economists">Dean Baker writes</a><br /><strong><br />
<blockquote></blockquote>
<p></strong> <strong>Worms, Pond Scum and Economists</strong></p>
<p>The effort to blame the awful plight of the young on Social Security and Medicare is picking up steam.<br />In the last week, there were several pieces in <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/%20%20blogs/wonkblog/wp/2013/03/15/yes-raising-the-retirement-age-would-be-bad-for-the-poor-no-that-%20%20doesnt-mean-its-unfair/">The Washington Post </a>and <a href="http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/03/14/stop-%20%20stealing-from-our-kids/">The New York Times</a> that either implicitly or explicitly blamed older workers and retirees for the bad economic plight facing young people today. There is now a full-court press to cut Social Security and Medicare benefits, ostensibly out of a desire to help young workers today and in the future.</p>
<p>Just to be clear, there is no doubt that young workers face dismal economic prospects at the moment.</p>
<p>…</p>
<p>This means that young people today can expect many more years of dire labor market conditions, because the remedies that could turn around their job situations have been blocked by nonsense spewing from economists. Incidentally, this situation works out very nicely for those on top, who are enjoying the benefits of record-high profit shares, which have also helped to fuel a soaring stock market.<br />The failure to see the largest asset bubble in the history of the world, coupled with the failure to prescribe an effective remedy to deal with the damage, should be sufficient to earn the economics profession the contempt of right-thinking people everywhere. But there is nothing too low for this group of professionals.</p>
<p>We are now seeing economists joining the crusade to cut Social Security and Medicare by implicitly or explicitly claiming that these programs are somehow responsible for the dismal economic plight of the young. The argument is that we can only free up money for helping our young if we take money from the old, a group with a median income of $20,000 a year.</p>
<p>By contrast, the upward redistribution of income to the richest 1 percent is equal to 10 percentage points of national income, or more than $1.3 trillion a year. To put this in the ten-year-budget-window context that dominates Washington debate, the amount that has been redistributed upward will be more than $16 trillion over the next decade. And that is based on the heroic assumption that the upward redistribution does not continue.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/worms-pond-scum-and-economists.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Social Security is the healthiest component of the U.S.’s retirement saving system</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/social-security-is-the-healthiest-component-of-the-u-s-s-retirement-saving-system.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/social-security-is-the-healthiest-component-of-the-u-s-s-retirement-saving-system.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2013 10:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security for the young]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/social-security-is-the-healthiest-component-of-the-u-s-s-retirement-saving-system.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Bloomberg&#8217;s Josh Barro is the lead writer for the Ticker, Bloomberg View&#8217;s blog on economics, finance and politics. Social Security is the healthiest component of the U.S.’s retirement saving system Last week I wrote that Social Security is the healthiest component of the U.S.’s retirement saving system and should therefore be expanded. This isn’t a [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2013-03-14/why-social-security-is-the-best-retirement-saving-vehicle.html">Bloomberg&#8217;s</a> Josh Barro is the lead writer for the Ticker, Bloomberg View&#8217;s blog on economics, finance and politics. </p>
<blockquote><p>Social Security is the healthiest component of the U.S.’s retirement saving system</p>
<p>Last week <a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2013-03-08/don-t-cut-social-security-expand-it.html">I wrote</a> that Social Security is the healthiest component of the U.S.’s retirement saving system and should therefore be expanded. This isn’t a popular position; liberals tend to prefer defined-benefit pensions from employers and conservatives defined-contribution accounts, such as 401(k)s and individual retirement accounts. But the reason Social Security works so well is that it lacks a fundamental problem that undermines the effectiveness of these other retirement vehicles.</p>
<p>Both defined-benefit pensions and defined-contribution accounts are based on a shared and problematic premise: It is possible to set aside x percent of today’s gross domestic product for retirement and generate retirement income from those savings that exceeds x percent of future GDP. This is to be achieved by investing retirement savings in assets that typically grow at a faster rate than the economy as a whole.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Such returns are possible. Some asset classes have long-run rates of return that exceed GDP growth: equities, for example. But the high returns are a compensation procyclical risk: These assets will tend to strongly outperform GDP when the economy does well and significantly underperform it during recessions.</p>
<p>It doesn’t make sense to finance retirement in such a risky way. Retirement savings exist disproportionately for the benefit of people with low or moderate means and a relatively low tolerance for risk. If retirement assets were invested safely, they would not be expected to grow faster than the economy as a whole.</p>
<p>So 401(k) and traditional pensions are both just efforts to finance retirement on the cheap by taking on excessive risk. The problem created by risk manifests itself in different ways with the different vehicles.</p>
<p>…</p>
<p>That is, private pensions no longer rely on the premise that retirement can be made cheaper through investment in assets that grow faster than GDP. But such a free lunch was what made the plans attractive for employers in the first place, and as employers have faced the plans&#8217; real costs, they have increasingly eliminated them.</p>
<p>In the public sector, the free lunch lives on in the financial statements of pension funds. Governments fund their pensions based on an expected rate of return on a risky portfolio of assets, most commonly between 7.5 and 8 percent a year, far above the roughly 5 percent growth path we might expect for nominal GDP.</p>
<p>…</p>
<p>All of these options (expanding Social Security or downshifting the risk in other investment vehicles) would cause retirement saving to appear to become more expensive. But it wouldn’t actually make saving more expensive: It would just replace hidden costs created by risk with explicit costs.<br />Americans would then face a stark reality: Retirement, which is basically just another word for spending the final sixth of your life on vacation, is expensive. I am agnostic on the question of whether people ought to respond by saving more or retiring later. Advocates of later retirement tend to be elite people with jobs that are interesting and not physically demanding. But facing up to the true cost of adequate retirement saving would help Americans make more sound choices about how to deal with the fact that retirement is expensive.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/social-security-is-the-healthiest-component-of-the-u-s-s-retirement-saving-system.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>A President Who&#8217;ll Cut Social Security &#8212; And Liberals Who Love Him Too Much</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/a-president-wholl-cut-social-security-and-liberals-who-love-him-too-much.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/a-president-wholl-cut-social-security-and-liberals-who-love-him-too-much.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2013 04:22:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[liberals]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[media pundits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/a-president-wholl-cut-social-security-and-liberals-who-love-him-too-much.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Richard Eskow  points us to a trend with liberals media types and Social Security: A President Who&#8217;ll Cut Social Security &#8212; And Liberals Who Love Him Too Much The spectacle of a supposedly liberal president repeatedly and needlessly trying to cut Social Security is enough to bring a reasonable, economically literate person to the point [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/rj-eskow/a-president-wholl-cut-soc_b_2835274.html%22Richard">Richard Eskow</a>  points us to a trend with liberals media types and Social Security:</p>
<blockquote><p>A President Who&#8217;ll Cut Social Security &#8212; And Liberals Who Love Him Too Much</p>
<p>The spectacle of a supposedly liberal president repeatedly and needlessly trying to cut Social Security is enough to bring a reasonable, economically literate person to the point of existential despair. To see leading liberal lights like Rachel Maddow and Ezra Klein chuckle indulgently at those foolish Republicans in Congress over the subject &#8212; <i>Don&#8217;t they know he&#8217;s already giving them what they want? </i>&#8212; is to risk plunging into the depths of that despair.</p>
<p>This week the president hosted a dinner for Republicans leaders where he worked to sell his budget proposal, including his harmful plan to cut benefits through the &#8220;chained CPI.&#8221; National Security was the main course and Social Security was the dessert. And guess who <i>wasn&#8217;t</i> coming to dinner: The elderly, the disabled, or any policy experts who understand the disastrous implications of the chained CPI.</p>
<p>The Maddow/Klein exchange (which we&#8217;ll bring to you as soon as a transcript is available) is the crest of a building wave in pro-Democratic Party commentary which says, as <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/wonkblog/wp/2013/03/01/what-we-have-here-is-a-failure-to-communicate/">Klein</a> puts it, that &#8220;what we have here is a failure to communicate.&#8221; Klein says that at least &#8220;some of the gridlock (in Washington) is due to poor information.&#8221; Jonathan Chait <a href="http://nymag.com/daily/intelligencer/2013/03/would-teaching-republicans-about-obama-help.html">bemoans</a> the fact that Republicans &#8220;won&#8217;t acknowledge [Obama&#8217;s] actual offer, which includes large cuts to retirement programs.&#8221;</p>
<p>&#8230;</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>But Democrats like Maddow, Klein, and Chait know better. They know exactly what Obama&#8217;s been trying to do.  And their only complaint seems to be that he&#8217;s not doing effectively enough. We&#8217;re not hearing much from the &#8216;left&#8217; side of the debate about the profound flaws, biases, and inherent cynicism behind both the President&#8217;s policy and his rhetoric.</p>
<p>Here are the facts:<br />1.Research suggests that Social Security cost-of-living increases are already inadequate. (See studies on &#8220;CPI-E&#8221; for more details on the best ways to increase them.)</p>
<p>2.Obama&#8217;s proposed chained-CPI cut would typically reduce benefits for 3 percent, and by as much as 6 percent for some recipients.</p>
<p>3.The White House&#8217;s decision to label this cut the &#8220;superlative CPI&#8221; is grotesque. It suggests that elderly women who receive an average of $950 or so per month are receiving &#8220;superlative&#8221; benefit increases each year.</p>
<p>4.The administration&#8217;s insistence on speaking of &#8220;entitlement reform,&#8221; mixing Medicare (which has a real cost problem because of our for-profit health system) with Social Security, is a cheap trick first devised by Republican consultants.</p></blockquote>
<p>(hat tip Nancy Ortiz)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/a-president-wholl-cut-social-security-and-liberals-who-love-him-too-much.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>President Obama insists on social safety net reform?</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/president-obama-insists-on-social-safety-net-reform.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/president-obama-insists-on-social-safety-net-reform.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2013 03:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/president-obama-insists-on-social-safety-net-reform.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[From the MSBN comes this announcement from President Obama on agenda for reform of the social safety net. President Barack Obama raised anew the issue of cutting entitlements such as Medicare and Social Security as a way out of damaging budget cuts, a White House official said Sunday, as both sides in Washington tried to [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>From the <a href="http://news.msn.com/politics/obama-renews-offer-to-cut-entitlements-to-end-budget-cuts">MSBN</a> comes this announcement from President Obama on agenda for reform of the social safety net.</p>
<blockquote><p>President Barack Obama raised anew the issue of cutting entitlements such as Medicare and Social Security as a way out of damaging budget cuts, a White House official said Sunday, as both sides in Washington tried to limit a fiscal crisis that may soon hit millions of Americans.</p>
<p>Signaling he might be ready to explore a compromise to end automatic spending cuts that began late Friday, Obama mentioned reforming those entitlement programs in calls with lawmakers from both parties Saturday afternoon.</p></blockquote>
<p>I suppose we will have to wait to find out what exactly is for sale. </p>
<p>Update:  <a href="http://www.whitehouse.gov/sites/default/files/docs/deficit_reduction_table_bucketed_r8.pdf">Spending Savings from Superlative CPI with protections for vulnerable</a>&#8230;.whitehouse.gov</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/president-obama-insists-on-social-safety-net-reform.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Europeans, Republicans Dreaming Up New Ways to Destroy Global Economy</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/europeans-republicans-dreaming-up-new-ways-to-destroy-global-economy.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/europeans-republicans-dreaming-up-new-ways-to-destroy-global-economy.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 27 Feb 2013 19:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[austerity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[European Union]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/europeans-republicans-dreaming-up-new-ways-to-destroy-global-economy.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[While we are busy paying attention to the 550th edition of Republican-caused fake crises (aka the sequester), a much more real crisis is brewing in the Eurozone. Richard Field at Trust Your Instincts flags a Reuters report that that Eurozone regulators are strongly considering a proposal to make not just investors in Cyprus banks pay [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>While we are busy paying attention to the 550th edition of  Republican-caused fake crises (aka the sequester), a much more real  crisis is brewing in the Eurozone. Richard Field at <a href="http://tyillc.blogspot.com/2013/02/are-european-policymakers-about-to.html">Trust Your Instincts</a> flags a <a href="http://www.reuters.com/article/2013/02/25/eurozone-cyprus-options-idUSL6N0BPDXL20130225">Reuters report</a> that that Eurozone regulators are strongly considering a proposal to  make not just investors in Cyprus banks pay for part of their bailout,  but bank depositors as well.</p>
<p>Cyprus is a tax haven, and  deposits in the banks there come to some 70 billion euros, more than 3  1/2 times the tiny country&#8217;s 18 billion euro gross domestic product. One  proposal under consideration would be to hold all deposits over 100,000  euros in escrow &#8212; for up to 30 years! Another proposal, says Reuters,  would &#8220;impose a retroactive tax on all deposits over 100,000 euros&#8230;&#8221;  If either of these options looks like it is close to being approved, it  is likely to cause a run on banks in Cyprus. As Field argues, if one of  these plans is established, depositors will likely wonder if it could be  applied to other debtor countries like Spain or Italy, causing even  more turmoil. (Note: 100,000 euros is the maximum that can be covered by  deposit insurance programs similar to the FDIC in the U.S.)</p>
<p>While  European leaders seem to want to blunder into a new way of creating a  euro crisis, the evidence continues that their preferred austerity  policies are failing. The European Commission has announced that the  eurozone will remain in recession throughout 2013, according to a  separate report by <a href="http://www.reuters.com/article/2013/02/22/us-europe-economy-eurozone-idUSBRE91L0B620130222">Reuters</a>. Previously, the Commission had predicted that the recession would end this year. As <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/02/23/austerity-europe-2/">Paul Krugman shows</a>,  the countries that have had the severest austerity have had the largest  contractions in their economy. Based on International Monetary Fund  estimates of the policy change in a number of European countries, he  plots this against the change in their real gross domestic product from  2008 to 2012:</p>
<p><img alt="" height="297" src="http://graphics8.nytimes.com/images/2013/02/23/opinion/022313krugman1/022313krugman1-blog480.png" width="480"><br />Source:  Paul Krugman (link above). Key: AUT-Austria; BEL-Belgium; DEU-Germany;  ESP-Spain; FIN-Finland; GRC-Greece; IRL-Ireland; ITA-Italy;  NLD-Netherlands; PRT-Portugal</p>
<p>So, for example, Greece has imposed austerity equal to about 15% of potential GDP, and seen its actual GDP shrink by about 18%.</p>
<p>Despite  the clear failure of austerity policies in the eurozone and Great  Britain (where 9 months of recession were followed by one quarter of  growth but a renewed slump in the last quarter of 2012, and <a href="http://www.usatoday.com/story/money/business/2013/02/22/moodys-downgrades-uk/1940065/">Moody&#8217;s just downgraded</a> the country&#8217;s debt), Republicans are still trying to impose budget cuts on the country that we voted against in November. <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2012/11/what-fiscal-cliff-means-for-middle-class.html">As I discussed then</a>,  the sequester&#8217;s discretionary budget cuts will be unambiguously bad for  the middle class. Now, Republicans are trying to convert the defense  cuts of the sequester into further slashing into middle class programs,  while President Obama has offered to convert Social Security&#8217;s inflation  adjustment to so-called &#8220;<a href="http://truth-out.org/news/item/14764-macho-men-social-security-and-the-chained-cpi">chained CPI</a>,&#8221;  which will slowly but relentlessly cut into benefits year after year  through the magic of compounding. According to Dean Baker at the link  above, the reduction would be about 0.3% per year, so benefits will be  3% lower after 10 years, 6% after 20 years, etc.</p>
<p>Considering how bad <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2013/01/the-fiscal-cliff-and-coming-retirement.html">middle class retirement prospects</a> are already looking, the President&#8217;s offer would be disastrous for  millions if implemented. The right course of action is simple: cancel  the sequester, forget about cutting Social Security (which is not part  of the so-called debt problem anyway), and focus on jobs and growth. As  Paul Krugman <a href="http://books.wwnorton.com/books/detail.aspx?ID=4294971028">says</a>, &#8220;End this Depression Now!&#8221;</p>
<p>Cross-posted from <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2013/02/europeans-dreaming-up-new-ways-to.html">Middle Class Political Economist</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/europeans-republicans-dreaming-up-new-ways-to-destroy-global-economy.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Dean Baker on Social Security and Obama</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/dean-baker-on-social-security-and-obama.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/dean-baker-on-social-security-and-obama.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 26 Feb 2013 12:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[northwest plan for a real social security fix]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social safety net]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/dean-baker-on-social-security-and-obama.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Via Truthout Dean Baker points to continuing insistent of President Obama to keep Social Security &#8216;on the table&#8217;. Dean Baker has a take on some numbers surrounding the politics and stories politicans offer: While most of the DC insiders probably don&#8217;t understand the chained CPI, everyone else should recognize that this technical fix amounts to [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Via <i>Truthout</i> <a href="http://truth-out.org/news/item/14764-macho-men-social-security-and-the-chained-cpi" target="_blank">Dean Baker</a> points to continuing insistent of President Obama to keep Social Security &#8216;on the table&#8217;.  Dean Baker has a take on some numbers surrounding the politics and stories politicans offer:  </p>
<blockquote><p>While most of the DC insiders probably don&#8217;t understand the chained CPI, everyone else should recognize that this technical fix amounts to a serious cut in benefits. It reduces benefits compared to the current schedule by 0.3 percent annually. This adds up through time. After someone has been getting benefits for 10 years, the cut in annual benefits is 3 percent. After 20 years, people would be seeing a benefit that is 6 percent lower, and after 30 years their benefit would be reduced by 9 percent. (AARP has a nice calculator which shows how much retirees can expect to lose from the chained CPI.)</p>
<p>We can debate whether the chained CPI benefit cut should be viewed as &#8220;large,&#8221; but there is no debate that chained CPI cut is a bigger hit to the typical retiree than the ending of the Bush tax cuts were to the typical high-end earner. Social Security provides more than half of the income for almost 70 percent of retirees. This means that the 3 percent cut in Social Security benefits amounts to a reduction in their income of more than 1.5 percent.</p>
<p>By contrast, if a wealthy couple has an income of $500,000 a year, as a result of President Obama&#8217;s tax hikes, they would be paying an addition three percentage points in taxes, or $3,000, on the income above $400,000. That comes to just 0.6 percent of their income.</p>
<p>If the proponents of using the chained CPI to cut Social Security want to claim that this cut is not a big deal, then they must also believe that the tax increases on the wealthy were not a big deal. That&#8217;s what the arithmetic says, and there is no way around it.</p></blockquote>
<p>(h/t Nancy Ortiz)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/dean-baker-on-social-security-and-obama.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rep Marsha Blackburn&#8217;s snow job. Explains how Social Security money flows</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/rep-marsha-blackburns-snow-job-explains-how-social-security-money-flows.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/rep-marsha-blackburns-snow-job-explains-how-social-security-money-flows.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 16 Feb 2013 04:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[C-span]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[entitlements reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[IOU's]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Marsha Blackburn]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medicaid]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medicare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[trust funds]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/rep-marsha-blackburns-snow-job-explains-how-social-security-money-flows.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[                                                                                                                                                                   I was watching C span Washington Journal this morning.  Rep Marsha Blackburn was the guest.  I got to listen to her explanation of how the Social Security funds flow and just had to post the clip.   Copied from the transcript of the clip: THEIRS MONEY THAT GOES TO MEDICARE AND SOCIAL SECURITY AND I [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>                                                                                                                                                                   I was watching C span Washington Journal this morning.  Rep Marsha Blackburn was the guest.  I got to listen to her explanation of how the Social Security funds flow and just had to post the clip.   Copied from the transcript of the clip:</p>
<blockquote><p>THEIRS MONEY THAT GOES TO MEDICARE AND SOCIAL SECURITY AND I THINK IT IS JUST IS SO  INAPPROPRIATE THAT THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT DOES NOT USE THAT AS A TRUST FUND BUT THEY MOVE  IMMEDIATELY TO THE GENERAL FUND  AND STACK UP IOU&#8217;S THAT ARE  SITTING IN A CABINET IN WEST VIRGINIA. </p></blockquote>
<p>What she says should not be allowed to stand and if C-span were half of what it used to be, she would not have had the following go uncorrected.  Thus I leave it to the Angry Bears to correct her here and thus document her ignorance of the subject.  <br /><a href="http://www.c-spanvideo.org/clip/4360645&#038;newclip" target="_blank"></a></p>
<p>I have not watched this lady before.  I could not help but think she is just a more polished version of Sarah Palin. She is totally capable of pulling off what we used to call a &#8220;snow job&#8221; when writing their essay.  </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/rep-marsha-blackburns-snow-job-explains-how-social-security-money-flows.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Carpe David Brooks. Before He Drives Me Crazy. [Freudian typo now corrected. 3:25 p.m.]</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/carpe-david-brooks-before-he-drives-me-crazy-freudian-typo-now-corrected-325-p-m.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/carpe-david-brooks-before-he-drives-me-crazy-freudian-typo-now-corrected-325-p-m.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2013 18:54:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[David Brooks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Innovation Economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medicare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Robert D. Atkinson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stephen J. Ezell]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The New York Times]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/carpe-david-brooks-before-he-drives-me-crazy-freudian-typo-now-corrected-325-p-m.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[An exchange between reader nitu mishra and me in the Comments thread this morning to this AB post of mine from yesterday. nitu mishra: Here’s a good article on 2012 Q4 earnings outlook. http://tinyurl.com/investing002 Me: Ah. If only I could actually understand graphs, without having to stare at them for ten minutes or so first, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>An exchange between reader nitu mishra and me in the Comments thread this morning to <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/02/the-national-review-invites-obama-to.html">this AB post of mine </a>from yesterday.
<div dir="ltr">nitu mishra: </p>
</div>
<div dir="ltr">Here’s a good article on 2012 Q4 earnings outlook.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">http://tinyurl.com/investing002</p>
</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Me: </p>
</div>
<div dir="ltr">Ah. If only I could actually understand graphs, without having to stare at them for ten minutes or so first, Nitu. But I don’t have to understand the graph posted at that url to know that corporate earnings are TANKING.  I know that because I already read David Brooks’s column today, and he says that Obama should propose a cut in corporate tax rates, because corporations need to have money to use for INVESTMENTS.  And of course Brooks wouldn’t say that unless corporate profits* ARE tanking and corporations, well, just can’t afford to invest.  They need further tax breaks in order to have the money to do that!</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Like Apple. </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">(And, pleeeeease: No one post that aggregate U.S. corporate profits are at all-time highs and that corporations are HOARDING their profits rather than using them to invest.  I know that. My comment is facetious.) </div>
<p>I’m back on <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/01/oh-no-david-brooks-thinks-social_29.html">my David-Brooks-formulaic-conflations watch</a> today, because, well, he has another column in today’s Times.  And (surprise!) it’s another classic I’ve-found-the-secret-formula-for-phoning-in-NYT-columns column.  So I can’t resist.</p>
<p>The formula, of course, as anyone who reads his columns even occasionally knows, is to summarize a new book he’s read about economic or social trends (or both!) and then use the last two or three paragraphs of the column to string together conclusions that are either non sequiturs to the information or ideas he’s just summarized from the book, or to state unexplained conclusions that are contrary to that information or those ideas and pretend that the information or ideas support those conclusions.</p>
<p>It’s easy.  And it’s a very nice gig. </p>
<p><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/12/opinion/brooks-carpe-diem-nation.html?_r=0">Today’s offering</a> is based on a book called “Innovation Economics.”  I’ve selected two excerpts from the column, that, I trust, together illustrate my point.  The first, from early in the column, is:</p>
<div dir="ltr">As Robert D. Atkinson and Stephen J. Ezell note in their book “Innovation Economics,” American firms are also lagging in their commitment to research and development. Between 1999 and 2006, for example, German firms increased research-and-development spending by 11 percent, Finnish firms by 28 percent and South Korean firms by 58 percent. During that same period, U.S. spending increased by a paltry 3 percent.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Increasingly, companies have to spend their money on retirees, not future growth. Last week, for example, Ford announced that it was spending $5 billion to shore up its pension program. That’s an amount nearly equal to Ford’s investments in factories, equipment and innovation.</div>
<p>And then the denouement:</p>
<div dir="ltr">The political debate, though, is largely oblivious to this mental shift. Republicans and Democrats are so busy arguing about the merits of government versus business that they are blind to the problem that afflicts them both.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">In his State of the Union address Tuesday night, President Obama is apparently planning to give us yet another salvo in that left-right war, as he did in his second Inaugural Address. One of his aides, in a fit of hubris, told Politico that the president will be offering Republicans a golden bridge to ease their retreat.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">But it would be great if Obama gave an imaginative speech that reframed things as present versus future.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">If the president were to propose an agenda for the future, he’d double spending on the National Institutes of Health. He’d approve the Keystone XL pipeline. He’d cut corporate tax rates while adding a progressive consumption tax. He’d take money from Social Security and build Harlem Children’s Zone-type projects across the nation. He’d means test Medicare and use the money to revive state universities and pay down debt.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Would Americans buy that agenda? Maybe. Americans are neglecting the future, but I bet they’re still in love with it.</div>
<p>The title of the column is “Carpe Diem Nation.”  The first excerpt is noteworthy both for its statistics and for the fact that Brooks has built a career on trashing European economic policy and culture as anti-entrepreneurial.  The second excerpt would be notable for its vertigo inducement, were vertigo inducement not a regular part of the formula, column after column.  But it is, so it’s not notable.  </p>
<p>In between those two excerpts, Brooks apprises readers who aren’t regulars, and who therefore don’t know, that his real purpose is to argue for the dismembering of the social safety network for the elderly, because, well, we couldn’t possibly raise taxes to cover that social safety network, as they do in, say, Germany and Finland.**  Raising FICA taxes very slightly would take care of Social Security needs, but rather than do that, or to raise taxes on upper-income folks and on corporations to Clinton-era levels, it’s better to remove basic sustenance income from millions of elderly if we want to build Harlem Children’s Zone-type projects across the nation.  <a name="more"></a></p>
<p>This is true especially regarding corporate taxes, since record corporate profits and outright hoarding of those profits by corporations doesn’t mean that increasing their taxes by raising tax rates or by closing loopholes would be a better investment for the country than reducing corporate taxes even further. I mean, you never know when Apple might conclude that it finally has enough after-tax profits to start investing them in research and development. </p>
<p>Of course, seniors who rely entirely or mainly on Social Security benefits and Medicare aren’t known for their dedication to Apple MacBooks, iPhones and iPads, so there’s no real need to worry that a reduction in those seniors’ meager income would hurt the economy by depriving Apple of enough money to enable the company to invest. </p>
<p>So carpe diem to cut taxes on corporations while ending Medicare and Social Security.  Just like Germany and Finland. If it’s the future that you’re interested in. 
<div></div>
<div>&#8212;-</div>
<div>*<i>The post originally said &#8220;corporate taxes ARE tanking&#8230;.&#8221;  That was a typo.  Or maybe a Freudian slip.</i><br /><i><br /></i><i>**Sentence was corrected to correct two typos&#8211;and to make sense. 11:21 p.m.</i></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/carpe-david-brooks-before-he-drives-me-crazy-freudian-typo-now-corrected-325-p-m.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>NW Plan for Social Security: Abridged Spreadsheet</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/nw-plan-for-social-security-abridged-spreadsheet.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/nw-plan-for-social-security-abridged-spreadsheet.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 10 Feb 2013 20:18:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[northwest plan for a real social security fix]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security trust funds]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/nw-plan-for-social-security-abridged-spreadsheet.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[First attempt at putting the NW Plan 2012 into viewable form. This graphic compresses the original spreadsheet in both axes. I will be putting links to the full spreadsheet in comments because I am not sure this one will share correctly (I am bouncing between Google Accts) link. In any event the key columns are [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-3RiiUnlnd64/URftkN8SAvI/AAAAAAAABSo/ZqVUcKDnevQ/s1600/NW+2012+Cropped.jpg" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-3RiiUnlnd64/URftkN8SAvI/AAAAAAAABSo/ZqVUcKDnevQ/s1600/NW+2012+Cropped.jpg" height="217" width="320"></a></div>
<p>First attempt at putting the NW Plan 2012 into viewable form. This graphic compresses the original spreadsheet in both axes. I will be putting links to the full spreadsheet in comments because I am not sure this one will share correctly (I am bouncing between Google Accts) <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0AoHUzhAPMGaLdEJRejlCcGg1QTU3Ym1tUzE2LUJJenc#gid=0" target="_blank">link</a>.</p>
<p>In any event the key columns are those marked NEW, especially the fourth column from the left &#8216;New Payroll Tax Rate&#8217; and the last two &#8216;New Calculated Trust Fund&#8217; and &#8216;New Trust Fund Ratio&#8217;.</p>
<p>This version of the spreadsheet terminates at 2045 simply because of graphic limitations, the original extends right through the 75 year window, but the key factor is that the Trust Fund Ratio stabilizes right at the 125 level right into the 2080s and still remains above 100 through the end of the range. In Social Security talk this means the NW Plan passes the Long Term Actuarial Balance test but just fails to meet the threshold for the stricter Sustainable Solvency measure which requires the TF Ratio to be trending at least slightly up.</p>
<p>On a final note. In the 2012 based NW Plan year end TF balances never drop in nominal terms meaning there is NEVER any net redemption of Trust Fund Principal. Which throws a whole new light on the asset/debt conundrum. But of that more in comments.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/nw-plan-for-social-security-abridged-spreadsheet.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
