<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>11 September &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Ten Years Gone</title>
		<link>./../../2011/09/ten-years-gone.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/09/ten-years-gone.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 11 Sep 2011 20:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[11 September]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[history]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/09/ten-years-gone.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[NYTBR, 11 September 2011 Ten years ago today, nineteen people, including fifteen Saudis&#8211;using funding from the House of Saud and led by a distinguished member of that House&#8211;used airplanes to attack the U.S., destroying the World Trade Towers, damaging the Pentagon, and being prevented from attacking the White House only by the heroic efforts of [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>NYTBR, 11 September 2011</p>
<p>Ten years ago today, nineteen people, including fifteen Saudis&#8211;using funding from the House of Saud and led by a distinguished member of that House&#8211;used airplanes to attack the U.S., destroying the World Trade Towers, damaging the Pentagon, and being prevented from attacking the White House only by the heroic efforts of passengers on board the fourth plane and a suicide mission by an unarmed U.S. fighter jet.</p>
<p>Fortunately, there was quick action from President Bush and his Administration. They detained all fourteen of Osama bin Laden&#8217;s relatives in the United States, interrogating each. This was followed by the execution of surgical strikes within Afghanistan, where Osama bin Laden himself was hiding. By the time Special Forces troops captured him in the caves near Tora Bora, in part due to intelligence gained from his relatives, domestic uprisings and U.N. support led to the overthrow of the Taliban government.<br /><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>There were rumors there would be war with Saudi Arabia. But he Administration enacted high-level discussions (using, allegedly, some still-classified data as incentives) that were quickly followed by regime change in Saudi Arabia. That country&#8217;s new leaders provided compensation for costs and victims, as well as intelligence on previously unknown Pakistani participation.</p>
<p>On the domestic front, Rudolph Giuliani&#8211;who had moved the NYC Emergency Response headquarters from the safety of the basement of One Police Plaza to the 25th floor of a building that had been attacked eight years before, and who declared spending money on upgrading communications equipment for firefighters a waste&#8211;was barely saved from a Lynch mob of New Yorkers. He is rumored to have moved to Arizona, having been shunned by the President and the news media.</p>
<p>So now, ten years later, we find some American authors writing alternative histories about that time. The most recent, and one of the most absurd, is Philip Roth&#8217;s <em>Becoming Who We Are</em>, in which the Bush Administration assists the Bin Laden family in flying out of the United States (even before domestic commercial flights resume), becomes even closer to the Saudi leadership (there is a scene in the novel of Bush holding hands with the Saudi King while posing for photographs), and declares war on Iraq.</p>
<p>Even more problematic, Roth imagines Giuliani being touted as a hero, while the Bush Administration tortures prisoners, committing what most readers will correctly view as war crimes.</p>
<p>Perhaps saddest of all, Roth postulates an uprising of &#8220;Christian Conservatives&#8221; who vociferously and repeatedly applaud both of the murder of hundreds of thousands of innocent civilians and wanton torture of prisoners—and who, in this novel, are largely credited with re-electing President Bush despite those revelations and an economy driven to stagnation by war—cheering the mere suggestion that an execution, even of someone who is clearly innocent, will occur. After Roth&#8217;s frequent but appropriate mention of &#8220;blood libel&#8221; in <em>The Plot Against America</em>, one probably ought not be surprised that some &#8220;Christian&#8221; characters of this novel would act in such a manner, but it is a daunting leap of faith nonetheless. (That Roth&#8217;s narrator is aware enough to note that it is not the &#8220;Christians,&#8221; but rather those in the highest income brackets who are—for the first time in United States history—not taxed to pay for a war who make the difference in the 2004 election arguably is even more damning of his portrayal.)</p>
<p>Roth has had a long and noble career, and his recent forays into alternative history&#8211;most notably his portrayal of <a href="http://delong.typepad.com/sdj/2011/09/liveblogging-world-war-ii-september-11-1941.html">leading isolationist Charles Lindbergh</a> [link added] in the aforementioned novel&#8211;have been based in a deep knowledge of the way those personages acted publicly and privately.  That he would undermine that with an absurdist piece in which the President of the United States squanders opportunities and weakens his own country by starting multiple wars is unfortunate at best. We can only hope Mr. Roth&#8217;s next work recovers the historical veracity for which he is known, rather than this deranged flight of fancy.</p>
<p><em>Becoming Who We Are</em>, by Philip Roth, Houghton Mifflin, 432 pages, $27.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/09/ten-years-gone.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Time Series Analysis</title>
		<link>./../../2009/09/time-series-analysis.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/09/time-series-analysis.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 07 Sep 2009 22:59:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[11 September]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bush Administration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[environment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obama appointment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/09/time-series-analysis.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[From what I can tell, this is an accurate sequence: 6 August 2001: Presidential Daily Briefing (PDB) given to GWB entitled &#8220;bin Ladin Determined to Strike in US.&#8221; 11 September 2001: On the 36th Anniversary of Augusto Pinochet&#8217;s US-President-ordered, CIA-supported, Coup in Chile, Bin Laden&#8217;s forces, weel, strike in the US. ca. 26 October 2004: [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>From what I can tell, this is an accurate sequence:</p>
<ol>
<li><a target="_blank" href="http://news.findlaw.com/hdocs/docs/terrorism/80601pdb.html">6 August 2001</a>: Presidential Daily Briefing (PDB) given to GWB entitled &#8220;bin Ladin Determined to Strike in US.&#8221;</p>
</li>
<li>11 September 2001:  On the 36th Anniversary of <a target="_blank" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1973_Chilean_coup_d'%C3%A9tat#U.S._Role">Augusto Pinochet&#8217;s US-President-ordered, CIA-supported, Coup in Chile</a>, Bin Laden&#8217;s forces, weel, <a href="http://www.cnn.com/SPECIALS/2001/memorial/">strike in the US</a>.
</li>
<li><a target="_blank" href="http://www.911truth.org/article.php?story=20041026093059633">ca. 26 October 2004</a>: Anthony &#8220;Van&#8221; Jones signs &#8220;truth petition&#8221; which requests investigation into, among other things, &#8220;<a target="_blank" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Van_Jones#9.2F11_Truth_petition">unanswered questions that suggest that people within the current administration may indeed have deliberately allowed 9/11 to happen</a>.&#8221;
</li>
<li>04 September 2006:  Condoleezza Rice admits (1) above <a target="_blank" href="http://crooksandliars.com/2006/09/05/condoleezza-rice-facing-ben-veniste-9-11-commission">publicly at the 9-11 Commission hearings</a>, eliminating the last vestige of plausible* deniability about foreknowledge of the attacks within, and at the highest levels of, the Administration.
</li>
<li>06 September 2009:  Three years and three days after Ms. Rice admitted that the GWB Administration—in the kindest possible interpretation—allowed 11 Sep 2001 to happen,** Van Jones resigns from the current Administration because he (along with John <em>Men are from Mars, Women are from Venus</em> Gray, a former Bush Administraion official, and a previous Ambassador to Iraq) exercised an American&#8217;s First Amendment rights (&#8220;<a target="_blank" href="http://www.law.cornell.edu/constitution/constitution.billofrights.html#amendmenti">to petition the government for a redress of grievances</a>&#8220;)  with a resulting inquiry that confirmed the justness of the original Petition.</li>
</ol>
<p>Don&#8217;t worry; nothing to see there. Right?</p>
<p>*No, declaring that you considered the PDB to be a discussion of &#8220;history&#8221; is not plausible in any real sense of that word.<br />**Whether as an act of malice or incompetence is left as an exercise, with the clear possibility of a spectrum of answers depending upon which officials are discussed.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/09/time-series-analysis.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
