<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>book reviews &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Presimetrics Review</title>
		<link>./../../2011/10/presimetrics-review.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/10/presimetrics-review.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 22 Oct 2011 18:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[book reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Presimetrics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[research]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/10/presimetrics-review.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Noted for the record: author Piaw Na reviews Mike Kimel&#8216;s Presimetrics at Piaw&#8217;s Blog: This is a great book to read if you&#8217;ve got a statistical bent and are willing to follow the data rather than your pre-conceived notions&#8230;.Many people like to say that they&#8217;re data-driven, but most people actually have prejudices that lead them [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Noted for the record: <a href="http://books.piaw.net/">author Piaw Na</a> reviews <a href="http://presimetrics.com/">Mike Kimel</a>&#8216;s <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Presimetrics-Facts-Presidents-Measure-Issues/dp/1579128351/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&#038;ie=UTF8&#038;qid=1319308574&#038;sr=1-1">Presimetrics</a> at <a href="http://piaw.blogspot.com/">Piaw&#8217;s Blog</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>This is a great book to read if you&#8217;ve got a statistical bent and are willing to follow the data rather than your pre-conceived notions&#8230;.Many people like to say that they&#8217;re data-driven, but most people actually have prejudices that lead them to believe what they believe, as opposed to actually looking into data and correlations. This book goes a long way towards providing those who want data the actual data with which to base their beliefs on&#8230;.This is the kind of book that deserves to sell better than it does. Highly Recommended.</p></blockquote>
<p>I left out all the good parts, so <a href="http://piaw.blogspot.com/2011/10/review-presimetrics.html">Go Read the Whole Thing</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/10/presimetrics-review.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Deficit: Why Should I Care?</title>
		<link>./../../2011/08/deficit-why-should-i-care.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/08/deficit-why-should-i-care.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2011 16:18:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[book reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[budget deficits]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/08/deficit-why-should-i-care.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Mike Kimel Hi folks! Long time readers probably know I&#8217;ve been haranguing on the deficit and the national debt for a long time. Last week I got an e-mail telling me about a new book called “Deficit: Why Should I Care?” by Marie Bussing-Burks. I had never heard of either the book or Ms. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by <strong>Mike Kimel</strong></p>
<p>Hi folks!  Long time readers probably know I&#8217;ve been haranguing on the deficit and the national debt for a long time. Last week I got an e-mail telling me about a new book called “Deficit: Why Should I Care?” by Marie Bussing-Burks.  I had never heard of either the book or Ms. Bussing-Burks, but the topic was interesting.  I was offered the opportunity to read a pdf version of the book.  That isn&#8217;t unusual &#8211; such offers seem to arrive at Angry Bear&#8217;s doorstep on a regular basis.</p>
<p>What is unusual though, is that I&#8217;ve read through much of the book already, and unlike most books purportedly written about the topic, I can safely recommend it to anyone who wants to learn more.  It is factual, interesting, well written, very informative and seems to be a fairly unbiased treatment of the issue.  That isn&#8217;t to say I agree with everything in the book, but I do think the book is very good.  Dan has arranged with the publisher for 50% discounts to be made available to any Angry Bear readers who  buy it between now and September 5.<br />
<br /><a name="more"></a><br />
<br />FYI, I looked up Ms. Bussing-Burks and found she is an assistant professor at the University of Southern Indiana.  </p>
<p>Full disclosure &#8211; I do not know anyone at the publisher nor Ms. Bussing-Burks.  Furthermore, I did not receive nor will I receive anything for having written any of the above. </p>
<p>(Rdan here&#8230;go to <a target="_blank" href="http://www.apress.com/catalogsearch/result/?q=deficit&#038;submit=Go">apress</a>, then click &#8216;your cart&#8217;, and on the e-book selction, add the coupon code <strong>DeficitABB</strong> in the appropriate box and follow the instructions for the discount)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/08/deficit-why-should-i-care.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
