<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>CDO &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The Meaning of &#034;Monty Python and the Meaning of Life&#034;</title>
		<link>./../../2010/02/the-meaning-of-monty-python-and-the-meaning-of-life.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/02/the-meaning-of-monty-python-and-the-meaning-of-life.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 06 Feb 2010 20:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Barry Ritholtz]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CDO]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[equilibrium theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mortgage markets]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[securitization]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[solvency crisis]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/02/the-meaning-of-monty-python-and-the-meaning-of-life.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Robert Waldmann Barry Ritholtz argues that the problem with mortgages was underwriting standards and not securitization. He appeals to the very great authority of Monty Python. Click the link. Ritholtz seems not to be familiar with this new idea in economic theory called &#8220;Nash equilibrium&#8221;. Over -rated yes. Totally irrelevant not so much. One can [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Robert Waldmann</p>
<p>Barry Ritholtz argues that the problem with mortgages was underwriting standards and not securitization.  He appeals to the very great authority of Monty Python.  Click <a href="http://www.ritholtz.com/blog/2010/02/how-can-lending-be-made-safer/?utm_source=feedburner&#038;utm_medium=feed&#038;utm_campaign=Feed%3A+TheBigPicture+%28The+Big+Picture%29">the link</a>.</p>
<p>Ritholtz seems not to be familiar with this new idea in economic theory called &#8220;Nash equilibrium&#8221;.  Over -rated yes.  Totally irrelevant not so much.  One can not assume that underwriting standards are exogenous.  If there had been no MBS, no firm would have underwritten those mortgages.  It was exactly because it was possible to blend them, and then sell them to people who didn&#8217;t spin the mortgage tapes before buying, that the mortgages existed in the first place.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Let me work with his analogy.  First, while I have great respect for the Monty Python team, few people have been killed by canned Salmon.   Even blended into mousse, it kills fairly quickly and can be tracked back to the canner.  The way bacteria work is that if you mix some contaminated stuff with other stuff you have trouble for sure.  It doesn&#8217;t work that things seem fine until people notice.  </p>
<p>At a way lower cultural level than Ritholtz I appeal to road runner cartoons.  Wile E. Coyote runs along in mid air until he notices.  Then he falls.  As noted by everyone, this is the way financial markets really work.  The non Monty Python quality  humor is based on the fact  that gravity doesn&#8217;t really work that way.  Neither do bacteria.  Analogies between rotten mortgages and rotten Salmon fail for this reason.</p>
<p>Notably, the ingredients in the Salmon mousse are few enough that the dead diners immediately know what went wrong when death points at the mousse.  That&#8217;s not the way MBS work let alone CDOs of MBSs or CDOS of tranches of CDOS.  </p>
<p>A better analogy would be making hamburger.  Bits from hundreds of steers end up in the same package at the supermarket.  If one bit has E. coli on it, you can get sick.  If they tried to sell you that bit, you wouldn&#8217;t buy it because it would stink.  However, mixed in with hundreds of uncontaminated bits of beef, it doesn&#8217;t stink.</p>
<p>Is there a hamburger problem?  Yes there is.  One is much more likely to get food poisoning from hamburger than from unprocessed meat.  Is the solution special regulation of hamburger?  It sure is.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/02/the-meaning-of-monty-python-and-the-meaning-of-life.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Why didn&#8217;t CDO purchasers just pool for themselves ?</title>
		<link>./../../2009/09/why-didnt-cdo-purchasers-just-pool-for-themselves.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/09/why-didnt-cdo-purchasers-just-pool-for-themselves.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 21 Sep 2009 22:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[asymmetrical information]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bank Crisis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CDO]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tranche]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/09/why-didnt-cdo-purchasers-just-pool-for-themselves.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Robert Waldmann One brief question about structured finance and a possible answer. Why did investors need financial operators to make pools for them ? Now it is easier to make sense of financial intermediaries which pool than of those which pool and tranche. The obvious explanation is that an investor investing a small amount of [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Robert Waldmann</p>
<p>One brief question about structured finance and a possible answer.  Why did investors need financial operators to make pools for them ?   Now it is easier to make sense of financial intermediaries which pool than of those which pool and tranche.  The obvious explanation is that an investor investing a small amount of money can&#8217;t buy a diversified portfolio without paying absurd amounts in odd lot fees.</p>
<p>However, this doesn&#8217;t seem to fit the CDO market.  Correct me in comments if I&#8217;m wrong, but I thought the final investors were entities with a good bit of money to invest &#8212; pension funds, endowments, insurance companies etc.  Importantly one can achieve almost as good a risk return portfolio buying only assets in a randomly chosen subset of say 10% of all assets.  The variance of a portfolio is a sum of say the market variance plus &#8230; plus idiosyncratic variance on single assets.  So a term which can&#8217;t be diversified away plus stuff plus terms which are proportional to the inverse of the number of assets in the portfolio.</p>
<p>I have an idea.  People investing other people&#8217;s money in fixed income instruments do not like to pool, because it is too easy ex post to find a better portfolio of fixed income instruments.  Some will default.  The principal is likely to note one bond that defaulted and ask the manager why he bought that bond not the similar one which didn&#8217;t default.  </p>
<p>Letting someone else pool means you get an asset which pays a fairly high fairly safe return and those ugly but unimportant specific underlying assets which defaulted are hiden from the principal&#8217;s eyes.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/09/why-didnt-cdo-purchasers-just-pool-for-themselves.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
