<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>income inequality &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Wealth: It&#8217;s Not for Everyone</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/wealth-its-not-for-everyone.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/wealth-its-not-for-everyone.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2013 22:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[econospeak]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income inequality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Inequality of wealth or income]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sandwichman]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/wealth-its-not-for-everyone.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Via Sandwichman at Econospeak comes this well done video on Wealth: It&#8217;s Not for Everyone, which is going to 3 million views from facebook, reddit, and elswhere:]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Via <a href="http://econospeak.blogspot.com/2013/03/one-of-its-anti-growth-crowd-got-about.html" target="_blank">Sandwichman</a> at <i>Econospeak</i> comes this well done video on Wealth: It&#8217;s Not for Everyone, which is going to 3 million views from facebook, reddit, and elswhere:</p>
<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/wealth-its-not-for-everyone.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mark Thoma presses the issue of increasing income inequality</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/mark-thoma-presses-the-issue-of-increasing-income-inequality.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/mark-thoma-presses-the-issue-of-increasing-income-inequality.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 28 Oct 2012 11:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2012 Presidential elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income inequality]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/mark-thoma-presses-the-issue-of-increasing-income-inequality.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Mark Thoma  presses the issue of increasing income inequality: Via an email from Lane Kenworthy, here&#8217;s more research contradicting the claim made by Kevin Hassett and Aparna Mathur in the WSJ that consumption inequality has not increased (here&#8217;s my response summarizing additional work contradicting their claim, a claim that is really an attempt to blunt [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>Mark Thoma  presses the issue of increasing income inequality:</p>
</div>
<blockquote><p>Via an email from Lane Kenworthy, here&#8217;s more research contradicting the claim made by Kevin Hassett and Aparna Mathur in the WSJ that consumption inequality has not increased (here&#8217;s <a href="http://economistsview.typepad.com/economistsview/2012/10/the-myth-that-growing-consumption-inequality-is-a-myth.html">my response</a> summarizing additional work contradicting their claim, a claim that is really an attempt to blunt the call to use taxation to address the growing inequality problem):</p>
<p><a href="http://www.russellsage.org/research/reports/consumption-inequality">Inequality of Income and Consumption: Measuring the Trends in Inequality from 1985-2010 for the Same Individuals, by Jonathan Fisher, David S. Johnson, and Timothy M. Smeeding</a>: <strong>I. Introduction: Income and Consumption</strong> The 2012 Economic Report of the President stated: “The confluence of rising inequality and low economic mobility over the past three decades poses a real threat to the United States as a land of opportunity.” This view was also repeated in a speech by Council of Economics Advisors Chairman, Alan Krueger (2012). President Obama suggested that inequality was “…the defining issue of our time&#8230;” As suggested by Isabel Sawhill (2012), 2011 was the year of inequality.</p>
<p>Recent research shows that income inequality has increased over the past three decades (Burkhauser, et al. (2012), Smeeding and Thompson (2011), CBO (2011), Atkinson, Piketty and Saez (2011)). And most research suggests that this increase is mainly due to the larger increase in income at the very top of the distribution (see CBO (2011) and Saez (2012)). Researchers, however, dispute the extent of the increase. The extent of the increase depends on the resource measure used (income or consumption), the definition of the resource measure (e.g., market income or after-tax income), and the population of interest.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>This paper examines the distribution of income and consumption in the US using data that obtains measures of both income and consumption from the same set of individuals and this paper develops a set of inequality measures that show the increase in inequality during the past 25 years using the 1984-2010 Consumer Expenditure (CE) Survey.<br />The dispute over whether income or consumption should be preferred as a measure of economic well-being is discussed in the National Academy of Sciences (NAS) report on poverty measurement (Citro and Michael (1995), p. 36). The NAS report argues:</p>
<blockquote><p>Conceptually, an income definition is more appropriate to the view that what matters is a family’s ability to attain a living standard above the poverty level by means of its own resources…. In contrast to an income definition, an expenditure (or consumption) definition is more appropriate to the view that what matters is someone’s actual standard of living, regardless of how it is attained. In practice the availability of high-quality data is often a prime determinant of whether an incomeor expenditure-based family resource definition is used.</p></blockquote>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/mark-thoma-presses-the-issue-of-increasing-income-inequality.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Growing inequality calls for both &#034;predistribution&#034; and (rightly directed) redistribution</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/growing-inequality-calls-for-both-predistribution-and-rightly-directed-redistribution.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/growing-inequality-calls-for-both-predistribution-and-rightly-directed-redistribution.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 24 Oct 2012 10:22:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[income inequality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linda Beale (Tax law)]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/growing-inequality-calls-for-both-predistribution-and-rightly-directed-redistribution.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Beale Growing inequality calls for both &#8220;predistribution&#8221; and (rightly directed) redistribution In putting forward my theme of democratic egalitarianism, I have often noted that there is no such thing as an economically egalitarian society&#8211;there will always be differentials among people, those differences often relate to social class and the education, privileged upbringing, and [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Linda Beale</p>
<p>Growing inequality calls for both &#8220;predistribution&#8221; and (rightly directed) redistribution</p>
<p>In putting forward my theme of <em>democratic egalitarianism</em>, I have often noted that there is no such thing as an economically egalitarian society&#8211;there will always be differentials among people, those differences often relate to social class and the education, privileged upbringing, and networking connections that ensure success for some and deny success to others as well as to innate abilities, so that those differences inevitably translate into some being better off economically than others.   </p>
<p>Because of those differences, the &#8220;powers that be&#8221;&#8211;i.e., existing concentrations of financial assets, prestige and associated political power among the privileged class at the very top of the income and wealth distribution&#8211; result in<em> redistribution </em><em>upwards</em> from poor and middle class to the upper crust.  And most in that privileged upper-crust think they&#8217;ve acquired it all on the basis of their own merit and that the reason others don&#8217;t have it is because they are irresponsible, don&#8217;t work hard enough, don&#8217;t have a good business sense or are just incompetent. </p>
<p>(That is of course the tale told by the like of Mitt Romney at his private fundraiser in Flordia, where he revealed his utter disdain for half of the US population and his self-indulging belief that he got where he is entirely on his own merit .  He can&#8217;t even see, much less acknowledge, either his silver-spoon upbringing of class, wealth and connections or the various government-subsidized upwards redistribution from which he has benefited through capital gains preferences, carried interest treatment, disregard of the harm caused by his leveraged-buyout business model, and government subsidies through high-value government contracts and low-cost government loans.) </p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Therefore, I have argued,  democratic institutions (government, programs, policies) must target achieving a sustainable economy that provides a decent livelihood for all.  They must also prevent inordinate inequality, because huge inequality among the citizenry foils all attempts to achieve either a sustainable economy or sustainable democratic institutions. </p>
<p>That means that government policies must focus on creating paths for <em>redistribution</em><em>downwards</em> from the upper crust to the middle and lower classes, undoing the corporatist top-down approach that has supported <em>class warfare</em> and allowed the wealthy to capture most of the productivity gains since Reagan&#8217;s presidency.  Two government systems can work, on the margins, to achieve some level of downwards redistribution&#8211;benefits and taxes.  Benefits do so by providing a safety net under those most vulnerable who have never achieved a sustainable economic livelihood&#8211;the unemployed and unemployable, the sick, the elderly, the children who have poor schools, poor families, and inadequate shelter, nutrition and opportunity.  Taxes do so by taking more from those who have grabbed an inordinate portion of the resource pie and using those revenues to fund benefits as well as infrastructure (human and physical) that supports the efforts by ordinary Americans to achieve sustainable livelihoods.</p>
<p>We have been moving backwards on both of these systems.  The radical right has spent the last 30-40 years pushing an agenda that ultimately wants to (i) dismantle or radically reduce benefits programs (voucherizing medicare, privatizing social security, cutting back on unemployment, allowing states to reduce medicaid and children&#8217;s health coverage, etc.) and (ii) eliminate taxes on corporations and the primary source of income of high-wealth individuals through a gradual reduction in progressive rate structure, elimination of the estate tax, elimination of capital gains taxes (and treatment of wealthy people&#8217;s wages as though they were capital gains, through provisions like stock options and carried interest).  Paul Ryan&#8217;s positions on Medicare and Social Security should be a clarion-call to get out the vote&#8211;against the Romney-Ryan ticket&#8211; of every person who does not earn more than $300,000 a year.   The Norquist-Koch Brothers-Karl Rove-Ryan-Romney agenda on taxes should similarly cause ordinary Americans who earn less than $300,000 a year to take to the streets and to refuse to vote for any member of the GOP.</p>
<p> Recall that the beginning of the current trend towards too little tax revenues and especially too little taxation of the ultra rich was radical reduction of rates with purported base-broadening (such as elimination of the capital gains preference, creation and then ramping up of the alternative minimum tax).  As could be expected, lower rates lived on (and were lowered even more by Bush) but much of the base broadening was short-lived:  lobbying by the privileged at the top led to a quick return to a capital gains preference and the undoing of the AMT as an inequality leveler.  The Bush tax cuts rewarded corporate owners and managers and the wealthy class with extraordinary tax relief, while imposing long-term deficits on the country, behind a cheerful facade of &#8220;tax simplification&#8221; that was irrelevant for the 70% of the population that uses the standard deduction.</p>
<p>There is a third leg to the reduction-of-inequality stool.  Tax reform that restores a truly progressive income tax is one leg.  Benefit reform that builds on the achievements of the New Deal rather than destroying them is another.  The third leg is what some call &#8220;predistribution&#8221;&#8211;paying attention to the means by which the uppercrust has seized all of the productivity gains and reduced the ability of everyone else to have a decent, sustainable livelihood. </p>
<p>British Labour leader Ed Miliband has called for predistribution as a new agenda in Britain.  See <em>Predistribution: A Big New Idea</em>, Noted, The Nation (Oct. 8, 2012), at 5. <br />The term [predistribution] was coined by US political scientist Jacob Hacker, who in 2011 noted that discussions of government responses to inequality often begin and end with redistribution [downwards]&#8211;taxing the rich to provide benefits for the rest.  But that&#8217;s only half the equation, Hacker said, uring progressives to pay more attention to &#8216;the way in which the market distributes its rewards in the first place.&#8217; That includes regulations that protect consumers and empower workers: &#8216;The regulation of markets to limit extremes and give the middle class more voice is hardly easy. &#8230; But it is both more popular and more effective than after-the-fact mopping up.&#8217;</p>
<p>Milibrand agrees.  Noting the high human cost of austerity, he said, &#8216;We need to care about predistribution as well as redistribution.&#8217; After trying &#8216;to make work pay better by spending more on trasfer payments,&#8217; he argued, government must &#8216;also make work pay better by making work itself pay.&#8217;</p>
<p>These concepts&#8211;predistribution (making up for malfunctioning markets to make work itself pay) and redistribution downwards (actual reallocation from market results through taxation and benefit policies)&#8211;are closely interrelated.  Successful redistribution downwards augments the ability of workers to afford necessities and small luxuries, and that economic activity empowers workers in the markets and gives workers an opportunity for a voice in the markets and workplaces compared to a position where employers and owners have almost dictatorial control and can garner all the workers&#8217; productivity gains for themselves.  Focus on predistribution, however, reminds us that worker rights are essential to a sustainable, broad-based economy</p>
<p>What kinds of rights are we talking about?  Surely a critical right is the workers&#8217; right to collective bargaining (supported by a &#8220;yes&#8221; vote on Proposal 2 in Michigan that would put that right in the state constitution where it could not be removed by the radical right legislative block).  Surely the right of the state to build infrastructure (that will create worker jobs) rather than allowing a wealthy tycoon to corner the market on international bridge crossings in Detroit and hog the revenues for himself rather than allow them to be earned by the people (Proposal 6, vote &#8220;no&#8221; so that Matty doesn&#8217;t have veto power allowing him to co-opt public infrastructure for his private profits).</p>
<p>Predistribution pays attention to how much ordinary workers are paid compared to how much the managers at the top get out of a company.  We should be &#8220;pushing local employers to narrow the pay ratio between the top and the bottom ranks of their workforce.&#8221;  Id.  For too long, we have acted like it is just fine for the &#8220;market&#8221; to demand that the wealthy be allowed to exploit communities and workers for their own benefit.  We need to say no.</p>
<p>Predistribution pays attention to regulations that protect workers&#8211;from worker safety to time off to family leave. It disregards the multinational corporations&#8217; pleas for laws to suit them and instead asks why we should be subsidizing their ability to move active business assets to foreign countries and leave US workers unemployed.  It acnkowledges that we have for too long allowed corporate owners and managers to snow us with their claims that &#8220;globalization&#8221; and &#8220;free trade&#8221; worked for our benefit, when in fact these are excuses for offshoring jobs so that the owners and managers can enjoy even higher &#8220;rent&#8221; profits.  As Milbrand says, &#8220;It&#8217;s just not true that all the top CEOs will leave the country unless we pay them whatever they demand.&#8221;  Id.</p>
<p>cross posted with <a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2012/10/growing-inequality-calls-for-both-predistribution-and-rightly-directed-redistribution.html">ataxingmatter</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/growing-inequality-calls-for-both-predistribution-and-rightly-directed-redistribution.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Plutocracy Rising</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/plutocracy-rising.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/plutocracy-rising.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 21 Oct 2012 20:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[income inequality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[progressive taxation]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/plutocracy-rising.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Via reader rjs news and Naked Capitalism comes this excerpt on income inequality and programs to address the issue: Bill Moyers: Plutocracy Rising &#8211; via Yves Smith &#8211; Bill Moyer’s latest show, with Matt Taibbi and and Chrystia Freeland, focuses on how the super rich have established a yawning chasm between themselves and ordinary Americans, both [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Via reader rjs news and Naked Capitalism<strong> </strong>comes this excerpt on income inequality and programs to address the issue:<br />
<blockquote><a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/10/bill-moyers-plutocracy-rising.html">Bill Moyers: Plutocracy Rising </a>&#8211; via Yves Smith &#8211; Bill Moyer’s latest show, with Matt Taibbi and and Chrystia Freeland, focuses on how the super rich have established a yawning chasm between themselves and ordinary Americans, both in financial and physical terms. One major focus is view the rich are where they are by virtue of their talents and efforts, not (say) by regulatory and tax arbitrage, and how they’ve convinced themselves and a large swathe of society of this myth.<br /> One place where I quibble is where and Freeland argues that “progressives” have dropped the ball by focusing on manufacturing jobs as a solution to the woes of the fallen middle class. That’s hardly the first or best remedy; more progressive taxation (on the order, say, of what we had in Reagan’s day) and getting rid of the favorable treatment of “carried interest” would have far more short term impact. And if I’ve heard the weak tea lefties correctly, the preferred fix for creating more manly jobs (remember Obama’s fixation with that?) is infrastructure spending, where the US has fallen way behind its advanced economy peers, and lousy infrastructure is an impediment to commerce. Freeland has spent too much time in Davos and is unduly enamored of the big multinational corporation business models of extended supply chains. But that aside, there is a lot of good stuff in this show</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/plutocracy-rising.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Explaining Class Warfare</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/explaining-class-warfare.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/explaining-class-warfare.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2012 17:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[capitalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Class war]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Class Warfare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income inequality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Income redistribution]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Job creation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[job creators]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[unemployment]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/explaining-class-warfare.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Last month one hundred and fourteen thousand unemployed moochers&#8230;suddenly yank the government teat out of their mouths, get off the couch for forty hours a week? Why? I say follow the money; cause I found out, that right around the time those people got those jobs&#8230;they started getting paid! And just where does that money [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><div>Last month one hundred and fourteen thousand unemployed moochers&#8230;suddenly yank the government teat out of their mouths, get off the couch for forty hours a week?  Why?</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>I say follow the money;  cause I found out, that right around the time those people got those jobs&#8230;they started getting paid!   </div>
<div></div>
<div>And just where does that money come from?  Right out of the pockets of the job creators.  How&#8217;s that for your socialist redistribution of wealth?  Folks, it&#8217;s called class warfare.   </div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div><a href="http://videocafe.crooksandliars.com/heather/colbert-pity-poor-billionaires" target="_blank">Mr Colbert</a> has created a new party that will issue a certificate to sooth the hurt of the job creators.  The Certificate of Richness issued by:  </div>
<div>Protecting Industry Titans and Yachtsman party.  The P.I.T.Y. party.</div>
<div></div>
<div>And right <a href="http://finance.yahoo.com/news/ceo-workers-youll-likely-fired-131640914.html;_ylt=AlaAuLdYqs7HHtbpDI5C47KiuYdG;_ylu=X3oDMTN1MnFnZ25nBG1pdANGaW5hbmNlIEZQIE1lZ2F0cm9uIDIEcGtnA2RmNDIxODQ2LTgzOGYtMzQzMC05YjNjLWY4NzE2M2Q4OTY0NgRwb3MDMQRzZWMDbWVnYXRyb24EdmVyAzc3NjY3MmY4LTEyZjAtMTFlMi05ZmZmLTU5YWVjNDdhNGIyMg--;_ylg=X3oDMTFpNzk0NjhtBGludGwDdXMEbGFuZwNlbi11cwRwc3RhaWQDBHBzdGNhdANob21lBHB0A3NlY3Rpb25z;_ylv=3" target="_blank">on cue</a>:</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<blockquote><div>If President Obama is re-elected and raises taxes, Westgate Resort&#8217;s David  Siegel says he will have to lay off workers and downsize his company &#8212; or even  shut it down.</div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/explaining-class-warfare.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>What is the Economic Middle Class?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/09/what-is-the-economic-middle-class.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/09/what-is-the-economic-middle-class.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Sep 2012 15:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[conservative thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income inequality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jazzbumpa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[middle class]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/09/what-is-the-economic-middle-class.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[My lovely wife shared this link with me on Facebook.  I got into a discussion in comments there with a right winger who suggested that $250,000 was a very reasonable estimate for median income in Boston. As it turns out, median household income in Boston is $51,914, close to the national average, and way below [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My lovely wife shared <a href="http://ed.msnbc.com/_news/2012/09/14/13865852-romney-thinks-250k-is-middle-income?threadId=3566072&#038;commentId=70055856#c70055856">this link</a> with me on Facebook.  I got into a discussion in comments there with a  right winger who suggested that $250,000 was a very reasonable estimate  for median income in Boston.</p>
<p>As it turns out, <a href="http://www.areavibes.com/boston-ma/employment/">median household income</a> in Boston is $51,914, close to the national average, and way below the  Mass. State average of $67,950.  But right wingers live in a data-free  world, so this is no surprise.</p>
<p>Another contention in  comments at that site is that the middle class is undefined and  undefinable. Not so.  I define middle class household income as the  middle quintile.  This range includes the median and a band around it  wide enough to hold 20 percent of the population.  You might wish to  concoct your own definition with a wider spread, but you&#8217;d better not be  asymmetric around the median.  Feel free to use the middle three  quintiles, if that is your preference.  But if your of concept of middle  class gets very far beyond 50% of the population, you really ought to  give more thought to what the word &#8220;middle&#8221; actually means.</p>
<p>Thinking about all this prompted a look at the various income quintiles.  The data, through 2009, is available at the <a href="http://www.census.gov/compendia/statab/cats/income_expenditures_poverty_wealth/household_income.html">Census Bureau web site</a>,  table 694.  This table provides historical data from 1967 through 2009  on the top income limit for the bottom 4 quintiles, and the bottom  income limit for the top 5%, expressed in constant 2009 dollars.</p>
<p>Graph  1 presents this data.  The 3rd quintile &#8211; my definition of the middle  class &#8211; is between the orange line and the yellow line.</p>
<p>
<div><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-pcXiiBoLVVU/UFUeGR2hgOI/AAAAAAAAB7A/4F-V4p4x7t0/s1600/Income+Quintiles.jpg"><img border="0" height="263" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-pcXiiBoLVVU/UFUeGR2hgOI/AAAAAAAAB7A/4F-V4p4x7t0/s400/Income+Quintiles.jpg" width="400"></a></div>
<p>In  1967, the threshold for the middle quintile was $32, 848.  By 2009, it  had increased by 17% to $38,550.  This is a compounded annual growth  rate of 0.38%</p>
<p>In 1967, the top limit for the middle  (and threshold to the 4th) quintile was $46, 621.  By 2009, it had  increased by 33% to $61,801. This is a compounded annual growth rate of  0.68%.</p>
<p>The threshold value for the fifth quintile  increased from $66,481 in 1967 by 80% to exactly $100,000 in 2009.  This  is a compounded annual growth rate of 0.98%.</p>
<p>To reach  the top 5% required an income of 106,684 in 1967.  By 2009, this had  increased by 69% to $180, 001.   This is a compounded annual growth rate  of 1.25%.</p>
<p>So my comment sparring partner and the  current presidential challenger he seems to support are a bit off base.   $250,000 in household income puts a family well above the 95th  percentile.  In fact, that is <a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2012-07-20/top-2-not-job-creators-or-millionaires-in-tax-debate.html">just enough household income</a> to crack the top 2%.</p>
<p>My ongoing hobby of debunking right wing nonsense aside, the point of this post is mainly to inform.<br />There are two main observations:<br />1)  While the bottom two quintiles haven&#8217;t changed much over the decades,  entry to the third quintile has crept up a bit; and into higher  categories it&#8217;s moved up a lot.  We recognize this as stagnation in the  bottom half and growing inequality in the top half, skewed powerfully to  the top.<br />2) This data set stops in &#8217;09, so Obama is outside the  discussion.  But we can see that all the way up to the 95th percentile,  income growth was dead flat during the Bush administration.  No wonder  the 95% percentile feels so poor.</p>
<p>But &#8212; surely, some  wealth was generated during those 8 years.  GDP growth was positive at  least some of the time.  I wonder where it all went?</p>
<p>Cross posted at <a href="http://jazzbumpa.blogspot.com/2012/09/what-is-economic-middle-class.html">Retirement Blues</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/09/what-is-the-economic-middle-class.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Trickle-Down Theory of Happiness</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/the-trickle-down-theory-of-happiness.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/the-trickle-down-theory-of-happiness.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 08 Jul 2012 03:34:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[1 %ers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economic perspectives]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income inequality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[labor share]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[poetry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[screwing]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/the-trickle-down-theory-of-happiness.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[                                                                                                              [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>                                                                                                                              A poem by Philip Appleman via Bill Moyers.</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<p>
<div></div>
<div>I think that about covers it.  But if it was not for you, try this one: The Ant</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/the-trickle-down-theory-of-happiness.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>One in 189 of those with $200,000 or more in AGI paid no federal taxes in 2009</title>
		<link>./../../2012/05/one-in-189-of-those-with-200000-or-more-in-agi-paid-no-federal-taxes-in-2009.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/05/one-in-189-of-those-with-200000-or-more-in-agi-paid-no-federal-taxes-in-2009.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 31 May 2012 01:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[income inequality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linda Beale (Tax law)]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/05/one-in-189-of-those-with-200000-or-more-in-agi-paid-no-federal-taxes-in-2009.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Beale One in 189 of those with $200,000 or more in AGI paid no federal taxes in 2009 [edited 5/30 to correct &#8220;one in four&#8221; goof] The IRS recently released another &#8220;statistics of income&#8221; report. This one has news that should make most ordinary Americans think twice about the GOP agenda of reducing [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Linda Beale</p>
<p>One in 189 of those with $200,000 or more in AGI paid no federal taxes in 2009</p>
<p>[edited 5/30 to correct &#8220;one in four&#8221; goof]</p>
<p>The IRS recently released another &#8220;statistics of income&#8221; report. This one has news that should make most ordinary Americans think twice about the GOP agenda of reducing taxes for the rich while cutting back on all kinds of programs that serve ordinary Americans&#8211;the fact that a <strong>large percentage of the upper crust&#8211;one out of every 189 Americans with $200,000 or more in income &#8211;pay no federal income taxes whatsoever</strong>. See Rubin, <a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2012-05-29/irs-finds-one-in-189-high-earners-paid-no-2009-u-s-tax.html">IRS Finds One in 189 High Earners Paid No U.S. Taxes in 2009</a>, Bloomberg.com (May 29, 2012).</p>
<p>How does someone with $200,000 or more in income pay no taxes, when ordinary folk with jobs who make $50,000 to $75,000 pay 15% to 25% of their income in taxes? 
<ul>
<li>As I&#8217;ve often discussed here (see items under charitable contribution deduction), rich folk can easily afford to give away more to charity and they get a tax bonus that is much more than that available to poorer folk when they do so. They get an especially big break if what they give away is appreciated stock that they bought a while ago&#8211;and rich folks own most of these financial assets, so they are the ones that get almost exclusive enjoyment of this lucrative loophole: they get to deduct the full value of the stock they donate, without having ever paid taxes on the appreciation. That&#8217;s one of the boondoggles in the Code that Congress can and should get rid of, no matter what else it does about taxes. </li>
<li>Another way rich folk pay less in taxes is by ensuring that the income they earn is of a type that isn&#8217;t subject to tax. Big CEOs generally have rich pension plans and other forms of deferred tax compensation that facilitate lowering their tax bills. Rich folk are the buyers of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Municipal_bond">municipal bonds</a>, which again enjoy a specific tax break in section 103 of the Code that excludes the interest income from the owners&#8217; tax returns. This is supposed to help municipalities, since the tax break gives the wealthy an incentive to buy the bonds even though they pay lower rates, since all the interest is tax free. But it is a costly break that provides an advantage only for the rich. Wouldn&#8217;t it be better to eliminate it and tax wealthy people on all of their interest income at ordinary income rates? Maybe the tax money could also fund programs for important municipal projects&#8211;like intracity rail transportation in Detroit, a much needed idea whose time has come&#8230;.. </li>
<li>A third way that rich people avoid taxes is by having so many deductions&#8211;high-end medical &#8220;equipment&#8221; (like swimming pools for arthritic patients), lots of interest on mortgages on high-end homes, and other deductions of special value to those who would otherwise pay tax at a higher rate.</li>
</ul>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />As the Rubin article notes, the IRS announced that for 2009 there were 10,080 households with &#8220;<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adjusted_gross_income">adjusted gross income</a>&#8221; of $200,000 or more who paid no US or foreign income taxes. Adjusted gross income is not <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Income">economic income</a>&#8211;AGI does not reflect items that are excluded from the calculation of income for tax purposes and is reduced by certain &#8220;above the line&#8221; deductions that are especially beneficial to the wealthy. &#8220;Using an expanded concept of income that includes some nontaxable items and looking only at U.S. income taxes, there were 35,061 households, or 0.88 percent, that paid nothing.&#8221; Id.</p>
<p>The <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alternative_Minimum_Tax">Alternative Minimum Tax</a> was initially enacted to deal with the general unfairness of having extraordinarily well-to-do people be able to avoid tax entirely. As it was modified over time, it came to function as a way to ensure that those who accumulate lots of different deductions nonetheless pay tax, by treating some of those deductions as unqualified preferences for AMT purposes. But the AMT has lost a lot of its punch as Congress has eviscerated its provisions, such as the limitation on foreign tax credits. This is one of the reasons that many progressives have supported two things&#8211;elimination of the preferential rate for capital gains (a type of income especially enjoyed by the ultra rich) and adoption of a new type of minimum tax on some high level of gross income (the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buffett_Rule">Buffett Rule</a>). This new information about the number of rich people who end up paying nothing in federal income taxes should result in more people telling Congress that it&#8217;s time to pass these two proposals.</p>
<p>crossposted with <a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2012/05/irs-finds-one-in-189-high-earners-paid-no-us-taxes-in-2009-1-2012-05-29-180606251-gmt-updates-with-gardner.html">ataxingmatter</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/05/one-in-189-of-those-with-200000-or-more-in-agi-paid-no-federal-taxes-in-2009.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Inequality on the Island</title>
		<link>./../../2012/05/inequality-on-the-island.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/05/inequality-on-the-island.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 13 May 2012 22:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[income inequality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Noni Mausa]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/05/inequality-on-the-island.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Noni Mausa Inequality on the Island Your island has 1000 people. 500 are working age, 500 are children or elderly and can’t do much.  That’s normal, and not a problem. The 500, working together, easily produce enough food and stuff for 5000 people, while also supporting the 500 young, old and disabled.  In fact, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by <strong>Noni Mausa</strong> </p>
<p><strong>Inequality on the Island</strong></p>
<p>Your island has 1000 people. 500 are working age, 500 are children or elderly and can’t do much.  That’s normal, and not a problem.</p>
<p>The 500, working together, easily produce enough food and stuff for 5000 people, while also supporting the 500 young, old and disabled.  In fact, the working 500 are so productive that in good times they have plenty of time to create music and art, write books, do research, and explore the sea, the land and the heavens.  And when members of the 500 grow old, there are youngsters ready and willing to take their place.</p>
<p>With 5000 livings floating around, no-one expects each person to have 5 livings.  Some will always have a bit more, others a bit less. But this variability can go too far.</p>
<p>By 2007 on the island, 200 people control 4250 of the 5000 livings,and of that group ten people control 1730 livings.  One of the 200 has 615 livings all to himself.</p>
<p>The other 800 people on the island have 750 livings to share, 0.94 each.  Half of these people are not workers, and need to be supported by the remaining 400.</p>
<p>These 400, subsisting on less than a living each, produce 80%of the island’s economy of 5000 livings, or 10 livings each.  In return they receive 1.88 livings with which to support themselves and one dependent.</p>
<p>There’s your inequality.  How does it look to you?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/05/inequality-on-the-island.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>US inequality is getting worse</title>
		<link>./../../2012/05/us-inequality-is-getting-worse.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/05/us-inequality-is-getting-worse.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 12 May 2012 03:16:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[income inequality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linda Beale (Tax law)]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/05/us-inequality-is-getting-worse.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Beale US inequality is getting worse The Congressional REsearch Service released a report in March showing that US inequality is getting worse. Linda Levine, US income distribution and mobility: trends and international comparisons, Congressional Research Service (Mar. 7, 2012). Here&#8217;s an excerpt from the summary provided in the report itself. Approaching three years [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Linda Beale</p>
<p><a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2012/05/us-inequality-is-getting-worse.html">US inequality is getting worse</a></p>
<p>The Congressional REsearch Service released a report in March showing that US inequality is getting worse. Linda Levine, <a href="http://assets.opencrs.com/rpts/R42400_20120307.pdf">US income distribution and mobility: trends and international comparisons</a>, Congressional Research Service (Mar. 7, 2012).</p>
<p>Here&#8217;s an excerpt from the summary provided in the report itself.</p>
<blockquote><p>Approaching three years into the recovery from the 2007-2009 recession, the unemployment rate remains over 8%. The persistent difficulty of many of the workers who lost jobs to find reemployment has meant reduced incomes for them and their families. A historically slow rebound in the labor market appears to be partly responsible for some groups’ focus on the distribution of the benefits of economic growth and for some policymakers’ interest in redistributing income through the tax code, for example. Varying perceptions about a trade-off between economic growth and income equality appear to underlie longstanding congressional deliberations about such policy issues as the progressivity of income tax rates, the tax treatment of capital gains, and the adjustment of the federal minimum wage. If income were equally divided across households, each quintile (fifth) would account for 20% of total income. The Congressional Budget Office and others have documented that the bottom fifth has long accounted for much less than 20% of total income. The bottom quintile’s share of income has remained little changed for the past few decades at less than 4%, according to U.S. Census Bureau data. In contrast, the income shares of the top fifth and the top 5% of households appear to have trended upward. The top fifth’s share of total household income rose from 42.6% in 1968 to 50.2% in 2010; the top 5%’s share, from 16.3% to 21.3%. (Estimates derived from      <br />federal income tax data suggest that those at the very top of the income distribution have experienced greater gains.) The middle class, defined as the middle 60%, received a       <br />disproportionately smaller share of the total economic pie in 2010 (46.5%) than in 1968 (53.2%).</p>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />***<br />Based on the limited data that are comparable across nations, the U.S. income distribution appears to be among the most uneven of all major industrialized countries and the United States appears to be among the nations experiencing the greatest increases in measures of inequality. Three leading explanations are put forth for these cross-country differences: (1) other advanced economies devote a larger share of national output to transfers, which tends to equalize income across households; (2) the progressivity of tax rates varies by country and thus has different effects on the distribution of after-tax income; and (3) equality in the distribution of earnings,      <br />which account for most household income, varies substantially across countries.</p></blockquote>
<p>So Inequality is increasing and mobility in the US economy is diminishing, as the rich get richer and the middle class gets poorer and the poor stay poor. Because so many Americans have believed the hype about &#8220;free markets&#8221; pushed by the right and the Chicago School economic perspective, they don&#8217;t understand the failures of the &#8220;free market&#8221; theory &#8211;for example, that it cannot accurately predict much of anything about the economy,and that its policy dictates are likely to be total failures since they are based on assumptions that simply don&#8217;t hold for actual societies (like infinite lifetimes, 100% consumption of incomes, a unitary preference and other nonsense). </p>
<p>They echo the radical right&#8217;s rhetoric antagonistic to redistribution in favor of those who are disadvantaged by the growing inequality, and blithely miss the way tax policy and spending policy redistributes upwards in ways that contributes to the increase in inequality. Americans are also lulled into complacency about the harm of increasing inequality by the American myth that everybody that has the will to take the risks can be a self-made millionaire. Thus, they miss any opportunities to force Congress to bring the oligarchy under control through wiser tax policy and legislative initiatives focused on addressing genuine public needs through democratic egalitarianism.</p>
<p>crossposted with <a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/">ataxingmatter</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/05/us-inequality-is-getting-worse.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
