<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>China &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Fear of China syndrome</title>
		<link>./../../2012/09/fear-of-china-syndrome.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/09/fear-of-china-syndrome.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 10 Sep 2012 00:46:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[bonds]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[China]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fear]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/09/fear-of-china-syndrome.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I overheard a conversation at a local restaurant on the impact of the US being dependent on China buying US bonds to finance federal debt.  Usullay missing from such conversations is the % of money involved, whether that is a lot, and what effect it has on federal debt and trade (and some kind of [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I overheard a conversation at a local restaurant on the impact of the US being dependent on China buying US bonds to finance federal debt.  Usullay missing from such conversations is the % of money involved, whether that is a lot, and what effect it has on federal debt and trade (and some kind of political or &#8216;war&#8217; value?)  Then via <a href="http://economistsview.typepad.com/economistsview/2012/09/fear-of-china-syndrome.html">Mark Thoma</a> came the Krugman piece on bonds and how the market works in Fear of China syndrome, so thought I would post the Krugman piece and some comment by Mark Sadowski from the post:</p>
<blockquote><p>Paul Krugman tries, once again, to explain why there&#8217;s no reason to fear that &#8220;terrible things will happen&#8221; if China stops purchasing our government bonds:</p>
<blockquote><p><a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/09/05/wicksell-goes-to-china/">Wicksell Goes To China, by Paul Krugman</a>: </p></blockquote>
</blockquote>
<blockquote><blockquote>The idea that we are at the mercy of the Chinese — that terrible things would happen if they stopped buying our bonds — is <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/09/05/opinion/its-mitts-world.html?_r=1&#038;hp">very influential</a>. Yet it’s <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/08/30/fear-of-china-syndrome/">just wrong</a>.<br />Think of it this way: the argument that interest rates would soar if the Chinese bought fewer bonds is the same as the argument that interest rates would soar when the U.S. government sold more bonds — which, as you may recall, was the subject of <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2009/05/02/liquidity-preference-loanable-funds-and-niall-ferguson-wonkish/">fierce debate</a> more than three years ago — and you know how that turned out. </p></blockquote>
</blockquote>
<blockquote><blockquote>Again, you can think of this in terms <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/09/04/natural-born-recovery-killers/">Wicksell</a>: we’re in a situation in which the incipient supply of savings — the amount that people would save at full employment — is greater than the incipient demand for investment. And this excess supply of savings leads to a depressed economy. </p></blockquote>
</blockquote>
<blockquote><blockquote>What China does by buying bonds is add to the excess savings — which makes our situation worse. (This is just another way of saying that the artificial trade surplus hurts our economy — just another way of stating the same thing). And we want them to do less of it; far from fearing that they will stop, we should welcome the prospect.</p>
<p></p></blockquote>
</blockquote>
<p><a name="more"></a>Lifted from comments from Economistview:</p>
<p>Mark A. Sadowski said in reply to Matt C&#8230;</p>
<p> This is old news. FYI QE2 ended in June of 2011.</p>
<p>On June 30, 2011 the Fed held $1,617 billion worth of Treasuries:<br />http://www.federalreserve.gov/releases/h41/20110630/</p>
<p>According to the most recent release (August 30) the Fed now holds $1,639 billion worth of Treasuries.<br />http://ftalphaville.ft.com/blog/2012/08/31/1140881/if-qe3-is-so-close-why-is-the-feds-balance-sheet-shrinking/</p>
<p>According to SIFMA:<br />http://www.sifma.org/research/statistics.aspx</p>
<p>$1,274 billion in Treasuries were issued between the end of June 2011 and the end of July 2012, meaning the Fed has bought less than 2% of all Treasuries issued in that time.</p>
<p>Moreover, the Fed&#8217;s balance sheet has actually been shrinking since December. That&#8217;s why there are tons of stories such as this if you bother to do the google:<br />http://ftalphaville.ft.com/blog/2012/08/31/1140881/if-qe3-is-so-close-why-is-the-feds-balance-sheet-shrinking/<br />..<br /><i>Correct current release lin</i>k:<br />http://www.federalreserve.gov/releases/h41/Current/</p>
<p>Matt C asked:<br />Even if QE2 is old news, what is the big change in the financial landscape since 2011?</p>
<p>Was it not bad in 2011 for China to be buying bonds then? If China was depressing the economy by buying bonds then, why wasn&#8217;t QE2 doing the same thing?</p>
<p>Mark A. Sadowski answers:<br />It makes a big difference who&#8217;s buying the bonds.</p>
<p>Krugman describes the situation as an excess of savings over desired investment. But another way of looking at it is as an excess demand for money over its supply.</p>
<p>When the Chinese buy US Treasury bonds they increase the demand for US dollars and drive up the dollar&#8217;s value (they were of course doing this intentionally to increase their net exports). When the Fed buys bonds they&#8217;re adding to the supply of dollars. This of course drives down the value of the dollar.</p>
<p>Increased demand for dollars is depressing. Increased supply of dollars is stimulative.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/09/fear-of-china-syndrome.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Most U.S. Trade Agreement Improve Trade Balance, but Effect Overwhelmed by NAFTA and China Trade</title>
		<link>./../../2012/08/most-u-s-trade-agreement-improve-trade-balance-but-effect-overwhelmed-by-nafta-and-china-trade.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/08/most-u-s-trade-agreement-improve-trade-balance-but-effect-overwhelmed-by-nafta-and-china-trade.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 22 Aug 2012 02:07:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[China]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kenneth Thomas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NAFTA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[trade balances]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/08/most-u-s-trade-agreement-improve-trade-balance-but-effect-overwhelmed-by-nafta-and-china-trade.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Kenneth Thomas Most U.S. Trade Agreement Improve Trade Balance, but Effect Overwhelmed by NAFTA and China Trade The U.S. trade deficit figures heavily in the analysis of Jeff Faux&#8217;s new book, The Servant Economy. Faux, the founder of the Economic Policy Institute (EPI), was one of the most important voices speaking out against NAFTA [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by <strong>Kenneth Thomas</strong></p>
<p><strong>Most U.S. Trade Agreement Improve Trade Balance, but Effect Overwhelmed by NAFTA and China Trade</strong></p>
<p>The U.S. trade deficit figures heavily in the analysis of Jeff Faux&#8217;s <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Servant-Economy-Americas-Sending/dp/0470182393">new book</a>, <i>The Servant Economy</i>. Faux, the founder of the Economic Policy Institute (EPI), was one of the most important voices speaking out against NAFTA when it was debated and ultimately passed by Congress in 1993.    <br />According to EPI&#8217;s 2011 <a href="http://www.epi.org/publication/2011-annual-report/">Annual Report</a>,&#8221;Presently, the United States&#8217; non-oil deficit alone costs more than five million U.S. jobs.&#8221; This underscores the importance of the deficit and what is at stake. In the book, Faux points out that the theoretical benefits of free trade assume full employment, but that is hardly ever the case. Thus, he argues, the trade deficit is indeed a job killer.    </p>
<p>Yet, as <a href="http://www.reuters.com/article/2012/07/31/column-dcjohnston-skorea-idUSL2E8IPM4720120731">David Cay Johnston notes</a>, the United States continues to negotiate new trade agreements while government agencies and government officials from the President down, tout them as engines of job creation. Johnston points out that the government predicted that our small pre-NAFTA trade surplus would continue, when instead we quickly went into a deficit that in 2011 reached $64.5 billion. Similarly, he says, the U.S. International Trade Commission predicted that normalizing trade relations with China would lead to a trade deficit of just $1 billion, when in fact it grew by 2011 to $295 billion!    </p>
<p>How have these trade agreements performed? At present, according to the <a href="http://www.ustr.gov/trade-agreements/free-trade-agreements/">U.S. Trade Representative</a>, the U.S. has free trade agreements with 19 other countries, with a 20th (with Panama) approved but not yet implemented. The 19 countries are: Australia, Bahrain, Canada, Chile, Colombia, Costa Rica, Dominican Republic, El Salvador, Guatemala, Honduras, Israel, Jordan, South Korea, Mexico, Morocco, Nicaragua, Oman, Peru, and Singapore.<br /><a name="more"></a>    <br />The <a href="http://www.census.gov/foreign-trade/balance/">U.S. Census Bureau</a> (then click on individual countries) has the answer to this. In 11 cases, the goods trade balance has improved from the year prior to the agreements&#8217; coming into effect through 2011, in one case it&#8217;s too soon to tell (Colombia, effective May 15, 2012), and only in seven cases did the trade balance worsen.    </p>
<p>Unfortunately, that&#8217;s the end of the good news, because our trade with most of these countries is relatively small: in six cases the improvement was under $2 billion dollars, which pales against the country&#8217;s overall goods deficit of $727.4 billion in 2011. The biggest gains have been with Singapore ($10.7 billion) and Australia ($9.1 billion).    </p>
<p>The losses, on the other hand, have been huge, with the culprits being NAFTA and liberalizing trade with China (not even a full free trade agreement, just <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2012/08/us-trade-deficit-largely-due-to-intra.html">making it easier for U.S. firms to offshore</a> their production to China). In the wake of NAFTA, the U.S. goods trade balance with Mexico has worsened by $66.2 billion, while our Canadian goods trade balance has worsened by $23.7 billion. Just since 2001, when China joined the WTO, and 2011, the goods trade deficit has increased from $83 billion to $295 billion. <a href="http://www.epi.org/publication/growing-trade-deficit-china-cost-2-8-million/">Robert E. Scott</a> of the EPI estimates that this massive deficit has &#8220;eliminated or displaced nearly 2.8 million U.S. jobs since 2001.&#8221; In addition, our Israel free trade agreement has added about $10 billion more to the deficit.    </p>
<p>As Faux argues, the trade deficit reduces demand for U.S. labor, and pushes wages down in the aggregate. Indeed, this is the tendency of trade in general for a <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2012/06/is-globalization-good-for-americas.html">labor-scarce country</a> like the United States. Faux&#8217;s vision of where this is leading us in the long term is a depressing one, which I will discuss in more detail in a future column.</p>
<p>cross posted with <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2012/08/most-us-trade-agreement-improve-trade.html">Middle Class Political Economist</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/08/most-u-s-trade-agreement-improve-trade-balance-but-effect-overwhelmed-by-nafta-and-china-trade.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Wired’s Embarrassing Whitewash of Foxconn</title>
		<link>./../../2012/02/wireds-embarrassing-whitewash-of-foxconn.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/02/wireds-embarrassing-whitewash-of-foxconn.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Feb 2012 16:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Apple]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[China]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[global economies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[multi-national business]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[socially respomsiblity]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/02/wireds-embarrassing-whitewash-of-foxconn.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Yves comments on Wired’s Embarrassing Whitewash of Foxconn : But Johnson admits he’s a tech toy writer who apparently has no knowledge of manufacturing …. Yet he’s remarkably uninhibited in using his fantasies and abject ignorance as a basis for making sweeping generalizations about the Taiwanese powerhouse.…I find this little chart (hat tip Richard Smith) from [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Yves comments on <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/02/wireds-embarrassing-whitewash-of-foxconn.html">Wired’s Embarrassing Whitewash of Foxconn</a> :<br />
<blockquote>But Johnson admits he’s a tech toy writer who apparently has no knowledge of manufacturing …. Yet he’s remarkably uninhibited in using his fantasies and abject ignorance as a basis for making sweeping generalizations about the Taiwanese powerhouse.<br /><strong>…</strong><br />I find this little chart (hat tip Richard Smith) from <a href="http://ninety9.tumblr.com/post/16997979949">ninety9</a> via<a href="http://alea.tumblr.com/post/17025694873/foxconn"> Alea</a> (who is the antithesis of a socialist) to be more though-provoking than the entire Wired piece:</p></blockquote>
<p><a href="http://lh3.ggpht.com/-05e5b_xb-8k/TzMPyEf_C_I/AAAAAAAAA0A/bVLSC9wEKw8/s1600-h/appleproducts%25255B2%25255D.png"><img alt="appleproducts" border="0" height="244" src="http://lh6.ggpht.com/-YZ6-4JRnNO0/TzMPyVeJ0SI/AAAAAAAAA0I/QmIAr7hPEMM/appleproducts_thumb.png?imgmax=800" title="appleproducts" width="201"></a></p>
<p>More can be found <a href="http://www.alternet.org/story/154043/iempire%3A_apple%27s_sordid_business_practices_are_even_worse_than_you_think?akid=8234.29972.LjUa9F&#038;rd=1&#038;t=3">here</a>.   Lots of links as well adding to the state financed aspects of Foxcomm.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/02/wireds-embarrassing-whitewash-of-foxconn.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Baby Steps</title>
		<link>./../../2011/11/baby-steps.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/11/baby-steps.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2011 10:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[China]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[real exchange rates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[trade imbalances]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/11/baby-steps.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[By Rebecca Wilder Baby Steps In the FT today, Martin Wolf discusses the symbiotic relationship of global creditors and debtors. According to the September 2011 IMF World Economic Outlook, China ran the largest current account surplus in 2007, while the US ran the largest current account deficit (in $). Well, if this creditor-debtor relationship is [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By <a href="http://www.economonitor.com/blog/author/rwilder3">Rebecca Wilder</a></p>
<p>Baby Steps
<p>In the FT today, <a href="http://www.ft.com/intl/cms/s/0/e71ab1d6-049d-11e1-ac2a-00144feabdc0.html#axzz1cZTnNsU2">Martin Wolf </a> discusses the symbiotic relationship of global creditors and debtors.  According to the <a href="http://www.imf.org/external/ns/cs.aspx?id=28">September 2011 IMF World Economic Outlook</a>, China ran the largest current account surplus in 2007, while the US ran the largest current account deficit (in $). Well, if this creditor-debtor relationship is to become more ‘balanced’, then evidence of success should stem from these two giants.</p>
<p>Progress has been made. The IMF forecasts China’s 2011 current account surplus will be broadly unchanged since 2007 (in levels $). In contrast, the 2011 US current account deficit is expected to have improved by 35% compared to 2007 levels. It’s baby steps toward a more balanced global capital market place. What’s driving this? Primarily the real exchange rate.</p>
<p>The chart below illustrates the real effective exchange rates for China and the US, as measured by a broad set of trading partners and relative inflation. The <a href="http://www.bis.org/statistics/eer/index.htm">BIS releases</a> this data. Notably, the Chinese economy experienced real appreciation coincident with US real depreciation (I chose the colors pink and blue for consistency with the ‘baby steps’ theme). Spanning the years 2005 – current, the Chinese yuan appreciated 25% in real and trade-weighted terms, while that of the US dollar depreciated 14%.</p>
<p>Progress is being made.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2011/11/reer_chart_china_usa.jpg"><img alt="" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2011/11/reer_chart_china_usa.jpg" width="600" height="390"></a></p>
<p> <a name="more"></a>
<p>Filed under: <a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/category/china/">China</a>, <a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/category/global-imbalances/">Global Imbalances</a>, <a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/category/real-exchange-rates/">Real Exchange Rates</a>, <a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/category/usa/">USA</a></p>
<p>Originally published at <a target="_blank" href="http://www.blogger.com/post-edit.g?blogID=5048766&#038;postID=84938654719771825">The Wilder View&#8230;Economonitors</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/11/baby-steps.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Retaliating Against Currency Manipulation: A Primer</title>
		<link>./../../2011/10/retaliating-against-currency-manipulation-a-primer.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/10/retaliating-against-currency-manipulation-a-primer.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2011 13:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[China]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[currency pegs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[IMF]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[trade balances]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WTO]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/10/retaliating-against-currency-manipulation-a-primer.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Kash at The Streetlight points us to other aspects of the world, touching upon the WTO and the IMF roles in global trade and China in particular: Retaliating Against Currency Manipulation: A Primer You&#8217;ve probably heard that this week the US Congress has been addressing the issue of how China controls its exchange rate with [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Kash at <em>The Streetlight</em> points us to other aspects of the world, touching upon the WTO and the IMF roles in global trade and China in particular:</p>
<p><a href="http://streetlightblog.blogspot.com/2011/10/retaliating-against-currency.html" target="'_blank">Retaliating Against Currency Manipulation: A Primer</a><br />
<blockquote>You&#8217;ve probably heard that this week the US Congress has been addressing the issue of how China controls its exchange rate with the US dollar. In particular, many have argued that China&#8217;s policy of only allowing the yuan (CNY) to appreciate very gradually against the dollar has kept Chinese products unreasonably cheap to American consumers, and American products unreasonably expensive to Chinese consumers. (See for example Paul Krugman&#8217;s column on <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/03/opinion/holding-china-to-account.html">Monday</a>.)</p></blockquote>
<p>And indicates a source worth reading:<br />
<blockquote><em>if you&#8217;re interested in more details regarding the legal options and implications of possible US retaliation against Chinese currency manipulation, you can&#8217;t do better than this paper by Jonathan Sanford of the Congressional Research Service: &#8220;<a href="http://digital.library.unt.edu/ark:/67531/metadc31498/m1/1/high_res_d/RS22658_2011Jan28.pdf">Currency Manipulation: The IMF and WTO</a>&#8220;.</em></p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/10/retaliating-against-currency-manipulation-a-primer.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Random Notes 3 June 2011</title>
		<link>./../../2011/06/random-notes-3-june-2011.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/06/random-notes-3-june-2011.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2011 17:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[accounting]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[asset values]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[blogs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Buce]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[China]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[housing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income inequality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Income redistribution]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[meta]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/06/random-notes-3-june-2011.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Buce has been on fire recently, so I&#8217;ll probably have to do a post about why this post is so off-target, though his conclusion is correct (short version: he&#8217;s been misled). If I&#8217;m reading this morning&#8217;s SIFMA Brief correctly, Moody&#8217;s—whose rating skills Robert has discussed at length—(1) may downgrade US debt if we spend too [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<ol>
<li><a href="http://underbelly-buce.blogspot.com/">Buce</a> has been on fire recently, so I&#8217;ll probably have to do a post about why <a href="http://underbelly-buce.blogspot.com/2011/05/can-taxpayers-thank-eliot-spitzer-for.html">this post</a> is so off-target, though his conclusion is correct (short version: he&#8217;s been misled).</p>
</li>
<li>If I&#8217;m reading this morning&#8217;s <a href="http://www.smartbrief.com/servlet/encodeServlet?issueid=B7FCF69E-7215-4E6D-AC62-53F6A3532773&#038;sid=4da1e808-6b9f-4d1d-bfb8-caea93b4c6d8">SIFMA Brief</a> correctly, Moody&#8217;s—whose rating skills Robert has discussed at length—(1) may downgrade US debt <a href="http://r.smartbrief.com/resp/cVvhCcmoBhBZAweeXXqh">if we spend too much </a>and (2) will downgrade US banks <a href="http://r.smartbrief.com/resp/cVvhCcmoBhBZAweltoih">unless we spend too much on them</a>.  Oh, and the banks object to regulation because it would <a href="http://r.smartbrief.com/resp/cVvhCcmoBhBZAweBelfW">&#8220;artificially&#8221; reduce asset values</a> (presumably, many of the same ones Moody&#8217;s wants protected).
</li>
<li>Relatedly, James Salt (probably h/t Felix) notes that &#8220;generous&#8221; UK banks are <a href="http://blogs.reuters.com/jim-saft/2011/06/02/beware-generous-uk-banks/">playing reporting games</a>.  (The US version is to deny the rework and leave the asset marked at unsustainable levels.)
</li>
<li>That <a href="http://holykaw.alltop.com/school-superintendent-requests-school-be-turn">this is spot-on</a> would make me sadder if I thought we still lived in anything resembling a meritocracy, or even a developing economy.
</li>
<li>If we needed further evidence of that, the state with the best secondary eduction system in the country is pushing forward with <a href="http://schoolfinance101.wordpress.com/2011/06/03/the-offensively-defensive-ideology-of-charter-schooling/">privatize-the-gains</a>.
</li>
<li>I&#8217;m more and more convinced that China &#8220;is different,&#8221; but very much not certain the differences will make an ultimate difference.  Daniel Gross <a href="http://finance.yahoo.com/blogs/daily-ticker/bear-china-shop-163217166.html">is inclined to think not</a>.  More on this as I finally finish my review of <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Boombustology-Spotting-Financial-Bubbles-Before/dp/0470879467/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&#038;s=books&#038;qid=1305207274&#038;sr=1-1"><em>BoomBustOlogy</em></a>, which you should expect to see some time before the apocalypse.
</li>
<li>I assume everyone has already seen <a href="http://www.stanford.edu/group/scspi/cgi-bin/facts.php">this</a>.  Just in case, <a href="http://www.stanford.edu/group/scspi/cgi-bin/facts.php">check out the facts</a>, stylised or not.
</li>
<li>Oh, and Felix is wrong <a href="http://blogs.reuters.com/felix-salmon/2011/05/31/the-stocks-housing-disconnect/">here</a>.  But that&#8217;s a post that will probably never be written by me.  Someone else want to send it in?</li>
</ol>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/06/random-notes-3-june-2011.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>It&#8217;s pretty obvious how China can achieve its top economic priority of price stability</title>
		<link>./../../2011/03/its-pretty-obvious-how-china-can-achieve-its-top-economic-priority-of-price-stability.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/03/its-pretty-obvious-how-china-can-achieve-its-top-economic-priority-of-price-stability.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2011 21:16:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[China]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[inflation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rebecca Wilder]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/03/its-pretty-obvious-how-china-can-achieve-its-top-economic-priority-of-price-stability.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Premier Wen Jiabao made stabilizing prices China&#8217;s top economic priority for 2011. Amid the surge in world energy costs, this story didn&#8217;t make the front page. However, Chinese policymakers did take their time spent out of the limelight to allow the Chinese yuan to appreciate roughly 0.3% against the US dollar. Chinese inflation is elevated [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Premier Wen Jiabao made stabilizing prices <a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2011-03-05/china-targets-8-growth-this-year-wen-pledges-to-decisively-curb-prices.html">China&#8217;s top economic priority </a>for 2011. Amid the surge in world energy costs, this story didn&#8217;t make the front page. However, Chinese policymakers did take their time spent out of the limelight to allow the Chinese yuan to appreciate roughly 0.3% against the US dollar.</p>
<p>Chinese inflation is elevated and near 5% (<a href="http://english.peopledaily.com.cn/90001/90778/98505/7311989.html">4.9% is the official rate </a>as of January 2011). I understand that China&#8217;s growth adjustment <a href="http://www.economist.com/economics/by-invitation/guest-contributions/world_must_give_china_time_adjust">will take time</a>; but if you&#8217;ve got unwanted inflation, then domestic policy is too loose (fiscal or monetary). And in this case, it&#8217;s the monetary policy that&#8217;s too loose &#8211; that goes for both currency and rates policies.</p>
<p>On the rates front: there&#8217;s a very frothy feel in domestic asset markets, specifically the property market. Low rates and easy money have sparked a(nother) property boom in China, one that policymakers are trying to tamp down. The <a href="http://www.economist.com/node/18250463?story_id=18250463&#038;CFID=158278198&#038;CFTOKEN=19449521">Economist published a recent article to the point</a>.</p>
<p>But it&#8217;s going to take much, much more than raising down payments and reserve requirements to shore up demand for risk assets. I mean, it really doesn&#8217;t take a genius to see that real rates are entirely too low. What&#8217;s the investment strategy here: nominal GDP is expected to grow at a 11% in 2011 (according to Economic Intelligence Unit, no link), while the lending rate <a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2011-02-08/china-raises-benchmark-one-year-deposit-lending-rates-by-25-basis-points.html">is just 6.06%</a>. There&#8217;s no rocket science here: money&#8217;s entirely too easy and inflationary pressures are there. </p>
<p>Furthermore, deposit rates are too low and capping domestic consumer demand. Rates need to rise.</p>
<p><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-93NDQUcvP14/TXZVwQ2fqFI/AAAAAAAADg0/dBVq3JMcAjk/s1600/china_growth.JPG"><img src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-93NDQUcvP14/TXZVwQ2fqFI/AAAAAAAADg0/dBVq3JMcAjk/s400/china_growth.JPG" border="0" alt=""></a><a name="more"></a><br />On the currency front. Although there&#8217;s been some appreciation in the nominal currency, the yuan,  Chinese policymakers only recently allowed their currency to fluctuate at all (again) on an annual basis (see chart below). Notice how the annual appreciation was near 0% spanning Q3 2009 to Q4 2010 (October). Since the central bank doesn&#8217;t fully sterilize the inflows of foreign currency from export sales, the depressed nominal rate on the yuan feeds through to the economy via inflation.</p>
<p><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-EJasLGU-SsE/TXZVwMD_DpI/AAAAAAAADgs/4jp9QTph4Vs/s1600/china_exchange_rates.JPG"><img src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-EJasLGU-SsE/TXZVwMD_DpI/AAAAAAAADgs/4jp9QTph4Vs/s400/china_exchange_rates.JPG" border="0" alt=""></a><br />Inflation is rising, which is perking up the Chinese real exchange rate. In January 2011, the trade-weighted real effective exchange rate appreciated at a 4% annual rate (according to the JP Morgan Index). The real exchange rate takes into account the nominal rate plus shifts in the purchasing power of the domestic currency, as measured by relative price fluctuations.</p>
<p>The chart illustrates that the nominal exchange rate is now gaining traction on an annual basis, since the Chinese government halted its movement against the USD in 2009. I suspect that the nominal momentum will continue to grind upward throughout this year in order to temper some of the inflationary impetus coming from outside its borders (like Fed policy). But as I said before, it&#8217;s Chinese policy that&#8217;s too loose at home.</p>
<p>The problem is, that Chinese policymakers want to rein in accommodative policy without raising rates too much because they don&#8217;t want the currency to appreciate markedly and are unable to fully sterilize all the flows. Inflation results.</p>
<p>If Chinese policymakers question how to achieve their top economic priority, price stability, then the answer to this self-induced problem is pretty obvious: significantly raise rates and the value of the currency.</p>
<p><em><strong>Rebecca Wilder</strong></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/03/its-pretty-obvious-how-china-can-achieve-its-top-economic-priority-of-price-stability.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>According to the Setser Test, it&#8217;s unlikely that China reduced its Treasury holdings in November</title>
		<link>./../../2011/01/according-to-the-setser-test-its-unlikely-that-china-reduced-its-treasury-holdings-in-november.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/01/according-to-the-setser-test-its-unlikely-that-china-reduced-its-treasury-holdings-in-november.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Jan 2011 20:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[China]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rebecca Wilder]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[TIC release]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/01/according-to-the-setser-test-its-unlikely-that-china-reduced-its-treasury-holdings-in-november.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[According to the Treasury International Capital System (TIC) release, foreigners were net buyers of US securities in November, +$39 billion over the month. Of the $61.7 billion in long-term Treasuries net purchased (notes and bonds), private investors claimed $50.6, while official investors (central banks, sovereign wealth funds, etc.) accrued a smaller $11.1 billion. Over the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_Et4TQ-a0gGU/TTY0hkgsvaI/AAAAAAAADcA/66WykKjfwt0/s1600/CA_TIC_chart.jpg"><img alt="" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_Et4TQ-a0gGU/TTY0hkgsvaI/AAAAAAAADcA/66WykKjfwt0/s320/CA_TIC_chart.jpg" border="0"></a>According to the <a href="http://www.treasury.gov/resource-center/data-chart-center/tic/Pages/index.aspx">Treasury International Capital System</a> (TIC) release, foreigners were net buyers of US securities in November, +$39 billion over the month. Of the $61.7 billion in long-term Treasuries net purchased (notes and bonds), private investors claimed $50.6, while official investors (central banks, sovereign wealth funds, etc.) accrued a smaller $11.1 billion. Over the last twelve months, foreign investors amassed $571 billion of the high-quality US securities: Treasury notes and bonds, agencies, and stocks, which includes the -$12 billion net sale of corporate bonds. Overall, it was a reasonably positive report, indicating that long-term asset sales are roughly in line with the current account deficit (chart to the upper left).</p>
<p>But the pundits follow <a href="http://www.treasury.gov/resource-center/data-chart-center/tic/Documents/mfh.txt">the table on</a> major foreign holders of US Treasuries. <a href="http://www.zerohedge.com/article/november-tic-data-update-china-treasury-holdings-decline-112-billion">They note</a> that the number 1 holder, China, reduced its holdings of Treasuries in November from just over $900 billion to just under. For some reason, investors and critics of the deficit alike are worried that when China is no longer named the US&#8217; biggest stockpiler of Treasury securities, Treasury rates will skyrocket. Oh, the bond vigilantes.</p>
<p>And this is when I really miss Brad Setser&#8217;s commentary (he is now at the National Economic Council). He noted time and time again, that the monthly TIC data tend to under-report the Chinese holdings, especially when they are shifting their portfolio holdings of US Treasuries up the curve. Well, that&#8217;s what the Chinese did in November: holdings of US Tbills dropped $21 billion, while longer-term note holdings increased a net $9.9 billion. (more after the jump)<br /><a name="more"></a></p>
<p><a href="http://blogs.cfr.org/setser/2009/06/19/i-am-pretty-sure-china-didnt-sell-treasuries-in-april-or-may-for-that-matter/">According to Brad Setser</a>, only in the annual <a href="http://www.treasury.gov/resource-center/data-chart-center/tic/Pages/fpis.aspx">survey of US portfolio holdings</a> are China&#8217;s measured holdings of US Treasuries accurate:<br />
<blockquote>This is actually a well established pattern. The past five surveys of foreign portfolio investment in the US have all revised China’s long-term Treasury holdings up (in some cases quite significantly) even as they revised the UK’s holdings down. The following graph shows the gap between Chinese long-term Treasury purchases in the TIC data and China’s actual purchases of long-term Treasuries– as revealed in the survey.</p></blockquote>
<p>Brad Setser&#8217;s quote was from 2009, but the story hasn&#8217;t changed since. In the 2010 report for 2009 foreign holdings, the level of Chinese Treasury holdings was revised up from the TIC-implied level by near $140 billion, while that of the UK was revised down (by over 100 billion, I might add). Clockwork.</p>
<p>So let&#8217;s apply Brad&#8217;s test, <strong>I&#8217;ll call it the Setser Test</strong>, to see if China actually reduced US Treasury holdings in November, as the November TIC release suggests. (I highlighted Brad&#8217;s test in bold italics, RW is me). <a href="http://blogs.cfr.org/setser/2009/06/19/i-am-pretty-sure-china-didnt-sell-treasuries-in-april-or-may-for-that-matter/">The test is listed in the middle of this post.<br /></a><br /><strong>Brad: First, the TIC data should show a fall in China’s holdings, i.e. net sales of Treasuries.</strong></p>
<p>RW: Yes.</p>
<p><strong>Second, the TIC data should also show limited purchases of Treasuries through the UK.</p>
<p></strong><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_Et4TQ-a0gGU/TTc4p5bSryI/AAAAAAAADcQ/ylPhU_-gc6I/s1600/treasury_country.JPG"><strong><img alt="" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_Et4TQ-a0gGU/TTc4p5bSryI/AAAAAAAADcQ/ylPhU_-gc6I/s320/treasury_country.JPG" border="0"></strong></a>RW: No. The UK bought near $25 billion in Treasury notes and bonds, which more than offset the drop in Chinese Treasury buying. In fact, if the TIC data is accurate, the UK is amassing a rather large stockpile of US Treasuries. This would be in sharp contrast with the average $48 billion balance of Treasury holdings since 2006 (<a href="http://www.treasury.gov/resource-center/data-chart-center/tic/Pages/ticsec.aspx">Table 4 or 5 depending on the year</a>)!</p>
<p><strong>Third, the Fed’s custodial holdings should not be rising at a strong clip — as, given China’s size, it is hard to see how China doesn’t make up a large fraction of all custodial holdings.</p>
<p></strong>RW: <a href="http://federalreserve.gov/releases/h41/Current/">The Fed&#8217;s custodial holdings</a> increased by a sizable $39 billion. More likely than not, this was due in part to Chinese activity.</p>
<p>So according to the Setser Test, it&#8217;s very unlikely that China reduced its Treasury holdings in November. In fact they probably increased their Treasury holdings, given the magnitude of the Fed&#8217;s custodial balance.</p>
<p>Rebecca Wilder</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/01/according-to-the-setser-test-its-unlikely-that-china-reduced-its-treasury-holdings-in-november.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Confusions and policies&#8230;let&#8217;s keep the players in mind all around</title>
		<link>./../../2010/12/confusions-and-policies-lets-keep-the-players-in-mind-all-around.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/12/confusions-and-policies-lets-keep-the-players-in-mind-all-around.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 18 Dec 2010 17:43:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[China]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[free trade]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[international trade]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/12/confusions-and-policies-lets-keep-the-players-in-mind-all-around.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Chinese Confusions by Paul Krugman These days, China seems to play the same role in much of our discourse that Japan did two decades ago. We look at our own follies — which are immense — and then look at the Chinese, and ascribe to them all the virtues of foresight and determination we lack. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a target="_blank" href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2010/12/17/chinese-confusions/">Chinese Confusions</a>  <br />by Paul Krugman</p>
<blockquote><p>These days, China seems to play the same role in much of our discourse that Japan did two decades ago. We look at our own follies — which are immense — and then look at the Chinese, and ascribe to them all the virtues of foresight and determination we lack.</p>
<p>But just like the Japanese, the Chinese are human, and their policy makers are subject to the same kinds of confusion and inability to make hard choices that are part of the human condition. And Chinese macroeconomic policy is in the process of becoming a cautionary tale.</p>
<p>Basic economics says that by deciding to keep the renminbi undervalued, the Chinese put themselves <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2010/11/17/swan-songs/">under inflationary pressure</a>; and sure enough, inflation is rapidly becoming a serious problem.</p>
<p>But political considerations seem to be <a href="http://curiouscapitalist.blogs.time.com/2010/12/17/china%E2%80%99s-inflation-problem-and-the-perils-of-unconventional-policy/?utm_source=feedburner&#038;utm_medium=feed&#038;utm_campaign=Feed:+timeblogs/curious_capitalist+(TIME:+The+Curious+Capitalist)">ruling out all the reasonable responses</a>. They won’t revalue, because that would hurt politically influential exporters. They’re reluctant to raise interest rates, because that would hurt politically influential real estate developers. They’re trying to impose quantitative limits on credit, but are finding that borrowers have enough influence to circumvent the limits. And now they’re trying price controls — which will inevitably come apart at the seams unless they do something about the underlying pressures.</p>
<p>It’s an edifying spectacle.</p>
<p>Now, <em>schadenfreude</em> should not lead to any complaceny on our part; China may be corrupt and unable to make sensible short-run choices, but in terms of fundamental inability to deal with long-term problems, we still have them beat hands down. Still, it’s worth remembering that all giants have feet of clay.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/12/confusions-and-policies-lets-keep-the-players-in-mind-all-around.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>China&#8217;s competitive devaluation</title>
		<link>./../../2010/10/chinas-competitive-devaluation.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/10/chinas-competitive-devaluation.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Oct 2010 12:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[China]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[currency]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/10/chinas-competitive-devaluation.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[China took the world by surprise on Tuesday by raising bank lending and deposit rates for the first time since 2007. The story is, that restrictive monetary policy (i.e., raising rates) is needed to curb excessive lending, with an eye on mitigating inflation pressures. See this Bloomberg article to the point. While restrictive monetary policy [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>China took the world by surprise on Tuesday by raising bank lending and deposit rates for the first time since 2007. The story is, that restrictive monetary policy (i.e., raising rates) is needed to curb excessive lending, with an eye on mitigating inflation pressures. See this <a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2010-10-19/china-central-bank-raises-one-year-lending-deposit-rates-25-basis-points.html">Bloomberg article to the point</a>.</p>
<p>While restrictive monetary policy is needed, raising rates is not the only tool available to policy makers: China could allow their currency (CNY) to appreciate. With support from the fiscal sector, a broad CNY appreciation would improve prospects for global growth ex China via import demand. Instead, the higher domestic rates may crimp domestic demand, perhaps reducing inflation, but contemporaneously lowering import demand.</p>
<p>In my view, China&#8217;s move yesterday should be viewed as competitive devaluation: reducing domestic prices in order to capture a competive edge. The currency war, as so-called by <a href="http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/33ff9624-ca48-11df-a860-00144feab49a.html">Brazil’s finance minister, Guido Mantega</a>, is afoot; and China just confirmed its participation.<a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Textbook economics says that a central bank cannot have it all: independent monetary policy, a fixed exchange rate, and open financial markets (the impossible trinity). China has a fixed exchange rate (currently, it&#8217;s effectively pegged to the USD, see chart below) with tightly monitored capital markets. This means that the Chinese economy effectively matches the &#8220;easy monetary conditions&#8221; of its counterpart, the US. Monetary policy in China is too loose.</p>
<p>Going forward, further accommodative monetary policy in the <a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2010-10-19/fed-presidents-reinforce-case-for-further-asset-purchases-by-central-bank.html">US</a> will likewise loosen policy further in China; inflation pressures will be even more robust. But, large-scale asset purchases on the part of the Fed will likewise weaken the USD, which is positive for US exports and negative for US import demand.</p>
<p>All in all, policy makers in China are looking at the USD move with tunnel vision. If the CNY maintians its current trajectory (effectively flat), then any shift in relative prices based on the recent (or future) rate hikes will reduce the CNY real exchange rate (all else equal, of course) &#8211; that&#8217;s competitive domestic devaluation.</p>
<p>The table has already been set.</p>
<p><strong>Chinese policy makers have slowed the nominal appreciation.</strong> Think about what could be if the CNY had maintained its 2005-2008 trajectory, where the CNY appreciated against the USD nearly 20%. Using the compounded annual growth rate (CAGR) over the same period, where the CNY gained 0.5% on a monthly basis against the USD, the month-end September CNY would be valued 11% higher against the USD than it is now.</p>
<p><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_Et4TQ-a0gGU/TL6-ylgYyZI/AAAAAAAADS8/gPTxPtIqdU0/s1600/CNY_chart.png"><img alt="" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_Et4TQ-a0gGU/TL6-ylgYyZI/AAAAAAAADS8/gPTxPtIqdU0/s400/CNY_chart.png" border="0"></a><br /><strong>They slowed real appreciation, too.</strong> The real appreciation of the CNY against its trading partners – the real exchange rate accounts for both nominal appreciation and price differentials across countries – slowed from an average 0.4% monthly gain spanning the period 2005-2008, as measured by the CAGR, to just 0.05% since then. (I use the JPMorgan real exchange rate index, but the <a href="http://www.bis.org/statistics/eer/index.htm">BIS makes similar data available free of charge</a>.)</p>
<p>The Chinese authorities are fully aware of the economic value of external demand (exports). The media will say that China’s trying to “cool” domestic inflation by raising domestic bank rates; but that’s not the full story. In my view, what they’re really trying to do is to <em>“cool” domestic inflation in order to shift relative prices and depreciate the real exchange rate, all to gain a competitive advantage in global goods markets</em>.</p>
<p><strong><em>Rebecca Wilder</em></strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/10/chinas-competitive-devaluation.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
