<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Law &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 12:45:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Reading articles on federal circuit courts&#8230;can a layman follow?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/reading-articles-on-federal-circuit-courts-can-a-layman-follow.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/reading-articles-on-federal-circuit-courts-can-a-layman-follow.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 27 Dec 2012 22:17:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Beverly Mann]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[federal circuit curts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Law]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/reading-articles-on-federal-circuit-courts-can-a-layman-follow.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[When I forwarded this link to Beverly Mann I was interested in  following the current thread on civil rights, the legalities of state use of torture,  the continuation  in the NDAA exclusion of the prohibition of the use of indefinite detention for domestic &#8216;terrorism&#8217;, etc.  This note is more a lesson for reading newsy items. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When I forwarded this link to Beverly Mann I was interested in  following the current thread on civil rights, the legalities of state use of torture,  the continuation  in the NDAA exclusion of the prohibition of the use of indefinite detention for domestic &#8216;terrorism&#8217;, etc.  This note is more a lesson for reading newsy items.</p>
<p><a href="http://truth-out.org/news/item/13542-court-rules-antiwar-activists-can-sue-government-spies">Court rules anti war activists can sue government spies</a>  </p>
<p><i>Beverly writes</i> in an e-mail today:</p>
<p>Hmm. This is good, but, for complicated procedural reasons&#8211;complicated procedural reasons? surprise, surprise!&#8211;it’s not quite what it would seem to be to a lay person.<br />    <br />The first tip-off, to me, is that the opinion is an “unpublished,” non-precedential one. Which is what most federal appellate opinions these days are. They’re written quickly, often not very carefully, usually by a judge’s law clerk, and, in several of the regional federal circuit courts (appellate courts), including in this one (the Ninth Circuit), written “per curiam,” i.e., the judge who wrote (or had a law clerk write) it is not identified; it’s just identified as issued by the three-judge panel. These opinions are not published in the formal law books, called the Federal Reporter series, and they do not have the force of law in any case but the one in which they’re issued. They can be mentioned in briefs in later, similar cases, but the judges in the later cases are not required to follow the holding in the earlier, non-precedential case.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>This opinion is so truncated and so poorly written that that I had to read it three times in order to understand what the hell was, and was not, decided in it. Two of the three judges&#8211;William Fletcher and Raymond Fisher&#8211;are among the few really liberal Clinton appointees (I’m much more familiar with Fletcher, who is prominent nationally). And both are really smart. So I’m sort of surprised that they allowed something so garbled to be issued in their name, in a case that, despite the attempt to keep it from making headlines (by making it an “unpublished” opinion), was bound to get some small bit of attention (although your email to me with the link to the article about it is the only thing I’ve seen written about it, maybe because it’s Christmas week and everyone’s on vacation).<br />     <br />The big problem with the way the opinion is written is that it conflates two separate legal doctrines: A longstanding Supreme Court-created legal doctrine called “qualified immunity” and a very new, and highly controversial, Supreme Court-created doctrine just known as “Twombly and Iqbal,” the two recent (2007 and 2009, respectively) Supreme Court opinions that created the doctrine by,in essence, rewriting a statutory federal rule of civil procedure that sets out minimum standards for specificity in a legal complaint (the document in which you file a civil lawsuit) in federal court.<br />    <br />“Qualified immunity” is entirely different than just plain old immunity, although the effect is the same: the defendant can’t be sued. The doctrine of qualified immunity&#8211;which the right wing Supreme Court justices keep expanding, notwithstanding their public protestations that they are “textualists” in interpreting statutes (suffice it to say that they most certainly are not)&#8211;holds that government officials and government employees cannot be held liable for violations of civil rights unless it already was clearly established in law that their action violated a civil right. Conservative justices and lower-court judges have increasingly required that the action by the government official or employee (e.g., a police officer) be nearly identical to the action at issue in an earlier Supreme Court case or appellate case issued by that federal appellate court (opinions issued by other regional federal appellate courts don’t count); otherwise the defendant official or employee has “qualified immunity” from liability.<br />     <br />“Qualified immunity” applies to people who are employed by, or are acting on behalf of or at the behest of, the federal government or a state or local government. It does not apply to anyone else.    <br />Another Supreme Court-created rule of law on “qualified immunity” is that, although there are almost no circumstances in which a party can appeal from an interlocutory order (an order issued before the entire lawsuit is resolved), government officials and employees can file an immediate interlocutory appeal if the trial-court-level judge denies their motion to dismiss the claims against them as barred by the doctrine of qualified immunity. That’s what happened here.<br />     <br />What’s so confusing is that, normally, the only issues in a “qualified immunity” interlocutory appeal are whether the defendant official or employee did violate a civil right and, if so, whether the law was clear enough at the time to place the defendant on reasonable notice that his or her actions would violate a clearly established civil right. In this case, though, the defendants apparently were not claiming that the civil rights at issue in the part of the complaint that the trial-court judge did not dismiss&#8211;First Amendment and Fourth Amendment rights that are relevant to the case&#8211;were not clearly established at the time of their actions. They were claiming instead that the complaint didn’t detail their actions that would amount to First and Fourth Amendment rights with enough specificity to satisfy the Supreme Court-created specificity requirement of Twombly and Iqbal (which actually is pretty much the opposite of the level of specificity that the actual statutory rule of federal procedure states).<br />     <br />Normally, that is not an issue that could be decided in an interlocutory appeal. But because the defendants were claiming (I guess) that the complaint was too unspecific to be able to tell whether the actions alleged in the complaint violated a civil right under clearly established law, they could raise this issue in the interlocutory “qualified immunity” appeal. And the three-judge panel said, in essence, that the claim that the defendants’ actions weren’t sufficiently specific to meet the Twombly/Iqbal test was ridiculous. The complaint detailed allegations of fact that could reasonably be seen by a jury as taken for an improper purpose under clearly established First Amendment law, and detailed allegations of fact that would violate the Fourth Amendment under clearly established law.<br />    <br />What was not at issue in the appeal, best as I can tell, is the issue of whether the military has “absolute immunity”&#8211;immunity from liability simply because it was the military, and civilians hired by the military, doing these things. Apparently, the defendants did not make that claim, and the article you linked to seems to suggest that that it is a surprise, or anyway that it is a surprise that the appellate court let the lawsuit proceed. It sounds to me like the plaintiffs an their lawyers feared that the government would raise the “state secrets” privilege. Here’s Wikipedia’s explanation of it:</p>
<blockquote><p>The state secrets privilege is an <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evidence_(law)">evidentiary rule</a> created by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States">United States</a> legal <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Precedent">precedent</a>. Application of the privilege results in exclusion of evidence from a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Legal_case">legal case</a> based solely on <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Affidavits">affidavits</a> submitted by the government stating that court proceedings might disclose sensitive information which might endanger national security. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_v._Reynolds">United States v. Reynolds</a>, which involved military secrets, was the first case that saw formal recognition of the privilege. </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Following a claim of &#8220;state secrets privilege&#8221;, the court rarely conducts an <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/In_camera">in camera</a> examination of the evidence to evaluate whether there is sufficient cause to support the use of this doctrine. This results in court rulings in which even the judge has not verified the veracity of the assertion. The privileged material is completely removed from the litigation, and the court must determine how the unavailability of the privileged information affects the case.</p></blockquote>
<p>But claiming a state-secrets privilege on this would have been preposterous, would not have succeeded, and would have been a public relations disaster. So, while the opinion is nice, it just doesn’t strike me as a big breakthrough. Then again, I’m no expert in national security law, so maybe I’m missing something.<br />   <br />The link to the opinion is file:///media/removable/USB%20Drive/9th%20Circuit%20Deicsion%20affirming%20denial%20of%2012(b)(6)-Iqbal%20(1).pdf.</p>
<p>Not sure you wanted such a long, detailed explanation, but this stuff is so technical that it requires one in order to be of any use.</p>
<p>Beverly</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/reading-articles-on-federal-circuit-courts-can-a-layman-follow.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Religious freedom, contraception, and law</title>
		<link>./../../2012/11/religious-freedom-contraception-and-law.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/11/religious-freedom-contraception-and-law.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 29 Nov 2012 13:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Supreme court]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/11/religious-freedom-contraception-and-law.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Lifted from a note from Beverly Mann in response to a query of mine, as a note of interest: Here&#8217;s a link to a long Politico article on those cases and on the prospects of their success: http://dyn.politico.com/printstory.cfm?uuid=67901EA4-2955-4FD7-A52E-1E8CB0EA8E56 Apparently it looks like the Supreme Court eventually will hear two or three of these cases, probably [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Lifted from a note from Beverly Mann in response to a query of mine, as a note of interest:</p>
<p>Here&#8217;s a link to a long Politico article on those cases and on the prospects of their success:</p>
<p><a href="http://dyn.politico.com/printstory.cfm?uuid=67901EA4-2955-4FD7-A52E-1E8CB0EA8E56">http://dyn.politico.com/printstory.cfm?uuid=67901EA4-2955-4FD7-A52E-1E8CB0EA8E56</a></p>
<p>Apparently it looks like the Supreme Court eventually will hear two or three of these cases, probably all at one time, and draw some line about which organizations and for-profit companies are entitled to be exempt from the contraception part of the mandate. But mainly, these lawsuits concern a federal statute called <em>The Religious Freedom Restoration Act</em>, which provides religious protections for these groups beyond what the Supreme Court has held that the First Amendment requires. That statute was passed in reaction to a Supreme Court opinion that defined the First Amendment&#8217;s Free Exercise clause more narrowly than a majority of Congress thought was appropriate.</p>
<p>The Politico article gives a pretty detailed rundown on this.</p>
<p><i>Beverly</i></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/11/religious-freedom-contraception-and-law.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>An Invitation for Libertarians</title>
		<link>./../../2011/06/an-invitation-for-libertarians.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/06/an-invitation-for-libertarians.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 26 Jun 2011 15:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[libertarian]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[liberty]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/06/an-invitation-for-libertarians.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[An Invitation for Libertarians Here at Angry Bear, we&#8217;ve had a number of posts on LIbertarians over the years. Inevitably, someone writes to tell us we&#8217;re misrepresenting Libertarians&#8230; even when we&#8217;re quoting well known libertarians. So&#8230; if you are libertarian consider this an invitation. Send me one to three paragraphs on what it means to [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>An Invitation for Libertarians</strong></p>
<p>Here at <a target="-blank" href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/">Angry Bear</a>, we&#8217;ve had a number of posts on LIbertarians over the years.  Inevitably, someone writes to tell us we&#8217;re misrepresenting Libertarians&#8230; even when we&#8217;re quoting well known libertarians.  </p>
<p>So&#8230; if you are libertarian consider this an invitation.  Send me one to three paragraphs on what it means to be a libertarian or what libertarianism is.  Or put it in comments.  (I beg the indulgence of non-libertarians to please not put up comments of their own.)  If you feel what you are writing about applies particularly to one or another strain of libertarianism, please make that clear. </p>
<p>I will put up as a separate post, verbatim, those e-mails and comments I get sent that seem to me to best tell the libertarian story from the libertarian perspective to the slightly left of center audience that resides here at Angry Bear.  (I can&#8217;t promise to print everything that comes in to avoid the sort of repetition that will simply detract from the story.) </p>
<p>Here&#8217;s your chance to have your story told in your words.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/06/an-invitation-for-libertarians.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Michelle Malkin Will Get the Vapors When She Sees This</title>
		<link>./../../2008/05/michelle-malkin-will-get-the-vapors-when-she-sees-this.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/05/michelle-malkin-will-get-the-vapors-when-she-sees-this.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2008 20:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Law]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/05/michelle-malkin-will-get-the-vapors-when-she-sees-this.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[As a direct result of the six-Republican, one Democrat California Supreme Court&#8217;s decision last week, people who have shared everything for 21 years now get to marry. Pull quote: As a Japanese American, I am keenly mindful of the subtle and not so subtle discrimination that the law can impose. During World War II, I [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As a direct result of the six-Republican, one Democrat California Supreme Court&#8217;s decision last week, people <a href="http://www.georgetakei.com/news.asp">who have shared everything for 21 years</a> now get to marry. Pull quote:<br />
<blockquote>As a Japanese American, I am keenly mindful of the subtle and not so subtle discrimination that the law can impose. During World War II, I grew up imprisoned behind the barbed wire fences of U.S. internment camps. Pearl Harbor had been bombed and Japanese Americans were rounded up and incarcerated simply because we happened to look like the people who bombed Pearl Harbor. Fear and war hysteria swept the nation. A Presidential Executive Order directed the internment of Japanese Americans as a matter of national security. Now, with the passage of time, we look back and see it as a shameful chapter of American history. President Gerald Ford rescinded the Executive Order that imprisoned us. President Ronald Reagan formally apologized for the unjust imprisonment. President George H.W. Bush signed the redress payment checks to the survivors. It was a tragic and dark taint on American history. [Updated to note: Three Republicans, including an alleged totemic icon. The Ancestral Party used to know how to Do the Right Thing.]</p>
<p>With time, I know the opposition to same sex marriage, too, will be seen as an antique and discreditable part of our history. As U.S. Supreme Court Justice Anthony Kennedy remarked on same sex marriage, &#8220;Times can blind us to certain truths and later generations can see that laws once thought necessary and proper, in fact, serve only to oppress.&#8221; </p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/05/michelle-malkin-will-get-the-vapors-when-she-sees-this.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Psycological Kevlar</title>
		<link>./../../2008/01/psycological-kevlar.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/01/psycological-kevlar.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 16 Jan 2008 01:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[PTSD]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Veterans]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/01/psycological-kevlar.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Psychological Kevlar Act of 2007 introduced by Patrick Kennedy was to help PTSD and brain trauma research expand. It has come to my attention that the DoD is thinking about using propranolol as a prophylactic to help reduce ptsd symptoms during conflict and after. I had found this articlefrom a wife of a soldier who [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://thomas.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/z?c110:H.R.3256"><br />Psychological Kevlar Act of 2007</a> introduced by Patrick Kennedy was to help PTSD and brain trauma research expand.</p>
<p>It has come to my attention that the DoD is thinking about using propranolol as a prophylactic to help reduce ptsd symptoms during conflict and after. I had found <a href="http://www.alternet.org/healthwellness/72956/">this article</a>from a wife of a soldier who had killed himself, and who had testified in a Dec. 12, 2007 congressional hearing on suicide among veterans that is apparently on the rise.  She has a strong and passionate viewpoint, but that is not for the post.</p>
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Propranolol">Propranolol</a> (brand name Inde by Wyeth) is used for a number of diagnosis not related to ptsd.  In addition it is used in the psychological Anxiety area as a beta blocker among other uses,  for example for rape victims  ptsd to help defuse the intensity of the experience in order to work in therapy.  Its efficacy is still experimental and not encouraging.</p>
<p>Failing to locate such information, I am wondering if readers may have leads.  While an econ blog, many here are also veterans.  Thanks.  Further information is coming if warranted.  I have e-mailed relevant experts that I know.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/01/psycological-kevlar.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
