<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>budget deficits &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Austerity and Budgets explained</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/austerity-and-budgets-explained.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/austerity-and-budgets-explained.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2013 15:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[austerity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[balanced budgets]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[budget deficits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[budget proposals]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/austerity-and-budgets-explained.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In support of Beverly&#8217;s latest post and all her past postings wanting for Obama (or the Dem&#8217;s in general I would say) to explain the truth about how a government&#8217;s money really flows, I present this video from the Watson Institute. (via Didby at Hullaaloo.)  I happen to agree, it would be nice if our [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In support of Beverly&#8217;s <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/03/douglas-holtz-eakin-balancing-budget-is.html" target="_blank">latest post</a> and all her past postings wanting for Obama (or the Dem&#8217;s in general I would say) to explain the truth about how a government&#8217;s money really flows, I present this video from the Watson Institute. (via Didby at Hullaaloo.)  I happen to agree, it would be nice if our president would get it straight, but&#8230;</p>
<p><a href="http://vimeo.com/15061570">The Watson Institute presents Mark Blyth on Austerity</a> from <a href="http://vimeo.com/globalconv">The Global Conversation</a> on <a href="http://vimeo.com/">Vimeo</a>.</p>
<p> Of course, my pet peeve is that no one is talking about our nation&#8217;s equity.  I am confident that the American family would get that part of financing as it relates to borrowing and investing.  Heck, how long was it before Amazon broke even yet they kept right on borrowing and growing?*  Or lets put it closer to home.  How many Americans purchased a home that was valued at and borrowed against for the purchase that was equal to their annual income?  What was the old rule&#8230;3 times the median income was the average home price?</p>
<p>*<a href="http://(incorporated%201994,%201st%20profit%20announced%202002)/" target="_blank">incorporated 1994</a>, 1st profit announced 2002</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/austerity-and-budgets-explained.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>$1 trillion to be spent on direct hiring&#8230;that&#8217;s the ticket!</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/1-trillion-to-be-spent-on-direct-hiring-thats-the-ticket.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/1-trillion-to-be-spent-on-direct-hiring-thats-the-ticket.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2013 03:36:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[budget deficits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chris Hayes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economic recovery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[new deal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the sequester]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/1-trillion-to-be-spent-on-direct-hiring-thats-the-ticket.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[With all this stalemate posturing in Washington, today Chris Hayes has come up with the best idea I have heard yet to move the players. And, in my opinion actually solve our economic depression. One trillion dollars to be spent on direct hiring by the government along with debt forgiveness.  A solution right out of [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>With all this stalemate posturing in Washington, today Chris Hayes has come up with the best idea I have heard yet to move the players.  And, in my opinion actually solve our economic depression.</div>
<div></div>
<div>One trillion dollars to be spent on direct hiring by the government along with debt forgiveness.  A solution right out of the New Deal program.  Unfortunately for Chris, Obama does not have the language within his vocabulary to recognize such an approach and thus in Obama&#8217;s <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/ref/us/politics/21seelye-text.html" target="_blank">own words</a>: “&#8230;put us on a fundamentally different path because the country was ready for it.”</div>
<div></div>
<div>In fact, not only does he not have the language within his vocabulary to recognize a solution from history, he thinks the <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/ref/us/politics/21seelye-text.html" target="_blank">60&#8217;s and 70&#8217;s</a> were full of excesses (while noting Kennedy moved the nation in a new direction&#8230;right into the excesses of the 60&#8217;s?)*</div>
<div></div>
<p>
<div>Visit NBCNews.com for <a href="http://www.nbcnews.com/">breaking news</a>, <a href="http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/3032507">world news</a>, and <a href="http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/3032072">news about the economy</a> </div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>Do you think anyone who remembers what it meant to be a leader in the Democratic Party was watching?   </div>
<div></div>
<div>*“I do think that, for example, the 1980 election was different. I think Ronald Reagan changed the trajectory of America in a way that, you know, Richard Nixon did not and in a way that Bill Clinton did not.”</div>
<div>&#8220;He put us on a fundamentally different path because the country was ready for it. I think they felt like, you know, with all the excesses of the 60s and the 70s, and government had grown and grown, but there wasn&#8217;t much sense of accountability in terms of how it was operating. I think people just tapped into &#8212; he tapped into what people were already feeling, which was, we want clarity, we want optimism, we want a return to that sense of dynamism and entrepreneurship that had been missing.”  </div>
<div></div>
<div><i>Don&#8217;t get me going on the people wanting &#8220;clarity&#8221; (security state that even the congress can&#8217;t get info on) and &#8220;optimism&#8221; (the audacity!).</i></div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/1-trillion-to-be-spent-on-direct-hiring-thats-the-ticket.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The rest of the dinner table deficit/debt discussion: Equity</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/the-rest-of-the-dinner-table-deficitdebt-discussion-equity.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/the-rest-of-the-dinner-table-deficitdebt-discussion-equity.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 23 Feb 2013 05:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[#spendingstheproblem]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[assets]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[budget deficits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[conservative thought]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[debt]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economic growth]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[equity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/the-rest-of-the-dinner-table-deficitdebt-discussion-equity.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I promise, there are numbers here, but lets have some fun first and write a screen play to set up the point. It is long, but&#8230; &#8220;Dear, I&#8217;m getting nervous. We seem to keep adding to how much money we owe and our income hasn&#8217;t changed for the better. What can we do?&#8221; At this [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I promise, there are numbers here, but lets have some fun first and write a screen play to set up the point.  It is long, but&#8230; 
<div></div>
<div>&#8220;Dear, I&#8217;m getting nervous.  We seem to keep adding to how much money we owe and our income hasn&#8217;t changed for the better.  What can we do?&#8221;</div>
<div></div>
<div>At this point of the conversation, the conservative ideology (Republican and Democratic Parties) suggests and encourages you to believe that the answer is something like: &#8220;Well Honey, as I look over the horizon I see no possibility for improving our current position.  The only thing we can do is cut back on our spending.  We have to stop spending on anything we don&#8217;t need to live.  If we are willing to sacrifice then eventually we&#8217;ll have savings that we can then use to invest such that we have more income.&#8221;</div>
<div></div>
<div>Now, for most Americans at this moment in the euphemistically labeled &#8220;business cycle&#8221; Honey&#8217;s response would be: &#8220;But I don&#8217;t know where else we can cut!&#8221; Of course to the conservative there is always something that money is being spent on that is in actuality an indulgence for which one should repent and thus cut from their spending if said spending is greater than one&#8217;s income.  This is true because no righteous individual would ever let the devil of consumption tempt them from the path to wealth heaven.  Redeem one&#8217;s self through the power of restraint of consumption urges.</div>
<div></div>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<div>There are multiple things wrong with such a screenplay.  For instance, I&#8217;ve noted in the past that we really do not need banks.  You and I could do everything we want without a bank.  I could build a business even, without a bank.  Granted I could not build it as big and as fast as with working with a bank, but I could build one.  What the bank does is allow one to borrow against the future.  Lending allows the acceleration of the experience and results of the  movement of money.  Certainly that acceleration can result in a loss just as easily as a win, but then that is why we have all sorts of experts in money that can help one make the better odds beating decision such that the acceleration produces a win.  Dear is corrected in that they could do cuts and save and then take the next step.  It was <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0093936/" target="_blank">Howard Prescott&#8217;s</a> approach.</div>
<div></div>
<div>We&#8217;re talking about lending here.  Borrowing money.  It is accepted within that part of the conservative ideology which focuses on the concept of money that lending and borrowing are a given.  It is an indisputable fact that such activity exists, is righteous and good.  It is as much a part of the reality of life as oxygen is.  It is a fact of nature.  Nothing could ever be fully realized without lending and borrowing.  Nothing!  Thus banks are a necessity for life it&#8217;s self.  So I hear.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Lending and borrowing is so much a part of nature that nature is currently ill and struggling because lending is not happening.  Business can&#8217;t get loans and thus expand resulting in job creation.  At least that is what I have been told.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Businesses can&#8217;t get loans and expand and hire.  Think about that statement and let&#8217;s change the screenplay.  &#8220;Dear, I&#8217;m worried we are missing an opportunity here.  You know our income is not changing and we are adding debt.  If you would just let me borrow some money I could hire someone to help me around the house and buy the tickets to that &#8216;How to make money in real estate&#8217; seminar.  We could apply that knowledge and within a few years be making more money.&#8221;     </div>
<div></div>
<div>Maybe you don&#8217;t think spending money on “How to make money in real estate” is the smart move, but is the proper natural answer to say: &#8220;Honey, you know we have to cut back on our spending and wait until we have saved enough to implement your plan.&#8221; ?  Is the proper natural answer to tell someone to wait until they have saved their money before they decide to get an education?  If your business is auto repair, is the proper answer to tell someone to wait until they have saved their money before they buy the tools needed for fixing cars?  Would RI have been able to implement their emissions testing which required the purchase of dynos by the garages if the answer was: Wait until you have saved the money to buy the dyno?</div>
<div></div>
<div>Of course not.  So this gets to one reason why the conservative concept, government borrowing is the wrong course of action, is it&#8217;s self so wrong never mind completely blasphemous according to their ideology. It is also why, when conservatives are in charge they do not cut and save.  They spend and borrow.  It is natural.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Let&#8217;s take Honey&#8217;s and Dear&#8217;s screenplay a little further.  &#8220;But Dear, right now the rates are very low, lower than our mortgage.  Also, the equity we have in the house is about 86%.  I&#8217;ve consulted with the accountant, your friend the business consultant, listened to CNBC, Fox Business and interviewed others regarding &#8216;How to make money in real estate&#8217;.  They all agree, my plan is doable and appears sound.  If we just take about 15% of the equity, invest it in our knowledge and then apply the knowledge we will be doing better.&#8221;</div>
<div></div>
<div>We are now at the stickler of our dear conservative&#8217;s answer.  &#8220;&#8230; I see no possibility for improving our current position&#8230;&#8221;.   This is the part of the answer one has to believe in if you are to accept that the solution is only to cut and save.  This is the part of the answer that completely will not fit, will make you choke, will make you stumble when considering any other scenario related to the dear conservative&#8217;s understanding of nature.  Lending and borrowing is natural, righteous and good.   Do you want to make the banks extinct in nature?  If the answer is to &#8220;cut and save&#8221; then that is the implied desired results if we are to believe &#8220;I see no possibility for improving our current position&#8221;.   Go ahead, try to gel the two concepts.  Try to make your brain hold &#8220;I see no possibility, we must cut and save&#8221; and &#8220;lending and borrowing are natural, righteous and good&#8221; at the same time.   </div>
<div></div>
<div>I ask you, be honest.  Which screenplay seems the more likely for Honey and Dear as they sit around the table.  Is it the one where they only cut spending or the one where a plan is laid out and they go to the bank so that they can accelerate the implementation and thus achieve the benefits sooner?    Which plan has the greater potential gain?  And, which one would be considered adding to the nations GDP?  Are the vast majority of the 99% really just sitting back and accepting their lot or are they actually trying to plan and implement the plan?  The simple fact that GDP is growing confirms the latter.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Here is the next thing wrong with the first screenplay but correct about the rewritten screenplay: equity.</div>
<div>At no time is the conservative (Republican or Democratic Party) using that word.  Have your heard anyone talk about the nations equity?  Its assets worth&#8230; net worth?  Even by those who know we need to spend (the freshwater Keynes minded economists) I have not seen it mentioned as part of why we could borrow without fear.  Borrowing is always justified with the rates are low, it would create jobs and grow the economy.  Of course with the subscript caution note of maybe inflation in the future.   </div>
<div></div>
<div>OK, everyone gets that part. Honey got that part.  But, Honey understood it further: equity.  Hell, the reason we had the real estate bubble is because the masses understood equity.  The righteous and good and natural banks pulled a Monsanto genetic manipulation and turned it into a retail product removing it from it&#8217;s natural environment and contaminated everything but, that&#8217;s another story.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Assets.  Tangible or otherwise.  Currently the entire discussion regarding our debt and deficit are all done based on income.  The numbers look huge.   $16.5 trillion in debt.   Deficits to add to the debt in the trillions and only $14 trillion per year to try to pay for it all. </div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>First, lets get Honey and Dear&#8217;s situation straight.   There is a very large chance as with you and I that  their annual income did not and was in fact much less than the value of the house they purchased.  Second, there are a vast majority of people who have, over 20 plus or minus years have paid off that house or are getting close to doing so with an annual income that is still multiples less than the value of the house.  Get it?  At the same time, that less than the value of the house annual income probably purchased some home improvements adding to the value of the assets?  The income probably purchased some education, adding to the value of the assets?  The income probably purchased some happy time, assuring the value of the knowledge assets?  That less than the value of the house annual income has created assets over time worth more than the annual income.  Multiples more.  But, and lastly there is one major difference between Honey and Dear and We the People nation.  The nation never will retire.  Think about it for a moment.</div>
<div></div>
<div>I have been thinking about the problem with the use of the dinner table discussion as a vehicle for explaining the drive toward deficit reduction.  I know the government is the counter force to all that the private sector does in an economy.  I know about the World Banks report on intangible assets and our wealth creation.  I have noted the 1% income was rising faster than our GDP.  How long do you think that could/can go on, talk about dinner table discussion!   However, the public is in tune with the idea of dinner table discussions and the idea of cutting back to make ends meet at this moment in the “business cycle”.  So what was missing?</div>
<div></div>
<div>The public knows you can&#8217;t spend more than you have at ever greater rates.  I venture that the small business person knows you can&#8217;t take money out of the business faster than you can make it too.  So, to try to convince them that deficit spending is the correct approach becomes the metaphor of spitting into the wind.   </div>
<div></div>
<div>What was missing from the dinner table discussion was the word “equity”. Honey mentioned equity and the entire conversation took on an entirely different perspective.  So, US equity?  What is the value of our assets?  What is our equity?  Have we mortgaged so much of the equity that we can&#8217;t take advantage of nature and borrow?  Of course, if this were the pre-recession period for sure the answer would be no.  In fact, we would be able to borrow over 100% with no money down and no income check.   But, We the People have learned even if banking has not.   </div>
<div></div>
<div>I went looking for equity numbers and found <a href="http://rutledgecapital.com/2009/05/24/total-assets-of-the-us-economy-188-trillion-134xgdp/" target="_blank">this article</a>: Total Assets of the U.S. Economy $188 Trillion  </div>
<div></div>
<blockquote><div>The best source of asset market, or balance sheet, information we have today is the document Z1: Flow of Funds of the United States produced after the end of each quarter by the army of economists working at the Federal Reserve Board.</div>
<div>One way to do it is to add up the numbers that we do know. I have done so in line 13. We know there are $141,512 billion in financial assets. We know that just three of those sectors own $46,301 billion in tangible assets. Adding those two numbers together produces a (reported) total asset number of $187,813 billion&#8230;</div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div>I&#8217;m not going to argue with or for this persons approach to the calculation.  There are some very good comments there regarding how to calculate the number.  <a href="http://rutledgecapital.com/2009/05/24/total-assets-of-the-us-economy-188-trillion-134xgdp/comment-page-1/#comment-654" target="_blank">One person</a> suggested this method:</div>
<div></div>
<blockquote><div>A reasonable tack to estimate the networth of the nation is to use our traditional financial technique of discounting the future predictable cash flows, using a ‘elected’ rate for discounting the cash flows&#8230;.So using this DCF discipline, we can posit that our net worth is about $234T.</div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>My first house in 1988 was purchased based on this method.  I had $60K in the bank but, based on my income, presto&#8230;I was now worth $250K.  I was smart and only bought the house I knew I could afford, not what my new found wealth suggested.</p>
<p>At <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wealth_in_the_United_States" target="_blank">Wikipedia </a>I learned that in 2008 the UN put our value at $118 trillion.</div>
<div></div>
<div>This is quit the range.  $118 to $234 trillion.   </div>
<div></div>
<div>Let&#8217;s rewrite the screenplay now. Honey convinced Dear that they should borrow the money so now they are talking to the bank. </div>
<div>Natural Bank: “Hello Dear and Honey, how may I help you?”   </div>
<div>Honey responds “Well, we need some money.  Currently our income is $14 trillion dollars and our debt is about $16.5 trillion and we are getting a little behind.  However, we have a plan to borrow some money and use it to improver our income flow.  Here is our business plan”.   </div>
<div>Natural Bank: “Well my quick read of your cover page looks promising, but I will need to let the department study it further.  In the meantime, what are your assets worth, do you have any equity?”</div>
<div>Honey responds: “Yes, based on the latest evaluations for property tax purposes our equity conservatively measured is $118 trillion but based on income flows as high as $234 trillion.  We like to use our own data tables from our accounting software and thus come up with $188 trillion”.</div>
<div>Natural Banker: “My, if this is true then certainly there is room to work with you.  How much were you considering to borrow?  We don&#8217;t get many potential clients such as yourself.  I think we can give you a special rate too!”</div>
<div></div>
<div>Kind of changes the ending of the dinner table discussion doesn&#8217;t it?  Honey and Dear have a debt that is between 7% of equity and 14% of equity.  Natural Bank is normally willing to go 75% of equity.    That gives us somewhere between $88.5 trillion and $175.5 trillion to invest in ourself.  That is money right now we could put to work that, as every Honey and Dear including Honey and Dear Small Business knows, if they invest it with an eye on improving their life, their income from the increased value of the assets will more than pay for the loan.  Also, the investment can only further improve the equity thus reducing the debt to equity ratio.  We&#8217;ll ignore inflation&#8217;s effect on debt.   This also ignores the fact that Dear and Honey are collecting rents from some of their assets that are well below historical market rates.  They were doing some of their friends a favor, unfortunately at their personal expense.</div>
<div></div>
<div>There is one more thing. As noted the nation will never retire.  There is no time in the life of the nation, unlike Honey and Dear where it will not work to produce income.  Never.  That means there is no time in the life of the nation where it will need to rely on savings to pay it&#8217;s bills.   In fact, if the nation decided to do this, it would die.  Kind of like parts of Europe currently.</div>
<div></div>
<div>What do you think?  Are you going to be the Dear that tells Honey &#8220;forget it&#8221;,  just cut your spending until you can save the money?  I think if you do, Honey is going to tell you where to go.  In fact, I believe Honey has been telling Dear where to go for a while based on the polls.  “If only you would just listen to me for once!”</div>
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/the-rest-of-the-dinner-table-deficitdebt-discussion-equity.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>&#8216;Deficit Debate Driven by the Wealthy&#8217;</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/deficit-debate-driven-by-the-wealthy.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/deficit-debate-driven-by-the-wealthy.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 31 Jul 2012 12:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[budget deficits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[deficit commission]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[deficit hawks]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/deficit-debate-driven-by-the-wealthy.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[And another view on the upcoming election deals we need to worry about in addition to party agendas and deals. Doubling down on upward distribution of wealth remains the name of this game&#8230;it is hard enough to debate real budget issues without this party going on: Deficit debate driven by the wealthy, by Michael Hiltzik, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>And another view on the upcoming election deals we need to worry about in addition to party agendas and deals. Doubling down on upward distribution of wealth remains the name of this game&#8230;it is hard enough to debate real budget issues without this party going on:</p>
<blockquote><p><a href="http://www.latimes.com/business/la-fi-hiltzik-20120729,0,2146392.column?track=rss&#038;utm_source=feedburner&#038;utm_medium=feed&#038;utm_campaign=Feed%3A+latimes%2Fbusiness+%28L.A.+Times+-+Business%29">Deficit debate driven by the wealthy, by Michael Hiltzik, Commentary, LA Times</a>: &#8230;The fiscal cliff is supposedly what lurks at the end of this year, when billions of dollars in tax cuts expire and government spending cuts mandated by the big deficit deal in 2011 kick in. According to the bipartisan Congressional Budget Office, the combination of a steep increase in the tax bite and a steep reduction in spending across the board could cut economic growth in 2013 to 0.5% from a projected 4.4%&#8230; The CBO says that by any traditional reckoning, that would mean recession.<br /><strong>…</strong><br />Yet there&#8217;s still reason for most Americans to fear the deal-making aimed at avoiding the fiscal cliff. For one thing, the debate seems increasingly to be driven by the wealthy, who can be trusted to protect their own prerogatives while declaring everyone else&#8217;s to be wasteful. Just two weeks ago, a squadron of CEOs and bankers, including Dimon and hedge fund billionaire Pete Peterson, lined up behind a campaign to impose adult supervision on our squabbling Congress.</p>
<p>Their working brief is a document grandiosely entitled &#8220;The Moment of Truth.&#8221;It&#8217;s a deficit-reduction plan cooked up by former Sen. Alan Simpson (R-Wyo.) and Erskine Bowles, an ex-investment banker claiming Democratic Party cred from his nearly two-year stint as chief of staff in the Clinton White House. &#8230;</p>
<p>In any environment of serious debate, Simpson-Bowles would be dismissed out of hand. &#8230; &#8220;The Moment of Truth&#8221; bills itself as a roadmap to deficit reduction, but it&#8217;s really a guide to cutting services and benefits for the working and middle class while raising revenues only modestly, if that. &#8230;</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/deficit-debate-driven-by-the-wealthy.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Employment and Deficits: A Tale of Two Administrations</title>
		<link>./../../2012/05/employment-and-deficits-a-tale-of-two-administrations.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/05/employment-and-deficits-a-tale-of-two-administrations.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 May 2012 10:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2012 elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2012 Presidential]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[budget deficits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[comparing presidents]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[employment]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/05/employment-and-deficits-a-tale-of-two-administrations.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Stan Collender notes that, for the first time in four years, the U.S. Treasury reported a surplus in the month of April.  It isn’t just that there was a surplus in April of 2008, though.  If you look back through Aprils (data here), the last time that month showed a deficit is 1983—the April less [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Stan Collender notes that, for the first time in four years, <a href="http://capitalgainsandgames.com/blog/stan-collender/2550/why-no-one-washington-wants-talk-about-fiscal-policy" target="_blank">the U.S. Treasury reported a surplus in the month of April</a>.  It isn’t just that there was a surplus in April of 2008, though.  If you look back through Aprils (data <a href="http://www.fms.treas.gov/mts/index.html" target="_blank">here</a>), the last time that month showed a deficit is 1983—the April less than six months after the last official “double-dip” of recessions.<br />Stan offers three reasons that the White House doesn’t want to point out this good news.  I consider the first two somewhat silly—the GOP never hesitates to take about the deficit, except to deny its responsibility, and no politically-alert Democrat will see the April surplus as representative of “the wrong fiscal policy” so much as an indication that employment last year was better than it has been.<br />It’s his third reason that is most interesting:<br />
<blockquote>While that&#8217;s likely to be $200 billion or more less than what was recorded for 2011, the deficit will still be close to $1 trillion and that would be hard to defend.</p></blockquote>
<p>I’m assuming the phrase “close to $1 trillion” means that Stan assumes the actual FY2012 deficit will be lower than $1T.  The original projection was just under $1.3T. Getting that down to $1T would be 23% better than the original projection, not to mention the psychological gain of being back down below thirteen digits again. Even $1.1T would be just about a 15% improvement over the original projections.  If a 15%+ improvement in the deficit over your projections isn’t worth saluting, then what is?<br />Stan concludes:<br />
<blockquote>This is a little-understood part of the federal budget debate. Even if the 2012 deficit was half of what it was in 2011, and even if that reduction were applauded by Wall Street and the economic community, it would still be a painfully difficult political issue. In fact, long after the deficit has fallen to the point where most economists are comfortable with it, the political advantage will still be with those who criticize it.</p></blockquote>
<p>Far be it for me to argue, but…just for the sake of argument, I decided to compare President Obama’s record with that of the last sitting President running for re-election on The Two Issues that Abide, The Deficit and Jobs.</p>
<p>First, Deficit:</p>
<p><a href="http://lh3.ggpht.com/-SPHWvOxqk58/T7HQ09QSLLI/AAAAAAAAA-g/VYF9f7IE8V8/s1600-h/dFYFSD%252520Obama%252520v%252520Bush%25255B11%25255D.png"><img alt="dFYFSD Obama v Bush" border="0" height="468" src="http://lh6.ggpht.com/-CaW3bgrqm2o/T7HQ1TqDlMI/AAAAAAAAA-o/K0d0HwwHbJ0/dFYFSD%252520Obama%252520v%252520Bush_thumb%25255B7%25255D.png?imgmax=800" title="dFYFSD Obama v Bush" width="644"></a> </p>
<p>We don’t, of course, have the data for the deficit at the end of this year yet. (We have data for subsequent years of debt for the Previous Administration, of course, but nothing that would have been public knowledge by the voting in November of 2004.)</p>
<p>The story here is a clear one: the previous incumbent increased the deficit significantly; the current one has reduced it from the baseline he inherited. (If the current year ends up with around a $1T deficit, Year 3 will be around +$400,000.)</p>
<p>So the current Administration has been taking the deficit in the “right direction.”  But, of course, that’s only good if you are in a growing economy (for the Democratic knowledgeable; see Stan’s second point) or because the Previous Administration was “priming the pump” for the Great Growth that would follow. (After all, what the 2001 tax regression didn’t solve, certainly the 2003 Hubbard-Mankiw version would.)</p>
<p>So let’s check how well that Growth Thing worked.  <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2011/09/private-sector-employment-in-jobless.html" target="_blank">I’ve already pointed out that the post-recession public-sector employment between the current and the previous Administrations was about 600,000 jobs almost nine months ago</a>.  So let’s be as nice as possible and compare Total Employment Gains since their respective Recessions, knowing that we’re spotting the Previous Administration when looking at total Non-Farm Payroll:</p>
<p><a href="http://lh4.ggpht.com/-z36rB9ASSmI/T7HQ2FGKb_I/AAAAAAAAA-w/VU7Pg4P8rlM/s1600-h/payemspostrecession%25255B3%25255D.png"><img alt="payemspostrecession" border="0" height="467" src="http://lh4.ggpht.com/-_A6VmjHz6_c/T7HQ25g3LwI/AAAAAAAAA-4/PPATlHRJrXY/payemspostrecession_thumb%25255B1%25255D.png?imgmax=800" title="payemspostrecession" width="644"></a> </p>
<p>The Obama Administration got employment back to the end-of-recession level after sixteen (16) months; it took the previous Administration twenty-eight (28) months. Counting from the end of the recession, the Previous Administration produced just under 1.4MM jobs in the thirty-four (34) months to the next election (Dec 2001-Oct 2004). </p>
<p>The Obama Administration has produced more than twice that (2.825MM) in thirty-three (33) months.<br />In summary, if we compare the current Administration to the previous one, it has (1) produced twice as many new jobs, (2) produced budgets that reduced the annual Federal deficit instead of making it greater, and (3) reduced our troop presence in wars started by the Previous Administration while finding and eliminating Public Enemy #1.</p>
<p>And the only thing it wants to talk about is the third.</p>
<p>As I said <i>chez </i>Collender, If this Administration is afraid to run on its gains because there is less &#8220;political advantage&#8221; in highlighting the improvements your Administration has produced than in getting bashed for something for which you will perpetually get bashed, then the country is truly lost.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/05/employment-and-deficits-a-tale-of-two-administrations.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Welfare, I&#8217;m not hurting from it and neither are you.</title>
		<link>./../../2012/02/welfare-im-not-hurting-from-it-and-neither-are-you.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/02/welfare-im-not-hurting-from-it-and-neither-are-you.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2012 06:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[austerity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[budget deficits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[corporate welfare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[federal spending]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GDP]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Great Recession]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[welfare]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/02/welfare-im-not-hurting-from-it-and-neither-are-you.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[A good friend and I got into an email debate. He sent me the latest message regarding how wonderful it is that Florida is going to be drug testing welfare recipients. I responded that I&#8217;ll consider the policy when we start testing all the CEO&#8217;s who get welfare for their sector of the economy, the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>A good friend and I got into an email debate.  He sent me the latest message regarding how wonderful it is that Florida is going to be drug testing welfare recipients.  I responded that I&#8217;ll consider the policy when we start testing all the CEO&#8217;s who get welfare for their sector of the economy, the lawyers, judges and all country club members.   </div>
<div></div>
<div>I also noted welfare is not the problem  He noted it&#8217;s not “the” problem, but it is “a” problem and he knows this from talking to people.  I know of welfare too.  I have served on two nonprofit boards, one for substance abuse and the other The Providence Center.  My family adopted a family when I was in junior high.  We had foster children.  I was a day counselor for 2 weeks in the summer of &#8217;73 for 7 to 12 year olds from 3 of the most horrible housing developments in the city of Providence.  We had the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Watchman_Institute">“Institute”</a> literally right around the corner from where I lived.  My daughter is doing a year with <a href="http://www.nw.org/network/index.asp">NeighborWorks America</a>.  </div>
<div></div>
<div>Welfare is not the problem.  But, my friend is a very smart person and an engineer, so I needed some numbers.  Using <a href="http://www.usgovernmentdebt.us/year_spending_2008USbn_13bs1n_40#usgs302">this site</a> I checked out what the ratio of spending on Family and Children and Housing is to our GDP. I used GDP and not the overall budget because hey, we all worked to earn that money and it might as well be used for something that is heart warming.  The following numbers are total national spending (Fed, State, Local).</div>
<div></div>
<p><a name="more"></a>
<div>The year 1962 is the first year that there is spending listed for both Family and Children and Housing.  Prior to that only Housing is listed as having spending. For 1962, the combined total ratio was 0.0027.  That is 0.27% of our GDP was spend on families, children and housing.  I started with 1970 and went forward using the endings of the presidential terms starting with 1980.</div>
<div>1970:   0.0035</div>
<div>1980:   0.0092</div>
<div>1988:   0.0093</div>
<div>1992:   0.0134</div>
<div>2000:   0.0092</div>
<div>2008:   0.0097</div>
<div>2010:   0.0141</div>
<div></div>
<div>First of all, these are miniscule percentages of our GDP.  Second, it sure looks to me like the best way to solve the “welfare problem” is to solve the economic problem.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Of course, this means nothing if we don&#8217;t have other government spending patterns to compare too.  I mean, how do we know if welfare is “out of control” if we can&#8217;t compare it to other spending?  The same data set has two other categories: General Government and Other Spending.  You can click on each to see the sub categories.  But, just so you know General Government consists of Executive and Legislative organ, Financial and General services.  Other does not include: Pensions, Education, Health, Defense, Protection, Transportation or interest.  Other is just that: Other.  Here is how the numbers look.</div>
<div></div>
<div><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-P_hSs7IusGU/TziVaARYHFI/AAAAAAAAAR4/OaEyKcOa2n0/s1600/Welfare+chart+post+2-12-12.JPG" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="240" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-P_hSs7IusGU/TziVaARYHFI/AAAAAAAAAR4/OaEyKcOa2n0/s320/Welfare+chart+post+2-12-12.JPG" width="320"></a></div>
<div>  </div>
<div>This is how the numbers flow as log function.</div>
<div><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-q_Ww0EO90A8/TziVdkLMeTI/AAAAAAAAASA/vycHbhD4Ud0/s1600/Welfare+graph+post+2-12-12.JPG" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="245" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-q_Ww0EO90A8/TziVdkLMeTI/AAAAAAAAASA/vycHbhD4Ud0/s320/Welfare+graph+post+2-12-12.JPG" width="320"></a></div>
<div></div>
<p>  
<div>Call me stupid, but it looks to me like what we spend on welfare is not much more than what the  government is spending on just doing the government thingy, unless of course people can&#8217;t get a job.  Interestingly enough, the share of GDP spent on welfare in 1992 and 2010 is the same.  In fact, at the peak of unemployment of the 2001 recession which was 2003, we spent just 0.0098 on welfare.    </div>
<div></div>
<div>Here is another comparison.  In 2009 we spent $167 billion on Family/Children and Housing.  That year, we also spent $161 billion in the Other category of “Economic Affairs”.  I don&#8217;t know what that is, but if it has anything to do with what we are experiencing I don&#8217;t think we got our money&#8217;s worth.  This item went from -7.0 in 1997 to 7.8 in 2002 to 17.5 in 2005 to 1.3 in 2007 back to 17.7 in 2008.  It landed at -79.7 in 2010.  Hummmmmmmmm.  I think Glen Beck would like this category.  You know, who&#8217;s been playing with the money in the cookie jar?  In fact, why did we not know that a cookie jar exists?  </div>
<div></div>
<div>It doesn&#8217;t make me feel good to think that we spend about as much on the top office operations of this country as we spend on helping people.  Think about it.  What percentage of the “welfare problem” do</div>
<div></div>
<div>you believe is a problem? You know those drug addled lazy moochers who are preventing all us moral and hardworking folks from living the good life of our congress persons.  Be careful now.  This is a trick question.  See, it won&#8217;t take much of a “problem” subtracted from what we spend to find ourselves spending less to take care of families and their children than we spend on the top office operations in this nation.  That&#8217;s just plain being cheap.  Down right, out and out cheap SOB&#8217;s even if we leave in all of the &#8220;problem&#8221;.     </div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/02/welfare-im-not-hurting-from-it-and-neither-are-you.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Disaster Aid Disaster Averted, barely</title>
		<link>./../../2011/09/disaster-aid-disaster-averted-barely.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/09/disaster-aid-disaster-averted-barely.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2011 18:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2012 Presidential elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[budget deficits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[diasaster relief]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[FEMA]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/09/disaster-aid-disaster-averted-barely.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[By Linda Beale Disaster Aid Disaster Averted, barely. Once again, Republicans intent on obstructing the normal operation of the federal government unless they can extract cuts to programs they don&#8217;t like (in the name of deficit reduction) applied the combination of House recalcitrance and Senate anti-majoritarian filibuster to threaten a government shutdown and siderail needed [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By <strong>Linda Beale</strong></p>
<p><a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2011/09/disaster-aid-disaster-averted-barely.html" target="_BLANK">Disaster Aid Disaster Averted, barely</a>.</p>
<p>Once again, Republicans intent on obstructing the normal operation of the federal government unless they can extract cuts to programs they don&#8217;t like (in the name of deficit reduction) applied the combination of House recalcitrance and Senate anti-majoritarian filibuster to threaten a government shutdown and siderail needed funding for emergency assistance to ordinary Americans until they could get at least some of their objectives. A compromise that will get money to FEMA and keep the government funded for a spell has been reached.</p>
<p>(AP video at <em>ataxingmatter</em>, see link&#8230;I am still mostly missing my internet connections)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/09/disaster-aid-disaster-averted-barely.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Deficit: Why Should I Care?</title>
		<link>./../../2011/08/deficit-why-should-i-care.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/08/deficit-why-should-i-care.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2011 16:18:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[book reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[budget deficits]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/08/deficit-why-should-i-care.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Mike Kimel Hi folks! Long time readers probably know I&#8217;ve been haranguing on the deficit and the national debt for a long time. Last week I got an e-mail telling me about a new book called “Deficit: Why Should I Care?” by Marie Bussing-Burks. I had never heard of either the book or Ms. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by <strong>Mike Kimel</strong></p>
<p>Hi folks!  Long time readers probably know I&#8217;ve been haranguing on the deficit and the national debt for a long time. Last week I got an e-mail telling me about a new book called “Deficit: Why Should I Care?” by Marie Bussing-Burks.  I had never heard of either the book or Ms. Bussing-Burks, but the topic was interesting.  I was offered the opportunity to read a pdf version of the book.  That isn&#8217;t unusual &#8211; such offers seem to arrive at Angry Bear&#8217;s doorstep on a regular basis.</p>
<p>What is unusual though, is that I&#8217;ve read through much of the book already, and unlike most books purportedly written about the topic, I can safely recommend it to anyone who wants to learn more.  It is factual, interesting, well written, very informative and seems to be a fairly unbiased treatment of the issue.  That isn&#8217;t to say I agree with everything in the book, but I do think the book is very good.  Dan has arranged with the publisher for 50% discounts to be made available to any Angry Bear readers who  buy it between now and September 5.<br />
<br /><a name="more"></a><br />
<br />FYI, I looked up Ms. Bussing-Burks and found she is an assistant professor at the University of Southern Indiana.  </p>
<p>Full disclosure &#8211; I do not know anyone at the publisher nor Ms. Bussing-Burks.  Furthermore, I did not receive nor will I receive anything for having written any of the above. </p>
<p>(Rdan here&#8230;go to <a target="_blank" href="http://www.apress.com/catalogsearch/result/?q=deficit&#038;submit=Go">apress</a>, then click &#8216;your cart&#8217;, and on the e-book selction, add the coupon code <strong>DeficitABB</strong> in the appropriate box and follow the instructions for the discount)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/08/deficit-why-should-i-care.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Another Reason You Can Have Him</title>
		<link>./../../2011/08/another-reason-you-can-have-him.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/08/another-reason-you-can-have-him.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2011 20:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2012 Presidential elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[budget deficits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ratings]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/08/another-reason-you-can-have-him.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Fitch won&#8217;t downgrade the U.S., but they have downgraded Chirstiedom, officially because he didn&#8217;t pillage the state&#8217;s severely-underfunded Pension Funds enough. Of course, those Pension Funds wouldn&#8217;t be so underfunded if they had been funded instead of f*ck*d by the Whitman Administration&#8217;s Coke-Induced Budgeting Practices. (The &#8220;miracle of compound interest&#8221; includes that it doesn&#8217;t compound [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Fitch <a href="http://blogs.reuters.com/muniland/2011/08/17/fitch-gives-usa-its-stamp-of-approval/">won&#8217;t downgrade the U.S.</a>, but they have <a href="http://www.sunherald.com/2011/08/17/3357252/fitch-downgrades-new-jerseys-gos.html">downgraded Chirstiedom</a>, officially because he didn&#8217;t pillage the state&#8217;s severely-underfunded Pension Funds enough.</p>
<p>Of course, those Pension Funds wouldn&#8217;t be <a href="http://money.cnn.com/2009/05/12/news/economy/benner_pension.fortune/index.htm">so underfunded</a> if they had been <em>funded</em> instead of <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2011/01/nj-public-pension-slugfest-reporting-omits-15-years-of-governors-stealing-from-workers.html">f*ck*d by the Whitman Administration&#8217;s</a> <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2011/08/kudlows-komedy-kapers-cross-post.html">Coke-Induced Budgeting Practices</a>. (The &#8220;miracle of compound interest&#8221; includes that it doesn&#8217;t compound so much when there&#8217;s no principal.)</p>
<p>[UPDATE: Blue Jersey <a href="http://bluejersey.com/diary/19222/bye-bye-2012-christie-causes-downgrade">highlights the line I missed</a>:<br />
<br />
<blockquote>Fitch believes that meeting the requisite increases in pension contributions will be challenging and is likely to conflict with other long term challenges, such as property tax relief, school funding, and infrastructure needs.</p></blockquote>
<p>Gosh, you mean you have to pay for services? As for the other highlight:<br />
<br />
<blockquote>The state&#8217;s recent economic performance has been weak and the state is expected to lag the nation in recovering from the recent recession.</p></blockquote>
<p>we could always use <a href="http://jaredbernsteinblog.com/another-look-at-government-job-growth-in-texas/">The Texas Solution: Hire More and More Government Workers</a>.]</p>
<p>So, <a href="http://www.dailykos.com/story/2011/08/17/1007910/-Alter:-Chris-Christie-holding-focus-groups-to-explore-2012-bid">if you want him</a>, as I said at <a href="http://xnerg.blogspot.com/">Skippy</a>, you can have him.  He&#8217;s got experience with ratings downgrades.<br />
<br />

</p>
<p>
<br />Sadly, I suspect Joe Wiesenthal <a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/new-jersey-is-downgraded-by-fitch-hurts-christ-christie-2011-8#ixzz1VJzbJQuf">has it right</a>:<br />
</p>
<blockquote><p>It might not be a big deal, and it might not be his fault, but this should probably kill any buzz about him running for President right now, given that THE DOWNGRADE is expected to be such a salient point of attack for any eventual GOP nominee.</p></blockquote>
<p>And since the downgrade was engineered by a Romney supporter, any suggestions of conspiracy here are unjustified.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/08/another-reason-you-can-have-him.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Kudlow&#8217;s Komedy Kapers (Cross-post)</title>
		<link>./../../2011/08/kudlows-komedy-kapers-cross-post.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/08/kudlows-komedy-kapers-cross-post.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 07 Aug 2011 00:09:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[bad economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[budget deficits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cursive-Z recession]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Great Recession]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Idiocy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax policy]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/08/kudlows-komedy-kapers-cross-post.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Brad DeLong asked a few days ago who he should be reading on a daily basis. Following is a cross-post from my nominee, The Hunting of the Snark: Kudlow&#8217;s Komedy Kapers Larry Kudlow is worried that Obama is ruining the economy. Larry KudlowAugust 5, 2011 4:30 P.M. More Obama Spending Won’t Do ItAnd stocks know [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Brad DeLong asked a few days ago who he should be reading <a href="http://delong.typepad.com/sdj/2011/07/time-for-the-annual-changing-out-of-my-thirty-daily-must-reads.html?utm_source=feedburner&#038;utm_medium=feed&#038;utm_campaign=Feed%3A+BradDelongsSemi-dailyJournal+%28Brad+DeLong%27s+Semi-Daily+Journal%29">on a daily basis</a>.  Following is a cross-post from <a href="http://agonyin8fits.blogspot.com/2011/08/larry-kudlow-is-worried-that-obama-is.html">my nominee</a>, <a href="http://agonyin8fits.blogspot.com/"><em>The Hunting of the Snark</em></a>:<br />
<h3>Kudlow&#8217;s Komedy  Kapers</h3>
<p>Larry Kudlow <a href="http://www.nationalreview.com/kudlows-money-politics/273844/more-obama-spending-won-t-do-it">is worried</a> that Obama is ruining the economy.</p>
<blockquote><p>Larry Kudlow<br />August 5, 2011 4:30 P.M. </p>
<p>More Obama Spending Won’t Do It<br />And stocks know it.</p>
<p>There he goes again.</p></blockquote>
<p>Because quoting Reagan is cool.</p>
<blockquote><p>Out on the campaign trail, President Obama is proposing more federal spending as his answer to sluggish growth and jobs. That won’t do it, Mr. President.</p></blockquote>
<p>Yes, when the private sector doesn&#8217;t provide jobs, don&#8217;t look to the government to provide jobs. That just won&#8217;t do it, Obama. That <i>just&#8230;won&#8217;t&#8230;.do!</i></p>
<blockquote><p>He wants more infrastructure spending, undoubtedly in the form of an infrastructure bank. That’s a terrible idea. It’s borrowed from Latin America, where bloated and corrupt bureaucratic construction agencies have helped bankrupt any number of countries in the past.</p></blockquote>
<p>It&#8217;s also borrowed from Roosevelt, but we all know how he secretly created the Depression by spending money. </p>
<blockquote><p>He wants to lengthen 99-week unemployment insurance, although numerous studies have shown that continuous unemployment benefits are associated with higher unemployment.</p></blockquote>
<p>I want to bronze that comment and turn it into an ashtray. Numerous studies have show that UI is associated with high unemployment! Obviously, the only solution is to stop handing out UI, and then we&#8217;ll have no more unemployment. <br /><a name="more"></a><br />
<blockquote>And he wants to extend the temporary payroll tax credit, which is not a permanent reduction in marginal tax rates, has no incentive effect, has not worked so far, and is really a form of federal spending — not real tax relief.</p></blockquote>
<p>How the rich suffer so from their high taxes.
<p></p>
<div><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-BiDgy0rWnbY/Tj1sEuNedBI/AAAAAAAAArg/_8JFpEmy8mA/s1600/income_top_0_1_marginal_tax.gif" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="400px" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-BiDgy0rWnbY/Tj1sEuNedBI/AAAAAAAAArg/_8JFpEmy8mA/s400/income_top_0_1_marginal_tax.gif" width="400px"></a></div>
<p>
<p></p>
<blockquote><p>Earlier this week, when he signed the debt-ceiling bill, the president ranted on about the need to raise tax rates on successful earners, investors, and small businesses. He’s trying to bring back tax hikes as part of the phase-two special committee seeking additional deficit reduction, even though his own party rebuffed him on this in the late stages of the debt talks. All this is a prescription to grow government, not the economy.</p></blockquote>
<p>Reagan actually raised taxes when it was necessary while Obama is just talking about raising taxes, but as we all know, the Reagan years <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/1995/07/04/business/economist-is-said-to-enter-a-six-month-drug-program.html">were a bit of a blur for Kudlow</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p>What the economy needs, Mr. President, is a strong dose of new incentives, with pro-growth tax reform that flattens marginal rates and broadens the base for individuals and businesses. This includes moving to territorial taxation that ends the double tax on foreign earnings of U.S. companies. Plus, we desperately need a complete moratorium on federal regulations. As Sen. Barrasso recently noted, the government put out 379 new rules on business in July alone, amounting to $9.5 billion in additional costs.</p></blockquote>
<p>Because US companies pay far, far too much in taxes. Just <a href="http://www.cbpp.org/cms/?fa=view&#038;id=784">ask</a> the Center On Budget and Policy Priorities (CBPP).</p>
<blockquote><p>The U.S. corporate tax burden is smaller than average for developed countries.[1] Corporations in 19 of the member states of the Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development paid 16.1 percent of their profits in taxes between 2000 and 2005, on average, while corporations in the United States paid 13.4 percent.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, some have argued that U.S. corporate tax rates unduly burden U.S. companies by pointing to the country’s top statutory tax rate, which is 35 percent. For example, a recent Wall Street Journal editorial calling for corporate tax cuts noted that this is the second highest top statutory tax rate among developed countries.[2] While true, this gives the false impression that the corporate tax burden is greater here than in other developed countries. Because the U.S. tax code offers so many deductions, credits, and other mechanisms by which corporations can reduce their taxes, the actual percentage of profits that U.S. corporations pay in taxes — or what analysts refer to as their effective tax rate — is not high, compared to other developed countries.</p>
<p>Because the average U.S. corporate tax burden is low, many economists believe a revenue-neutral corporate tax reform that reduces statutory corporate tax rates, while broadening the tax base by eliminating costly tax breaks, could improve economic efficiency and likely benefit the U.S. economy.</p></blockquote>
<p>Kudlow:</p>
<blockquote><p>None of these pro-growth reforms are in sight. So the stock market is going through a nasty 10 percent correction over fears of another recession (and European debt default).</p>
<p>That’s definitely not a recession reading.</p></blockquote>
<p>Yes, you read that right. Kudlow says we are not in a recession. <a href="http://www.nationalreview.com/kudlows-money-politics/273607/no-recession">From an earlier post</a></p>
<blockquote><p>No Recession</p>
<p>Strong profits, easy money, and Tea Party gains argue against it.</p>
<p>Stocks and bond yields are sinking as Wall Street disses the debt deal and instead focuses on a likely double-dip recession.</p>
<p>Everyone is gloomy. But is this pessimism getting a little overbaked?</p>
<p>Granted, the economy is sputtering, with less than 1 percent growth in the first half of the year. But if there is a recession in the cards, it will be the first time one occurs when the yield curve is steeply positive (an ultra-easy Fed) and corporate profits are strong.</p>
<p>And since we do have ultra-easy money and strong profits, I don’t believe we’re heading into a recession. Nor do I believe stocks will continue to swoon.</p>
<p>The principal reason for the sub-par first-half economy is the rise of inflation, which severely damaged real incomes and consumer spending. We experienced a mini oil shock, which has dampened the whole economy. Actually, it’s worth remembering that oil shocks and inverted yield curves, along with falling profits, are the most important leading indicators of recessions. We don’t have this right now.</p></blockquote>
<p>Back to the present:</p>
<blockquote><p>But at least we got some good news on jobs. The July jobs report came in stronger than expected. It’s not great. But at least nonfarm payrolls increased 117,000 — as the prior two months were revised upward by 56,000 — while private payrolls gained 154,000.</p>
<p>That’s definitely not a recession reading. But neither is it a strong performance. If the economy were really rebounding, we would be creating 300,000 new jobs a month.</p>
<p>In the report, the unemployment rate slipped to 9.1 percent from 9.2 percent. But that’s mostly because nearly 200,000 workers left the civilian labor force. Another negative is the household employment survey, which fell 38,000 in July after dropping nearly half a million in June. That survey measures job creation among small owner-operated businesses or the lack thereof.</p>
<p>Yet when looking at the new jobs report, along with reasonable gains in chain-store sales and car sales, plus the ISM Purchasing Managers reports (which stayed above the 50 percent line), I repeat my thought that we are not headed for a double-dip recession.</p></blockquote>
<p><a href="http://www.usnews.com/opinion/blogs/peter-roff/2011/08/05/uptick-in-unemployment-nothing-to-cheer-about">The US New and World Report</a> begs to differ.</p>
<blockquote><p>According to the latest figures, the U.S. economy created 117,000 new jobs, causing the unemployment rate to drop slightly, from 9.2 percent in June to 9.1 percent in July. But, as Jeff Cox writes over at CNBC, &#8220;there is far more than meets the eye&#8221; to this bit of economic good news, which is certainly nothing to cheer about.</p>
<p>The U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics breakdown says there were 139,296,000 people working in July, compared to 139,334,000 the month before, or a drop of 38,000. That&#8217;s because, as a number of labor economists point out, the disparity is the result of something the government calls &#8220;discouraged workers&#8221;—people who don&#8217;t have jobs but were not looking for work during the reporting period.&#8221;</p>
<p>This is where the numbers showed a really big spike—up from 982,000 to 1.119 million, a difference of 137,000 or a 14 percent increase. These folks are generally not included in the government&#8217;s various job measures,&#8221; Cox wrote, adding that if you count those people as part of the workforce, the job creation and drop in unemployment disappear.</p>
<p>Other signs of continued weakness in the recovery include that the percentage of long-term unemployed remained unchanged in July and that the labor force participation rate has continued its downward trend since the beginning of the recession, dropping 0.2 percentage point to 63.9 percent in July. This is, the Congressional Joint Economic Committee reports, &#8220;the lowest labor participation rate in the United States since January 1984.&#8221; [See a collection of political cartoons on the economy.]</p>
<p>Addressing the weak numbers, the White House continues to point fingers almost everywhere except at itself—which is where the blame belongs. President Barack Obama, who, along with congressional Democratic leaders, promised that unemployment would not exceed 8 percent as long as the stimulus package was approved, has yet to explain how he could have been so tragically wrong.</p></blockquote>
<p>The great thing about being a conservative is that no matter what it happening, it proves that their economic theories are correct. Kudlow:</p>
<blockquote><p>Over two years of so-called economic recovery, growth has averaged about 2.5 percent. It fell to less than 1 percent in the first half of this year, largely from a commodity-price shock that included oil-, gasoline-, and food-price spikes. That price shock resulted mainly from the Fed’s QE2 depreciation of the dollar — a big mistake. It eroded real consumer incomes and spending.</p></blockquote>
<p>Let&#8217;s ask <i>Economist Online</i> <a href="http://economistonline.muogao.com/2008/01/put-dollar-depreciation-in-httpeconomistonline-blogspot-com200801put-dollar-depreciation-in-historical_02.html">what it thinks about the dollar</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p>Put dollar depreciation in historical perspective</p>
<p>It&#8217;s a brand new year. I thought I’d have some big-picture review of what’s going on in the world economy today. Here is my first piece on US dollar.</p>
<p>The graph below will scare you a lot…in fact, the dollar index fall from 115 in 2002 to mid 70s at the end of 2007, that equals a 33% drop.</p></blockquote>
<p>
<p></p>
<div><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-vr1sep5BRcc/Tj2XeI949zI/AAAAAAAAAr4/6Vl6J7jLD9A/s1600/1dollar%2Bdepreciation.png" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="240px" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-vr1sep5BRcc/Tj2XeI949zI/AAAAAAAAAr4/6Vl6J7jLD9A/s400/1dollar%2Bdepreciation.png" width="400px"></a></div>
<blockquote><p>Hmmm, a sharp drop, isn’t it? But wait a minute, have we witnessed the similar happened before? Let’s look at the following graph and have some historical perspective. From 1985 to 1989, the trade-weighted dollar index actually had a bigger fall, from 145 to 90, almost down 38%, and it fell even further until 1995.
<p></p>
<div><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-k09zIq_Q5SY/Tj2Xwf5PcTI/AAAAAAAAAsA/KZYR8SO3CuM/s1600/dollar%2Bdepreciation.png" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="240px" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-k09zIq_Q5SY/Tj2Xwf5PcTI/AAAAAAAAAsA/KZYR8SO3CuM/s400/dollar%2Bdepreciation.png" width="400px"></a></div>
</blockquote>
<p>Holy Dollar Depreciation, Batman! It fell even more under Reagan than it did during Obama!</p>
<p>Kudlow:</p>
<blockquote><p>Lately, the dollar has stabilized and energy prices have come down quite a bit. That will reduce inflation and support better consumer spending. Businesses are already highly profitable and cash-rich. They are investing some of that, but not nearly enough to create sufficient new jobs. Who would, with all these Washington policies?</p></blockquote>
<p>It&#8217;s not lack of demand, it&#8217;s politics! <br />
<blockquote>
<p>Finally, the Fed remains ultra-easy with excess liquidity and a zero interest rate.</p>
<p>So it looks to me like we will return to the sub-par 2.5 percent growth trend rather than dip back into recession. However, at this pace, unemployment may hover around 9 percent right up to election time next year.</p>
<p>More spending won’t do it Mr. President. Tax and regulatory incentives will. </p></blockquote>
<p>Cut taxes and regulations and watch the economy boom&#8211;for the very rich. Who are doing quite well now as it is.
<p></p>
<div><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-h4lAE8oDkeA/Tj2Zuziy0pI/AAAAAAAAAsI/3jHtYVZZhSY/s1600/income%2Binequality%2Bgraph.png" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="291px" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-h4lAE8oDkeA/Tj2Zuziy0pI/AAAAAAAAAsI/3jHtYVZZhSY/s400/income%2Binequality%2Bgraph.png" width="400px"></a></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/08/kudlows-komedy-kapers-cross-post.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
