<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Industrial Orders &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Europe&#8217;s industrial new orders: 3 very different stories</title>
		<link>./../../2011/03/europes-industrial-new-orders-3-very-different-stories.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/03/europes-industrial-new-orders-3-very-different-stories.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 20:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Eurozone]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Industrial Orders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rebecca Wilder]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spain]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/03/europes-industrial-new-orders-3-very-different-stories.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Spain vs. Germany vs. UK: production trends showing holes in some growth stories Eurostat reports new orders for January: In January 2011 compared with December 2010, the euro area1 (EA17) industrial new orders index2 rose by 0.1%. In December 20103 the index grew by 2.7%. In the EU271, new orders increased by 0.2% in January [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Spain vs. Germany vs. UK: production trends showing holes in some growth stories</p>
<p>Eurostat reports new orders <a href="http://epp.eurostat.ec.europa.eu/cache/ITY_PUBLIC/4-23032011-AP/EN/4-23032011-AP-EN.PDF">for January</a>:<em><br />
<blockquote><em>In January 2011 compared with December 2010, the euro area1 (EA17) industrial new orders index2 rose by 0.1%. In December 20103 the index grew by 2.7%. In the EU271, new orders increased by 0.2% in January 2011, after a rise of 2.9% in December 20103. Excluding ships, railway &#038; aerospace equipment4, for which changes tend to be more volatile, industrial new orders increased by 1.6% in the euro area and by 1.9% in the EU27.</em> </p></blockquote>
<p></em><br /><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-D4qzZusav5U/TYpPFUS2hwI/AAAAAAAADjc/2YAvtUw7MXk/s1600/industrial_new_orders_EA16.JPG"><img alt="" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-D4qzZusav5U/TYpPFUS2hwI/AAAAAAAADjc/2YAvtUw7MXk/s400/industrial_new_orders_EA16.JPG" border="0"></a>This was a disappointing report, as Bloomberg consensus was expecting a 1% monthly gain. The Eurostat <a href="http://epp.eurostat.ec.europa.eu/cache/ITY_PUBLIC/4-23032011-AP/EN/4-23032011-AP-EN.PDF">press release </a>reports new orders by country and production type only(capital, consumer, intermediate, durable, and nondurable). However, I look at the origination of orders by region: domestic, non-domestic extra-euro (which is the same as non-domestic for the Euro area as a whole), and non-domestic intra-euro.</p>
<p>The idea is, that with ubiquitous fiscal austerity, Euro area countries rely on external demand for growth. So here&#8217;s my question: how&#8217;s Spain to survive? (more after the jump)<a name="more"></a></p>
<p><strong>Exhibit 1</strong>: Spain&#8217;s industrial sector is barely growing amid fiscal austerity</p>
<p>No industrial production growth = a big problem. It&#8217;s not just fiscal austerity, per se, it&#8217;s that the economy needs plenty of nominal income gains to improve the cyclical budget deficit in order to even see the benefits of structural adjustment. The <em>structural balance</em> cyclically adjusts the government deficit (or surplus) for non-structural items to leave just the structural deficit (net spending on pension payments, unemployment insurance, normal capital expenditures, etc.).</p>
<p>Without growth to increase nominal revenues, the negative cyclical balance will keep the overall balance very much in the red. Spain needs growth! Apparently, it&#8217;s not coming from the industrial sector.</p>
<p><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-rKf9CY8Fxuc/TYpPFz1GB6I/AAAAAAAADjs/MOZE-LtPxQc/s1600/industrial_new_orders_Spain.JPG"><img alt="" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-rKf9CY8Fxuc/TYpPFz1GB6I/AAAAAAAADjs/MOZE-LtPxQc/s400/industrial_new_orders_Spain.JPG" border="0"></a><br />Spain was deriving quite a bit of industrial demand from within the Eurozone (the red line in the chart above) through the end of September 2010; however, that source of order growth is tapering off. Now, it seems that extra-euro industrial orders growth (the green line) may start a sideways trend, too. Normally I wouldn&#8217;t put too much stock in one data point &#8211; but with tightening across Asia and possibly the UK (not the US for a bit), slower orders growth is inevitable.</p>
<p><strong>Exhibit 2</strong>: The German industrial machine</p>
<p>The German machine is also deriving industrial production growth from extra-euro orders. Notably, too, domestic orders have been strong. But for all of the talk about <a href="http://www.eurointelligence.com/article/browse/1/article/back-to-strong-vigilance-but-note-trichet-is-also-playing-politics.html?tx_ttnews%5BbackPid%5D=743&#038;cHash=3d85a76fa15aa1508ea1ffe5f4990fe8">Germany&#8217;s overheating export sector</a>, industrial production is still near 6% below its Q1 2008 level.</p>
<p><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-AC8MS7JICn0/TYpPFS1-UBI/AAAAAAAADjk/LqLsIWyPQZo/s1600/industrial_new_orders_Germany.JPG"><img alt="" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-AC8MS7JICn0/TYpPFS1-UBI/AAAAAAAADjk/LqLsIWyPQZo/s400/industrial_new_orders_Germany.JPG" border="0"></a>And finally,</p>
<p><strong>Exhibit 3</strong>: The poster child for fiscal austerity, the UK.</p>
<p>Why? Because they&#8217;re nominal exchange rate depreciated quite markedly, allowing the trade-sensitive industrial base to find a very shallow bottom. On a trade-weighted basis, the British pound is 24% lower than in mid-2007, according to the JP Morgan nominal effective exchange rate index.</p>
<p><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-H3mWwW1IH7U/TYpPGC-UpKI/AAAAAAAADj0/iESROjohA04/s1600/industrial_new_orders_UK.JPG"><img alt="" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-H3mWwW1IH7U/TYpPGC-UpKI/AAAAAAAADj0/iESROjohA04/s400/industrial_new_orders_UK.JPG" border="0"></a></p>
<p>I&#8217;d like to hear how you all think that Spain&#8217;s going to get through this as the ECB raises short-term rates (for those of you who do not know my Euro-centric commentary, you can see a list of my recent commentary on the Eurozone, which includes articles on the ECB by <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/search/label/Rebecca%20Wilder">my name on the AB sidebar</a>), Germany slows, the US struggles to keep the consumer alive, and emerging Asia tightens its belt.</p>
<p>Spain&#8217;s a trillion dollar economy, and the fourth in terms of GDP in the Eurozone&#8230;</p>
<p><em><strong>Rebecca Wilder</strong></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/03/europes-industrial-new-orders-3-very-different-stories.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
