<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>revolving door &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Populist rehetoric for the election campaign</title>
		<link>./../../2012/05/populist-rehetoric-for-the-election-campaign.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/05/populist-rehetoric-for-the-election-campaign.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 09 May 2012 15:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[finance]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[prosecutions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[revolving door]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/05/populist-rehetoric-for-the-election-campaign.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Via The Dailey Beast is a link to Lehman Brother&#8217;s e-mails and documents and an unanswered question for investors and the public With the Occupy protesters resuming battle stations, and Mitt Romney in place as the presumptive Republican nominee, President Obama has begun to fashion his campaign as a crusade for the 99 percent&#8211;a fight [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Via <a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2012-05-06/lehman-e-mails-show-wall-street-arrogance-led-to-the-fall.html">The Dailey Beast</a> is a link to <a href="http://www.jenner.com/lehman/docs/" ttarget="_blank">Lehman Brother&#8217;s e-mails and documents </a> and <a href="http://www.thedailybeast.com/newsweek/2012/05/06/why-can-t-obama-bring-wall-street-to-justice.html">an unanswered question for investors and the public</a> <br />
<blockquote>With the <a href="http://www.thedailybeast.com/articles/2012/05/02/did-may-day-save-occupy-wall-street.html" target="_blank">Occupy protesters resuming battle stations</a>, and <a href="http://www.thedailybeast.com/newsweek/2012/05/06/romney-s-new-foreign-policy-for-afghanistan.html" target="_blank">Mitt Romney in place as the presumptive Republican nominee</a>, President Obama has begun to fashion his campaign as a crusade for the 99 percent&#8211;a fight against, as one Obama ad puts it, &#8220;a guy who had a Swiss bank account.&#8221;</p>
<p><strong>&#8230;</strong>  </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Casting Romney as a plutocrat will be easy enough. But the president&#8217;s claim as avenging populist may prove trickier, given his own deeply complicated, even conflicted, relationship with Big Finance.<br />&#8230;  </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>&#8220;There hasn&#8217;t been any serious investigation of any of the large financial entities by the Justice Department, which includes the FBI,&#8221; says William Black, an associate professor of economics and law at the University of Missouri, Kansas City, who, as a government regulator in the 1980s, helped clean up the S&#038;L mess. Black, who is a Democrat, notes that the feds dealt with the S&#038;L crisis with harsh justice, bringing more than a thousand prosecutions, and securing a 90 percent conviction rate. The difference between the government&#8217;s response to the two crises, Black says, is a matter of will, and priorities. &#8220;You need heads on the pike,&#8221; he says. &#8220;The first President Bush&#8217;s orders were to get the most prominent, nastiest frauds, and put their heads on pikes as a demonstration that there&#8217;s a new sheriff in town.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/05/populist-rehetoric-for-the-election-campaign.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Wall Street breakfast leftovers</title>
		<link>./../../2010/12/wall-street-breakfast-leftovers.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/12/wall-street-breakfast-leftovers.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 05 Dec 2010 20:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[revolving door]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wall street]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/12/wall-street-breakfast-leftovers.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Revolving door continues. Citigroup (C) is rumored to be in advanced talks to hire Peter Orszag, who served as budget director for the Obama administration until he stepped down in July 2010. Sources said Orszag might take a job in Citi&#8217;s I-banking division and an announcement could come as soon as today. Citigroup, which is [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://noir.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=newsarchive&#038;sid=a2SmeO7WJ9hI">Revolving door continues.</a> Citigroup (<a href="http://seekingalpha.com/symbol/c">C</a>) is rumored to be in advanced talks to hire Peter Orszag, who served as budget director for the Obama administration until he stepped down in July 2010. Sources said Orszag might take a job in Citi&#8217;s I-banking division and an announcement could come as soon as today. Citigroup, which is still recovering from its $45B bailout, would be only the latest in a long string of companies that have poached workers from the political sector, and of employees who have bounced back and forth between regulating (directly or indirectly) financial firms and then working for them.</p>
<p>
<p><a href="http://www.cnbc.com/id/40447573">States to face tighter finances.</a> States may have to make additional spending cuts over the next couple of years or else face the possibility of deteriorating financial health as tax revenues recover at a slow pace and support from the federal government dwindles. A new report from the National Governors Association and the National Association of State Budget Officers warned of &#8220;extremely tight fiscal conditions for states,&#8221; and at least 23 states are already anticipating budget deficits totaling $40.5B in 2012.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/12/wall-street-breakfast-leftovers.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
