<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>financial transaction tax &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>If Europe Adds a Financial Transactions Tax, Will We Follow?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/if-europe-adds-a-financial-transactions-tax-will-we-follow.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/if-europe-adds-a-financial-transactions-tax-will-we-follow.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 14 Oct 2012 01:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[financial transaction tax]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linda Beale (Tax law)]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/if-europe-adds-a-financial-transactions-tax-will-we-follow.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Beale If Europe Adds a Financial Transactions Tax, Will We Follow? Has the time come for the US to impose a financial transactions tax?  It would have several positive features.  First, it would raise revenues, which are sorely needed for everything from climate change action to infrastructure improvements to aid for needy families.  [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Linda Beale</p>
<p> <a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2012/10/if-europe-adds-a-financial-transactions-tax-will-we-follow.html">If Europe Adds a Financial Transactions Tax, Will We Follow?</a></p>
<p>Has the time come for the US to impose a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Financial_transaction_tax">financial transactions tax</a>?  It would have several positive features.  First, it would raise revenues, which are sorely needed for everything from climate change action to infrastructure improvements to aid for needy families.  Second, it would raise revenues from those who are most responsible for the financialization of the economy&#8211;investment bankers, fund managers, and high speed traders interested in bigger and bigger profits no matter the result for ordinary folks.  Third, it would act in some small way to discourage excessive trading that contributes to the volatility of the stock market. </p>
<p>Of course, such a tax (frequently called a &#8220;<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tobin_tax">Tobin Tax</a>&#8221; after the Nobel economist who recommended it) would be best if applied by all sophisticated nations.  It appears that the European Union is getting closer to making a financial transactions tax a reality in at least some of the participating countries.  See James Kanter, <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/10/10/business/global/trading-tax-gets-backing-from-italy-and-spain.html">Tax on Financial Trades Gains Support in Europe</a>, New York Times (Oct. 10, 2012).  Britain will remain exempt so the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/City_of_London">City of London</a> (Europe&#8217;s parallel to Wall Street) would continue on its merry way (or even increase the financialization of the UK economy as trades moved from participating countries to London).  Wall Street has lobbied heavily against any tax on its activities, and would fight bitterly if the US were to impose such a tax while London remained exempt.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>So my guess is that even if the EU finance ministers approve the measure for some participating European nations, it will take some time before it spreads to Britain and the United States.  Like climate change, we seem determined to put off addressing real problems until they are upon us with such force that we cannot possibly continue as before.  Thus, our financialized economy rocks along pretending that derivatives are safer and banks are fine and life can go on as before, and Congress debates climate change as a &#8220;she said, he said&#8221; matter rather than looking at the breadth and depth of scientific evidence supporting man-made effects that are reshaping the globe while we watch.</p>
<p>cross posted with <a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/banks-and-financial-institutions/">ataxingmatter</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/if-europe-adds-a-financial-transactions-tax-will-we-follow.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Nader Argues for a Financial Transactions Tax</title>
		<link>./../../2011/11/nader-argues-for-a-financial-transactions-tax.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/11/nader-argues-for-a-financial-transactions-tax.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2011 14:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Corporate Taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[financial transaction tax]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linda Beale (Tax law)]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/11/nader-argues-for-a-financial-transactions-tax.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Beale Nader Argues for a Financial Transactions Tax Ralph Nader provided an op-ed on the question of a financial transaction tax, &#8220;Time for a Tax on Speculation,&#8221; Wall St. Journal, A17 (Nov. 2, 2011).  He ties the need for the tax as a curb to speculation to the growing concern among ordinary Americans [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Linda Beale</p>
<p>Nader Argues for a Financial Transactions Tax
<p>Ralph Nader provided an op-ed on the question of a financial transaction tax, &#8220;Time for a Tax on Speculation,&#8221; Wall St. Journal, A17 (Nov. 2, 2011).  He ties the need for the tax as a curb to speculation to the growing concern among ordinary Americans about corporate power and Wall Street excesses.</p>
<p>A financial transactions tax would impose a small charge on the value of stock, bond and derivatives transactions&#8211;probably somewhere around 0.25% to 0.5% (the latter is the figure pushed by Nader and groups like National Nurses United). Such a tax would raise a considerable amount of money and at the same time serve another important function&#8211;curbing speculative and high-frequency trading.</p>
<blockquote><p>[This tax] has the potential to curb risky speculative trading that contributes little real economic value.  The Capital Institute&#8217;s John Fullerton has stated that a financial speculation tax could have a significant impact on the high-frequency trading and other &#8216;quant&#8217; trading strategies that now comprise an astonishing 70% of vastly bloated equity-trading volume. <a name="more"></a> Over the past few decades, trading volume has grown exponentially.  In 1995, the total shares of stock traded on the Nasdaq and the NYSE, not including derivates and other options, was 188 billion.  By the peak of the financial crisis, in 2008, this annual number had skyrocketed to three trillion.</p>
<p>*** Sen. Harkin, Rep. DeFazio and others in the past few years have proposed protecting ordinary investors from the direct effects of the tax by providing exemptions for mutual funds, retirement funds and for the first $100,000 in trades made annually by an individual</p>
</blockquote>
<p>originally published at <a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2011/11/financial-transactions-tax-nader-argues-for-it.html">ataxingmatter</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/11/nader-argues-for-a-financial-transactions-tax.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
