<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>meritocracy &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>A web of privilege supports this so-called meritocracy</title>
		<link>./../../2012/05/a-web-of-privilege-supports-this-so-called-meritocracy.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/05/a-web-of-privilege-supports-this-so-called-meritocracy.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 16 May 2012 13:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Brad DeLong]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[meritocracy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[perceived competence]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/05/a-web-of-privilege-supports-this-so-called-meritocracy.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Brad DeLong points to an article by Gary Younge in The Guardian: A web of privilege supports this so-called meritocracy: Shortly after Mitt Romney&#8217;s failed 2008 campaign for the Republican nomination his son Tagg set up a private equity fund with the campaign&#8217;s top fundraiser. One of the first donors was his mum, Anne. Next [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://delong.typepad.com/sdj/2012/05/a-web-of-privilege-supports-this-so-called-meritocracy-gary-younge-comment-is-free-the-guardian.html#comments">Brad DeLong</a> points to an article by Gary Younge in <i>The Guardian</i>:<br />
<blockquote><a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2012/may/06/leveson-murdoch-cameron-brooks-privilege">A web of privilege supports this so-called meritocracy</a>: Shortly after Mitt Romney&#8217;s failed 2008 campaign for the Republican nomination his son Tagg set up a private equity fund with the campaign&#8217;s top fundraiser. One of the first donors was his mum, Anne. Next came several of his dad&#8217;s financial backers. Tagg had no experience in the world of finance, but after two years in the middle of a deep recession the company had netted $244m from just 64 investors. </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Tagg insists that neither his name nor the fact that his father had made it clear he would run for the presidency again had anything to do with his success. &#8220;The reason people invested in us is that they liked our strategies,&#8221; he told the New York Times. </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Class privilege, and the power it confers, is often conveniently misunderstood by its beneficiaries as the product of their own genius rather than generations of advantage, stoutly defended and faithfully bequeathed. Evidence of such advantages is not freely available. It is not in the powerful&#8217;s interest for the rest of us to know how their influence is attained or exercised. But every now and then a dam bursts and the facts come flooding forth&#8230;</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/05/a-web-of-privilege-supports-this-so-called-meritocracy.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>What is meritocracy?</title>
		<link>./../../2011/12/what-is-meritocracy.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/12/what-is-meritocracy.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2011 15:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2012 Presidential elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[meritocracy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[opportunity costs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[winners and losers]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/12/what-is-meritocracy.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Andrew Gelman points to our confusions regarding merit in our social perceptions of winners and losers. I might make a list of naughty and nice sayings for another post. Tyler Cowen pointed to an article by business-school professor Luigi Zingales about meritocracy. I’d expect a b-school prof to support the idea of meritocracy, and Zingales [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a target="_blank" href="http://andrewgelman.com/2011/12/lamentably-common-misunderstanding-of-meritocracy/?">Andrew Gelman</a> points to our confusions regarding merit in our social perceptions of winners and losers.  I might make a list of naughty and nice sayings for another post.<br />
<blockquote>
<p>Tyler Cowen <a href="http://marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2011/10/assorted-links-267.html">pointed</a> to <a href="http://www.city-journal.org/2011/21_4_meritocracy.html">an article</a> by business-school professor Luigi Zingales about meritocracy. I’d expect a b-school prof to support the idea of meritocracy, and Zingales does not disappoint.</p>
<p>But he says a bunch of other things that to me represent a confused conflation of ideas. Here’s Zingales:</p>
<blockquote><p>America became known as a land of opportunity—a place whose capitalist system benefited <em>the hardworking and the virtuous</em> [emphasis added]. In a word, it was a meritocracy.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That’s interesting—and revealing. Here’s what I get when I look up “meritocracy” in the <a href="http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/meritocracy">dictionary</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>1 : a system in which the talented are chosen and moved ahead on the basis of their achievement     <br />2 : leadership selected on the basis of intellectual criteria</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Nothing here about “hardworking” or “virtuous.” In a meritocracy, you can be as hardworking as John Kruk or as virtuous as Kobe Bryant and you’ll still get ahead—if you have the talent and achievement. Throwing in “hardworking” and “virtuous” seems to me to an attempt (unconscious, I expect) to retroactively assign <em>moral</em> standing to the winners in an economic race.    <br />Later, Zingales writes:</p>
<blockquote><p>The fundamental role of an economic system, even an extremely primitive one, is to assign responsibility and reward.</p>
<p> <a name="more"></a> </p></blockquote>
<p>Huh? Again he seems to be conflating economics with morality, in a similar way as when economists Mankiw and Weinzierl implied that the state only has a right to tax things that are “unjustly wrestled from someone else.” Zingales in the above quote is taking the economic functions of prices, wages, supply, and demand and transmuting them into to the morally-loaded terms “responsibility” and “reward.”</p>
<p>Finally, in his praise of meritocracy, Zingales doesn’t seem to be aware of the concept’s self-contradicting nature. As James “Effect” Flynn has <a href="http://andrewgelman.com/2007/12/meritocracy_won/">pointed out</a>,</p>
<blockquote><p>The case against meritocracy can be put psychologically: (a) The abolition of materialist-elitist values is a prerequisite for the abolition of inequality and privilege; (b) the persistence of materialist-elitist values is a prerequisite for class stratification based on wealth and status; (c) therefore, a class-stratified meritocracy is impossible.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>To put it another way, Zingales talks a lot about the threat to meritocracy from business capturing government regulation or from pitchfork-wielding hordes raising the marginal tax rate, but he doesn’t consider some much more direct effects of meritocracy such as <a href="http://andrewgelman.com/2011/06/how_to_party_yo/">this</a>.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>More can be read at Andrew&#8217;s place. (link is at beginning)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/12/what-is-meritocracy.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Why I Will Not Read Forbes Magazine</title>
		<link>./../../2008/03/why-i-will-not-read-forbes-magazine.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/03/why-i-will-not-read-forbes-magazine.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2008 15:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Forbes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[humor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[meritocracy]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/03/why-i-will-not-read-forbes-magazine.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[We&#8217;ve had a lot of fun with stuff written by Steve Forbes here at Angry Bear. But the magazine that bears his (or his father&#8217;s) name publishes humor by others as well. I was going to respond to Sammy&#8217;s post in the comments to that post, but figured my response could stand alone. Sammy quotes [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We&#8217;ve had a lot of fun with stuff written by Steve Forbes here at Angry Bear.  But the magazine that bears his (or his father&#8217;s) name publishes humor by others as well.  </p>
<p>I was going to respond to <a href="http://angrybear.blogspot.com/2008/03/sammy-on-freedom-and-competitive.html">Sammy&#8217;s post</a> in the comments to that post, but figured my response could stand alone.  Sammy quotes <a href="http://www.forbes.com/home/opinions/2008/03/22/america-compete-innovation-oped-cx_jcmn_0325compete.html">this article</a> in Forbes by Jim Clifton, CEO of the Gallup Organization and C. L. Max Nikias, Provost of the University of Southern California.  They tell us:</p>
<blockquote><p>A quarter of a century ago, most leading economists&#8211;whether liberal or conservative&#8211;predicted that American economic growth would fall behind Japan and Germany by 2007. They typically estimated that Japan&#8217;s annual gross domestic product would be roughly $5 trillion by now, with Germany at around $4 trillion, and the U.S. lagging behind at roughly $3.5 trillion.</p>
<p>The predictions for Japan and Germany were reasonably accurate. But America grew to $13 trillion.</p></blockquote>
<p>The BEA tells us that the <a href="http://www.bea.gov/national/xls/gdplev.xls">nominal GDP for the US in 1983 was 3.5 trillion</a>.  I wonder if the authors or Forbes magazine would care to produce a list of these leading economists who were predicting that the US&#8217; nominal GDP would not grow at all in 25 years, especially considering the early 80s were characterized by fears of high inflation.  I do remember predictions from that time of how Japan was going to take over the world.  I don&#8217;t have time to look any of &#8217;em up right now, but I do wonder how many of those predictions appeared in Forbes magazine at the time.</p>
<p>One final observation &#8211; since they&#8217;re looking for reasons why the US has not performed badly in the past twenty-five years, and considering that the positions of authority these guys are in, I would humbly suggest they scratch &#8220;meritocracy&#8221; from their list.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/03/why-i-will-not-read-forbes-magazine.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
