<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>PPACA &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The future of YOUR health insurance premiums</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/the-future-of-your-health-insurance-premiums.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/the-future-of-your-health-insurance-premiums.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2013 17:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Maggie Mahar]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[PPACA]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/the-future-of-your-health-insurance-premiums.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Maggie Mahar run75441: Maggie Mahar writes on future insurance premium increases something consistently arises in the debate on the PPACA. The complete post can be found at healthinsurance.org The future of YOUR health insurance premiums Today, many Americans are asking, “Will my premiums go up in 2014?” There is no simple answer. According to [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by <strong>Maggie Mahar</strong></p>
<p>run75441: Maggie Mahar writes on future insurance premium increases something consistently arises in the debate on the PPACA.  The complete post can be found at <a href="http://www.healthinsurance.org/blog/2013/01/22/the-future-of-your-health-insurance-premiums/" target="_blank">healthinsurance.org</a></p>
<p>The future of YOUR health insurance premiums</p>
<p>Today, many Americans are asking, “Will my premiums go up in 2014?”</p>
<p>There is no simple answer.</p>
<p>According to Families USA, the Affordable Care Act (ACA) will have a <a href="http://familiesusa2.org/assets/pdfs/health-reform/helping-families/National-Report.pdf">positive effect on the typical family’s budget</a>. Using an economic model that can factor in all provisions of the Act, Family’s USA estimates that by 2019, when the law is fully implemented, “the average household will be $1,571 better off.”<br />Even high-income families will save: thanks to rules that limit co-pays, and reward providers for becoming more efficient, “those earning $100,000 to $250,000″ will spend $779 less on medical care.”<br />But these are “averages.” They don’t tell you whether your premiums will rise or fall.</p>
<p>The answer will depend on: your income, your age, your gender, whether a past illness or injury has been labeled a <a href="http://www.healthinsurance.org/glossary/pre-existing-conditions/">pre-existing condition</a>, who you work for, and what type of insurance you have now:</p>
<p>If you work for a large company:</p>
<p>The ACA will have a “negligible” <a href="http://www.cbo.gov/sites/default/files/cbofiles/ftpdocs/107xx/doc10781/11-30-premiums.pdf">effect on your premiums</a> says the Congressional Budget Office (CBO).<br />This doesn’t mean that your costs won’t climb in 2014. As long as medical product-makers and providers continue to raise prices, premiums will edge up each year.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>But in 2012 average premiums for employer-based insurance rose by just 3 percent for single coverage and 4 percent for families, a “<a href="http://www.healthinsurance.org/blog/2012/02/13/health-care-cost-increase-lowest-in-50-years/">modest increase</a>” when compared to 8 percent to 12 percent jumps in past years. And on average, <a href="http://ehbs.kff.org/pdf/2012/8345.pdf">employee co-pays and deductibles remained flat</a>.</p>
<p>Granted, a 3 percent to 4 percent increase still <a href="http://money.cnn.com/2012/09/11/pf/insurance/health-insurance-premiums/index.html">outpaces growth in workers’ wages</a> (1.7 percent percent) and general inflation (2.3 percent) percent). But as <a href="http://www.healthinsurance.org/blog/2012/09/29/the-next-step-for-obamacare/">reform reins in spending</a>, annual increases for large groups could fall to 2 percent – or less.</p>
<p>If you work for a small company with more than 50 employees:</p>
<p><a href="http://www.healthinsurance.org/blog/2012/12/01/can-businesses-really-not-afford-obamacare/">Your boss will be more likely to offer affordable benefits</a>, in part because, if he doesn’t, he will have to pay a penalty.</p>
<p>Moreover, he will find insurance less expensive. Today, <a href="http://www.whitehouse.gov/administration/eop/cea/Health-Care-Reform-and-Small-Businesses">small businesses pay 18 percent more than large companies</a> because the administrative costs of hand-selling plans to small groups are sky-high.<br />But starting in 2014, businesses with fewer than 100 employees will begin buying insurance in exchanges where they will become part of a large group, and eligible for lower rates.</p>
<p>Finally, some <a href="http://www.healthcare.gov/law/features/employers/small-employer-tax-credit/index.html">companies with fewer than 25 employees will receive subsidies</a> that cover 50 percent of what they lay out for insurance.</p>
<p>If you work for a small firm where many employees are older, female, or suffer from a pre-existing condition:</p>
<p>Your premiums may well fall. Today, most states let <a href="http://www.acscan.org/pdf/healthcare/imple%20mentation/background/NewFederalRatingRules.pdf">insurers charge small firms more if many of their workers are older or are women</a>.  They also can jack up premiums <a href="http://www.healthcare.gov/law/resources/reports/preexisting.html">if just a few workers fall ill or are injured</a>.</p>
<p><i>This post originally appeared on <a href="http://www.healthinsurance.org/blog/2013/01/22/the-future-of-your-health-insurance-premiums/">healthinsurance.org</a>. To find out more about the importance of where you live, whether you are a woman, whether you are young (20-something to 30-something) or older (in your 50-65), your income, and your health status please click there.</i></p>
<p><i>Or if you like, you can return to HealthBeat to comment.</i>  run75411</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/the-future-of-your-health-insurance-premiums.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Health Care Thoughts: Regulatory Bumbling</title>
		<link>./../../2011/12/health-care-thoughts-regulatory-bumbling.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/12/health-care-thoughts-regulatory-bumbling.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 30 Dec 2011 15:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[ACO]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[healthcare thoughts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[PPACA]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/12/health-care-thoughts-regulatory-bumbling.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt Health Care Thoughts: Regulatory Bumbling The people who daily manage health care services (and their advisers) have been shocked at the inability of the Obama administration to manage the administrative regs roll out process. The 2009 stimulus act contained multi-year funding for adopting electronic medical records (EMR/EHR) systems. The funding [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt</p>
<p>Health Care Thoughts: Regulatory Bumbling</p>
<p>The people who daily manage health care services (and their advisers) have been shocked at the inability of the Obama administration to manage the administrative regs roll out process.  The 2009 stimulus act contained multi-year funding for adopting electronic medical records (EMR/EHR) systems.</p>
<p>The funding required &#8220;meaningful use&#8221; and the published regulations were and are nearly incomprehensible, especially at the physician practice level.   EMR/EHRs are making progress but it is largely due to the integration of physician practices into integrated delivery systems.</p>
<p> Then there is PPACA. The first major regulatory effort were the SSP accountable care organization (ACO) regulations, and that was a disaster. Even the administration&#8217;s allies ran for the hills.  The administration has spent the last half of 2011 creating new ACO sub programs and revising regulations, and has finally convinced some providers to jump on board the pioneer ACO program. <br /><a name="more"></a>(Some of the desired innovation and integration is happening, but it is being pushed by fear of  the future economics of health care rather than directly by PPACA.) .</p>
<p> The C.L.A.S.S. long-term care financing program died in its crib. Early on Secretary Sebelius announced the program was not financially viable, and got into a shouting match with Congressional Democrats when she announced she could change the program without Congress changing the empowering statute.  There were attempts at CPR, but the program now appears to be really dead.</p>
<p> The most recent botch (already mentioned in an earlier post here) are the &#8220;essential benefits&#8221;  regulations. As described in WAPO (12/16) the administration punted the decisions to the states.   Depending on your perspective, this could be seen as &#8220;flexibility&#8221; or seen as &#8220;surrender.&#8221; We are still digesting these rules (it occurs to me multi state employers are going to freak on this).  The 2200 pages of PPACA will be backed by many thousands of pages of administrative law.</p>
<p>At the provider and insurer level these regulations are the real meat of the act. A smooth roll out would certainly make PPACA more valuable.  Lawyers specializing in health care administrative law are delighted. Consultants and writers are happy as well (I plead guilty).  Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/12/health-care-thoughts-regulatory-bumbling.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>MLR bomb&#8230;</title>
		<link>./../../2011/12/mlr-bomb.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/12/mlr-bomb.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2011 15:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[health care reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medical loss ratio]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MLR]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[PPACA]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/12/mlr-bomb.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[There is a amazing piece in Forbes that Tim Worstall (also at Forbes) notes reporting on scary news that is misleading: I’m very confused by this piece from fellow Forbes contributor Rick Ungar. He tells us that there’s a bomb buried in Obamacare (or more formally, the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act) and that [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There is a amazing piece in Forbes that Tim Worstall (also at Forbes) notes reporting on scary news that is misleading:</p>
<blockquote><p>I’m very confused by this piece from fellow Forbes contributor <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/rickungar/2011/12/02/the-bomb-buried-in-obamacare-explodes-today-halleluja/">Rick Ungar</a>. He tells us that there’s a bomb buried in Obamacare (or more formally, the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act) and that it’s just gone off. Further, that it will mean the end of private, for profit, health care insurance on any large scale: whatever remains will be just a luxury item for those who like to beat the queues as such insurance is in the UK where we have the NHS.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a target="_blank" href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/">Angry Bear&#8217;s Bruce Webb</a> noted the MLR in the legislation on <a target="_blank" href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2009/07/hr3200-sec-116-golden-bullet-or-smoking.html%22">July 28, 2009</a> (and <a target="_blank" href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2011/01/mlr-provisions-kick-in-today.html">here </a> and <a target="_blank" href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2009/12/medical-loss-ratio-revisited-cost-and.html">here</a>), among the first to offer analysis, but hardly a surprise now.<br /><a name="more"></a><br />Tim [edited for clarity] quotes Ungar and then refutes:
</p>
<blockquote><blockquote>That would be the provision of the law, called the medical loss ratio, that requires health insurance companies to spend 80% of the consumers’ premium dollars they collect—85% for large group insurers—on actual medical care rather than overhead, marketing expenses and profit. Failure on the part of insurers to meet this requirement will result in the insurers having to send their customers a rebate check representing the amount in which they underspend on actual medical care.
<p>This is the true ‘bomb’ contained in Obamacare and the one item that will have more impact on the future of how medical care is paid for in this country than anything we’ve seen in quite some time. Indeed, it is this aspect of the law that represents the true ‘death panel’ found in Obamacare—but not one that is going to lead to the death of American consumers. Rather, the medical loss ratio will, ultimately, lead to the death of large parts of the private, for-profit health insurance industry.</p>
<p>Why? Because there is absolutely no way for-profit health insurers are going to be able to learn how to get by and still make a profit while being forced to spend at least 80 percent of their receipts providing their customers with the coverage for which they paid.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>What confuses me here is that in a competitive market it’s entirely normal for an insurer to have a loss ratio higher than 80%. There are plenty of entirely profitable and growing insurance companies that have loss ratios over 100%. So I cannot really understand why the law insisting on an MLR of 80% (or 85% in the large group market) is going to cause all for profit insurance companies to fall over.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Now of course one wonders what is important in addition to this scarey announcement of a medical cost bomb? Issues of accounting for expenses, a more recent mlr formula that is more permissive, enforcement issues.  And even why the ratios may be central as a part of the legislation. Another post of course.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/12/mlr-bomb.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Health Care Thoughts: No CLASS Act</title>
		<link>./../../2011/09/health-care-thoughts-no-class-act.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/09/health-care-thoughts-no-class-act.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2011 14:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[CLASS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health care thoughts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[PPACA]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/09/health-care-thoughts-no-class-act.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Health Care Thoughts: No CLASS Act The Community Living Assistance Services and Supports, aka CLASS, was to be an integral part of PPACA (Obamacare), providing a funding source for some part of long-term care costs. When DHHS Secretary Sebelius declared she would have to fix the program because the poor design was not financially viable, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>Health Care Thoughts</strong>: No CLASS Act</p>
<p>The Community Living Assistance Services and Supports, aka CLASS, was to be an integral part of PPACA (Obamacare), providing a funding source for some part of long-term care costs.</p>
<p>When DHHS Secretary Sebelius declared she would have to fix the program because the poor design was not financially viable, the vultures started to circle. Now it appears the Obama administration is likely to abandon the program, due to the poor design.</p>
<p>Liberals will not believe me, but complexity is the enemy of successful implementation, and PPACA is too complicated to work. </p>
<p>Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt </p>
<p>(I don&#8217;t agree with Rusty&#8217;s notion that &#8216;liberals&#8217; won&#8217;t agree&#8230;comments after the jump)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/09/health-care-thoughts-no-class-act.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
