<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>intergenerational equity &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The Age Rating Game</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/the-age-rating-game.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/the-age-rating-game.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2013 12:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Health Insurance]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health insurance reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[intergenerational equity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Maggie Mahar]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/the-age-rating-game.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Maggie Mahar Health Care Blog discusses some of the rhetoric employed in media on how to pay for health insurance. In other words, when costs are distributed over a large group, older adults save more than younger adults lose. Still, many believe that older Boomers can and should pick up the higher tab for their [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://thehealthcareblog.com/blog/2012/08/20/the-age-rating-game-will-older-americans-pay-more-under-health-reforma/">Maggie Mahar</a> Health Care Blog discusses some of the rhetoric employed in media on how to pay for health insurance.</p>
<blockquote><p>In other words, when costs are distributed over a large group, older adults save more than younger adults lose.</p>
<p>Still, many believe that older Boomers can and should pick up the higher tab for their own care. After all, throughout their financial lives, they have been luckier than most: they enjoyed first crack at the employment market when jobs were plentiful, and first dibs on housing when homes were affordable.</p>
<p>&#8230;</p>
<p>Yet in recent years, the economy has not been kind to the rock ‘n roll generation. One in six is now unemployed, and from 2000 to 2011, the average (mean) after-tax income of Americans age 45 to 54 (who are now in their 50s and early 60s) <a href="http://www.advisorperspectives.com/dshort/updates/Household-Incomes-by-Age-Brackets.php">plunged by 13.3 percent</a>.</p>
<p>By that measure, the recession has hit them harder than other age groups except Americans aged 15 to 24. Over those years, this cohort should have been enjoying their peak earning years. But as <a href="http://www.advisorperspectives.com/dshort/charts/census/household-income-age-brackets.html?household-income-age-45-54-mean-real-growth.gif">the chart below reveals</a>, they didn’t.</p>
<p><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-RlS-9tu562Y/UR4aUozDPBI/AAAAAAAABgc/EPUnBjRdAKU/s1600/household-income-by-age-bracket-mean-real.gif" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-RlS-9tu562Y/UR4aUozDPBI/AAAAAAAABgc/EPUnBjRdAKU/s320/household-income-by-age-bracket-mean-real.gif"></a></p>
</blockquote>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />
<blockquote>Yet there’s a trade off: if age rating were abolished, younger adults would be charged more, and some would decide they can’t afford insurance. Bottom line: “the number of uninsured older Americans would be roughly offset by increases in the number of uninsured adults in the two younger age groups (18-34 and 34-44).”</p>
<p>This worries policymakers for two reasons. First, we need young, healthy Americans in the pool to keep insurance costs down. Secondly, if young families decide to forego insurance, many won’t buy separate policies for the children.<br />How do we choose between children and their grandparents?</p>
<p>If we don’t want to ration care, the only rational solution is to bring down the cost by trimming waste in our health care system. This will be difficult. Most of the fat isn’t hanging out on the edges of the steak – it’s marbled throughout in the form of unnecessary treatments and over-priced products. It needs to be removed carefully, with a scalpel. But it can be done.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/the-age-rating-game.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Intergenerational Real Benefits in Social Security (Rosser Equation Illustrated)</title>
		<link>./../../2010/07/intergenerational-real-benefits-in-social-security-rosser-equation-illustrated.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/07/intergenerational-real-benefits-in-social-security-rosser-equation-illustrated.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 12 Jul 2010 11:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[intergenerational equity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/07/intergenerational-real-benefits-in-social-security-rosser-equation-illustrated.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Bruce Webb In 2003 CBO published an Issue Brief illustrating the relative contribution of Aging and Real Benefit Growth to future Social Security spending called The Future Growth of Social Security: It’s Not Just Society’s Aging with results graphed above:. Discussion under the fold. Approximately 55 percent of the higher spending is due to [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fjW71B3WLTQ/TDr-dGhrUkI/AAAAAAAAAYg/_NuX8l3Dw70/s1600/SocSecAging+Fig+2.jpg"><img src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fjW71B3WLTQ/TDr-dGhrUkI/AAAAAAAAAYg/_NuX8l3Dw70/s400/SocSecAging+Fig+2.jpg" border="0" alt=""></a><br /><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fjW71B3WLTQ/TDr-cgLV4GI/AAAAAAAAAYY/Mpy8KECHBig/s1600/SocSecAging+Fig3.jpg"><img src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fjW71B3WLTQ/TDr-cgLV4GI/AAAAAAAAAYY/Mpy8KECHBig/s400/SocSecAging+Fig3.jpg" border="0" alt=""></a><br /><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fjW71B3WLTQ/TDr-cfzmLaI/AAAAAAAAAYQ/XBQK-kBtvec/s1600/SocSecAging+Fig4.jpg"><img src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fjW71B3WLTQ/TDr-cfzmLaI/AAAAAAAAAYQ/XBQK-kBtvec/s400/SocSecAging+Fig4.jpg" border="0" alt=""></a><br />by Bruce Webb</p>
<p>In 2003 CBO published an Issue Brief illustrating the relative contribution of Aging and Real Benefit Growth to future Social Security spending called <a target="_blank" href="http://www.cbo.gov/ftpdocs/43xx/doc4380/07-01-SocSecAging.pdf">The Future Growth of Social Security: It’s Not Just Society’s Aging</a> with results graphed above:.</p>
<p>Discussion under the fold. <br /><a name="more"></a><br />
<blockquote>Approximately 55 percent of the higher spending is due to an expected increase in the number of beneficiaries, as the number of new claimants grows and as life expectancy rises. The Social Security trustees estimate that the population age 65 or older will increase from 37 million today to 75 million in 2035 and to 95 million in 2075. <br />Life expectancy for people currently age 65 is estimated to be 83 years. In 2035, it is estimated to be 85 years, and in 2075, 87 years. <br />The remaining 45 percent of the rise in spending is due to a projected increase in the real value of Social Security benefit checks. Under the trustees’ assumptions, the purchasing power of the average earner’s benefits at retirement is expected to nearly double between now and 2075.Source: Congressional Budget Office. </p></blockquote>
<p>This increase in purchasing power is the result of adjusting initial retirement benefits by real wage increases over the worker&#8217;s lifetime. The end result is that retirees share in both the upside and downside of economic growth, if Real Wage for workers is stagnant so do will be initial benefits, if on the other hand workers gain Real Wage increases in line with the traditional relation found between Productivity and Wage (something that broke down some the last decade) then the rising tide really will lift all boats.</p>
<p>A couple of further notes. If retirement benefits are projected to increase in real terms by close to 100% over the next 75 years, then a projected cut of 20-25% on Trust Fund exhaustion would STILL see those future workers with larger baskets of goods than similarly situated retirees (this is what we call &#8216;Rosser&#8217;s Equation&#8217;).</p>
<p>But this real term increase doesn&#8217;t come at the expense of younger workers still in the work force, at least not without some forced special pleading. The goal clearly shown in Fig 2 is to keep overall replacement values steady with each future generation just able to hold onto its share of the overall societal increase. This seems fair to me.</p>
<p>There are some that insist that if you &#8216;really&#8217; look at the numbers you will see that Social Security was simply too generous to earlier generations. How you reconcile this with these graphs showing that each generation will be able to afford a bigger basket of goods than their predessessor would seem difficult. Because arguments from ROI (but I could have had EVEN MORE, and screw Grandma) seem pretty hard-hearted and selfish. But perhaps someone can make the moral case in comments.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/07/intergenerational-real-benefits-in-social-security-rosser-equation-illustrated.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Maybe Bristol Palin is Right</title>
		<link>./../../2010/05/maybe-bristol-palin-is-right.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/05/maybe-bristol-palin-is-right.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 May 2010 17:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[economic growth]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[family]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income inequality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[intergenerational equity]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/05/maybe-bristol-palin-is-right.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[No, not that anyone should pay her $15,000-$30,000 to talk to teenagers about why they should be abstinent. (Short version: &#8220;As with my mother, I wasn&#8217;t, and look what I&#8217;m doing now. Uh, well&#8230;&#8221;) But, via Andrew Samwick, a study from the Pew Foundation (PDF) using PSID data finds that: Among children who start in [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>No, not that anyone should <a href="http://today.msnbc.msn.com/id/37216290/ns/today-today_people/">pay her $15,000-$30,000 to talk to teenagers about why they should be abstinent</a>. (Short version: &#8220;As with my mother, I wasn&#8217;t, and look what I&#8217;m doing now. Uh, well&#8230;&#8221;)</p>
<p>But, <a href="http://capitalgainsandgames.com/blog/andrew-samwick/1731/divorce-and-upward-mobility">via Andrew Samwick</a>, <a href="http://economicmobility.org/assets/pdfs/Family_Structure.pdf">a study from the Pew Foundation</a> (PDF) using PSID data finds that:<br />
<blockquote>Among children who start in the bottom third of the income distribution,<br />only 26 percent with divorced parents move up to the middle or top third<br />as adults, compared to 42 percent of children born to unmarried mothers<br />and 50 percent of children with continuously married parents.</p></blockquote>
<p>Or, in ratio terms, it is only 19% more likely that the child&#8217;s eventual economic status will be improved if the mother marries someone and stays married until the child is eighteen, compared to a 61.5% improvement in the expected well-being of the child if the mother remains unmarried for the entire eighteen years.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, twice as many children have parents who divorce before the child is nineteen (14%) than are raised by unwed mothers (7%).</p>
<p>There may also be elements of selection bias in the data: a woman who opts to raise a child on her own instead of getting married is more likely to instill that independence of spirit in her child than someone who enters into what turns out to be a bad marriage.</p>
<p>The other interesting table in the study shows how severely income inequality increased across a generation.
<p><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_wM5Pj6NF0jA/S_QoXm2XCTI/AAAAAAAAAa0/vl401TBrvqE/s1600/mobilitytable1.JPG"><img src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_wM5Pj6NF0jA/S_QoXm2XCTI/AAAAAAAAAa0/vl401TBrvqE/s400/mobilitytable1.JPG" border="0" alt=""></a></p>
<p>Note that the bottom tier improves the least, that the 50th percentile grows much slower than even the 75th, and that the percentage change in the Mean is greater than the percentage change at any tier except the 90th percentile.</p>
<p>So much for the rising tide having lifted all boats—clearly, it capsized a few.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/05/maybe-bristol-palin-is-right.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>PSA</title>
		<link>./../../2009/09/psa-2.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/09/psa-2.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2009 03:14:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[economic development]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[human capital]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[intergenerational equity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/09/psa-2.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[It&#8217;s true that I have been a bit nastier than usual with some posts (especially this one and this one—though the latter was rather justified by preceding events, as Tom detailed.) The sight of economists who should know better saying &#8220;Ewww, tariffs&#8221; in the manner of second grade boys who think girls have &#8220;cooties&#8221; is [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It&#8217;s true that I have been a bit nastier than usual with some posts (especially <a target="_blank" href="http://angrybear.blogspot.com/2009/09/plural-of-datum-is-foreboding.html">this one</a> and <a target="_blank" href="http://angrybear.blogspot.com/2009/09/coming-soon-from-major-economists-near.html">this one</a>—though the latter was rather justified by preceding events, <a target="_blank" href="http://angrybear.blogspot.com/2009/09/travels-of-cheap-tire-in-global-economy.html">as Tom detailed</a>.) The sight of economists who should know better saying &#8220;Ewww, tariffs&#8221; in the manner of second grade boys who think girls have &#8220;cooties&#8221; is rather tiring.  It&#8217;s almost as if they note that a strong rule of law is necessary to ensure that problems of asymmetric information are remedied and then complaining when those laws are actually used.  Oh, wait&#8230;</p>
<p>Part of this is that people who should know better—maybe not Max B., but certainly Barry O.—keep pretending that Democrats have no obligation to be better than Republicans at addressing issues of inequality and opportunity.  In which case one might as well vote for Republicans, if one can find those small-government, fiscally-conservative candidates that only Andrew Samwick seems to believe still exists.</p>
<p>But I am cautiously optimistic today. Thanks to <a target="_blank" href="http://lancemannion.typepad.com/lance_mannion/">Lance Mannion</a>, I&#8217;ll be spending most of this week blogging/reporting the <a target="_blank" href="http://www.clintonglobalinitiative.org/">Clinton Global Initiative</a> in New York City. While many of the participants are The Usual Suspects, there is at least some hope that they will approach the world better than they appear to approach their electorate.</p>
<p>If there is anything, especially on Thursday, that someone especially wants to cover, feel free to note it in comments. (Or, if you&#8217;re going to be there, say hello.)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/09/psa-2.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Intergenerational Equity, Unfunded Liability and Selfish Boomers</title>
		<link>./../../2008/09/intergenerational-equity-unfunded-liability-and-selfish-boomers.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/09/intergenerational-equity-unfunded-liability-and-selfish-boomers.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2008 18:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[intergenerational equity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[unfunded liability]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/09/intergenerational-equity-unfunded-liability-and-selfish-boomers.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The newest buzzphrase in the Social Security world is &#8216;Intergenerational Equity&#8217;. It is indeed the theme of the new movie IOUSA (to whose webpage I link) which itself is pretty much a documentary of the Concord Coaltion&#8217;s Fiscal Wake Up Tour. (The fact that Concord was founded by Pete Peterson and rights to distribute the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The newest buzzphrase in the Social Security world is &#8216;Intergenerational Equity&#8217;. It is indeed the theme of the new movie <a href="http://www.agorafinancial.com/iousa.html?gclid=CMrNleqo1JUCFQL8iAodDBMgiw">IOUSA</a> (to whose webpage I link) which itself is pretty much a documentary of the Concord Coaltion&#8217;s <a href="http://www.concordcoalition.org/act/fiscal-wake-tour">Fiscal Wake Up Tour</a>. (The fact that Concord was founded by Pete Peterson and rights to distribute the IOUSA film are in the hands of the <a href="http://www.pgpf.org/">PGPF: Peter G. Peterson Foundation</a> not being a coincidence at all.)</p>
<p>One of EconomistMom&#8217;s (who is a/the chief economist at Concord) first posts was entitled <a href="http://economistmom.com/2008/06/the-young-people-get-it/">The Young People Get It</a> which in turn was plugging the <a href="http://www.youthentitlementsummit.org/Welcome.html">Youth Entitlement Summit 2008</a> in turn sponsored by <a href="http://www.age-usa.org/">Americans for Generational Equity</a> an organization first founded in 2006 and funded by the usual group of conservative foundations.</p>
<p>The idea isn&#8217;t new exactly, in Googling around today I found this lengthy article from Sept 2003 that probably explains it better than I can (I have only read the first page so far) <a href="http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0CYZ/is_3_30/ai_109352146">Generational equity, generational interdependence, and the framing of the debate over social security reform</a>. But before I turn this one over to a discussion of that let me highlight one thing.</p>
<p>If you go to the IOUSA webpage and look for the first part of the description of the overall issue you find it framed as follows (bolding mine) :<br />
<blockquote>I.O.U.S.A. boldly examines the rapidly growing national debt and its consequences for the United States and its citizens. As the Baby Boomer generation prepares to retire, will there even be any Social Security benefits left to collect? Burdened with an ever-expanding government and military, increased international competition, overextended entitlement programs, and debts to foreign countries that are becoming impossible to honor, America must mend its spendthrift ways or face an economic disaster of epic proportions.</p></blockquote>
<p>Sure they go on to talk about military spending and foreign debt but the discussion ALWAYS starts and mostly ends with Social Security and equally ALWAYS with a dig at Baby Boomers.</p>
<p>Having run into this particular article I want to post this now as Part 1 and get some discussion going on the overall topic and then return to the theme of &#8216;Social Security Crisis = Selfish Boomers&#8217; in a latter post. Consider this homework for the would-be well-prepared student. Or contra-wise an episode of &#8216;Know your enemy&#8217;.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/09/intergenerational-equity-unfunded-liability-and-selfish-boomers.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
