<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>immigration &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The most money goes to which law enforcement agency?</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/the-most-money-goes-to-which-law-enforcement-agency.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/the-most-money-goes-to-which-law-enforcement-agency.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 09 Jan 2013 15:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Federal budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[federal regulation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[public perceptions]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/the-most-money-goes-to-which-law-enforcement-agency.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Think Progress offers a note of caution when we think we have reality nailed for government spending and results. And how &#8216;public displays&#8217; by our politicians offer up little information: During the 2012 fiscal year, the federal government spent more on immigration enforcement — $18 billion — than on every other federal law enforcement agencies [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://thinkprogress.org/justice/2013/01/07/1407461/cost-of-a-broken-system-us-spent-more-on-immigration-than-all-other-federal-enforcement-agencies-combined/" target="_blank">Think Progress</a> offers a note of caution when we think we have reality nailed for government spending and results.  And how &#8216;public displays&#8217; by our politicians offer up little information:</p>
<blockquote><p>During the 2012 fiscal year, the federal government <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/huff-wires/20130107/us-immigration-spending/?utm_hp_ref=homepage&#038;ir=homepage">spent more on immigration enforcement</a> — $18 billion — than on every other federal law enforcement agencies combined, according to a new <a href="http://www.migrationpolicy.org/pubs/pillars-reportinbrief.pdf">report</a> from the Migration Policy Institute. The spending on Immigration and Customs Enforcement and Customs and Border Protection dwarfs the combined $14.4 billion spent on the FBI; Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms and Explosives; Drug Enforcement Administration and U.S. Secret Service.
<p>The U.S. has <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/huff-wires/20130107/us-immigration-spending/?utm_hp_ref=homepage&#038;ir=homepage">spent</a> more than $187 billion on immigration enforcement since President Reagan <a href="http://www.migrationpolicy.org/pubs/pillars-reportinbrief.pdf">signed</a> the Immigration Reform and Control Act in 1986 — which first made it illegal for employers to hire undocumented workers along with strengthening U.S. border security. Adjusted for inflation, the U.S. now spends <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2013/01/07/immigration-enforcement-cost_n_2425647.html?1357584619">15 times as much</a> on immigration enforcement as it did in the mid-1980s. And the number of deportations and immigration-related prosecutions has also <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2013/01/07/immigration-enforcement-cost_n_2425647.html?1357584619">jumped along with the increased spending</a>:</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/the-most-money-goes-to-which-law-enforcement-agency.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Posts I Won&#8217;t Write</title>
		<link>./../../2011/12/posts-i-wont-write.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/12/posts-i-wont-write.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2011 22:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2012 Presidential]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health Care]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[privatization]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Republican brand]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/12/posts-i-wont-write.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Buce sends us to Der Spiegel&#8217;s description of Barack Obama&#8217;s potential 2012 opponents (&#8220;You Think This is Bad?&#8221;) John Kay in today&#8217;s FT (no link) tells us why letting economists pontificate about finance is a Mug&#8217;s Game. The mugging being of people who are stupid enough to believe economists. (If Brad DeLong or Mark Thoma [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://underbelly-buce.blogspot.com/2011/12/der-spiegel-is-not-impressed.html">Buce</a> sends us to <a href="http://www.spiegel.de/international/world/0%2C1518%2C800850%2C00.html">Der Spiegel&#8217;s description of Barack Obama&#8217;s potential 2012 opponents</a> (&#8220;You Think This is Bad?&#8221;)</p>
<p>John Kay in today&#8217;s FT (no link) tells us why letting economists pontificate about finance is a Mug&#8217;s Game. The mugging being of people who are stupid enough to believe economists. (If Brad DeLong or Mark Thoma links to this one, I&#8217;ll add a link to them.)</p>
<p><a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/answer-sheet/post/when-an-adult-took-standardized-tests-forced-on-kids/2011/12/05/gIQApTDuUO_blog.html">This</a> (from Kaplan Daily of all places, but Valerie Strauss is one of the only Bright Lights there) is probably the most important general article about standardized testing and education.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.bluejersey.com/diary/19941/who-will-save-the-children">This one</a> tells the truth and shames the devil, as it were. Those fooling themselves that vouchers and charter schools will lead to improvement in anything other than excess rents going into the pockets of the people who are hired to run them (such as <a href="http://www.edisonlearning.com/">Christopher Cerf, President and COO</a> and <a href="http://www.phoenix.edu/">Christopher Christie, lobbyist</a>) either have forgotten or are ignoring history:</p>
<blockquote><p>Decades of research have shown that not only do the for-profit, corporate models being forced on school districts from coast to coast not work, they present a separate and unequal solution, and offer huge profits for investors.</p></blockquote>
<p>Anyone stupid enough to believe the &#8220;anti-piracy&#8221; crowd has the best interest of Creators in mind <a href="http://www.dangerousminds.net/comments/major_anti_piracy_campaign_accused_of_pirating_its_soundtrack">needs to mark that belief to market</a>. For another data point (via <a href="http://www.eschatonblog.com/">Dr. Black</a>), see <a href="http://mediamatters.org/blog/201112060011">here</a>.</p>
<p>On a more positive note—not to mention having grown up watching Bob Braun as a local, afternoon talk-show host—I want to note Mr. Braun being one of the only reasons to read The Star-Ledger, and especially highlight his series dealing with ICE abusing its power (nu?) and <a href="http://blog.nj.com/njv_bob_braun/2011/12/braun_red_tape_suspicion_delay.html">almost preventing</a> a girl from <a href="http://blog.nj.com/njv_bob_braun/2011/12/braun_red_tape_suspicion_delay.html">saving her sister&#8217;s life</a>.</p>
<p>This one <a href="http://blog.nj.com/njv_bob_braun/2011/12/braun_elizabeth_girl_will_be_a.html#incart_mce">has a happy ending</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/12/posts-i-wont-write.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mandatory submission to e-verify program&#8230;a few points more</title>
		<link>./../../2011/07/mandatory-submission-to-e-verify-program-a-few-points-more.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/07/mandatory-submission-to-e-verify-program-a-few-points-more.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2011 09:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[taxes]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/07/mandatory-submission-to-e-verify-program-a-few-points-more.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Op ed by Nancy Ortiz Scott Hochberg&#8217;s article Making E-Verify Mandatory: The Perfect Storm for Crippling the Social Security Administration and Jeopardizing the Social Safety Net discusses issues regarding the e-Verify system and a move in Congress to make it mandatory for everyone hired for a job in the US. He points out that eVerify [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Op ed by <strong>Nancy Ortiz</strong></p>
<p>Scott Hochberg&#8217;s article <a target="_blank" href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2011/07/making-e-verify-mandatory-perfect-storm.html">Making E-Verify Mandatory: The Perfect Storm for Crippling the Social Security Administration and Jeopardizing the Social Safety Net</a> discusses issues regarding the e-Verify system and a move in Congress to make it mandatory for everyone hired for a job in the US. He points out that eVerify is every bit as much a threat to SS and Medicare as any of the other benefit, COLA, or Medicare provider cuts now being discussed. I read Hochberg&#8217;s article with great interest and have a few additional points to add to his excellent analysis of this subject.  </p>
<p>When the Immigration Reform Act took effect in 1987, I was the manager of the SS office in Northern Santa Barbara County in strawberry, broccoli, lettuce and wine grape country. Thousands of migrant workers pass through the area at the height of the picking season between January and May. Many stay with or without authorization so that about 60% of the population is Hispanic and/or non-English speaking/non-US national. You will find similar demographics up and down the California Central Coast in agricultural areas, so there&#8217;s nothing unusual about this.<br /><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>I&#8217;ll spare you the war stories of actually implementing IRCA&#8217;s social security number provisions. This was the Bush I administration notable for its parsimony in budgeting for SSA operations. (How bad was it? How about no hiring, no overtime and no photocopy paper bad?) Farm workers in the area lined up with their new Immigration work visas in hand outside our office door at 6:00A and we interviewed Social Security Number applicants until 5:00P every day from 1987 til mid-1989. It was hard to get anything else done, but the normal operation got busier because of the recession that put maybe 15% of the workforce in our area out of work.</p>
<p>Alright, now it won&#8217;t take much imagination to imagine the same situation but worse, because now every worker  would be subject to e-verify. Not just the &#8220;obvious illegals,&#8221; every single one who applied for a job. Hochberg&#8217;s article summarizes the projected workload from this but SSA&#8217;s workforce is now 20 or more years older <br />and really, really ready to retire. And, of course, Congress is talking about cutting the whole federal civil service workforce 10% across the board while maintaining an indefinite hiring freeze and whacking every agencies&#8217; budget in its 2 Trillion to 4 Trillion dollar spending cuts. The President is ready to agree to at least 2 Trillion in cuts, but discussions are continuing.</p>
<p>Perhaps you can see now why making it illegal to work in the US without lawful admission was a bad, terrible, awful, rotten, really bad idea from the git-go. &#8220;All we would have to do to&#8221; avoid this debacle is revoke this provision and we could go back to doing business the way we did before 1987. The punitive notion of making<br />work without documents a &#8220;crime&#8221; has resulted in a flood of counterfeit and stolen documents. Field workers often buy many sets of documents (at high prices) before getting a set that will pass employers&#8217; inspection. Every town in California and other border states has document mills.  Sanctions against employers for hiring undocumented workers are virtually never imposed. Identity theft, impossible to prevent and prosecute effectively, is epidemic. And, on and on. All because of the notion that working in the US should be a crime.</p>
<p>If you remain unconvinced, let me remind you that the budget for SSA&#8217;s New New Computer Center was reduced about in this last round of spending cuts. This will make it impossible to meet an early construction deadline made necessary by the fragility of the existing computer system. This is estimated to result in causing SSA&#8217;s now aged and outdated computer processing and data storage systems to collapse<br />sometime between now and 2013. 2013 is supposedly the outside range of functionality assuming nothing catastrophic (such as a major power grid black out) happens between now and then. Otherwise, it can go at any time. Finally, I don&#8217;t need to remind you of the pending DIB appeals workload of approx. 700K cases still on hand.</p>
<p>But, in closing let me ask you&#8211;can you prove you are a US citizen or lawfully admitted alien with permission to work if I ask you right this minute? No, your drivers&#8217; license isn&#8217;t enough. Your SS card isn&#8217;t ID.  You may have a US Passport but it won&#8217;t resolve the matter unless it is current. Your current or former employer&#8217;s assurance isn&#8217;t enough either.</p>
<p>Prove to me who you are or you can&#8217;t work here any more. And, it says here on this little No Match notice that you aren&#8217;t who you say you are. So, what about it? Exactly who are you anyway, Mr. Working American?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/07/mandatory-submission-to-e-verify-program-a-few-points-more.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Making E-Verify Mandatory: The Perfect Storm</title>
		<link>./../../2011/07/making-e-verify-mandatory-the-perfect-storm.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/07/making-e-verify-mandatory-the-perfect-storm.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2011 11:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[EVerify]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[liberty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/07/making-e-verify-mandatory-the-perfect-storm.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In addition to the controversy over the ARRP position on Social Security, there are other issues affecting retirement that surface via immigration legislation. Scott Hochberg has given Angry Bear permission to post his article from this weekend from Huffington Post. (hat tip coberly) Making E-Verify Mandatory: The Perfect Storm for Crippling the Social Security Administration [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In addition to the controversy over the ARRP position on Social Security, there are other issues affecting retirement that surface via immigration legislation.  Scott Hochberg has given Angry Bear permission to post his article from this weekend from Huffington Post. (hat tip coberly)</p>
<p>Making E-Verify Mandatory: The Perfect Storm for Crippling the Social Security Administration and Jeopardizing the Social Safety Net by Scott Hochberg</p>
<p>There has been much recent buzzing about <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/18/us/18aarp.html?_r=2"><u>AARP&#8217;s ambiguous, half-denied statements</u></a> about their (new?) willingness to cut Social Security benefits, and rightly so. As the largest membership organization of seniors in the country, AARP&#8217;s tactical gamble could be an unfortunate game-changer in any deficit deal negotiated behind closed doors in Washington.</p>
<p>But believe it or not, one of the biggest threats to Social Security this summer could come from an entirely different direction, from an initiative whose main target is not even related to social program spending. <a name="more"></a>  I&#8217;m talking about <a href="http://www.nilc.org/immsemplymnt/ircaempverif/e-verify-facts-about-2011-02-15.pdf"><u>E-Verify</u></a>, a proposed system for curbing the legal employment of every single undocumented worker in America. While seemingly immigration-related, a mandatory E-Verify program could cripple the Social Security Administration (SSA) by concurrently draining already-limited funding while imposing heavy burdens on one of the most efficient government programs in existence. Oh yes, and it would threaten the timely distribution of all new Social Security benefits.</p>
<p>For those not familiar with it, E-Verify is a tool designed to prevent the employment of undocumented workers in the United States. Employers run the personal information of new hires though the E-Verify electronic system, which is connected to the SSA master database of Americans with Social Security numbers. In its developmental stages, the program has been optional for employers, but new legislation proposed by <a href="http://lamarsmith.house.gov/News/DocumentSingle.aspx?DocumentID=246547"><u>Rep. Lamar Smith</u></a> (R-TX) would make it mandatory. This would be dubious policy for a number of reasons, and many diverse groups, from the pro-immigrant community to businesses and agricultural companies, have come out against it.</p>
<p>One key message of these groups that is often overlooked is that E-Verify would add significant responsibilities and workload to an agency that is already overworked and underfunded. The Social Security Administration is one of the most efficient government agencies, operating at less than 1 percent overhead costs. Forcing SSA to handle the administrative nightmare of E-Verify is worse than the usual conservative position of &#8220;starving the beast&#8221; &#8212; it is more like starving the beast and making it run a marathon while carrying a 50 lb. backpack. That&#8217;s because in addition to drastically increasing the responsibilities SSA would be faced with, the agency is already dealing with massive budget cuts that limit its administrative capacity. There are three compelling lines of argument against mandatory E-Verify:</p>
<p>1. Mandatory E-Verify would cost American workers their jobs and create confusion at SSA.</p>
<p>When E-Verify finds an inconsistency between a name and that person&#8217;s work authorization, it issues a &#8220;tentative nonconfirmation&#8221; (TNC), after which an employee has several days to contact SSA or DHS to correct the error or risk losing their job. Unfortunately, a significant number of these TNCs are <a href="http://www.uscis.gov/USCIS/E-Verify/E-Verify/Final%20E-Verify%20Report%2012-16-09_2.pdf"><u>issued in error</u></a>. (<a href="http://www.maldef.org/assets/pdf/e-verify_Trasvina_testimony_HRCommittee.pdf"><u>Errors are usually due</u></a> to clerical mistakes from inputting data, especially with hard-to-spell names or ones that have been hyphenated or changed, as well as errors by the workers themselves when filling out government forms.) In 2010, of the 16 million E-verify queries by employers, 128,000 (0.8 percent of the total) required the employee to go to SSA or call DHS to fix the problem. Of those 0.8 percent errors, 0.3 percent were discovered to be in error and were later corrected. But 0.5 percent &#8212; <i>over half of all errors</i> &#8212; were falsely issued &#8220;final nonconfirmations,&#8221; essentially forcing their employer to wrongly fire them. 0.3 percent may not sound like very many, but with a total American workforce of 154 million, that translates to <a href="http://www.americanprogress.org/issues/2011/06/e_verify.html"><u><i>over 770,000 jobs lost</i></u></a>. (Tyler Moran, Policy Director of the National Immigration Law Center, has a thorough explanation of how many workers would be affected, and why it is so hard for workers to challenge the system.)</p>
<p>So what does this mean for SSA? It translates to an already overburdened staff that now has to deal with hundreds of thousands of extra calls and office visits, sometimes entailing a lengthy review process for individual cases. In 2008, when there were only 7 million E-Verify queries, <a href="http://www.socialsecurity.gov/oig/ADOBEPDF/A-03-09-19052.pdf"><u>88,000 people</u></a> called the 1-800 number or visited SSA due to E-Verify errors. If the program were mandatory, SSA would have to review 154 million records in the initial implementation period: if the rate of people calling SSA was the same as 2008, that would be nearly <i>2 million more calls</i> into the agency during that period alone.</p>
<p>2. SSA is already underfunded and overburdened, and cannot afford to take on the consuming and perpetual E-Verify project.</p>
<p>SSA has long been underfunded. Agency administrative expenses alone have been shorted 8 of the last 10 years (compared with the amount it requested of Congress to operate at full capacity). There was a particularly huge cut in 2011, almost a billion dollars below the required level, that was part of the last-minute compromise between Speaker Boehner and the Democrats a few months ago.</p>
<p>Because of those negotiations, SSA has already had to take several measures to limit its regular operations because it simply can&#8217;t afford them &#8212; many of which (ironically, although perhaps not unintentionally) will increase costs further. For one, last month the agency stopped sending out annual earnings statements to all workers under 65. (Leave aside the fact that they only <a href="http://newshour.tumblr.com/post/6076678767/social-security-administration-stops-sending-earnings"><u>cost SSA $30 million in 2011</u></a>, and help millions of Americans with their retirement planning while double-checking that SSA has the correct data for them.) The agency still expects that it will experience increased call volume from confused people wondering why they didn&#8217;t get their statements and hoping to confirm their information either in person or on the phone.</p>
<p>E-Verify proponents often claim, in response, that SSA would be funded to keep up with its new responsibilities. While that&#8217;s theoretically possible, it&#8217;s unlikely, given the Republicans&#8217; current impulse to cut every government program in sight. It&#8217;s easy to imagine a scenario whereby SSA is forced to cut <i>even more</i> of its regular operations in order to accommodate the new E-Verify agenda. Critical goals of the agency, such as reducing the <a href="http://www.gao.gov/new.items/d11125.pdf"><u>unacceptably long backlog for pending claims</u></a>, would have to be ignored further into the future. Or maybe it was the point all along to cripple the administration of Social Security benefits themselves and attack this <a href="http://strengthensocialsecurity.org/sites/default/files/SocialSecurity&#038;FutureofDemocraticParty_ShortFormREV_1.pdf"><u>extremely popular program</u></a> through the back door.</p>
<p>3. E-verify would remove millions of taxpayers from the pool that pays into Social Security, thus weakening the solvency of the Trust Fund.</p>
<p>As we&#8217;ve seen, the point of E-Verify is to remove illegal workers from legal employment, likely ending their tax contributions to Social Security and other federal revenue streams. This is a wasted opportunity, as any undocumented worker that pays taxes provides a net gain to the system (since they don&#8217;t collect benefits). As we all should know by now, undocumented workers are not going to leave the country when E-Verify comes knocking. They fill an important niche in our economy and are here to stay &#8212; the only difference is that more of them will be funneled into the underground economy, or miscategorized as (partially tax-exempt) independent contractors. One 2008 bill that would have made E-Verify mandatory without a pathway to legalization would have <a href="http://www.cbo.gov/ftpdocs/91xx/doc9100/hr4088ltr.pdf"><u>decreased federal revenue by $22 billion</u></a> over 10 years.</p>
<p>Of the approximately 8 million undocumented workers, it is estimated that about two-thirds of them pay payroll taxes into the Social Security Trust Fund, <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/09/02/AR2010090202673.html."><u>accounting for $12 billion in 2007</u></a>. (The Trust Fund is the total pot of surplus money paid into Social Security that is not immediately sent out as benefits, now totaling $2.7 trillion.) In sum, undocumented workers have contributed somewhere between $120 and $240 billion to the Trust Fund, accounting for 5.4 to 10.7 percent of its total assets. In addition, these workers tend to be younger than the average American, so the impact of their tax contributions will grow as the Baby Boomers retire and the percentage of seniors in America rises from 12 percent to 18 percent. According to the chief actuary of SSA, without the contributions of undocumented workers, the Trust Fund would run out of assets <i>six years earlier</i> than estimated in the 2010 Trustees Report. That&#8217;s staggering.</p>
<p>According to most experts, mandatory E-Verify wouldn&#8217;t affect those who already receive Social Security benefits, because current beneficiaries receive their checks through a mostly automatic process. But this much is sure: nearly everyone else would be affected. It is anyone&#8217;s guess how SSA would respond to being buried with new caseloads at a time when, <i>even pre-E-Verify</i>, &#8220;unprecedented workloads combined with declining budgets [have] damaged [the agency&#8217;s] service delivery,&#8221; according to the <a href="http://waysandmeans.house.gov/UploadedFiles/Moran_Embargoed_Testimony.pdf"><u>SSA Commissioner</u></a> himself. I&#8217;ll leave it to the immigration experts to suggest <a href="http://www.nilc.org/immsemplymnt/SSA_Related_Info/SSA-subcommittee-Moran-testimony-4-14-11.pdf"><u>how E-Verify needs to be improved</u></a> before making it mandatory &#8212; but for now at least, mandatory E-Verify is the surest way to threaten the social safety net with paralysis. Let&#8217;s hope that if E-Verify makes it through the Senate without comprehensive reform attached, Obama will roll out the veto on this one.</p>
<p>&#8212; </p>
<p><strong>Scott Hochberg</strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/07/making-e-verify-mandatory-the-perfect-storm.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Constitutional Originalism and Immigration</title>
		<link>./../../2010/05/constitutional-originalism-and-immigration.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/05/constitutional-originalism-and-immigration.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 28 May 2010 17:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[constitution]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/05/constitutional-originalism-and-immigration.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Bruce Webb Something has been bugging me. Why is it that the same people that indignantly claim that a requirement for people to show proof of insurance is unconstitutional but that it is perfectly fine, nay imperative that people show proof of citizenship or legal residency? Exactly where in the Constitution does it give [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Bruce Webb</p>
<p>Something has been bugging me. Why is it that the same people that indignantly claim that a requirement for people to show proof of insurance is unconstitutional but that it is perfectly fine, nay imperative that people show proof of citizenship or legal residency? Exactly where in the Constitution does it give the Congress the right to control the border to start with?</p>
<p><a target="_blank" href="http://www.usconstitution.net/const.html">Constitution of the United States</a></p>
<p>Neither in 1776 or 1789 were there barriers to visiting or working in the Colonies or the United States. And from what I see the power to determine who was a Citizen or not was left to the various States with the reservation in Article IV Sec 2 that &#8220;The Citizens of each State shall be entitled to all Privileges and Immunities of Citizens in the several States.&#8221;</p>
<p>There is a drive afoot led by Rand Paul and others to repeal that section of the 14th Amendment that provides that everyone born on American soil is as such a Citizen<br />
<blockquote>1. All persons born or naturalized in the United States, and subject to the jurisdiction thereof, are citizens of the United States and of the State wherein they reside. No State shall make or enforce any law which shall abridge the privileges or immunities of citizens of the United States; nor shall any State deprive any person of life, liberty, or property, without due process of law; nor deny to any person within its jurisdiction the equal protection of the laws.</p></blockquote>
<p> Well okay, but that would seem to just restore the situation to the status quo ante in which time there were no controls, and certainly no federal controls on free migration into or between the United States.</p>
<p>My ancestors did not have papers. Some of them reached the US before there was a US while others came from Ireland and Germany in the 1820s and 1830s and as far as I can tell the only requirement for entry was the price of passage. In fact from what I can glean the first restrictions on immigration only came in the 1870s and 1880s and were initially focused on criminals and lunatics to which in the 1890s were added &#8216;Asiatics&#8217; and then in the 1920s national quotas, the latter designed to keep the US from being flooded with people from Southern Europe.<br />http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_United_States_immigration_legislation</p>
<p>Tea Partiers and allied groups claim NOTHING about their efforts is based on race, ALL is about returning to the Constitution as interpreted by the Founders. They equally claim that the &#8216;General Welfare&#8217; clause in the Preamble and in Article II is not meant to be interpreted as giving Congress explicit powers and equally claim that Congress has greatly abused the Commerce Clause. Which leaves me this question. If you folks are so focused on Original Intent why NOT restore the immigration laws back to what they were in 1840? Because clearly you wouldn&#8217;t want to be accused of cherry picking the Constitution. Would you?</p>
<p>Consider this an open thread on immigration, originalism or anything related.</p>
<p>(P.S. Please keep clear the distinction between &#8216;naturalization&#8217; and &#8216;immigration&#8217;. Clearly the States individually and the United States as a whole had powers to control who was a citizen, the question is what the Constitutional authority is to regulate residence by non-citizens whether from another country or another state.)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/05/constitutional-originalism-and-immigration.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>H-1B Database</title>
		<link>./../../2008/10/h-1b-database.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/10/h-1b-database.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2008 01:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[H1B]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[market wages]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[statistics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/10/h-1b-database.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Here&#8217;s what Happens When I Click a Link by Accident: Does anyone believe the market rate for taxi drivers in Maryland is $11.41 an hour? The base salary for an Assistant Professor of Economics is $115-120K for elite schools (well, Harvard and Stanford, but you get the idea).* Morgan Stanley offered $85,000 for an Analyst [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Here&#8217;s what Happens When I Click <a href="http://www.iq.harvard.edu/blog/sss/archives/2008/10/dol_visa_data_r.shtml">a Link</a> by Accident:
<ol>
<li>Does anyone believe the market rate for taxi drivers in Maryland is $11.41 an hour?</li>
<li>The base salary for an Assistant Professor of Economics is $115-120K for elite schools (well, Harvard and Stanford, but you get the idea).*</li>
<li>Morgan Stanley offered $85,000 for an Analyst in 2006.  No indication whether it was a bonus-<s>paying</s>eligible position (though presumably the answer would have been &#8220;yes&#8221;).</li>
</ol>
<p>Have fun with the database.  Sure to stun and amaze.</p>
<p>*Columbia offered far less for next year: an Assistant Professor at the Medical Center campus for $90,000 in 2006, an Associate Professor at the main campus for $95,000 in 2007.  But not certain what the specialties are.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/10/h-1b-database.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
