<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>military spending &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>What is Bahrain?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/09/what-is-bahrain.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/09/what-is-bahrain.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Sep 2012 14:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[arms sales]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bahrain]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[foriegn policy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[military spending]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/09/what-is-bahrain.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Nick Turse at Tom Dispatch reminds us amid the election flurry&#8230; Secretary of State Hillary Clinton was unequivocal in her condemnation. “We have confronted the Russians about stopping their continued arms shipments to Syria,” she said in remarks earlier this year. “They have, from time to time, said that we shouldn’t worry; everything they’re shipping [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Nick Turse at <a href="http://www.tomdispatch.com/post/175594/tomgram%3A_jen_marlowe%2C_the_%22secret%22_revolution_that_could_set_the_middle_east_aflame/?utm_source=TomDispatch&#038;utm_campaign=b0620ac92a-T">Tom Dispatch</a> reminds us amid the election flurry&#8230;<br />
<blockquote>Secretary of State Hillary Clinton was unequivocal in her condemnation. “We have confronted the Russians about stopping their continued arms shipments to Syria,” she said in <a href="http://www.state.gov/secretary/rm/2012/06/192200.htm">remarks</a> earlier this year. “They have, from time to time, said that we shouldn’t worry; everything they’re shipping is unrelated to their actions internally. That’s patently untrue.”</p>
<p>…</p>
<p>&#8230;year earlier, the ruling Sunni minority of the tiny Persian Gulf kingdom had unleashed its security forces on pro-democracy protesters, leaving many wounded or dead, while others were arrested and tortured. The <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766">U.S. government</a>, which bases the Navy’s Fifth Fleet in Bahrain, stayed largely silent about the abuses and then, a few months later, the Department of Defense notified Congress that it had brokered a new arms deal with the country. The Pentagon had arranged for the sale of $53 million worth of weapons and equipment &#8212; 44 armored Humvees and hundreds of TOW missiles &#8212; to Bahrain’s oil-rich monarchy.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Despite some Congressional opposition, the Obama administration used a legal loophole to move forward with the sale, without any formal public notification, according to a January report by <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766">Foreign Policy</a>. (The Defense Security Cooperation Agency, the branch of the Pentagon<strong> </strong>that coordinates sales and transfers of military equipment to allies, did not respond to TomDispatch’s request for information on the current status of the arms deal.)</p>
<p>Even if had there been public notice of the sale in the U.S., the response would, at best, have been muted. While American media outlets followed the revolutions in Tunisia and Egypt closely, covered Libya’s revolution with zeal, and have remained focused on the brutal civil war in Syria, the story of Bahrain’s popular, largely nonviolent uprising has largely been limited to scattered coverage and wire service roundups. Thankfully, TomDispatch’s <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766">Jen Marlowe</a> traveled to Bahrain this summer to witness the continuing uprising and the brutal government response firsthand, before being detained and then <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766">thrown out</a> of the country. She offers a ground-level view of the “secret” revolution that few Americans have been able to follow and the reasons why they need to.</p>
<p>Earlier this year, armored vehicles <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766">patrolled</a> the streets after Bahrain’s security forces battled protesters on the first anniversary of the 2011 uprising. Next year, thanks to the Obama administration, they may have brand new American Humvees on hand for the crackdown.      <em>Nick Turse</em></p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/09/what-is-bahrain.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Romney’s Weird Plan to Decouple Military Spending From National Security Needs and to Tie It Instead to … GDP??</title>
		<link>./../../2012/08/romneys-weird-plan-to-decouple-military-spending-from-national-security-needs-and-to-tie-it-instead-to-gdp.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/08/romneys-weird-plan-to-decouple-military-spending-from-national-security-needs-and-to-tie-it-instead-to-gdp.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2012 16:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[CNNMoney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[military spending]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obama campaign]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/08/romneys-weird-plan-to-decouple-military-spending-from-national-security-needs-and-to-tie-it-instead-to-gdp.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Romney&#8217;s plan calls for linking the Pentagon&#8217;s base budget to Gross Domestic Product, and allowing the military to spend at least $4 dollars out of every $100 the American economy produces.” &#8212; Defense spending to spike $2.1 trillion under Romney, CNN Money, May 10, 2012.) In a post here two weeks ago I noted that [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>Romney&#8217;s plan calls for linking the Pentagon&#8217;s base budget to Gross Domestic Product, and allowing the military to spend at least $4 dollars out of every $100 the American economy produces.”
</p>
</div>
<div>&#8212; <i><a href="http://money.cnn.com/2012/05/10/news/economy/romney-defense-spending/index.htm">Defense spending to spike $2.1 trillion under Romney</a></i>, CNN Money, May 10, 2012.)</div>
<div></div>
<div>In a post here two weeks ago I noted that peculiar proposal of Romney’s, and also mentioned my dismay that neither the Obama campaign nor (to my knowledge) any other mainstream-media outlet had mentioned it.  I titled the post <i><a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/07/crony-capitalism-and-its-variety-of.html">Crony Capitalism and Its Variety of Flavors</a></i>.  The occasion for the post was the Romney campaign’s then-newly-invigorated “crony capitalism” schtik featuring, of course, Solyndra. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I said in the post that, given Romney’s open (if unnoticed) proposal to untether actual national-security <i>needs</i> from national-security <i>spending</i>and attaching it instead to GDP, its purpose is utterly unrelated to national security.  It’s unabashedly “a stunningly perverse pinstriped-patronage version of Keynsian economics,” I said. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>My post got about as much attention as the May 10 CNNMoney report.  But now the Obama campaign<a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/frame_game/2012/08/obama_s_ad_against_military_spending_have_polls_shifted_on_the_defense_budget_.html"> has a new ad out</a> highlighting the absurdity of Romney’s plan to <i>increase</i> defense spending—presumably (although the ad doesn’t say this) so that we’ll be prepared when Romney clumsily gets us into an unnecessary war.  (Current candidates as enemies: Britain and the Palestinians, in addition to Iran.)  The ad is excellent.  But it would be even better if it mentioned that Romney’s spending plan doesn’t even <i>purport</i>to be tied to defense <i>needs</i>, but instead to, um, GDP.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>It really should point this out and should note the only possible explanation for that.  So should Obama himself.</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/08/romneys-weird-plan-to-decouple-military-spending-from-national-security-needs-and-to-tie-it-instead-to-gdp.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
