<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Linda Greenhouse &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Anthony Kennedy and Antonin Scalia Say the Confederacy Won the Civil War and the Purpose of the Reconstruction Amendments Was to Reinforce Rather Than Diminish State Sovereignty. (Except on Affirmative Action, the Second Amendment, and Real Estate Property “Takings.”)</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/anthony-kennedy-and-antonin-scalia-say-the-confederacy-won-the-civil-war-and-the-purpose-of-the-reconstruction-amendments-was-to-reinforce-rather-than-diminish-state-sovereignty-except-on-affirmativ.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/anthony-kennedy-and-antonin-scalia-say-the-confederacy-won-the-civil-war-and-the-purpose-of-the-reconstruction-amendments-was-to-reinforce-rather-than-diminish-state-sovereignty-except-on-affirmativ.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2013 20:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[affirmative action]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ala. v. Holder]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Anthony Kennedy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Antonin Scalia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linda Greenhouse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The New York Times]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Supreme Court]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Voting Rights Act of 1965; Fisher v. University of Texas; Shelby County]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/anthony-kennedy-and-antonin-scalia-say-the-confederacy-won-the-civil-war-and-the-purpose-of-the-reconstruction-amendments-was-to-reinforce-rather-than-diminish-state-sovereignty-except-on-affirmativ.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Leaving race aside for the moment (did someone mention that the Voting Rights Act has something to do with empowering black voters – who just might, for some strange reason, prefer Democrats?), what the court’s conservatives seem to see in Section 5 is a threat to state sovereignty — the “sovereign dignity” of the states, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">Leaving race aside for the moment (did someone mention that the Voting Rights Act has something to do with empowering black voters – who just might, for some strange reason, prefer Democrats?), what the court’s conservatives seem to see in Section 5 is a threat to state sovereignty — the “sovereign dignity” of the states, a phrase Justice Anthony M. Kennedy has used in another federalism context. This theme ran throughout the argument. Justice Scalia referred to Section 5 as imposing “these extraordinary procedures that deny the states sovereign powers which the Constitution preserves to them.” Justice Kennedy asked whether “if Alabama wants to acknowledge the wrongs of its past, is it better off doing that if it’s an independent sovereign or if it’s under the trusteeship of the United States government?”</p>
</div>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/03/06/a-big-new-power/">A Big New Power</a>, Linda Greenhouse, The New York Times, today, discussing the Feb. 26 argument at the Supreme Court in a case challenging the continuing constitutionality of the Voting Rights Act</div>
<p>Just so you know, the main Reconstruction Amendment at issue in Shelby County, Ala. v. Holder, the Voting Rights Act case&#8211;the 15th Amendment&#8211;provides in full:</p>
<div dir="ltr">Section. 1. The right of citizens of the United States to vote shall not be denied or abridged by the United States or by any State on account of race, color, or previous condition of servitude.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Section. 2. The Congress shall have power to enforce this article by appropriate legislation.</div>
<p>That language in Section 2, giving Congress the “power to enforce this article by appropriate legislation,” is standard Constitutional Amendment language.  It appears also in the other Reconstruction Amendment at issue in Shelby County&#8211;the 14th Amendment&#8211;a five-section amendment, the two relevant ones which read:</p>
<div dir="ltr">Section. 1. All persons born or naturalized in the United States and subject to the jurisdiction thereof, are citizens of the United States and of the State wherein they reside. No State shall make or enforce any law which shall abridge the privileges or immunities of citizens of the United States; nor shall any State deprive any person of life, liberty, or property, without due process of law; nor deny to any person within its jurisdiction the equal protection of the laws.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Section. 5. The Congress shall have power to enforce, by appropriate legislation, the provisions of this article.</div>
<p>Section 1, but not Section 5, also, as it happens, is at issue in the other culture-wars blockbuster Supreme Court case this term, Fisher v. The University of Texas, a.k.a., the big affirmative-action-in-state-university-admissions-policy case.  </p>
<p>John Roberts will write the 5-4 opinions in both cases.  In Fisher, he and Kennedy will agree that the Union won the Civil War, and that the three Reconstruction Amendments&#8211;the third one, the 13th Amendment, actually being the first of the three; it abolished slavery&#8211;did not, after all, flip the Supremacy Clause in Article VI, Clause 2.  It said (and the 5-4 Court majority will confirm in Fisher) still says:</p>
<div dir="ltr">This Constitution, and the Laws of the United States which shall be made in pursuance thereof; and all treaties made, or which shall be made, under the authority of the United States, shall be the supreme law of the land; and the judges in every state shall be bound thereby, anything in the constitution or laws of any state to the contrary notwithstanding. </div>
<p>But Fisher was argued early in the Court’s term, in October, and probably will be decided before Shelby County. <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/03/john-roberts-curious-voting-statistics.html">So Roberts</a> &#038; Kennedy &#038; Co. will be able to clarify very quickly that&#8211;as Kennedy, Thomas and the others routinely and unselfconsciously, and without explanation&#8211;say, states are sovereigns.  Not that states have some but not all the attributes of sovereigns; no, that states are sovereigns.  And so, the Supremacy Clause notwithstanding, states need not comply with federal constitutional or statutory law.  Except, of course, on issues important to 1980s-90s Republican White House, Justice Department and judicial appointees.  </p>
<p>These folks have a list, and they are checking off each item on it, even when that means that in the very same Court term they’ll casually flip the Supremacy Clause back and forth. As it will this term.  Christmas will come in May and June this year.  Or at least Santa Claus will.</p>
<p>Federal trusteeships of states are, it will become clear by the end of this Court term, constitutional only when the trusteeship is of a state, such as Texas, whose legislature enacts a statute that butts up against a 1980s-’90s-era rightwing cause célèbre&#8211;a bullet point on the list.  Federal trusteeships of states are clearly unconstitutional, however, when the trusteeship is explicitly authorized in the Constitution itself, as it is in Section 2 of the 15th Amendment, but the explicit authorization is itself on the list.  That’s because, then, it turns out, that despite appearances&#8211;i.e., the language in the Amendment itself&#8211;the purpose of the 15th Amendment was not to make the states’ racial-minority citizens better off vis-à-vis the states, but apparently, as matter of historical fact, the opposite.  </p>
<p>Who knew?  Other than the Republican far-right, that is?  </p>
<p>Not me, and probably not you.  You probably learned, incorrectly, back in U.S. History class that the Reconstruction Amendments were added after the Civil War in order to make the states’ racial minorities better off vis-à-vis the states.  But, then again, you also probably learned that the Confederacy lost the Civil War.  Even those of you who went to upscale suburban schools or to fancy private ones.  Well, those of you who took that class pre-1980s, anyway.  But we’ll soon be disabused of that misconception, in a high-profile Supreme Court 5-4 opinion that will be simply the denouement of a decades-long juggernaut by a bizarre cadre of legal wingnuts who have gained a stranglehold on the American judicial system to deny that the Confederacy did not win the Civil War.  </p>
<p>Sort of like the Tea Party congressional delegation’s decision to deny the result of last November’s election, but with no near-term reversal possible in 2014.  Only an unexpected vacancy on the Court will do that.  </p>
<p>Meanwhile, if Alabama wants to acknowledge the wrongs of its past, it will be better off doing that if it’s an independent sovereign rather than if it’s under the trusteeship of the United States government.  Which is good, since Alabama surely will want to acknowledge the wrongs of its past.  (Assuming, of course, that constitutional wrongs were committed in the past, which in this case presumes facts not in evidence at the Supreme Court on the day of the argument in <i>Shelby County</i>.  Including the fact that that Section 1 of the 15th Amendment eliminated the concept that <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/02/racial-entitlements-such-as-right-to.html">the right to vote is a racial entitlement</a>.)  I suggest a statue.  And as an independent sovereign, which “it”&#8211;the intended beneficiary of the 15th Amendment&#8211;is better off as, Alabama might decide to erect one.  
<div></div>
<div>But these extraordinary procedures that deny the states sovereign powers which the Constitution preserves to them apply only to extraordinary procedures enacted by Congress. They do not apply to extraordinary procedures in the Supreme Court.  Such as the one in which the Reconstruction Amendments are rewritten, right along with Civil War and Reconstruction-era history.  </div>
<div></div>
<div>I do have a suggestion for Texas, though, just as I have one for Alabama, since, when Texas, like Alabama, wants to acknowledge the wrongs of its past, it will be better off doing that if it’s an independent sovereign rather than if it’s under the trusteeship of the United States government.  </div>
<div>Again here, I suggest a statue&#8211;this one honoring all the white Texas high school seniors who narrowly missed the cut to gain admission to their state’s flagship university since the current state statute and its predecessor statute were enacted.  </p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/anthony-kennedy-and-antonin-scalia-say-the-confederacy-won-the-civil-war-and-the-purpose-of-the-reconstruction-amendments-was-to-reinforce-rather-than-diminish-state-sovereignty-except-on-affirmativ.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>John Roberts and Elena Kagan: Mirror Images of Each Other</title>
		<link>./../../2012/06/john-roberts-and-elena-kagan-mirror-images-of-each-other.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/06/john-roberts-and-elena-kagan-mirror-images-of-each-other.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2012 14:16:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[ACA litigation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Elena Kagan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jeff Shesol]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Roberts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ken Houghton]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linda Greenhouse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obamacare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/06/john-roberts-and-elena-kagan-mirror-images-of-each-other.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The second biggest surprise of the day, after the survival of the Affordable Care Act, is that we’ve never really gotten over our collective crush on John Roberts. How else to explain today’s outpouring of praise, not merely for the decision but for the man himself, for his statesmanship and judicial modesty? All these years, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>The second biggest surprise of the day, after the survival of the Affordable Care Act, is that we’ve never really gotten over our collective crush on John Roberts. How else to explain today’s outpouring of praise, not merely for the decision but for the man himself, for his statesmanship and judicial modesty? All these years, it now appears, we’ve held it in our hearts; we’ve written it in our diaries, remembering every one of those sweet nothings he once whispered about “common ground” and “humility.” No, we never really gave up on Roberts. Not during that long judicial bender he took with the boys—Nino, Clarence, Tony, and Sam; not during the <em>Citizens United</em> argument, when he called the government “big brother”; not when he swept away a century’s worth of campaign finance regulations. So complete is our swoon, in the afterglow of the ACA ruling, that <a href="http://www.thedailybeast.com/articles/2012/06/28/obamacare-supreme-court-ruling-john-roberts-changes-his-legacy.html" target="_blank">Bob Shrum has written</a> that if Roberts had been Chief Justice in 2000, <em>Bush v. Gore</em> might have gone the other way.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212; <a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/jurisprudence/2012/06/john_roberts_is_hardly_the_hero_and_judicial_statesman_people_make_him_out_to_be_.html#comments">John Roberts Is No Hero: Why ourcrush on the chief justice is silly—and undeserved</a>, Jeff Shesol, Slate, Jun. 28
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>To which I posted the following comment:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I write on legal and political issue issues for a left-of-center blog and have indicated there that I detest and really fear John Roberts because of his deeply diabolical nature and his checklist of ‘80s-era Federalist Society things-to-do.   Linda Greenhouse has written several columns, two or three of them within the last few months, highlighting those two quintessential John Roberts traits.  But Greenhouse, and I, predicted that Roberts would save the ACA because the case is so high-profile and the grounds for striking down the statute so utterly artificial that it would place more public scrutiny on the types of things he and his cadre normally get away with with virtually no public awareness.  I don’t think he did what he did out of a sense of statesmanship, nor in order to gut the Commerce Clause; I think the Commerce Clause ruling will have almost no practical effect, and he could have done the same thing with it simply by joining the other four conservatives in a 5-4 ruling striking down the ACA. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I think he’s, in a way, the mirror image of Elena Kagan, who in high-profile cases usually votes liberal but who, best as I can tell, almost never goes out on a limb for the “nobody” “cert” petitioner and actually fights to get a “cert grant,” as Sotomayor does, and who I’d bet doesn’t even vote very often to hear such cases.  Her priorities seem to be her own public image and being buddies with the “in” crowd on the Court, whereas Roberts’ priority is making as many dramatic changes to the law as he can, but doing so as much under the public’s radar as possible.  (I also think Kagan is a bit naïve on some issues because of her unfamiliarity with them—see, e.g.: federal habeas review of state-court convictions—and fairly easily snowed.)
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>So I agree with Ken Houghton in his post below that John Roberts is not the friend of progressives.  I disagree with Ken, though, that Roberts has set up some trap through which he will later orchestrate the striking down of the ACA as a violation of equal protection because of the way in which the Medicaid expansion is administered (if I understand Ken correctly) is nil.  Roberts ended his opinion with a statement saying that the proper manner in which to determine the ultimate fate of the ACA is through the political process, not the judicial process—and I think he means it.  There are two parts of Roberts’ opinion—the part concerning Congress’s regulatory powers under the Commerce Clause and the part concerning Congress’s power to enact federal-state partnership legislation <i>a la </i>Medicaid—that raise serious concerns about the impact on <i>other</i>legislation.  I wrote separate posts yesterday about each of these, and I’ll be writing another one on Medicaid issue later today. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>But any lawsuits concerning some aspect of how the law is working in practice, once it gets underway, would result in the possible tweaking of an HHS regulation or in the manner in which a particular state is implementing the Act, but I just don’t foresee a successful attack on the constitutionality of some provision in the Act itself. 
</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/06/john-roberts-and-elena-kagan-mirror-images-of-each-other.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Linda Greenhouse’s ACA-Litigation-Outcome Tea-Leave Reading (And Why I Think She’s Right)</title>
		<link>./../../2012/06/linda-greenhouses-aca-litigation-outcome-tea-leave-reading-and-why-i-think-shes-right.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/06/linda-greenhouses-aca-litigation-outcome-tea-leave-reading-and-why-i-think-shes-right.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Jun 2012 19:14:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Einer Elhauge]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linda Greenhouse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New York Times]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obamacare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Supreme court]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the ACA]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/06/linda-greenhouses-aca-litigation-outcome-tea-leave-reading-and-why-i-think-shes-right.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In an email exchange between Dan and me on Tuesday, I wrote: Btw, the Supreme Court has been amazingly slow this term in issuing opinions in high-profile cases.  Most of the opinions they’ve issued recently are on pretty esoteric issues; they’re important, but pretty inside-baseball.  A good example is an opinion they issued yesterday.  Here’s [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div></div>
<div>In an email exchange between Dan and me on Tuesday, I wrote:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Btw, the Supreme Court has been amazingly slow this term in issuing opinions in high-profile cases.  Most of the opinions they’ve issued recently are on pretty esoteric issues; they’re important, but pretty inside-baseball.  A good example is an opinion they issued yesterday.  Here’s a great article on it at SCOTUSblog….  If you read it, I think you’ll see what I mean by esoteric and inside-baseball.  I do have to say—as the author of the article does—that Alito’s dissent is spot-on.  And, as the author says, it’s downright baffling that five justices signed on to Thomas’s wacky opinion.  The article indicates that Thomas apparently flipped Scalia after the oral argument.  Scalia had it right the first time.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>In <a href="http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/06/13/when-enough-is-enough/?hp&#038;gwh=AE467B2FA4F6F36F262DF6A64F9CCD88">an op-ed piece yesterday</a> in the New York Times, Linda Greenhouse, that paper’s longtime Supreme Court correspondent, who retired three or four years ago but still writes two or three op-ed commentaries a month there, mentioned the Court’s slow pace in issuing its “big” opinions this term.  Then she discusses an opinion that the Court issued on June 4 that, like most Supreme Court opinions, got little attention in the mainstream press but is nonetheless important. </div>
<div>
</div>
<p><a name="more"></a>
<div>Most Supreme Court opinions decide “procedural,” “jurisdictional” or “standard-of-judicial-review” questions, which sometimes involve constitutional questions, often under the guise of statutory-interpretation ones.  Often, the court treats these cases as though they present only issues of interpretation of a federal statute and pretend that the case does not implicate constitutional law even if really does.  But the case Greenhouse discussed, <i>Amour v. City of Indianapolis</i>, was squarely a constitutional-law case involving the Fourteen Amendment’s equal protection clause, and did not involve a federal statute but instead a Supreme Court-created standard of judicial review of the constitutionality of a government policy or law that has the effect of discriminating against some class of people. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Under the Court’s longtime equal-protection jurisprudence, the law is more tolerant of certain types of government discrimination than of other types of discrimination.  Laws or policies whose purpose is purely fiscal are among the types of government actions entitled to the most tolerant, or most “deferential,” level of judicial “scrutiny.”  Courts are not entitled to bar those laws or policies as violative of the equal protection clause unless there is no conceivable legally legitimate “rational basis” for the discrimination.   Greenhouse observes (as most liberal court watchers have recognized) that the conservative justices select out a few favorite conservative causes—most notably, the cause of George W. Bush becoming president instead of Al Gore, but also challenges to government affirmative action programs, and issues concerning religious speech in public schools (which Greenhouse doesn’t mention), and property-rights and tax cases—in which to champion the right of equal protection, while otherwise normally accepting virtually any stated basis for government discrimination as a sufficiently rational one to pass constitutional muster.  Of these conservative-favored types of cases, the deferential “rational basis”—i.e., almost anything goes—standard is applied only to the property and tax-type cases.  Conservative legal-movement types <i>hate</i>that it is.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div><i>Armour</i>concerned a sewer improvement assessment in an Indianapolis subdivision.  Greenhouse summarizes:</div>
<p>
<div>The city gave the 180 property owners affected a choice of how to pay the $9,278 assessment: in a lump sum, or over time with interest. Most chose to pay over 10, 20 or 30 years. Three dozen paid up front, and the city then played them for suckers, announcing a year later that it was changing the way it financed sewer improvements and would issue bonds to cover most of the cost. It would forgive the indebtedness of the installment-payers. But the city refused to give the full-payers any of the refund they demanded.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The full-payers sued for a refund of all but the first year’s pro-rated assessment.  In a 6-3 opinion written by Breyer, the majority accepted as a sufficiently legitimate rational basis the city’s claim that the refund process would be difficult administratively and that the city then also would probably have to make similar refunds in other parts of the city.  Roberts wrote a strong dissent, but, as Greenhouse points out, it was fact-based rather than an attempt to change the law itself.  Roberts, joined by Scalia and Alito, said that the city’s proffered basis was not sufficiently legitimate under the rational-basis to pass equal protection muster.  But he did not advocate a change in equal protection legal doctrine itself; he did not suggest that the Court should abandon the rational-basis test for property-rights and other fiscal cases.  And Kennedy joined Breyer’s majority opinion.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Which Greenhouse interprets as potentially indicative of the outcome of the Affordable Care Act case.  I do too, although I’d already concluded more than two months ago that Roberts and Kennedy probably would vote to uphold the individual-mandate provision.  I based that in part on <a href="http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/04/04/embarrass-the-future/">an earlier Greenhouse op-ed</a> in the Times, in which she discussed a comment by Kennedy late in the oral argument on the challenge to the individual mandate, and a comment by Roberts.  Neither comment had gotten much attention in the press coverage immediately following the argument (and I hadn’t read the lengthy transcript of the argument).  I also concluded once the dust had settled two or three weeks after the argument, and I’d read many articles and commentaries about it, that the majority might tacitly and effectively uphold the mandate’s constitutionality, by not formally making that ruling at this time but making it clear that eventually they will.  I still think that’s a possibility, but one that, because of recent historical findings by a Harvard professor published a few weeks after the argument, is less likely now. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>In several posts on AB beginning about a year ago, I argued that the challengers’ Commerce Clause argument—that in enacting the ACA, Congress’ exceed its power under the Commerce Clause—was really a disguised Fifth Amendment “substantive due process” argument (liberty! freedom!), not a Commerce Clause argument at all.  Under the Supreme Court’s Commerce Clause jurisprudence, beginning in the mid-1930s with cases challenging the constitutionality of some of the New Deal legislation, and including a high-profile opinion issued in 2005, the ACA appears comfortably within the authority of Congress’s Commerce power.  It was that darned liberty thing that really was at issue: the slippery slope to Congress’s requiring the purchase of broccoli.   That is, this is a Fifth Amendment substantive due process argument, not a Commerce Clause argument.  As I pointed out, the “freedom” issue would be the same whether Congress achieved the end through it Commerce power or instead through its taxing power. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And, in fact, the ACA’s enforcement mechanism—the penalty for not obtaining medical insurance arguably is a tax.  And since that’s the only enforcement mechanism—there is no provision for arrest and imprisonment, for example—the taxing power would suffice.  But that still would leave the issue of freedom! liberty!  And that slippery slope to broccoli-purchase mandates.  Unless, of course, the ACA mandate is no different, in a liberty! freedom! sense, whether enacted through the Commerce power or instead through the taxing power, than, say, Medicare and Social Security, but that a broccoli mandate, whether enacted through the Commerce power or instead through the taxing power is very different, and <i>would</i> be a violation of Fifth Amendment substantive due process (personal choice, liberty). 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Shortly after I wrote my first AB post making this argument, the first of two appellate-court opinions upholding the law under a virtually identical analysis was issued, both of them written by conservative-movement leading lights.  In the second of the two, issued last August, another leading-light movement-conservative judge dissented, but only from the determination that the law was within Congress’s Commerce Clause power, not from the conclusion that the law unconstitutionality infringed upon individual liberty.  That judge said that had Congress tweaked the statute even just slightly, enacting through the taxing power rather than through the commerce-regulating power, running the mandated insurance purchase through the government, the statute would be constitutional, both in that Congress would have the authority to enact it and that the mandate would not violate constitutional precepts of individual liberty.  And it turns out that the lawyer for the statute’s challengers agrees, as (apparently) does either Kennedy or Roberts (I can’t remember which).  And probably both do.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>It was a third appellate case that the Supreme Court agreed to hear.  In that case, the Obama administration originally argued that the ACA’s penalty provisions was a tax, that the ACA was enacted under both the Commerce power and the taxing power—and that under a federal “jurisdictional” statute known as the Tax Anti-Injunction Act, which bars the courts from hearing a constitutional challenge to a federal taxing statute until after the tax is due, the courts lacked “jurisdiction” (legal authority) to consider the constitutional challenge at all until April 2015, when the first penalties under the ACA would be due.  But when that case on appeal, the administration reversed its position and said the penalty was, well, just a penalty, not a tax, and that the ACA was enacted solely under Congress’s Commerce power.  If so, the courts could hear the challenges to the Act.  That appellate court agreed, and in a split opinion held the mandate provision unconstitutional under what the majority said was a finding that Congress exceeded its Commerce power authority but what, the language of the opinion made clear, was really a finding that the mandate violated Fifth Amendment due process, or individual liberty, rights.  This, although the opinion didn’t mention the Fifth Amendment or due process.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>When the Supreme Court agreed to hear that case, it decided to hear as a threshold issue, although neither side had asked it to do so, whether the penalty is really a tax and therefore its constitutionality cannot be decided until 2015.  That issue was argued on the first of the three days of argument.  The next day, late in the argument on the mandate issue, Kennedy or Roberts asked the lawyer for the challengers whether an insurance mandate enacted under Congress’s taxing power would be constitutional—that is, whether Congress not only had the authority to enact such a mandate through the taxing power but also whether such a mandate would be constitutional; in other words, whether it wouldn’t violate a due process liberty right and lead to the possible forced purchase of broccoli. The lawyer said Congress could enact such a mandate through its taxing power, and apparently the justices didn’t dispute this. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>So if a majority of the Court concludes that the mandate penalty is a tax, they can postpone an actual ruling on its constitutionality until after April 2015, while  strongly suggesting in its opinion this month that the mandate and its enforcement-mechanism penalty do not unconstitutionally violate individual liberty. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>But I don’t think they’ll do that.  In an article titled “<a href="http://www.tnr.com/article/politics/102620/individual-mandate-history-affordable-care-act">IfHealth Insurance Mandates Are Unconstitutional, Why Did the Founding FathersBack Them?</a>”, published in the New Republic in mid-April (three weeks after the Supreme Court arguments), Harvard law professor Einer Elhauge pointed out that on two occasions in this country’s earliest days, Congress, whose members the included several drafters of the Constitution, enacted statutes mandating that certain citizens purchase a private product.  In one instance the product was guns, in the service of a creating a citizens’ militia.  In the other instance, the product was medical insurance, which ship owners were required to buy for their seamen, enacted apparently under Congress’s Commerce power.  Neither law was thought to violate constitutional concepts of individual liberty.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Which creates sort of an obstacle for the conservative “originalist” justices.  And which causes me to think that a majority will uphold the mandate as authorized under the Commerce power and that the penalty is, after all, not a tax but instead just a penalty.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Which in turn causes me to disclaim my prediction before I’m even proven wrong.  After all, this type of prediction is worth the cost of the paper it’s not even written on. If that.
</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/06/linda-greenhouses-aca-litigation-outcome-tea-leave-reading-and-why-i-think-shes-right.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Showtime At The Supreme Court</title>
		<link>./../../2012/03/showtime-at-the-supreme-court.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/03/showtime-at-the-supreme-court.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 25 Mar 2012 00:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[ACA litigation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Beverly Mann]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dahlia Lithwick]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linda Greenhouse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obamacare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Supreme court]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/03/showtime-at-the-supreme-court.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Dan emailed me several days ago asking whether I thought I should write a preshow (my word, not his) post about next week’s marathon Supreme Court oral arguments on the constitutionality of Obamacare, a.k.a., the Affordable Care Act.  Six hours of argument, two each day, Monday through Wednesday, in which the Court will hear argument, first, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>Dan emailed me several days ago asking whether I thought I should write a preshow (my word, not his) post about next week’s marathon Supreme Court oral arguments on the constitutionality of Obamacare, a.k.a., the Affordable Care Act.  Six hours of argument, two each day, Monday through Wednesday, in which the Court will hear argument, first, on whether the courts even have “jurisdiction” (the legal authority) to even consider the challenges to the Act’s constitutionality before the challenged provisions of the Act have gone into effect, and, then, on the challenges to separate parts of the Act by various challengers who will be directly affected by the respective provision. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>It promises to be a long three days.  And by the time Dan emailed me, I already was sick of reading previews.  I wrote back to Dan:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I don’t think there’s anything to say, really, at this point.  There’ve been a zillion articles/commentaries about it within the last week or so, but they don’t really say anything.  Mostly they just kind of speculate about how Roberts, Scalia and Kennedy might vote, based on things like what Scalia wrote in a concurring opinion in a Commerce Clause case a few years ago (Scalia expressed an “expansive” view of Congress’s Commerce Clause powers), and how Roberts wants to be remembered. It’s obligatory writing for people like Adam Liptak, the NYT Supreme Court correspondent, but pretty pointless, really.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>But two articles published on Thursday, one by former (longtime) New York Times Supreme Court correspondent Linda Greenhouse, who in retirement writes a periodic commentary column in the Times, and Slate Supreme Court and general-legal-issues writer Dahlia Lithwick, are, I think, worth reading. </p>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />Greenhouse’s is titled “<a href="http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/03/21/never-before/">Never Before</a>,” and the thrust of her article is that those two words—“never before”—are the sum and the (non)legal substance of the challengers’ arguments.  “Unprecedented,” she notes, “is a description, not an analysis.”  Or a legal argument.  It is instead merely a political argument.  And transparently so, which is why she predicts that the Court will uphold the statute, by a comfortable margin. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Well, actually, she predicts that the Court will uphold the statute by a comfortable margin because, well, for all the incessant hype, this is not, under extensive and pretty darn clear Supreme Court precedent relevant to each of the separate stated constitutional grounds argued, a close case at all—and because John Roberts cares a lot about how the Court is perceived during his tenure as its chief. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Or, more accurately, at least in my opinion, because under Supreme Court precedent this is not a close case and  this is too high-profile a case for its outcome not to impact the public’s perception of the Court.  By which I mean, and I think she means, that while Roberts &#038; Co. regularly make out like bandits in the night, hijacking the law and transforming it into reflection of a 1980s <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federalist_Society">Federalist Society </a>checklist, they do so only to the extent to which they expect that they can escape widespread public revulsion.  Which in turn is determined by the extent to which the news media actually focuses on these ideological-agenda rulings <i>before</i> the Court issues the ruling.  </p>
<p>That, after all, is how we got <i>Citizens United v. FEC</i>.  Roberts &#038; Co. misjudged.  Oops.  Well, for heaven’s sake … I mean … y’know … who knew that the public would, um, actually <i>get</i> the <i>Citizens United</i> ruling?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Lithwick’s <a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/jurisprudence/2012/03/the_supreme_court_is_more_concerned_with_the_politics_of_the_health_care_debate_than_the_law_.single.html">article </a>makes much the same point as Greenhouse’s—that as a matter of law, this is not a close case—but with a slight twist.  After giving a nod of recognition to the Greenhouse , which was published in that morning’s paper, Lithwick says that while she expects that the Court will uphold the statute, she’s not all that sure.  As a legal matter, she says, this case is not the case of the century nor of the decade nor even of this term.  Unless, of course, a 5-4 majority surprises almost all the legal commentators who actually know the law and follow the Court.   
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Which, she says, wouldn’t surprise her all that much, because the case is not really about the law at all, but instead about “optics, politics, and public opinion.”  But ultimately, she thinks, Roberts and one or two of the others just won’t think this case is worth the cost in public opinion. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I agree.  It’s not as if they get to pick a president in this one.  There are, as Lithwick notes, other cases in their pipeline that could well do that. The oral arguments in those cases are, like the arguments next week, likely to be mere shows.  But with a more limited-release audience and opposite results.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/03/showtime-at-the-supreme-court.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
