<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Ron Paul &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Ron Paul Challenges Liberals &#8211; or Maybe Not</title>
		<link>./../../2012/01/ron-paul-challenges-liberals-or-maybe-not.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/01/ron-paul-challenges-liberals-or-maybe-not.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2012 17:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[jazzbumpa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[libertarian]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[pseudoliberals]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ron Paul]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/01/ron-paul-challenges-liberals-or-maybe-not.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Matt Stoller, the former Senior Policy Advisor to Rep. Alan Grayson and a fellow at the Roosevelt Institute has a couple of very interesting articles posted at Naked Capitalism,  Why Ron Paul Challenges Liberals, and the follow-up, Naked Capitalism, “A Home for All Sorts of Bircher Nonsense” These are thought-provoking, in many ways insightful, and [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Matt Stoller, the former Senior Policy Advisor to Rep. Alan Grayson  and a fellow at the Roosevelt Institute has a couple of very interesting  articles posted at Naked Capitalism,  <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2011/12/matt-stoller-why-ron-paul-challenges-liberals.html">Why Ron Paul Challenges Liberals</a>, and the follow-up, <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/01/naked-capitalism-a-home-for-all-sorts-of-bircher-nonsense.html">Naked Capitalism, “A Home for All Sorts of Bircher Nonsense”</a></p>
<p>These  are thought-provoking, in many ways insightful, and strike me as  required reading, for a variety of reasons, including some valuable  historical insights.  However, one thought they provoke from me is that  the main thesis is spectacularly wrong-headed.  Stollar talks about what  a great ally Paul&#8217;s staff was, when working on certain issues.  I  should say, &#8220;when working <i>against</i> certain issues&#8221; or  things, like war and the unfettered evil workings of the Federal  Reserve.  The correct vocabulary is worth emphasizing.  Liberals and  Libertarians may find common ground in what they are against, but it is  quite unlikely that they will ever find anything substantial that they  both are for.</p>
<p>Stollar goes on to point out what he calls &#8220;<i>a big problem</i>&#8221;  with liberalism.  This is the mixture of two elements, support for  federal power and the anti-war sentiment that arose with Viet Nam and  has continued though today.  In the same paragraph, Stollar says, &#8220;<i>Liberalism doesn’t really exist much within the Democratic Party so much anymore.</i>&#8221;   This is an important thought, but he doesn&#8217;t pursue it, and as he goes  on seems to conflate Democrats with Liberals, as suits his convenience.   In the final paragraph of the first post he refers to: &#8220;<i>a completely hollow liberal intellectual apparatus arguing for  increasing the power of corporations through the Federal government to  enact their agenda.</i>&#8221;  Seriously, WTF?  I have absolutely no idea what the hell that is supposed to mean.</p>
<p>The second article is especially weak, and essentially devoid of any intellectual content.  Stollar decides to &#8220;<i>highlight a few of the reactions here without much of a rebuttal.</i>&#8221;   Why would anyone do that?  Does he believe the reactions are  self-refuting?   Is he too lazy to rebut, or does he simply not have a  good rebuttal?<br /><a name="more"></a><br />At least he clearly sets forth the thesis of the first article:  &#8220;<i>that the same financing structures that are used to  finance mass industrial warfare were used to create a liberal national  economy and social safety.</i>&#8221;   Here is the source of Stollar&#8217;s  alleged intra-liberal conflict, that Paul is somehow supposed to  illuminate and inform.  Though Stollar says: &#8220;<i>I’ll be describing in much more detail the shifting of the social  contract underlying this failure, which has nothing to do with Ron Paul  and would exist with or without him</i>.&#8221;  So referencing Paul in the first place was a bit of a red herring.</p>
<p>He then goes on to provide extended quotes from posts by <a href="http://digbysblog.blogspot.com/2012/01/no-stoller-and-sullivan-there-is-no.html">David Atkins</a>, who he describes as &#8220;<i>wrestling with what liberalism is</i>&#8221; and <a href="http://digbysblog.blogspot.com/2012/01/on-coherent-liberalism.html">Digby</a>, who he simply rejects out of hand, though with a lot of words that don&#8217;t quite reach the level of snark</p>
<p>What Stollar describes as &#8220;<i>contradictions within modern liberalism</i>&#8221;   boils down to liberalism needing big government to be interventionist,  as Atkins demonstrates, but not imperialistic.  But this is a totally  coherent position. The problem lies not with progressive liberalism, but  with the practical realities of managing a power system &#8211; which is what  governemnt is &#8211; in a way that advances the common good, while holding  the drive for imperialistic and domestic domination in check.  This is  going to be a central practical problem with any governing system or  political philosophy &#8211; at least for one that takes seriously the idea of  advancing the common good.  To say it is the problem of liberalism is  to ignore human nature, political reality, and the entirety of history.</p>
<p>Thus,  a liberal can hold the positions that American involvement in WW II was  necessary, but that our involvement in Viet Nam was not.  Ditto Kosovo,  vis-a-vis Iraq.   One can also recognize that the only entity with  enough heft to balance the power of trans-national mega-corporations is  government, but Stollar does not choose to give that any consideration.</p>
<p>Stollar concludes: &#8220;<i>As the New Deal era model sheds the last trappings of anything  resembling social justice or equity for what used to be called the  middle class (a process which Tom Ferguson has been relentlessly  documenting since the early 1980s), the breakdown will become impossible  to ignore.  You can already see how flimsy the arguments are, from the  partisans.</i>&#8220;</p>
<p>I don&#8217;t know how one gets from the  systematic dismantling of the New Deal by successive Republican  administrations (and you can include both Clinton and Obama in this  list) to the New Deal model shedding anything at all.  And, no, I can&#8217;t  see how flimsy liberal partisan arguments have anything to do with an  assault on the middle class that has taken place from the right.</p>
<p>Stollar  has constructed a straw man problem.  Which is a shame, since there are  real problems to be dealt with.  One is the growth of right wing  populism, as exemplified by the Tea Party &#8211; at least to the extent that  is is real, and not a Fox News fabrication.  Another is to harness the  energy of the Occupy Movements, which provide some evidence that there  is progressive populism that could be a source of real political  strength.  Most critically, though, as things stand now, there is no  political left in this country with any actual power.  </p>
<p><a href="http://coreyrobin.com/2012/01/03/ron-paul-has-two-problems-one-is-his-the-other-is-ours/">Corey Robin describes</a> the central problem of American liberalism in the 21st Century, and closes the loop back to Stollar&#8217;s Ron Paul idea like this.</p>
<div><i>Our problem—and again by “our” I mean a left that’s social democratic  (or welfare state liberal or economically progressive or whatever the  hell you want to call it) and anti-imperial—is that we don’t really have  a vigorous national spokesperson for the issues of war and peace, an  end to empire, a challenge to Israel, and so forth, that Paul has in  fact been articulating.  The source of Paul’s positions on these issues  are not the same as ours (again more reason not to give him our  support).  But he is talking about these issues, often in surprisingly  blunt and challenging terms. Would that we had someone on our side who  could make the case against an American empire, or American supremacy,  in such a pungent way.</i></div>
<p>Digging a level  deeper, the reason we don&#8217;t have such a spokesperson is that our  political system is essentially owned by corporate interests, which is  why we get alleged liberals like Clinton and Obama in Democratic  leadership, while genuine progressives like Bernie Sanders, Dennis  Kucinich, and even Alan Grayson are marginalized.  On top of this, the  right has a vigorous and powerful propaganda machine &#8211; hence the Tea  Party; and the small number of progressive voices in broadcast media is  nowhere close to providing a balance.</p>
<p>Money owns  politics, and corporate interests, along with a small entrenched elite,  own the vast majority of the money.  The key to achieving progressive  solutions is to get the money out of politics.  But in the wake of  Citizens United, that prospect is a forlorn hope.  That is my &#8220;<i>coherent structural critique of the American political order</i>&#8221; in one short paragraph.</p>
<p>Cross posted at <a href="http://www.jazzbumpa.blogspot.com/2012/01/ron-paul-challenges-liberals-or-maybe.html">Retirement Blues</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/01/ron-paul-challenges-liberals-or-maybe-not.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
