<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Bradley Manning &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>PJ Crowley Resigns After Remarks Bashing Bradley Manning&#8217;s Detention</title>
		<link>./../../2011/03/pj-crowley-resigns-after-remarks-bashing-bradley-mannings-detention.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/03/pj-crowley-resigns-after-remarks-bashing-bradley-mannings-detention.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2011 15:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Bradley Manning]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/03/pj-crowley-resigns-after-remarks-bashing-bradley-mannings-detention.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The Guardian via Alternet offers this note on the Bradley Manning pre-trial treatment: PJ Crowley Resigns After Remarks Bashing Bradley Manning&#8217;s Detention PJ Crowley, the official spokesman at the state department, has fallen on his sword after calling the treatment of Bradley Manning, the alleged source of the WikiLeaks files, &#8220;counterproductive and stupid&#8221;. The resignation [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/environment">The Guardian</a> via Alternet offers this note on the Bradley Manning pre-trial treatment:</p>
<p><a target="_blank" href="http://www.alternet.org/story/150229/pj_crowley_resigns_after_remarks_bashing_bradley_manning%27s_detention?akid=6653.29972.0PCDLV&#038;rd=1&#038;t=27"><strong>PJ Crowley Resigns After Remarks Bashing Bradley Manning&#8217;s Detention  </strong></a>
<p>PJ Crowley, the official spokesman at the state department, has fallen on his sword after calling the treatment of <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/bradley-manning">Bradley Manning</a>, the alleged source of the <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/media/wikileaks">WikiLeaks</a> files, &#8220;counterproductive and stupid&#8221;.</p>
<p>The resignation followed Crowley&#8217;s <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/mar/11/bradley-manning-clinton-crowley-comments?INTCMP=SRCH">remarks to an MIT seminar last week about Manning&#8217;s treatment in military prison</a>.</p>
<p> <a name="more"></a>
<p>Crowley had said: &#8220;What is being done to Bradley Manning is ridiculous and counterproductive and stupid on the part of the department of defence.&#8221;</p>
<p>The remarks forced President Obama to address for the first time the issue of Manning&#8217;s handling at Quantico marine base in Virginia. Obama defended the way Manning is being treated, saying he had been reassured by the Pentagon that his confinement was appropriate.</p>
<p>In a resignation letter, Crowley said he took full responsibility for his remarks. Though he attacked the leaking of classified information, which he called &#8220;a serious crime under US law&#8221;, he stood by his earlier criticism of the Pentagon.</p>
<p>In words that could cause further difficulty for Obama, Crowley said his comments &#8220;were intended to highlight the broader, even strategic impact of discreet actions undertaken by national security agencies every day and their impact on our global standing and leadership. The exercise of power in today&#8217;s challenging times and relentless media environment must be prudent and consistent with our laws and values.&#8221;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/03/pj-crowley-resigns-after-remarks-bashing-bradley-mannings-detention.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
