<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>a balanced-budget amendment &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The National Review Invites Obama to Nip the Call-For-A-Balanced-Budget-Amendment Gimmickry In the Bud Tomorrow Night. Really.</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/the-national-review-invites-obama-to-nip-the-call-for-a-balanced-budget-amendment-gimmickry-in-the-bud-tomorrow-night-really.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/the-national-review-invites-obama-to-nip-the-call-for-a-balanced-budget-amendment-gimmickry-in-the-bud-tomorrow-night-really.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2013 21:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[a balanced-budget amendment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Greg Sargent]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Boehner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Cornyn]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitch McConnell]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The National Review]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the State of the Union address]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/the-national-review-invites-obama-to-nip-the-call-for-a-balanced-budget-amendment-gimmickry-in-the-bud-tomorrow-night-really.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The National Review scoops the Senate GOP’s next move, and note in particular the last paragraph: Frustrated by the months of non-stop budget fights, Senate Republicans are set to mount a fiscal counteroffensive this week with the reintroduction of a balanced-budget amendment. Senate minority leader Mitch McConnell and minority whip John Cornyn are leading the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">The National Review <a href="http://www.nationalreview.com/corner/340317/gop-renews-push-balanced-budget-amendment-robert-costa">scoops the Senate GOP’s next move</a>, and note in particular the last paragraph:</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Frustrated by the months of non-stop budget fights, Senate Republicans are set to mount a fiscal counteroffensive this week with the reintroduction of a balanced-budget amendment.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Senate minority leader Mitch McConnell and minority whip John Cornyn are leading the effort. They hope to unveil a bill by Thursday with unanimous Republican support. [&#8230;]</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">House Republican aides say most conservatives in the lower chamber are going to support the Senate’s plan. Speeches and media appearances are being arranged for later this week. [&#8230;]</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">According to a Senate GOP aide, the legislation would cap federal spending at 18 percent of GDP. It would also require a supermajority for tax hikes and debt-limit increases.</div>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/plum-line/wp/2013/02/11/no-end-to-the-gops-fiscal-gimmickry/?hpid=z3">No end to the GOP’s fiscal gimmickry</a>, Greg Sargent, today</div>
<p>Okay, why would the National Review, or any high-profile non-mainstream source, put this out a day before the State of the Union address, if not to give Obama a chance to mention it, along with an accompanying explanation of how such an amendment would, say, cause recessions to spiral into depressions&#8211;during which time the availability of, say, unemployment compensation would decrease rather than increase, and emergency FEMA funds for, say, the destruction of South Carolina’s coastal region after a major hurricane would have to be offset by cuts in, say, veteran’s benefits or payments to active military personnel? </p>
<p>Any alternative theories about why the National Review did this today?  I can’t think of any.</p>
<p>If Obama doesn’t take this ball, this magnificent gift, and run with it tomorrow&#8211;if he doesn’t expose this crowd for the unremittingly sophomoric gimmick-a-day ignoramuses that they are&#8211;then I’m throwing up my hands.  </p>
<p>The National Review’s editors and staff must be starting to really fear the sequester.  And I’m not saying that facetiously. 
<div></div>
<div>They also must actually recognize the likelihood that last November&#8217;s election results weren&#8217;t a fluke.  A majority of the public even in some seemingly-safely gerrymandered Republican congressional districts and red states with Senate elections next year are not necessarily going to want to hand a box of matches to lunatics and mental adolescents, now that they&#8217;re learning that that&#8217;s what these people are. 
<div></div>
<div></div>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/the-national-review-invites-obama-to-nip-the-call-for-a-balanced-budget-amendment-gimmickry-in-the-bud-tomorrow-night-really.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
