<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>news &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Not riding the luge, just working with guns on campus</title>
		<link>./../../2010/02/not-riding-the-luge-just-working-with-guns-on-campus.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/02/not-riding-the-luge-just-working-with-guns-on-campus.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 13 Feb 2010 01:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[academia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[news]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/02/not-riding-the-luge-just-working-with-guns-on-campus.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[UPDATE III: The Daniel Kaufmann of the Kaufmann Governance Institute lays out the details: This misses another huge challenge altogether, totally absent in the reporting by the New York Times and other main outlets: Amy Bishop had walked into the Faculty meeting, and sat quietly for a long while during its proceedings, with a fully [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>UPDATE III: The Daniel Kaufmann of the Kaufmann Governance Institute <a href="http://thekaufmannpost.net/harvard-educated-professor-kills-faculty-colleagues-second-amendment-from-alabama-and-massachusetts/?utm_source=feedburner&#038;utm_medium=feed&#038;utm_campaign=Feed:+thekaufmannpost+(The+Kaufmann+Governance+Post)&#038;utm_content=Google+Reader">lays out the details</a>:<br />
<blockquote>This misses another huge challenge altogether, totally absent in the reporting by the New York Times and other main outlets:  Amy Bishop had walked into the Faculty meeting, and sat quietly for a long while during its proceedings, with a fully loaded gun…</p>
<p>It is as if such ease of access to guns, and ability to carry them undetected (or detected?), even by high powered scientist professors in university campus, is simply taken for granted nowadays in the U.S.</p></blockquote>
<p>UPDATE II: <a href="http://www.boston.com/news/local/breaking_news/2010/02/professor_accus.html">Everything old is new again</a>.  (h/t <a href="http://twitter.com/GregMitch/statuses/9067059215">Greg Mitchell</a>)</p>
<p>Three <a href="https://www.uah.edu/biology/faculty.html">of these people</a> are, <a href="http://www.detnews.com/article/20100212/NATION/2120453/Woman-held-after-3-die-in-Alabama-university-shooting">according to current reports</a>, dead.</p>
<p>Details <s>to follow elsewhere</s> <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2010/feb/13/three-dead-alabama-university-shooting">from the Guardian</a>:<br />
<blockquote>A biology professor has been charged with murder after a shooting spree at the University of Alabama, Huntsville, left three dead and three wounded.</p>
<p>Amy Bishop, 42, was charged yesterday with one count of capital murder, which means she could face the death penalty if convicted. Three of Bishop&#8217;s fellow biology professors were killed and three other university employees were wounded.</p>
<p>University spokesman Ray Garner said the three killed were Gopi K Podila, the chairman of the Department of Biological Sciences, and two other faculty members, Maria Ragland Davis and Adriel Johnson&#8230;.</p>
<p>AH student Andrew Cole was in Bishop&#8217;s anatomy class yesterday morning and said she seemed perfectly normal.</p>
<p>&#8220;She&#8217;s understanding, and was concerned about students,&#8221; he said. &#8220;I would have never thought it was her.&#8221;</p>
<p>Bishop, a neurobiologist who studied at Harvard University, was taken in handcuffs to the county jail last night and could be heard saying: &#8220;It didn&#8217;t happen. There&#8217;s no way&#8230; They are still alive.&#8221;</p>
<p>Police said they were also interviewing a man as &#8220;a person of interest&#8221;.</p>
<p>Three others were wounded in the gunfire. They were identified as department members Joseph Leahy and Stephanie Monticello, both in a critical condition in intensive care, and Luis Cruz-Vera.</p>
<p>Sammie Lee Davis, whose wife was killed in the shooting, gave a phone interview to the Associated Press in which he said he was told his wife was at a meeting to discuss the tenure of another faculty member who got angry and started shooting. He said his wife had mentioned the suspect before, describing the woman as &#8220;not being able to deal with reality&#8221; and &#8220;not as good as she thought she was&#8221;.</p></blockquote>
<p>Giving new meaning to &#8220;publish or perish.&#8221;  Or, as 2slugbaits noted in comments:<br />
<blockquote>Huntsville always struck me as one of those towns that has a split personality.  A high end BMW on one side of the garage alongside an old Ford F-150 pickup truck with a gun rack and a Confederate flag design on the back window&#8230;.A town that was essentially founded by a Nazi scientist who is praised by deeply religious Pentecostals as a great man without a past worth mentioning.  Huntsville seems to have a strange effect on people.  I have a lot of friends who have moved there and after a few years they are barely recognizable&#8230;.It&#8217;s a peculiar blending of a transient and rootless culture that was grafted onto a deep Old South culture.  That must be how you end up with guys who are PhD rocket scientists during the week and then on Sunday they believe Adam and Eve rode dinosaurs in 4004 BC.  If you&#8217;re an unstable Harvard educated scientist, Huntsville is probably not a good career choice.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/02/not-riding-the-luge-just-working-with-guns-on-campus.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Anerica&#8217;s Finest News Source Explains Glenn Beck Viewers</title>
		<link>./../../2009/11/anericas-finest-news-source-explains-glenn-beck-viewers.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/11/anericas-finest-news-source-explains-glenn-beck-viewers.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 16 Nov 2009 22:34:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[humor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[news]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rule of law]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/11/anericas-finest-news-source-explains-glenn-beck-viewers.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Passionate defenders, gather ye round: &#8220;Right there in the preamble, the authors make their priorities clear: &#8216;one nation under God,'&#8221; said Mortensen, attributing to the Constitution a line from the Pledge of Allegiance, which itself did not include any reference to a deity until 1954. &#8220;Well, there&#8217;s a reason they put that right at the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Passionate defenders, <a target="_blank" href="http://www.theonion.com/content/news/area_man_passionate_defender_of?utm_source=onion_rss_daily">gather ye round</a>:<br />
<blockquote>&#8220;Right there in the preamble, the authors make their priorities clear: &#8216;one nation under God,'&#8221; said Mortensen, attributing to the Constitution a line from the Pledge of Allegiance, which itself did not include any reference to a deity until 1954. &#8220;Well, there&#8217;s a reason they put that right at the top.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/11/anericas-finest-news-source-explains-glenn-beck-viewers.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Clinton derangement syndrome</title>
		<link>./../../2009/08/clinton-derangement-syndrome.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/08/clinton-derangement-syndrome.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2009 14:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Clinton]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[news]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/08/clinton-derangement-syndrome.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[rdan Joe Conason of Salon gets this one right. Here was an effort that exemplified the best of America &#8212; a society that values the lives of its citizens enough to send a former head of state, with all the power of government behind him, to the aid of two women in distress. Here was [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>rdan</p>
<p><a target="_blank" href="http://www.salon.com/opinion/conason/2009/08/07/clinton/?source=newsletter">Joe Conason of Salon</a> gets this one right.</p>
<blockquote><p>Here was an effort that exemplified the best of America &#8212; a society that values the lives of its citizens enough to send a former head of state, with all the power of government behind him, to the aid of two women in distress. Here was a happy reunion, bringing wives home to their husbands and a mother back to her little girl, that surely uplifted the spirit of anyone who actually believes in family values. Here was a moment of pride and joy.</p>
<p>But not for Gordon Liddy, the demented felon and radio bigot who <a target="_blank" href="http://mediamatters.org/mmtv/200908050002">cackled about &#8220;Ling Ling and Wee Wee being locked up for nine hours in an airplane with Bill Clinton.&#8221;</a> Not for Rush Limbaugh, the obsessive guttersnipe who wondered aloud whether Clinton &#8220;hit on those two female journalists on the long flight home.&#8221; Not for Andrea Peyser, the curdled tabloid columnist who insisted that <a target="_blank" href="http://www.nypost.com/seven/08062009/news/columnists/homecoming_drama_is_all_about_bubba_183219.htm">&#8220;the whole shebang was nakedly scripted and staged as a device to help rehabilitate the image of former President Bill Clinton&#8221;</a>(and who neglected to mention that Clinton did not speak to the eagerly waiting press corps and has given not a single interview on the North Korea mission). Not for Times columnist Maureen Dowd, who predictably seized on Clinton&#8217;s mission as an opportunity for gratuitous and ugly insults to his wife, weirdly imagining that the prisoner release was &#8220;some clever North Korean revenge plot, giving the limelight to Daddy to punish Mommy.&#8221; And not for the editors of the Huffington Post, who posted <a target="_blank" href="http://www.politico.com/blogs/michaelcalderone/0809/HuffPo_blogger_appalled_by_HuffPo_headline.html">a very strange headline</a> &#8212; &#8220;Bill Upstages Hillary &#8230; Once Again&#8221; &#8212; on an Associated Press story that didn’t mention her at all.</p></blockquote>
<p>Of course the visit was scripted-it probably took a lot of negotiation. Such ex-presidential forays into particular situations has precedent for those who negotiate. But crude innuendo at the expense of these two women and their families is wrong.  And to be thinking that the visit was done without Department of State input and approval strikes me as stupid.  Let it be folks, your ratings are okay.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/08/clinton-derangement-syndrome.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
