<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>tax subsidies &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Build it anyway, and some of them may come</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/build-it-anyway-and-some-of-them-may-come.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/build-it-anyway-and-some-of-them-may-come.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Jan 2013 05:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[tax subsidies]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/build-it-anyway-and-some-of-them-may-come.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[ &#8220;Build it anyway, and some of them may come&#8221; probably won&#8217;t sell bonds and loan programs to voters. If you build it they might not come But if the city and its residents are desperate to keep the Coyotes in town, they have to understand that doing so comes at a cost that likely won&#8217;t [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-s0CVAPY5tWc/UNiq8uZ6TxI/AAAAAAAABOs/UHKASAtIglw/s1600/Field-of-Dreams-Team4.jpg" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="147" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-s0CVAPY5tWc/UNiq8uZ6TxI/AAAAAAAABOs/UHKASAtIglw/s320/Field-of-Dreams-Team4.jpg" width="320"></a></div>
<p> &#8220;Build it anyway, and some of them may come&#8221; probably won&#8217;t sell bonds and loan programs to voters.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/business/archive/2012/09/if-you-build-it-they-might-not-come-the-risky-economics-of-sports-stadiums/260900/#" target="_blank">If you build it they might not come</a></p>
<blockquote><p>But if the city and its residents are desperate to keep the Coyotes in town, they have to understand that doing so comes at a cost that likely won&#8217;t be replaced &#8212; not by sales tax revenue, not by economic growth, and not by outside spending. When the city subsidizes hockey, it reduces its ability to pay for public safety officials, public transportation, and services upon which its citizens rely.<br />That&#8217;s a choice the city is free to make, of course, but it shouldn&#8217;t pretend that the mere presence of the Coyotes is an economic investment. Doing so simply enables a further transfer of public dollars to a private enterprise, without much hope for a return.</p></blockquote>
<p>I suppose there is a difference between a corn field and a stadium, and I think Costner didn&#8217;t ask for special loans and tax status.   But a thrity year loan is not as flexible as jobs.</p>
<p><a href="http://thinkprogress.org/economy/2012/12/20/1368251/oakland-police-sports/" title="http://thinkprogress.org/economy/2012/12/20/1368251/oakland-police-sports/">Oakland funds stadium, fire police</a></p>
<p>Oakland was no different, laying off 200 police officers, despite the city having the fifth-highest crime rate in the country. However, the city chose to fire those officers while <a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2012-12-20/oakland-pays-17-million-for-nfl-raiders-as-cops-get-cut.html">preserving a $17 million payment</a> to the National Football League’s Oakland Raiders and Major League Baseball’s Oakland Athletics:<br />
<blockquote><strong>Oakland, California, the fifth-most crime ridden city in America, faced a $32 million budget deficit last year. It closed the gap by dismissing a fourth of its police force, more than 200 officers.</strong><br /><strong>Untouched was the $17.3 million that the city pays to stage 10 games a season for the National Football League’s Oakland Raiders and to host Major League Baseball’s Athletics in the O.co Coliseum.</strong> The funds cover debt financing and operations and are supplemented by $13.3 million from surrounding Alameda County, based on data compiled by Bloomberg from public records. </p></blockquote>
<p>Nearly <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/business/archive/2012/09/if-you-build-it-they-might-not-come-the-risky-economics-of-sports-stadiums/260900/">every single NFL stadium</a> was built with public money or benefits from public infrastructure built specifically nearby. This money, as many studies have shown, <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/business/archive/2012/09/if-you-build-it-they-might-not-come-the-risky-economics-of-sports-stadiums/260900/">does not provide much</a> <a href="http://articles.baltimoresun.com/2012-08-13/news/bs-ed-baltimore-washington-olympics-20120813_1_olympics-bid-london-olympics-olympic-tourism">economic benefit</a> to the surrounding community.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/build-it-anyway-and-some-of-them-may-come.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>New Report Highlights Flaws of North Carolina Mega-Incentives</title>
		<link>./../../2012/06/new-report-highlights-flaws-of-north-carolina-mega-incentives.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/06/new-report-highlights-flaws-of-north-carolina-mega-incentives.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Jun 2012 12:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[incentives]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kenneth Thomas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax subsidies]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/06/new-report-highlights-flaws-of-north-carolina-mega-incentives.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Kenneth Thomas New Report Highlights Flaws of North Carolina Mega-Incentives My new report for the North Carolina Budget and Tax Center, Special Deals, Special Problems&#8211;An Analysis of North Carolina&#8217;s Legislature-Approved Economic Development Incentives, has just been published. It covers a range of issues I&#8217;ve emphasized here before as well as some basic considerations reporters [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Kenneth Thomas</p>
<p>New Report Highlights Flaws of North Carolina Mega-Incentives </p>
<p>My <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766">new report</a> for the North Carolina Budget and Tax Center, <i>Special Deals, Special Problems&#8211;An Analysis of North Carolina&#8217;s Legislature-Approved Economic Development Incentives</i>, has just been published. It covers a range of issues I&#8217;ve emphasized here before as well as some basic considerations reporters really need to pay more attention to.    </p>
<p>North Carolina has some of the best economic development practices in the country, in terms of <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766">online transparency</a>, <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766">performance requirements</a>, <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766">use of clawbacks</a> for non-performance by companies, sunset clauses for tax expenditures, hard caps for many tax credit programs (see my report on these points), etc. The state publishes an <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766">economic development inventory</a> I consider to be of very high quality and consistent with international definitions of a subsidy. The most recent edition shows that in the 2008-9 fiscal year the state spent about $1.2 billion on economic development, enough to hire 24,000 people at $50,000 a year in wages and benefits.    </p>
<p>At the same time, however, the state has persistently had problems in overvaluing potential investments and consequently offering wildly excessive subsidies for them. The best known case is <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766">Dell in 2004</a>, when Virginia offered the company a $37 million incentive package, while the state and local bid from North Carolina came to almost $300 million on a nominal basis ($174 million present value). Other deals discussed in the report are Google ($260 million nominal value, $140 million present value), Apple ($321 million over 30 years nominal value, no present value calculation available), and a provision in a 2011 special incentives bill to allow Alex Lee Inc. to keep $2 million it should have forfeited for not keeping job promises. This last case illustrates how special legislative deals weaken the state&#8217;s performance requirements; this case will make future companies think that there may be no penalty for non-performance.    </p>
<p>Reporters take note! This publication describes useful techniques for comparing the size of incentive packages regardless of project size or payout period of the incentive. From the European Union I borrow the term &#8220;aid intensity,&#8221; which measures the size of the incentive relative to the amount of the investment or the number of jobs created. The idea is that a $1 million incentive would be large for a call center but a rounding error for an automobile assembly plant. As a result, we need a standardized way of comparing incentives.    </p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>While in this country one can sometimes find cost per job analyzed for some subsidy packages, the EU actually uses the subsidy/investment metric as its primary measure of aid intensity. <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766">In my last post</a> I discussed a mall redevelopment which could conceivably have an aid intensity of 96%. For comparison purposes, we should note that the highest aid intensity allowed for large firms anywhere in the European Union, is 50%, and that is only allowed in the poorest regions of the EU, mainly in eastern Europe. (Richer regions have lower allowable maxima.) A region&#8217;s maximum is cut by half for large projects over 50 million euro, and by 66% for spending over 100 million euro.    </p>
<p>The other important concept is present value, a familiar one to accountants and economists, but not widely understood among the general public. The basic idea is simple: receiving a dollar today is worth more than receiving a dollar next year, which is worth more than receiving a dollar in two years, etc. Since incentive packages can pay out immediately (with a cash grant) or over a period of 30 or more years, we need to use present value to properly compare the size of incentives with different payout periods. This requires finding a a &#8220;discount rate&#8221; by which to reduce future payments. We then use the present value as the numerator in calculating aid intensity to be able to compare across different sizes of projects.    </p>
<p>Using Google as an example, this $600 million project will receive $260 million over 30 years and create 210 jobs. As mentioned above, this is its nominal cost, before discounting the future dollars. Following the practice of a 1990s study by the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development to compare subsidies among its then 23 members, I used a discount rate equal to the 10-year Treasury bond yield to come up with a present value of $140.6 million. Then the aid intensity is $140.6 million/$600 million, or 23%, and the cost per job at present value is $669,489.</p>
<p>We can then use these two measures of aid intensity to compare the incentive to that given for other projects and inform our judgment of whether it was a better or worse deal than other states have made, in the current context where states make such deals all the time. Of course, I believe there should be limits placed on state and local governments so we can sharply reduce net incentive spending, which has few national benefits&#8211;but that is a long time in the future.    </p>
<p>North Carolina provides an intriguing case study because it does so much right in economic development, but it makes special deals outside its statutory incentive programs. The result is high costs and weakened bargaining position in the future. It&#8217;s a case we can learn a lot from. </p>
<p>crossposted with <a href="http://www.blogger.com/%3Ca%3Ehttp://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2012/06/new-report-highlights-flaws-of-north.html%3C/a%3E" target="_blank">Middle Class Political Economist</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/06/new-report-highlights-flaws-of-north-carolina-mega-incentives.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>David Cay Johnson and taxed by the boss</title>
		<link>./../../2012/05/david-cay-johnson-and-taxed-by-the-boss.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/05/david-cay-johnson-and-taxed-by-the-boss.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 May 2012 12:22:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[David Cay Johnson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[local economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[state interventions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax subsidies]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/05/david-cay-johnson-and-taxed-by-the-boss.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Reuters brings us a post from David Cay Johnson on a less well known funding mechanism from state coffers to private businesses. Granted there are a lot of others as well. See this post by Kenneth Thomas    (link repaired) on how competition between government is different than between private businesses: Across the United States more [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://blogs.reuters.com/david-cay-johnston/2012/04/12/taxed-by-the-boss/" target="_blank">Reuters</a> brings us a post from David Cay Johnson on a less well known funding mechanism from state coffers to private businesses.  Granted there are a lot of others as well. See <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/04/guest-post-greg-mankiw-doesn-understand.html" target="_blank">this post by Kenneth Thomas  </a>  (link repaired) on how competition between government is different than between private businesses:</p>
<blockquote><p>Across the United States more than 2,700 companies are collecting state income taxes from hundreds of thousands of workers – and are keeping the money with the states’ approval, says an eye-opening report published on Thursday.</p>
<p>The report from Good Jobs First, a nonprofit taxpayer watchdog organization funded by Ford, Surdna and other major foundations, identifies 16 states that let companies divert some or all of the state income taxes deducted from workers’ paychecks. None of the states requires notifying the workers, whose withholdings are treated as taxes they paid.</p>
<p>General Electric, Goldman Sachs, Procter &#038; Gamble, Chrysler, Ford, General Motors and AMC Theatres enjoy deals to keep state taxes deducted from their workers’ paychecks, the report shows. Foreign companies also enjoy such arrangements, including Electrolux, Nissan, Toyota and a host of Canadian, Japanese and European banks, Good Jobs First says.<br /><a name="more"></a><br />Why do state governments do this? Public records show that large companies often pay little or no state income tax in states where they have large operations, as this column has documented. Some companies get discounts on property, sales and other taxes. So how to provide even more subsidies without writing a check? Simple. Let corporations keep the state income taxes deducted from their workers’ paychecks for up to 25 years.</p></blockquote>
<p>The snappier <a href="http://youtu.be/4sZzQQLX-AI" target="_blank">You tube version is here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/05/david-cay-johnson-and-taxed-by-the-boss.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tax subsidies for &#8230; ?</title>
		<link>./../../2011/11/tax-subsidies-for.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/11/tax-subsidies-for.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2011 15:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[banks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax subsidies]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/11/tax-subsidies-for.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Think Progress points us to a study by Citizens for Tax Justice on what industries receive tax subsidies by amount and percentage, with pages of how data was compiled at the end.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a target="_blank" href="http://thinkprogress.org/economy/2011/11/07/363234/financial-tax-subsidies/">Think Progress</a> points us to a study by Citizens for Tax Justice on what industries receive tax subsidies by amount and percentage, with pages of how data was compiled at the end.</p>
<p><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-TzHAK7GkrFw/TsUcd0vWaCI/AAAAAAAAAw4/NHjvoacNtUI/s1600/tax%2Bsubsidies.PNG"><img src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-TzHAK7GkrFw/TsUcd0vWaCI/AAAAAAAAAw4/NHjvoacNtUI/s320/tax%2Bsubsidies.PNG" border="0" alt=""></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/11/tax-subsidies-for.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Agribusiness, Food, Vegetarianism&#8212;-and Taxes</title>
		<link>./../../2009/11/agribusiness-food-vegetarianism-and-taxes.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/11/agribusiness-food-vegetarianism-and-taxes.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 19 Nov 2009 23:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[agribusiness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[corporate welfare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[environmentalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[excise taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[pollution]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sin taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax subsidies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[vegetarianism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/11/agribusiness-food-vegetarianism-and-taxes.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[[cross-posted on ataxingmatter&#8211;see posting there for additional comments] As some of you may know, I am one of the many people who eat a vegetarian diet. I don&#8217;t eat cows, pigs, fish, whales, sharks, chicken, turkey, sheep, wild game, tame game&#8230; As I sometimes say when people ask me about my diet, I eat everything [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>[cross-posted on<a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2009/11/agribusiness-food-vegetarianismand-taxes.html?cid=6a00d8341cf2a753ef012875b9af95970c#comment-6a00d8341cf2a753ef012875b9af95970c"> ataxingmatter</a>&#8211;see posting there for additional comments]</p>
<p>As some of you may know, I am one of the many people who eat a vegetarian diet. I don&#8217;t eat cows, pigs, fish, whales, sharks, chicken, turkey, sheep, wild game, tame game&#8230; As I sometimes say when people ask me about my diet, I eat everything you eat, except for a very short list of items&#8211;the critters that can move themselves from one place to another (or move their appendages) under their own propulsion.</p>
<p>(Note that we often have two words for animals that we eat&#8211;their live-form word &#8211;e.g., cow, sheep, pig&#8211; and their edible-corpse form word &#8211;e.g., beef, mutton, pork. That evolved when we borrowed the Romance language word for what we ate but kept the Germanic language word for the animals.)</p>
<p>It started when I was a child&#8211;I was one of those who would cut the meat into tiny pieces and then spread it all over my plate so it looked like I&#8217;d eaten it. The idea of eating a cow, with those beautiful liquid brown eyes, was repulsive. (My father came from a family with thirteen kids in the hills of Tennessee, so I&#8217;d seen cows up close.) I even took a whole piece of veal once and hid it behind the dining room cabinet (taking it out to the wastebasket after it dried)! I refused to eat the squirrel and venison that my dad brought home from hunting trips (mostly, if not always, somebody else&#8217;s kill). I even refused to let my cocker spaniel share in that dead stock.</p>
<p>But now that I&#8217;m an adult, why do I maintain that diet? I get asked that a lot.</p>
<p>Funny, nobody says (with shocked exression)&#8211;&#8220;Gee, you eat meat? Why would anyone ever want to eat a toxins-laden dead corpse of an animal that lived a horrendous life and suffered an agonizing death? &#8221; But they do often ask&#8211;usually treating it as a good-natured tease about a wacky alternative diet&#8211;why I&#8217;d want to avoid eating corpses.</p>
<p>James McWilliams got me thinking about this again this morning, when I read his &#8220;<a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2009/11/15/AR2009111502210.html?wpisrc=newsletter">Bellying up to environmentalism</a>&#8221; in the Washington Post for Nov. 16, 2009, where he noted that we should be asking questions in the reverse, that make meateaters feel uncomfortable at defending their own meateating. After all, there&#8217;s really no good reason for eating meat other than that someone is so addicted to its taste that he or she can&#8217;t exert the willpower to do without it.<br /><a name="more"></a><br />The whys for not eating meat, on the other hand, are legion. Let me just list a few here, from the mundane to the truly significant:</p>
<p>1. cooking is easier&#8211;throw veggies in a pot and steam them; throw veggies in a pot and make soup, throw veggies in a fry pan and fry them, throw beggies in a pot and bake them; and variants thereon</p>
<p>2. clean-up is a lot easier&#8211;none of that icky clinging greasy layer of animal fat on every pan</p>
<p>3. refrigerated leftover use is easier&#8211;throw the leftovers in a pot and steam them (etc. from one above) and there&#8217;s none of that congealed lard on top of the leftovers in the fridge</p>
<p>4. rotten vegetables in the fridge are less disgusting than rotten corpses in the fridge</p>
<p>5. a decent diet is generally considerably cheaper</p>
<p>6. the more people who adopt a vegetarian diet, the more people who are currently going hungry could be fed
<ul>
<li>one of the many articles I&#8217;ve read said something that stuck with me (sorry, don&#8217;t have the cite)&#8211;that it takes the same resources to feed one meat-eater that it takes to feed about 80 vegetarians. </li>
<li>That&#8217;s because of the huge waste as you use up primary foodstuffs to feed the animals that will be slaughtered, then use up primary energy stuffs to slaughter, process, ship and deliver the meat to the meat eater, compared to even transported vegetables (localvore, with vegetables, is even more saving of resources)</li>
</ul>
<p>7. without meat-eating, there are no feedlots where animals literally eat and sleep out the remainder of their short lives in their own shit</p>
<p>8. you can have a small flock of hens who live out their natural lives with nice living conditions (indoor/outdoor) </p>
<ul>
<li>disclosure: I had one hen who lived to be 22; she was still laying eggs up until the week or so before her death from natural causes</li>
</ul>
<p>9. Hens lay bigger and bigger eggs each year that they live past the first year w(hen most are slaughtered) and they still lay fairly regularly</p>
<ul>
<li>disclosure: 6 eggs every 7 days was typical in my experience</li>
</ul>
<p>10. Even hens have personalities</p>
<ul>
<li>disclosure: when I lived in upstate New York, I had one named Gumption who loved to fly up to the top of a two-story house and survey her domain, and another named &#8220;kiss me&#8221; who would follow me around all day like a pet dog</li>
</ul>
<p>11. Animals that we eat are as smart as&#8211;or smarter than&#8211;animals that we keep for pets (pigs compared to dogs, for example)</p>
<p>12. Animals care for their young and suffer when their young are taken from them (think dairy cattle and the young that are bred so that the mothers will give milk)</p>
<p>13. Some eating of animals is even more obnoxious than the norm (think &#8220;veal calves&#8221; that are taken and put in tiny sheds to they can fatten without any musculature development or &#8220;foie gras&#8221; where geese are fattened by having food stuffed down their throats with a tube)</p>
<p>14. Life is precious: there is no reason to sacrifice animal lives to lead a decent human life, so why do it?</p>
<p>15. Agribusiness&#8211;the main way that animals are raised and sold for meat&#8211;is an environmental nightmare</p>
<ul>
<li>use of fertilizers to grow the grain that is fed to the cattle that are fed to the humans results in polluted land, water and air and uses up petroleum and other resources</li>
<li>consolidation results in long transportation (inhumane to animals; wasteful of oil and gas resources)</li>
<li>the subsidies (including some tax expenditures) for agriculture have gotten out of control&#8211;costly, misdirected, ill-conceived, and essentially now a form of corporate welfare for huge agribusiness enterprises</li>
</ul>
<p>16. A meatless diet is healthier for humans than a meat-based diet, so we could cut health-care costs by simply cutting out meat</p>
<p>17. The process of butchering animals is a cruel leftover from the dark ages&#8211;people who work in slaughterhouses are inured to suffering, and that may well spill over into their &#8220;normal&#8221; lives outside work</p>
<p>18. The process of butchering animals is itself a source of harm&#8211;</p>
<ul>
<li>sick animals are slaughtered, making it possible that eaters of that dead flesh will be sickened as well (mad cow disease);</li>
<li>animals are slaughtered in the midst of their own excrement, and some of that excrement gets into the food chain (making people sick as well);</li>
<li>the leftovers from the animal slaughter have to be gotten rid of somehow, leading to even more water, land and air pollution</li>
<li>workers are exposed to awful conditions&#8211;not just the process of mercilessly killing animals day in and day out, but also the risk of infection and injury on the line</li>
</ul>
<p>19. The use of antibiotics in animal feed (given to healthy and unhealthy animals alike) ensures that resistant strains will develop even more rapidly, while leaving excess antibiotics not absorbed by the animals to pass out in their urine and excrement and into the land and water to act as toxins to others (including fish and birds and humans) leading to additional environmental nightmares&#8230;</p>
<p>20. Agribusiness pig farms and cattle feedlots are a blight on any humans within their vicinity (as well as a disaster for the natural world, noted above under environmental problems) from the stench of the manure (that can pollute the countryside for miles around) to the ugliness of the barren, treeless manure-laden fields.</p>
<p>So what to do? Maybe we should enact an excise tax on all meat products, like a&#8221;sin&#8221; tax for sodas and sweets and cigarettes. Comments, anyone?</p>
<p>PS Arthur C. Clarke has a great sci fi short story, taking place some time in the future, when a more advanced civilization than ours is aghast at the purported discovery that their ancestors used to&#8211;cover the young ones&#8217; ears&#8211;eat dead corpses of animals&#8230;..Clarke&#8217;s ideas were way ahead of his time in lots of ways.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/11/agribusiness-food-vegetarianism-and-taxes.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>31</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
