<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>executions &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The Mordant Litmus of Texas?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/05/the-mordant-litmus-of-texas.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/05/the-mordant-litmus-of-texas.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 10 May 2012 16:23:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[economic conditions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[executions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Noni Mausa]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/05/the-mordant-litmus-of-texas.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Noni MausaThe Mordant Litmus of Texas? The other day I was listening to a fascinating interview on US executions. "So far this year, 5 convicted criminals felt the executioner'sneedle. Michael Graczyk watched as they took their last breath. Thereporter from the Associated Press has witnessed more than 300executions. It's believed he's seen more men and [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><tt>by <strong>Noni Mausa</strong></tt><br /><tt><strong>The Mordant Litmus of Texas?</strong></p>
<p>The other day I was listening to a fascinating interview on US executions.<br /> "So far this year, 5 convicted criminals felt the executioner's<br />needle. Michael Graczyk watched as they took their last breath. The<br />reporter from the Associated Press has witnessed more than 300<br />executions. It's believed he's seen more men and women put to death<br />than anyone else in the United States."<br /> (Link is <a href="http://www.cbc.ca/thecurrent/episode/2012/05/03/execution-reporter-michael-graczyk/">here</a>. Audio  is <a href="http://www.cbc.ca/thecurrent/popupaudio.html?clipIds=2230340722">here</a>)</p>
<p>But what caught my ear was the moment in the interview when Graczyk<br />remarked that in 1982, Texas resumed executions.  I thought, there's<br />another entry for my file "It all started in 1980."</p>
<p>From 1964 to 1982, eighteen years, Texas executed nobody.</p>
<p>In 1964 the US Supreme Court negated all death penalties nationwide in<br />"Furman v. Georgia" due to unacceptable trial-and-sentencing<br />procedures.  (details <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Capital_punishment_in_Texas#History">here</a>, in case you care.)</tt><br /><tt></tt><br /><tt><a name="more"></a></tt></p>
<p><tt><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-noDPkhlPaTY/T6vqthlNvRI/AAAAAAAAA2Y/_mF_uFjKqyY/s1600/laughable_graph_%231.jpg" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="221" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-noDPkhlPaTY/T6vqthlNvRI/AAAAAAAAA2Y/_mF_uFjKqyY/s320/laughable_graph_%231.jpg" width="320"></a><br />States revised their trial procedures and by 1976 the Supremes allowed<br />that under these new procedures states could resume executions.  Yet<br />Texas didn't use this until 1982 (a single execution), and then things<br />took off.</p>
<p>However, this post has nothing to do with capital punishment, but with<br />the economy.  And I noticed something interesting.</p>
<p>See, all this led me to look at the number of Texas executions over<br />time.  In this very rough (don't laugh) graph,</p>
<p>there were three peaks in Texas executions -- in the late 1800s, in the 30s,<br />and today's.  Each peak has outdone the previous, and the 2000-2010<br />numbers were the highest ever.</p>
<p>For those who don't notice it, these eras equate to the Long Depression, the Great Depression, and our current depression.</p>
<p>Now, I realize that an element of the growth in executions is tied to<br />population growth, and if I had time I could chart that out.  However,<br />Texas population growth can be seen in this chart (<a href="http://www.lsjunction.com/texians/charta.gif">http://www.lsjunction.com/texians/charta.gif</a>), and is shown to be a<br />long smooth exponential rise since 1800.  Taking that into account,<br />there would still be three big bumps in the distribution of<br />executions.  In my second laughable graph, you can see executions<br />really take off in the late 90s, leading into the biggest decade ever<br />-- 2000-2010, 248 executions.</p>
<p>It certainly looks to me like America's deepest recession /<br />depressions, are linked to Texas executions in some way.  But<br />laughable graph #2</p>
<div><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-J7rZRhtxK3Q/T6vp3UGAVaI/AAAAAAAAA2Q/fkQFRYu4oIU/s1600/laughable_graph_%232.jpg" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="197" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-J7rZRhtxK3Q/T6vp3UGAVaI/AAAAAAAAA2Q/fkQFRYu4oIU/s320/laughable_graph_%232.jpg" width="320"></a></div>
<p>shows that the link is probablypredictive rather than resultant -- something is happening in the society which causes a buildup of personal disasters and/or punitive overreaction, before the bubble bursts.</p>
<p>If this is the case, then laughable graph #2 seems to show a dismally<br />hopeful trend, as execution rates have dropped since the housing and<br />finance bubbles burst in 2007-2008.</tt><br /><tt></tt></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/05/the-mordant-litmus-of-texas.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
