<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>NJ &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>My Governor, as usual, Fails Math</title>
		<link>./../../2011/02/my-governor-as-usual-fails-math.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/02/my-governor-as-usual-fails-math.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 09 Feb 2011 20:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[human capital]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[innumeracy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NJ]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[state spending plans]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/02/my-governor-as-usual-fails-math.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[You have to love Chris Christie. The man who said NJ couldn&#8217;t afford a tunnel whose cost with overruns was expected to be less than $10B is now backing a tunnel whose initial cost estimate is $13B. That the great state of New Jersey has sent an actual physicist to Congress, let alone supplies and [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>You have to love Chris Christie. The man who <a href="http://www.examiner.com/essex-county-conservative-in-newark/arc-tunnel-cancelled-reaction-predictable">said NJ couldn&#8217;t afford a tunnel whose <em>cost with overruns</em> was expected to be less than $10B</a> is now <a href="http://www.examiner.com/essex-county-conservative-in-newark/christie-claims-vindication-on-gateway-tunnel-project">backing a tunnel</a> <a href="http://www.examiner.com/essex-county-conservative-in-newark/two-nj-senators-pushing-new-trans-hudson-tunnel-project">whose <em>initial cost estimate</em> is $13B</a>.</p>
<p>That the great state of New Jersey <a href="http://holt.house.gov/">has sent an actual physicist to Congress</a>, let alone supplies and hosts most of the talent in the Pharmaceutical and Financial Services industry,* and is run by a man who says we couldn&#8217;t afford $10.5B that PATH would control but should give $13B to something Amtrak will continue to control is rather close to proof that G-d is either non-existent or a thug with a sick sense of humor.</p>
<p>And now, he&#8217;s <a href="http://www.lifesitenews.com/news/nj-governor-christie-vetoes-bill-that-would-fund-planned-parenthood/">saving money again</a> (h/t <a href="http://whiskeyfire.typepad.com/whiskey_fire/2011/02/turn-to-dust-and-so-i-think-she-must.html">Thers</a>):</p>
<blockquote><p>Bill A3273 would have expanded New Jerseys’ Medicaid program, essentially reversing action Christie took in July 2010 to ensure <strong>$7.5 million</strong> in taxpayer money would not go to supporting family planning clinics, most of which [29 of 58 is half, not &#8220;most,&#8221; but apparently conservative reporters can&#8217;t do math either] are run by Planned Parenthood.</p>
<p>&#8220;In Fiscal year 2012, it is anticipated that the state’s Medicaid program faces a budget shortfall of <strong>$1.1 billion</strong>,&#8221; said Governor Christie in a statement. <em>Expanding Medicaid to more people &#8220;does not make sense from an overall fiscal and health care policy perspective</em>,&#8221; he said.</p></blockquote>
<p>Words can confuse numbers, so let me, er, &#8220;spell this one out.&#8221;<br /><a name="more"></a><br />In Christie-world, not spending $7,500,000 upfront is going to solve a deficit of $1,100,000,000. Those three extra zeroes on the deficit number are, after all, an Arabic creation, and can be ignored if you&#8217;re a blithering idiot or a Republican governor.**</p>
<p>Ignoring, of course, that an increase in conceptions and undesired births, combined with a decline in available prenatal care will lead to more <a href="http://www.mylot.com/w/discussions/1559964.aspx">underweight</a>, <a href="http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4191/is_20050120/ai_n10044077/">premature</a>, <a href="http://www.indiaparenting.com/pregnancy/122_3033/importance-of-a-healthy-diet.html">under- and malnourished</a> babies that will grow up to require more services than they would have had they been healthy and/or desired.</p>
<p>In Christie-world&mash;<a href="http://whereschristie.com/">that&#8217;s where you go, remaining out of touch</a>, knowing that your Lieutenant Governor is visiting her dying father out of the country, so that <a href="http://politics.blogs.foxnews.com/2010/12/27/chris-christie-leaves-snow-democratic-governor-behind-new-jersey#">the Senate president is left to declare a State of Emergency</a>—proper prenatal care doesn&#8217;t pay for itself.</p>
<p>In Christie-world, being <a href="http://digbysblog.blogspot.com/2011/02/red-lining-blue-states.html">the state most tasked with subsidizing the Red States</a> enables one to position to quit and run for higher office.*** Or at least that&#8217;s the only simple, direct, &#8220;rational&#8221; explanation for not investing in human capital and spending more on a less-desirable project.</p>
<p>If Chris Christie isn&#8217;t planning to be a short-timer, he&#8217;s certainly making certain that his legacy will be one of higher debt and lower preparedness. The next generation of New Jerseyites may be as innumerate as he is.</p>
<p>In which case, who do the Blue Staters think will pay for all their wars and welfare?</p>
<p>*Non-hedge fund financial services talent, that is. They generally <a href="http://digbysblog.blogspot.com/2011/02/red-lining-blue-states.html">live and work in Connecticut</a>, from which they pillage with impunity.</p>
<p>**See also <a href="http://www.google.com/search?q=%22Mitch+Daniels%22+site%3Adelong.typepad.com&#038;hl=en&#038;num=10&#038;lr=&#038;ft=i&#038;cr=&#038;safe=images&#038;tbs=">Daniels, Mitch</a>, and <a href="http://digbysblog.blogspot.com/2011/02/well-that-worked-out-well-gray-davis.html">Schwarzenegger, Arnold</a>.</p>
<p>***I would say this is part-wishful thinking on my part, but the result would be a mix of Glenn Beck and Sarah Palin appearing regularly on CNN or Faux News while—in the grand tradition of previous budget pillager and &#8220;centrist&#8221; Christine Todd Whitman—the rest of us are left to clean up the mess.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/02/my-governor-as-usual-fails-math.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
