<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>market &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Markets Need Regulators &#8211; Food Edition</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/markets-need-regulators-food-edition.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/markets-need-regulators-food-edition.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 23 Feb 2013 13:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[market]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mike Kimel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[regulators]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/markets-need-regulators-food-edition.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Mike Kimel Markets Need Regulators &#8211; Food Edition Back in college, I had a chat with one of my more libertarian economics professors about the need for regulation. He thought regulation was completely un-necessary. &#8220;But what about mislabeled food?&#8221; I asked, &#8220;How do we even know that what is labeled on the side of [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Mike Kimel</p>
<p>Markets Need Regulators &#8211; Food Edition</p>
<p>Back in college, I had a chat with one of my more libertarian economics professors about the need for regulation.  He thought regulation was completely un-necessary.</p>
<p>&#8220;But what about mislabeled food?&#8221; I asked, &#8220;How do we even know that what is labeled on the side of the box or the can is what is inside?&#8221;</p>
<p>His reply was one I&#8217;ve heard, in one variation or another, many times since, &#8220;A company that sells customers something than they ordered will quickly go out of business.&#8221;</p>
<p>I&#8217;ve known it was BS every time I heard that, but it is interesting and unfortunate to see validation lately.</p>
<p>In the US, we have <a href="http://articles.chicagotribune.com/2013-02-21/news/ct-met-phony-fish-20130221_1_seafood-fraud-fish-fraud-grouper-samples">mislabeledfish</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>Chicago diners who think they are eating red snapper may actually be munching on goldbanded jobfish.</p>
<p>Those who order Alaskan cod may really be tucking into a threadfin slickhead. And fans of yellowtail could just be getting a fish tale.</p>
<p>These are some of the findings of a Chicago fish fraud investigation to be released Thursday by conservancy group Oceana.</p>
<p>After its troubling seafood fraud investigations in East and West Coast cities over the last two years, the group expanded its testing to other cities, including Chicago. Thirty of 93 fish samples taken from Chicago restaurants, retail chains and sushi bars were mislabeled, mirroring percentages found in other cities.</p>
<p>Eight of nine Chicago red snapper samples tested by Oceana turned out to be different fish, the report said. And none of the three<br />yellowtail samples tested was actually yellowtail. Single samples sold as corvina, jack, mackerel and even perch did not match those descriptions, according to Oceana&#8217;s DNA tests.</p>
<p>The ocean conservancy organization does not list the names of the restaurants or stores where it bought the fish because &#8220;we didn&#8217;t know where, along the supply chain, the mislabeling first occurred,&#8221; said Beth Lowell Oceana&#8217;s seafood fraud campaign director.&#8221;So we didn&#8217;t want to call out businesses that may not have known their fish was mislabeled.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>This comes in the heel of the horsemeat (and occasionally donkey meat) sold as beef scandal in Europe.</p>
<p>What is interesting is that a) these behaviors have been going on for a long time and b) they were either spotted by a shrunken regulator (in Europe) or a non-profit (in the US).  The market&#8217;s incentives didn&#8217;t stop any of the players involved.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Now, one could respond that &#8220;this didn&#8217;t actually harm anyone&#8217;s health.&#8221;  That may be true, but it is fraud. Lack of damage isn&#8217;t true of all cases.  We&#8217;ve all read about cases where adulterated food products did kill, where mechanical components that didn&#8217;t meet stated standards caused deadly accidents, or pharmaceuticals that weren&#8217;t as stated caused tremendous harm.  Different fields have different stories.  Decades ago, I knew people who worked with blood banks, buying and selling blood products for use in medical and pharmaceutical tests and manufacturing.  Apparently it wasn&#8217;t uncommon for low quality, poorly tested, and badly identified blood from East Germany to be surreptitiously mislabeled as its high quality, tested-to-the-nines West German equivalent, and with a wink and a nod, enter the bloodstream so to speak.  Who knows how many people were harmed by that?  More familiar to most Americans these days is the mislabeling of financial products &#8211; there were an awful lot of risky financial products mislabeled as being AAA safe.</p>
<p>For commerce to work, confidence in the products being sold needs to exist.  But the marketplace by itself can&#8217;t provide that &#8211; the financial incentive apparently is just a bit too strong for some of the players.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/markets-need-regulators-food-edition.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>When Competition, Easy Entry, and No Government Produces Lousy Results: A Quick Look at the Anti-Virus and Anti-Malware Market</title>
		<link>./../../2012/05/when-competition-easy-entry-and-no-government-produces-lousy-results-a-quick-look-at-the-anti-virus-and-anti-malware-market.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/05/when-competition-easy-entry-and-no-government-produces-lousy-results-a-quick-look-at-the-anti-virus-and-anti-malware-market.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 19 May 2012 01:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[market]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/05/when-competition-easy-entry-and-no-government-produces-lousy-results-a-quick-look-at-the-anti-virus-and-anti-malware-market.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Mike Kimel When Competition, Easy Entry, and No Government Produces Lousy Results: A Quick Look at the Anti-Virus and Anti-Malware Market The other day I had to take my computer in to an expert for tune-up. I had all the usual onboard &#8211; an antivirus, anti-spyware software, etc. But the machine was running very, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Mike Kimel</p>
<p>When Competition, Easy Entry, and No Government Produces Lousy Results:  A Quick Look at the Anti-Virus and Anti-Malware Market    </p>
<p>The other day I had to take my computer in to an expert for tune-up.  I had all the usual onboard &#8211; an antivirus, anti-spyware software, etc.  But the machine was running very, very slowly.</p>
<p>   The expert I took it to cleaned out a lot of malware, removed my old anti-virus and anti-malware software, and installed new stuff.  He swears by this stuff, and so far, my machine is working much better than it was before.</p>
<p>But here&#8217;s the thing&#8230; the previous set of anti-virus and anti-malware had been highly recommended just a few years by PC Magazine and CNET users and other similar sources.  I know, because that&#8217;s why I installed those programs in the first place.</p>
<p>   Which leads me to believe that in a couple of years, I should go through the process of investigating anti-virus and anti-malware software again.  It seems, in fact, one&#8217;s choices with computers come to this:</p>
<p>   1.  Live with a machine that gets slower and slower and slower&#8230; <br />2.  Periodically go through the effort of investigating anti-virus and anti-malware software, making sure that the stuff you use continues to be highly rated and effective. <br />3.  Pay someone else to engage in number 2 for you. <br />4.  Pick an operating system that is unpopular enough that it isn&#8217;t targeted by malicious software and deal with its foibles.  Also, switch to another unpopular OS if the one you&#8217;re using starts becoming popular enough to attract the attention of malicious individuals.   </p>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />That&#8217;s a lot of time and attention one has to go through simply to use a piece of equipment that is now required to do business in much of the world, and even after going through the time and effort, there is no way to know whether the product you are purchasing (or not) is the best one available for the price.  Put another way &#8211; the outcome of this market is not one most of us would consider efficient.     </p>
<p>And yet, the market seems to be characterized by most of the factors that a libertarian or conservative economist look for to produce an optimal outcome.  It is relatively easy and inexpensive to enter and exit the market for anti-bad things software, the market is literally global (you can buy software made anywhere and download it from your desk in minutes), the cost of such products is low (many are given away free), there&#8217;s a heck of a lot of information out there, and there&#8217;s virtually no government involvement in the process.   </p>
<p>So why are the outcomes of this market so poor?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/05/when-competition-easy-entry-and-no-government-produces-lousy-results-a-quick-look-at-the-anti-virus-and-anti-malware-market.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
