<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>republican roadmap &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The Republicans have a savings plan. Gut the Nation&#8217;s Personality</title>
		<link>./../../2011/01/the-republicans-have-a-savings-plan-gut-the-nations-personality.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/01/the-republicans-have-a-savings-plan-gut-the-nations-personality.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2011 21:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Deficit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Republican brand]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[republican roadmap]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[utter stupidity]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/01/the-republicans-have-a-savings-plan-gut-the-nations-personality.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by: Daniel Becker Well, the repubs finally have put up.  They have a $2.5 trillion, ten year savings plan.  No, don&#8217;t worry.  You will be kept safe as all national security is untouched.  However, you can expect to wake up the next day from passage in a nation with an completely different personality.  As in [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by: Daniel Becker</p>
<p>Well, the repubs <a href="http://finance.yahoo.com/news/House-GOP-Lists-25-Trillion-usnews-2718863982.html?x=0&#038;sec=topStories&#038;pos=main&#038;asset=&#038;ccode=">finally have put up</a>.  They have a $2.5 trillion, ten year savings plan.  No, don&#8217;t worry.  You will be kept safe as all national security is untouched.  However, you can expect to wake up the next day from passage in a nation with an completely different personality.  As in 180 degree different.</p>
<blockquote><p>Here is the overview provided by the Republican Study Committee:</p>
<p>FY 2011 CR Amendment: Replace the spending levels in the FY 2011 continuing resolution (NYSE: CR &#8211; News) with non-defense, non-homeland security, non-veterans spending at FY 2008 levels. The legislation will further prohibit any FY 2011 funding from being used to carry out any provision of the Democrat government takeover of health care, or to defend the health care law against any lawsuit challenging any provision of the act. $80 billion savings.</p>
<p>Discretionary Spending Limit, FY 2012-2021: Eliminate automatic increases for inflation from CBO baseline projections for future discretionary appropriations. Further, impose discretionary spending limits through 2021 at 2006 levels on the non-defense portion of the discretionary budget. $2.29 trillion savings over ten years.</p>
<p>Federal Workforce Reforms: Eliminate automatic pay increases for civilian federal workers for five years. Additionally, cut the civilian workforce by a total of 15 percent through attrition. Allow the hiring of only one new worker for every two workers who leave federal employment until the reduction target has been met. (Savings included in above discretionary savings figure).</p>
<p>&#8220;Stimulus&#8221; Repeal: Eliminate all remaining &#8220;stimulus&#8221; funding. $45 billion total savings.</p>
<p>Eliminate federal control of Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac. $30 billion total savings.</p>
<p>Repeal the Medicaid FMAP increase in the &#8220;State Bailout&#8221; (Senate amendments to S. 1586). $16.1 billion total savings.</p></blockquote>
<p>The 100 item list is below</p>
<p><a name="more"></a>Some of the items, cutting them, you just have to ask: How are they going to get the job done?  Like cutting by 20% the federal vehicle budget or cut in half the congressional printing and binding budget?  What, we&#8217;re going to suddenly seen legislation that is only 1/2 the size of pages?  I&#8217;m sorry folks, but this list is nothing but an ideological hit list.  There is not thought at all regarding intergration as it relates to investing in this country or even governing.  Can you say: New York snow storm clearing disaster?</p>
<p>Here is the full list of cuts:</p>
<p>Additional Program Eliminations/Spending Reforms</p>
<p>Corporation for Public Broadcasting Subsidy. $445 million annual savings.<br />Save America&#8217;s Treasures Program. $25 million annual savings.<br />International Fund for Ireland. $17 million annual savings.<br />Legal Services Corporation. $420 million annual savings.<br />National Endowment for the Arts. $167.5 million annual savings.<br />National Endowment for the Humanities. $167.5 million annual savings.<br />Hope VI Program. $250 million annual savings.<br />Amtrak Subsidies. $1.565 billion annual savings.<br />Eliminate duplicative education programs. H.R. 2274 (in last Congress), authored by Rep. McKeon, eliminates 68 at a savings of $1.3 billion annually.<br />U.S. Trade Development Agency. $55 million annual savings.<br />Woodrow Wilson Center Subsidy. $20 million annual savings.<br />Cut in half funding for congressional printing and binding. $47 million annual savings.<br />John C. Stennis Center Subsidy. $430,000 annual savings.<br />Community Development Fund. $4.5 billion annual savings.<br />Heritage Area Grants and Statutory Aid. $24 million annual savings.<br />Cut Federal Travel Budget in Half. $7.5 billion annual savings.<br />Trim Federal Vehicle Budget by 20%. $600 million annual savings.<br />Essential Air Service. $150 million annual savings.<br />Technology Innovation Program. $70 million annual savings.<br />Manufacturing Extension Partnership (MEP) Program. $125 million annual savings.<br />Department of Energy Grants to States for Weatherization. $530 million annual savings.<br />Beach Replenishment. $95 million annual savings.<br />New Starts Transit. $2 billion annual savings.<br />Exchange Programs for Alaska, Natives Native Hawaiians, and Their Historical Trading Partners in Massachusetts. $9 million annual savings.<br />Intercity and High Speed Rail Grants. $2.5 billion annual savings.<br />Title X Family Planning. $318 million annual savings.<br />Appalachian Regional Commission. $76 million annual savings.<br />Economic Development Administration. $293 million annual savings.<br />Programs under the National and Community Services Act. $1.15 billion annual savings.<br />Applied Research at Department of Energy. $1.27 billion annual savings.<br />FreedomCAR and Fuel Partnership. $200 million annual savings.<br />Energy Star Program. $52 million annual savings.<br />Economic Assistance to Egypt. $250 million annually.<br />U.S. Agency for International Development. $1.39 billion annual savings.<br />General Assistance to District of Columbia. $210 million annual savings.<br />Subsidy for Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority. $150 million annual savings.<br />Presidential Campaign Fund. $775 million savings over ten years.<br />No funding for federal office space acquisition. $864 million annual savings.<br />End prohibitions on competitive sourcing of government services.<br />Repeal the Davis-Bacon Act. More than $1 billion annually.<br />IRS Direct Deposit: Require the IRS to deposit fees for some services it offers (such as processing payment plans for taxpayers) to the Treasury, instead of allowing it to remain as part of its budget. $1.8 billion savings over ten years.<br />Require collection of unpaid taxes by federal employees. $1 billion total savings.<br />Prohibit taxpayer funded union activities by federal employees. $1.2 billion savings over ten years.<br />Sell excess federal properties the government does not make use of. $15 billion total savings.<br />Eliminate death gratuity for Members of Congress.<br />Eliminate Mohair Subsidies. $1 million annual savings.<br />Eliminate taxpayer subsidies to the United Nations Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change. $12.5 million annual savings.<br />Eliminate Market Access Program. $200 million annual savings.<br />USDA Sugar Program. $14 million annual savings.<br />Subsidy to Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD). $93 million annual savings.<br />Eliminate the National Organic Certification Cost-Share Program. $56.2 million annual savings.<br />Eliminate fund for Obamacare administrative costs. $900 million savings.<br />Ready to Learn TV Program. $27 million savings.<br />HUD Ph.D. Program.<br />Deficit Reduction Check-Off Act.</p>
<p>TOTAL SAVINGS: $2.5 Trillion over Ten Years</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/01/the-republicans-have-a-savings-plan-gut-the-nations-personality.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Campaigning on Tax Increases II The Republicans.</title>
		<link>./../../2010/08/campaigning-on-tax-increases-ii-the-republicans.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/08/campaigning-on-tax-increases-ii-the-republicans.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Aug 2010 23:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[budget deficits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Fiscal stimulus]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[republican roadmap]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[taxation]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/08/campaigning-on-tax-increases-ii-the-republicans.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Robert Waldmann Kevin Drum writes&#8220;The GOP leadership has released &#8220;Tread Boldly,&#8221; a guidebook for Republican members of congress during the summer recess, and it includes a whole section called &#8220;Spending Restraint Solutions for Discussion.&#8221; Finally, we&#8217;ll get some details! So here they are: &#8216;Canceling unspent “stimulus” funds, saving up to $266 billion &#8230;&#8217; Being hep [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Robert Waldmann</p>
<p>Kevin Drum <a href="http://motherjones.com/comment/reply/72731">writes</a><br />&#8220;The GOP leadership has released &#8220;Tread Boldly,&#8221; a guidebook for Republican members of congress during the summer recess, and it includes a whole section called &#8220;Spending Restraint Solutions for Discussion.&#8221; Finally, we&#8217;ll get some details! So here they are:</p>
<p>&#8216;Canceling unspent “stimulus” funds, saving up to $266 billion &#8230;&#8217;</p>
<p>Being hep and up to date with the interwebs, the Republicans <a href="http://www.gop.gov/resources/library/documents/recesskits/2010-August.pdf">posted a pdf.</a></p>
<p>My point is that they just declared their willingness to increase the taxes paid by over 95% of working US families.  There is no way they can get &#8220;up to $266 billion&#8221; by cancelling other parts of the stimulus and not cancelling the tax cuts.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Notably  <a href="http://tinyurl.com/383zezq">&#8220;of the $787 billion in the Recovery Act, about 94% is either in tax cuts, payments, or projects under contract. &#8220;</a>  Are the Republicans proposing that the Federal Government violate signed contracts ?  Wouldn&#8217;t that be a seizure ?  </p>
<p>The payments include extended unemployment insurance (I&#8217;m not sure that&#8217;s the only payment).  Total additional government consumption (the standard word for government investment too) was $ 265 billion, so one can&#8217;t save $266 billion by cutting the un-contracted funds (about $ 50 billion).<br />http://tinyurl.com/383zez</p>
<p>Of course the Republicans would like nothing less than to have to explain that the ARRA included tax cuts for over 95% of working families in the USA and to explain that they want to eliminate those cuts (as all currently Republican legislators not from Maine voted against those tax cuts).</p>
<p><a href="http://reddit.com/submit"> <img src="http://reddit.com/static/spreddit7.gif" alt="submit to reddit" border="0"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/08/campaigning-on-tax-increases-ii-the-republicans.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Republican Roadmap=No Taxes for Oprah, Pelosi, Soros</title>
		<link>./../../2010/02/republican-roadmapno-taxes-for-oprah-pelosi-soros.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/02/republican-roadmapno-taxes-for-oprah-pelosi-soros.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2010 15:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[republican roadmap]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax reform]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/02/republican-roadmapno-taxes-for-oprah-pelosi-soros.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Bruce Webb Well I doubt that will be the slogan on the signs at the next Teabag Rally but it is an accurate summation of Rep. Paul Ryan&#8217;s Roadmap to America&#8217;s Future tax reform plan. From the website (bolding mine): This plan discards a needlessly complex and manipulative tax code, replacing it with a [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Bruce Webb</p>
<p>Well I doubt that will be the slogan on the signs at the next Teabag Rally but it is an accurate summation of Rep. Paul Ryan&#8217;s <a target="_blank" href="http://www.roadmap.republicans.budget.house.gov/Issues/Issue/?IssueID=8514">Roadmap to America&#8217;s Future</a> tax reform plan. From the website (bolding mine):<br />
<blockquote>This plan discards a needlessly complex and manipulative tax code, replacing it with a simplified mechanism that promotes work, saving, and investment.</p>
<p>Provides individual income tax payers a choice of how to pay their taxes – through existing law, or through a highly simplified code that fits on a postcard with just two rates and virtually no special tax deductions, credits, or exclusions (except the health care tax credit).<br />Simplifies tax rates to 10 percent on income up to $100,000 for joint filers, and $50,000 for single filers; and 25 percent on taxable income above these amounts. Also includes a generous standard deduction and personal exemption (totaling $39,000 for a family of four).<br />Eliminates the alternative minimum tax [AMT].<br />Promotes saving by eliminating taxes on interest, capital gains, and dividends; also eliminates the death tax.<br />Replaces the corporate income tax – currently the second highest in the industrialized world – with a border-adjustable business consumption tax of 8.5 percent. This new rate is roughly half that of the rest of the industrialized world.</p></blockquote>
<p>Some attention has been paid to the Roadmap&#8217;s plan to privatize Social Security and voucherize Medicare but little to this aspect. Under Ryan&#8217;s Roadmap billionaires don&#8217;t pay taxes. At all.</p>
<p>In our system there are multi-millionaires whose wealth came from a combination of wages and bonuses, film and sports stars come to mind, but the truly rich earned their billions from returns of capital, they own property and companies and make their money by selling them and pocketing the gains. Under the Ryan Roadmap every form of gain from capital is tax free.</p>
<p>They really do believe that Capitalists are Masters of the Universe, that they are so important they don&#8217;t even have to contribute to pay for the weapons systems used to protect their interests around the world or from terrorism here at home. Some of us have recognized that the end point of Republican tax policy added up to &#8216;No Tax for Billionaires&#8217;, it is just that no Republican dared compile that entire agenda and put it down on paper. Well here it is, it is the Roadmap to Plutocracy, that is the Republican vision of America&#8217;s Future, that &#8216;wage slave&#8217; no longer be a metaphor, instead workers will pay for everything.</p>
<p>And you can bet that the Capitalists will still be claiming WORKERS are the Parasites.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/02/republican-roadmapno-taxes-for-oprah-pelosi-soros.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
