<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>student loans &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Student debt triples since 2004</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/student-debt-triples-since-2004.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/student-debt-triples-since-2004.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2013 15:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[student debt]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[student loans]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[student-loan program]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/student-debt-triples-since-2004.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The New York Fed has some interesting statistics regarding the increase and composition of student debt by age and amounts. Such debt has tripled in the last nine years.  Lots of reading to be had.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.newyorkfed.org/newsevents/mediaadvisory/2013/Lee022813.pdf" target="_blank">The New York Fed</a> has some interesting statistics regarding the increase and composition of student debt by age and amounts.  Such debt has tripled in the last nine years.  Lots of reading to be had.</p>
<p><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-dgev6E0yqfQ/UTNelhNG1iI/AAAAAAAABiI/X61xzXaYDNk/s1600/student+debt.PNG" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-dgev6E0yqfQ/UTNelhNG1iI/AAAAAAAABiI/X61xzXaYDNk/s320/student+debt.PNG" height="326" width="400"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/student-debt-triples-since-2004.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Updated cost projections for the Pell Grant program</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/updated-cost-projections-for-the-pell-grant-program.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/updated-cost-projections-for-the-pell-grant-program.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 09 Feb 2013 17:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[college]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Pell grants]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[student debt]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[student loans]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/updated-cost-projections-for-the-pell-grant-program.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[New America points us to Pell Grant cost projections: The Congressional Budget Office this week released updated cost projections for the Pell Grant program – and the estimates show an unexpected surplus over the past several years. The figures are much awaited because they dictate what lawmakers must allocate to the program in the upcoming [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://edmoney.newamerica.net/blogposts/2013/new_pell_grant_estimates_buy_time_long_term_fix_still_needed-78890">New America</a> points us to Pell Grant cost projections:</p>
<blockquote><p>The Congressional Budget Office this week released <a href="http://www.cbo.gov/sites/default/files/cbofiles/attachments/43912_PellGrants.pdf">updated cost projections for the Pell Grant program</a> – and the estimates show an unexpected <em>surplus</em> over the past several years. The figures are much awaited because they dictate what lawmakers must allocate to the program in the upcoming fiscal year 2014 appropriations process if they want to keep the program running at its current level of benefits and with existing eligibility rules.<br />In 2010 and 2011, those estimates sparked panic. The program was burning through money faster than anyone expected, prompting Congress and the Obama administration to shift funding from other programs and cut parts of the Pell Grant program itself three separate times.</p>
<p>The funding emergency was exacerbated by the fact that congressional lawmakers and the Obama administration had tried to maintain a large increase in the maximum grant, first funded without any long-term funding plan by the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009. The latest round of temporary funding was set to dry up in 2014, leaving a $5.8 billion hole in the program. In 2015, the number would jump to $8.7 billion, and stay at about that level indefinitely.</p>
<p>Luckily for procrastinators in the White House and on Capitol Hill – and for Pell Grant supporters – the latest <a href="http://www.cbo.gov/sites/default/files/cbofiles/attachments/43912_PellGrants.pdf">Congressional Budget Office estimates</a> have come to their rescue. According to CBO, the program was actually <em>overfunded </em>the past few years, leaving a surplus of $9.2 billion. The CBO doesn’t give much explanation as to what changed. For that we’ll have to wait for the president.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/updated-cost-projections-for-the-pell-grant-program.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Learning To Owe</title>
		<link>./../../2011/12/learning-to-owe.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/12/learning-to-owe.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 04 Dec 2011 20:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education cost]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[student debt]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[student loans]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/12/learning-to-owe.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[A few thoughts from a friend of mine and an introduction from a movie I (run75441) watch each year. &#8220;I don&#8217;t need 24 hours. I don&#8217;t have to talk to anybody. I know right now, and the answer&#8217;s no. No! Doggone it! You sit around here and you spin your little webs and you think [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A few thoughts from a friend of mine and an introduction from a movie I (run75441) watch each year.</p>
<p><i> &#8220;I don&#8217;t need 24 hours. I don&#8217;t have to talk to anybody. I know right now, and the answer&#8217;s no. No! Doggone it! You sit around here and you spin your little webs and you think the whole world revolves around you and your money! Well, it doesn&#8217;t, Mr. Potter! In the, in the whole vast configuration of things, I&#8217;d say you were nothing but a scurvy little spider!&#8221; </i>George Bailey
<p><a href="http://blog-thebell.blogspot.com/2011/10/learning-to-owe.html">Learning To Owe</a>    </p>
<p>by The Bell</p>
<p>The Cost of Education Is Crushing the Opportunity We Mean It to Provide</p>
<p>The Occupy Wall Street movement has no formal goals but several consistent memes have emerged among the crowd demonstrations in various cities across the country. Most of these have to do with the concentration of wealth and the collusion/corruption between big business and government. However, a more selfish trend also has surfaced among the demonstrators – many want their college student loans forgiven.  </p>
<p>A small, informal survey among New York protestors last week by equity research analyst David Maris found ninety-three percent of them advocated student-loan clemency. This idea actually is neither original to OWS nor unique among its members.</p>
</p>
<table border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<p><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-hkGwcblHRGM/Tq7FQZPEwqI/AAAAAAAAAfg/yi3k85KqA7c/s1600/LearningToOwe.bmp"><img title="clip_image001" border="0" alt="clip_image001" src="http://lh5.ggpht.com/-6KrqYE0-52I/TtvJM77e4nI/AAAAAAAAAxk/0wA0dcKSsKA/clip_image001%25255B3%25255D.jpg?imgmax=800" width="244" height="153"></a></p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<p><i>Sign bewailing large student loan debt</i>             <br /><i>from one Occupy Wall Street protestor</i></p>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><a name="more"></a>
<p>New York University Professor Andrew Ross recently proposed a radical solution to student loan debts the he calls “A Pledge of Refusal.” The idea requires those who owe to sign a pledge to stop making payments on their student loans once the pledge garners a million signatures. Meanwhile, an online petition supporting student loan forgiveness has collected over a half million signatures.   </p>
<p>President Obama announced a plan last week to provide student loan relief. First, he is reducing the maximum repayment on student loans from fifteen percent of discretionary annual income to ten percent. Second, he will allow borrowers to combine loans from the Family Education Loan Program with direct government loans, with a lower consolidated interest rate. Obama plans to use his Executive authority to bypass Congress for this program.   </p>
<p>Democratic Representative Hansen Clarke of Michigan wants to go even further. He has introduced legislation (H.R. 365) that includes creating incentives for banks to negotiate with distressed lenders, providing tax credits for education expenses and student loan debt, and making more private student loans eligible for discharge in bankruptcy proceedings.   <br />Both Obama’s and Clarke’s solutions fall short of general clemency but protestors are unlikely to obtain this remedy. A Rasmussen poll found only twenty-one percent of American adults in favor of blanket forgiveness as contrasted to sixty-six percent opposed. Many feel clemency would be unfair to lenders as well as those borrowers who repaid their student loans. At worst, they write off OWS protestors and other advocates for loan forgiveness as spoiled, lazy slackers who expect a free ride.   </p>
<p>Such epithets are unfair, counters conservative columnist Nicholas Kristoff this week in the <i>New York Times</i>. “While alarmists seem to think that the movement is a ‘mob’ trying to overthrow capitalism, one can make a case that, on the contrary, it highlights the need to restore basic capitalist principles like accountability.” Kristoff goes on to deplore how “some financiers have chosen to live in a government-backed featherbed. Their platform seems to be socialism for tycoons and capitalism for the rest of us . . . they can privatize profits while socializing risk.”   <br />Representative Clarke concurs that most protestors “are not asking for [a bailout]. They are simply asking for a system that is not rigged against them.” When big bankers and investment firms can make poor decisions without suffering obvious consequences, then the motivation for individuals requesting similar absolution may not be admirable but it is understandable.   <br />While the current crop of students and recent graduates may be whining about the problem more than past generations, they face an objectively bigger problem. This year, the average borrower graduating from a four-year college left school with roughly $24,000 of student debt, with ten percent facing debt of $40,000 or more, according to the College Board. Total student loan debt will exceed $1 trillion this year and it now exceeds outstanding credit card debt, according to the Federal Reserve Bank of New York.   </p>
<p>Only seven percent of graduating bachelor’s degree holders come from the bottom quarter of income earners, as compared to twelve percent back in 1970. Intended as relief and opportunity for the distressed poor, student loans have become an unavoidable middle class reality. In addition, a series of laws passed by Congress last decade have increased the difficulty of discharging debt, including student loans, through bankruptcy.   <br />The website <i>College Scholarships</i> reports on several programs that forgive or reduce student loan debt for graduates willing to work in high need/disadvantaged areas. The problem is such programs are limited to highly targeted professions, such as nurses, attorneys, and teachers. What is more, they often require a minimum of five years experience. Traditionally, graduates take such jobs immediately after graduation to acquire experience, when they are most inclined to social activism and less acclimated in their lifestyles to larger salaries.   </p>
<p>I attended college for six years, ultimately earning a master’s level degree in 1984. I won several scholarships, based on merit; qualified for several grants, based on need; and I worked. In spite of this, I fell short of the necessary money for tuition and books on a couple of occasions. I took out a couple of federal student loans to make up the difference that I was able to repay within a few years of graduation.   </p>
<p>Contrast my experience with that of Robert Applebaum, who graduated from Fordham Law School in 1998 with about $65,000 in debt. After going to work as an Assistant District Attorney in Brooklyn, his salary forced him to put his student loans in “forbearance,” which prevents default but allows continued accrual of interest. Applebaum began repaying his loans upon leaving the DA’s office in 2004 but remains $88,000 in debt today.   <br />Tommaso Boggia is an MPA candidate at Presidio Graduate School and an advocate for student loan clemency. He writes at the website <i>Triple Pundit</i>, “Regardless of work ethic, more and more middle class families are slipping into poverty, in part because of the heavy debt burden of house ownership and of pursuing a higher education degree . . . A whole generation is seeing their plans and ambitions shackled by the extra weight of their student loan payments. These young people are unable to buy a home, start a family, or do the socially important but underpaid jobs in the social services sector.”   </p>
<p>In the post-World War II era, a college education was the chief means by which children from working poor families could leapfrog into the middle class or even affluence. Increasingly, however, the cost of this requirement is becoming the very thing holding them back from the opportunities promised by the American Dream.  </p>
<p>The most cited reason for exploding debt is the ever-increasing cost of college. Average in-state tuition and fees at four-year public colleges rose an additional eight point three percent in 2001 alone, passing $8,000/year ($17,000/year with room and board). In addition, the American Council on Education notes that budget cuts and other austerity measures have reduced state appropriations to higher education by eighteen percent over the last three years.   </p>
<p>Richard Vedder, Director of the Center for College Affordability and Productivity and author of the book <i>Going Broke by Degree – Why College Costs Too Much</i>, maintains that we are looking at the problem exactly backwards. Writing in the <i>National Review</i>, he argues that just as an abundance of easily obtainable, low interest mortgages spurred the housing bubble that caused the 2008 financial crisis, “Arguably, federal student financial assistance is creating a second bubble in higher education.”   </p>
<p>Vedder also points out that government doles out loans without discrimination to a student’s prospects of success in college, despite the fact that over forty percent of those pursuing a bachelor’s degree fail to receive one within six years, or chances of success after college, regardless of whether a student’s field of study offers poor versus good job/career availability. During a 2011 <i>PBS NewsHour</i> appearance, Vedder argued American society must “open up opportunities for people to consider a variety of different options after high school, one of which is college, but there are many others.”  </p>
<p>Most of us may not agree with those advocating total clemency for student loan debt. While this solution may be overly simplistic and impractical, it seems clear that some reforms are necessary – whether the efficiencies proposed by Obama, the incentives proposed by Clarke, or Vedder’s more draconian measures toward higher education in general. It also means we need to give OWS protestors and other loan forgiveness advocates more credit for identifying a real, substantive, and systemic problem beyond their selfish interests.  </p>
<p>If we value an education for our children as much as we claim, our society has to find a way to re-engineer it back from the crushing burden it has become to more of the opportunity we aspire it to be. Right now, the main thing we are teaching our kids is learning to owe. This is neither opportunity nor American exceptionalism. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/12/learning-to-owe.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sallie Mae couldn&#8217;t have predicted&#8230;Model Validation Part 3</title>
		<link>./../../2008/04/sallie-mae-couldnt-have-predicted-model-validation-part-3.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/04/sallie-mae-couldnt-have-predicted-model-validation-part-3.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2008 21:43:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[model validation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[student loans]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/04/sallie-mae-couldnt-have-predicted-model-validation-part-3.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Higher Ed Watch reports on Sallie Mae: Last week, we wrote that Sallie Mae and its promoters on Wall Street claim the company was &#8220;blind-sided&#8221; by the rising default and delinquency rates on subprime private loans it made to low-income and working class students at poor performing higher education trade schools. It&#8217;s a convenient argument [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_RPTAaOI4RN8/R-0X9URkFyI/AAAAAAAAAH4/BeNE7jMpwWk/s1600-h/sallie_mae_red_flags2_0.png"><img alt="" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_RPTAaOI4RN8/R-0X9URkFyI/AAAAAAAAAH4/BeNE7jMpwWk/s320/sallie_mae_red_flags2_0.png" border="0"></a><br /><a href="http://www.newamerica.net/blog/higher-ed-watch/2008/blind-sided-sallie-mae-2885">Higher Ed Watch</a> reports on Sallie Mae:</p>
<blockquote><p>Last week, <a href="http://www.newamerica.net/blog/blog/higher-ed-watch/2008/class-action-lawsuit-challenges-sallie-mae-s-subprime-lending-practices-2589" target="_blank">we wrote that Sallie Mae and its promoters on Wall Street claim the company was &#8220;blind-sided&#8221; </a>by the rising default and delinquency rates on <a href="http://www.newamerica.net/blog/higher-ed-watch/2008/subprime-mess-reaches-higher-ed-1823" target="_blank">subprime private loans it made to low-income and working class students</a> at poor performing higher education trade schools. It&#8217;s a convenient argument considering that the loan giant is facing at least one, and possibly several, class action lawsuits by angry shareholders who accuse the company of deliberately misleading them about the amount of risk it was assuming. But the argument is disingenuous at best.<br />Financial analysts have long raised red flags about Sallie Mae&#8217;s private lending practices. During earnings calls and at shareholder meetings and investment conferences, analysts regularly peppered Sallie Mae officials with questions about whether the company, which is used to having government backing on its loans, had the expertise needed to assess the risks associated with lending unsecured, private loan debt to financially-needy students.<br />&#8230;.<br />In 2005, Fortune Magazine brought attention to the analysts&#8217; worries in an article entitled, <a href="http://money.cnn.com/magazines/fortune/fortune_archive/2005/12/26/8364649/index.htm" target="_blank">&#8220;When Sallie Met Wall Street.&#8221; </a>That piece specifically raised concerns about the loan company&#8217;s dealings with schools owned by Career Education Corporation, which it noted had had been accused &#8220;in multiple lawsuits in several states of using hard-sell tactics to recruit students, promising them high-paying jobs that don&#8217;t materialize and leaving them with mountains of debt that they can&#8217;t pay off.&#8221;<br />The article&#8217;s author &#8212; Bethany McLean (who, by the way,<a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A64769-2002Jan17.html" target="_blank"> helped break the Enron scandal</a>) &#8212; proved prescient in predicting the predicament in which Sallie Mae now finds itself. McLean wrote:<br />[A] big question looms in Sallie Mae&#8217;s private credit business: How many students who take out these high-interest loans will end up defaulting? After all, private credits are basically unsecured loans to people without jobs. Sallie argues that there won&#8217;t be a problem. Each quarter it books a reserve for potential losses; at this time its loss on private credit loans in repayment are running at only 2.4%. Plus, Sallie says, almost half its private credit loans are guaranteed by a parent.<br />But because private credit is a new business and because students are taking on unprecedented levels of debt, there are no historical measurements by which to gauge potential defaults. As Sallie&#8217;s financials note, &#8220;the provision for loan losses is inherently subjective as it requires material estimates that may be susceptible to significant changes.&#8221; And the current low delinquency rate may be misleading, because as of the end of 2004 nearly half the students to whom Sallie has lent private money hadn&#8217;t left school yet.</p></blockquote>
<p>Lots of financials are changing.</p>
<p>Update:  PGL posted on <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/angrybear.blogspot.com/2007/01/student-loans-and-default-risk.html">Student loans and default risk</a> in January, 2007.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/04/sallie-mae-couldnt-have-predicted-model-validation-part-3.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
