<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Romneycare &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The Binders That Bind</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/the-binders-that-bind.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/the-binders-that-bind.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 17 Oct 2012 17:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Andrea Mitchell]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[binders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obamacare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[oil drilling leases and permits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Romneycare]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/the-binders-that-bind.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The most revealing moment last night came as Ann Romney walked toward her husband onstage at the end.  That expression on her face.  I thought she looked like a woman in a binder. It is, I suppose, poetic justice for Romney that an obviously misspoken phrase of that sort is the catch phrase from last [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div></div>
<div>The most revealing moment last night came as Ann Romney walked toward her husband onstage at the end.  That expression on her face.  I thought she looked like a woman in a binder.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>It is, I suppose, poetic justice for Romney that an obviously misspoken phrase of that sort is the catch phrase from last night.  But the phrase, while generating <a href="http://www.politico.com/politico44/sidecar/2012/10/nkingofdc-138734.html">hilarious witticisms</a>, is not the reason why Romney won’t recover.  Instead, it is the binders that Romney has placed <i>himself</i> in that surely became clear to many of his new-found fans of the last two weeks—the binders that underlie his entire campaign. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Most significantly, in my opinion, that his tax plan is, rather than the new math—as he’s been claiming—actually is <i>no</i> math. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And that he takes contradictory positions at the same time—starkly, last night, for example, that he’s proud that because of him, virtually everyone in Massachusetts has healthcare insurance, yet Obamacare must be repealed because it’s keeping employers from hiring.  (There were others that surely became clear to a lot of people, but this one just bowled me over, because he said these two things within a few minutes of each other.)
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And—yes; finally!—that he habitually plucks statistics out of their context and misrepresents their meaning, although the most clearly illustrative one was one that Obama wasn’t able to make fully clear last night because of time constraints on his reply to Romney’s allegation.  It will be easy for him to do so now, though.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>That statistic: Romney’s claim that Obama has reduced oil production from drilling on federal lands by 14% by denying drilling permits and leases.  Romney first claimed, falsely, that there has been a 14% reduction in oil production from drilling on federal lands <i>since Obama took office</i>.  After Obama repeatedly interjected that that was false and that the level of that oil production actually had <i>increased</i> during his administration, Romney finally qualified his claim; production had decreased by 14% <i>over the past year</i>.
</p>
</div>
<div><a name="more"></a></div>
<div>I loved it that Obama stepped forward—literally—and explained that the leases and permits that his administration had revoked were ones that the leaseholders and permit holders <i>had not been using</i>, and that <i>that was the reason</i> for the revocations; he wanted the leases and permits to be reissued to others, who would <i>use</i> them.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>That was a great moment, albeit one that probably won’t get much attention.  But even more important is that, as Andrea Mitchell explained during the NBC recap and analysis, the 14% reduction occurred (as Romney finally acknowledged) only in the last year—and that the <i>reason</i> for the drop was … a fire at, and consequent shutdown, of a major refinery in Texas!  And, even with that 14% drop in the last year, production from drilling on federal lands <i>has increased more than 10% since Obama took office. </i>
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I think the Obama campaign should do an ad on this, saying that apparently Romney <i>thought it was Obama administration policy to have a fire at a major refinery</i>.  And that Romney’s so inept at math that he doesn’t know the difference between a 10% increase and a 14% decrease.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The public will get the point.  Romney is trying to game them. Not a particularly attractive trait in a presidential candidate.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>But one misuse of a statistic by Romney came earlier in the debate, and it downright <i>shouted</i> sophistry, thanks to Obama’s unmasking of it: Romney’s comparison of gas prices in January 2009 and gas prices now.  When Obama pointed out why gas prices were so low when he assumed office—and why they’ve doubled since then—I <i>knew</i> Obama would win the debate.  And when, later, during the discussion of the policy similarities between G.W. Bush’s policies and Romney’s proposed ones, Obama cleverly said Romney probably would send gas prices falling, by crashing the economy and thus lowering demand for oil, I thought then that Obama won the election last night.  </div>
<div></div>
<div>And in the light of today, I’m pretty sure of it.</div>
<div>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Binders.  Indeed.
</p>
</div>
<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/the-binders-that-bind.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>As Goes Obamacare, So Goes Romneycare … and State Laws Requiring Auto Insurance?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/03/as-goes-obamacare-so-goes-romneycare-and-state-laws-requiring-auto-insurance.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/03/as-goes-obamacare-so-goes-romneycare-and-state-laws-requiring-auto-insurance.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Mar 2012 19:07:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[ACA litigation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lyle Denniston]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obamacare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Romneycare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Supreme court]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/03/as-goes-obamacare-so-goes-romneycare-and-state-laws-requiring-auto-insurance.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I’ve written repeatedly now on AB that the challenge to the constitutionality of the ACA’s minimum-coverage provision (a.k.a., the individual-mandate provision) is not really a Commerce Clause challenge but instead a challenge under the Fifth Amendment’s due process clause, under what is known as the “substantive due process” constitutional law doctrine.  The Fifth Amendment’s due [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>I’ve written repeatedly now on AB that the challenge to the constitutionality of the ACA’s minimum-coverage provision (a.k.a., the individual-mandate provision) is not really a Commerce Clause challenge but instead a challenge under the Fifth Amendment’s due process clause, under what is known as the “substantive due process” constitutional law doctrine.  The Fifth Amendment’s due process clause limits what the federal government can do <i>vis-à-vis</i> individuals.  A clause in the Fourteenth Amendment is nearly identical, and identical in substance, to the Fifth Amendment’s due process clause, except that it limits what state governments can do <i>vis-à-vis</i> individuals.  
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>SCOTUSblog’s Lyle Denniston’s <a href="http://www.scotusblog.com/2012/03/argument-recap-it-is-kennedys-call/#more-141900">early report</a> suggests that I was right.  The outcome of the case, he predicts, will depend on whether Kennedy believes that the Court can uphold the mandate provision without opening the door to unlimited congressional mandating of purchase specific things, not because Congress lacks that power under the Commerce Clause but instead because it violates liberties protected under the Fifth Amendment’s due process clause. Denniston does not mention the Fifth Amendment, but, whether or not the justices themselves did specifically, that is the upshot.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The “substantive due process” doctrine holds that there are certain incursions into personal autonomy and certain impositions on individual liberty beyond which the Constitution allows the government to go.  It is this doctrine by which the Court has stricken down such laws as state laws barring the sale and use of contraceptives, state laws prohibiting abortion under all circumstances (<i>Roe v. Wade</i>),  and state laws criminalizing sodomy.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>But based on Denniston’s early report about the nature of Kennedy’s concerns, I don’t see how, absent an utterly artificial Commerce Clause-based ruling, a ruling that the mandate unconstitutionally infringes upon person choice, upon personal liberty, would not also mean that Massachusetts’s “Romneycare” law, and state laws that  require drivers to purchase auto insurance, would be constitutionally permissible. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Kennedy likes to wax eloquent, as he did last year in an opinion in a case called <i>Bond v. United States</i>, about how divisions of power among various governments—by which he means state governments vs. the federal one—protect individuals from tyranny. (He&#8217;s usually less interested in constitutional checks than on balances to state power—especially to state-court power—but that&#8217;s another subject.)  In <i>Bond</i>, he said, rightly, in my opinion, that a person indicted under a federal criminal law has legal “standing” (the legal right) to argue that the federal statute unconstitutionally infringed upon an area of criminal law reserved solely for the states to address, because the federal statute impinged (literally, in that case) <i>her</i> personal freedom.  So if the problem with the insurance mandate is that it exceeds Congress’s authority under the Commerce Clause, then a ruling that the ACA, a federal statute, is unconstitutional would not affect state statutes.</div>
<div>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>But that’s a separate issue from whether the mandate is an unconstitutional violation of personal liberty irrespective of whether or not the Commerce Clause power would allow Congress to enact the law.  And under the Court’s longtime Commerce Clause jurisprudence, Congress does have the authority to legislate the mandate to buy health insurance, given the impact on the healthcare market of the uninsureds’ usage of health care.  A ruling to the contrary would be transparently artificial. Which probably won’t matter to Kennedy.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212;-</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div><i>This will be cross-posted later today to the Firedoglake blog.</i>
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/03/as-goes-obamacare-so-goes-romneycare-and-state-laws-requiring-auto-insurance.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Why Romney Doesn’t Want A Canadian National Healthcare ID Card</title>
		<link>./../../2012/02/why-romney-doesnt-want-a-canadian-national-healthcare-id-card.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/02/why-romney-doesnt-want-a-canadian-national-healthcare-id-card.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2012 17:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Ann Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Beverly Mann]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Canadian National Healthcare ID card]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[David A. Fahrenthold]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obamacare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Romneycare]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/02/why-romney-doesnt-want-a-canadian-national-healthcare-id-card.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Romney’s best line of the day was unscripted. A stray Canadian had driven from Ontario to ask Romney a question and in the process joked that Romney could not have his ID card for Canada’s national health-care system. The ball sat on the tee for a long second before Romney hit it. “I don’t want [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>Romney’s best line of the day was unscripted. A stray Canadian had driven from Ontario to ask Romney a question and in the process joked that Romney could not have his ID card for Canada’s national health-care system.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The ball sat on the tee for a long second before Romney hit it. “I don’t want it!” Romney said. The crowd roared.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212; “<a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/two-michigan-rallies-reveal-romney-santorum-flaws/2012/02/21/gIQA5Sz9ZR_print.html">Two Michigan rallies revealRomney, Santorum flaws</a>,” David A. Fahrenthold, Washington Post, Feb. 25, reporting on a rally earlier that day in Shelby Township, Mich. (suburban Detroit)
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Hmm.  Well, okay.  Romney and his wife Ann, an MS victim, have about $220 million with which to pay their medical expenses. </div>
<div></div>
<div>But there’s another reason that they don’t need national medical insurance: They live in Massachusetts, and so, by law, <i>have</i> medical insurance, even though neither Romney nor Ann is employed and even though Ann has a serious medical condition the onset of which predates the end of their coverage through Romney’s last employer.  That law is known, among those who deride it, as “Romneycare.”
</p>
</div>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/02/why-romney-doesnt-want-a-canadian-national-healthcare-id-card.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
