<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>job piracy &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Job Piracy Marches on in Alabama</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/job-piracy-marches-on-in-alabama.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/job-piracy-marches-on-in-alabama.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2013 01:36:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[economic development]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[job piracy]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/job-piracy-marches-on-in-alabama.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Unmentioned in the recent Good Jobs First report on job piracy, it turns out that both relocation subsidies and retention subsidies are commonplace in Alabama. Greg Varner (@varnergreg) directs me to this report on how a Birmingham auto dealership, Serra Automotive, is demanding a multimillion incentive deal to keep it from relocating to another municipality [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Unmentioned in the recent <a href="http://www.goodjobsfirst.org/sites/default/files/docs/pdf/shellgame.pdf">Good Jobs First report</a> on job piracy, it turns out that both relocation subsidies and  retention subsidies are commonplace in Alabama. Greg Varner  (@varnergreg) directs me to <a href="http://www.al.com/opinion/index.ssf/2013/02/airbus_got_paid_to_play_serra.html">this report</a> on how a Birmingham auto dealership, Serra Automotive, is demanding a  multimillion incentive deal to keep it from relocating to another  municipality in the metro area. As <i>Birmingham News</i> columnist John Archibald tells the story:<br />
<blockquote>Across the Birmingham area cities spend tens of millions of dollars on incentives. Sadly, it is rarely to draw new opportunity or gain new blood. Instead we spill blood, as competition for existing businesses in the region pits city against city.  <br />It happens all the time.<br />Birmingham commits millions to steal a hospital from Irondale, and St. Clair sweetens a deal to lure a coffee maker out of Jefferson County. Birmingham outspends the suburbs to take a Walmart, and the escalation continues.<br />We love the smell of industrial recruitment in the morning. And it gets us frustratingly  nowhere.<br />We beat each other senseless. For a zero-sum game.<br />Because the city – the cities across the Birmingham area – pay to keep what they already have. Taxpayers lose and the region gains no jobs.</p></blockquote>
<p>Here we have an example of the intra-metro area <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2011/07/new-good-jobs-first-study-shows-micro.html">job piracy</a> that Good Jobs First covered in its <a href="http://www.goodjobsfirst.org/paidtosprawl">2011 report</a> on the Cleveland and Cincinnati metro areas, <i>Paid to Sprawl</i>.  It would be interesting to see if Birmingham shows the same tendencies  as those two regions, where most moves, even from one suburb to another,  put facilities further from the city center. My guess is that&#8217;s exactly  what we would find.</p>
<p>And I should emphasize, as the  most recent Good Jobs First study does, that the state of Alabama knows  how to put anti-piracy provisions in state subsidy programs. The very  first entry on p. 45 of <i>The Job Creation Shell Game</i> shows  Alabama&#8217;s Enterprise Zone Credit program as containing no-raiding  language. Since cities are legally the creation of states, it&#8217;s time for  Alabama to clip its cities&#8217; wings and force them to stop this  completely indefensible intra-state job piracy. The same holds true in  many other states.</p>
<p>Cross-posted from <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2013/03/job-piracy-marches-on-in-alabama.html">Middle Class Political Economist</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/job-piracy-marches-on-in-alabama.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Billions for job piracy even as states cut budgets</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/billions-for-job-piracy-even-as-states-cut-budgets.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/billions-for-job-piracy-even-as-states-cut-budgets.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2013 17:34:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Good Jobs First]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[job piracy]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/billions-for-job-piracy-even-as-states-cut-budgets.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[According to Center on Budget and Policy Priority data cited by Louise Story, in 2011 the states enacted $156 billion of austerity measures, between budget cuts and tax hikes. Despite their budgetary woes, however, this did not stop them from throwing billions of dollars a year into the worst kind of corporate subsidy, relocation incentives [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>According to Center on Budget and Policy Priority data cited by <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/12/02/us/how-local-taxpayers-bankroll-corporations.html?ref=louisestory&#038;_r=0">Louise Story</a>,  in 2011 the states enacted $156 billion of austerity measures, between  budget cuts and tax hikes. Despite their budgetary woes, however, this  did not stop them from throwing billions of dollars a year into the  worst kind of corporate subsidy, relocation incentives that move  existing facilities from one state to another without creating any new  jobs. A <a href="http://www.goodjobsfirst.org/sites/default/files/docs/pdf/shellgame.pdf">new report</a> from Good Jobs First documents their widespread use, which is <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2012/02/bad-trends-in-economic-development-weak.html">far more common</a> than most people would imagine.</p>
<p>One great aspect of this report is that it goes beyond the two examples of <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2011/07/new-good-jobs-first-study-shows-micro.html">interstate border wars</a> we hear the most about, New York-New Jersey-Connecticut and  Kansas-Missouri. We learn about Texas and Georgia vs. the world, North  Carolina-South Carolina (especially in the Charlotte metro area),  Tennessee-Mississippi (particularly with Memphis as target), and Rhode  Island-Massachusetts. In addition, we learn more about the flip side of  job piracy, retention subsidies, of which <a href="http://clawback.org/2012/02/20/sears-now-come-the-penalty-free-headquarters-layoffs/">Sears&#8217; two in Illinois</a> are the most egregious.</p>
<p>For  example, Continental Tire moved its North American headquarters and 320  jobs from Charlotte to Lancaster County, South Carolina, in 2009.  Georgia gave Ohio-based NCR Corp. (formerly National Cash Register) $109  million to relocate that same year. In 2010, Hamilton Beach received at  least $2 million to move from Memphis to Olive Branch, Mississippi,  while in 2009 McKesson received $4 million from Mississippi in addition  to local incentives to move from Memphis to neighboring DeSoto County.  Rhode Island, in a widely publicized move, gave Boston Red Sox pitcher  Curt Schilling&#8217;s video game company 38 Studios a $75 million loan to  move from Massachusetts in 2009, only to see the  firm go bankrupt in  2012. There are many more examples in the report, but you get the idea.</p>
<p>The  existence of relocation subsidies makes it possible for companies to  demand incentives to stay in a particular state, i.e., retention  subsidies. Two of the three largest ones went to Sears in Illinois, $168  million in 1989 and another $275 million in 2012 when the 1989 deal  expired. The second largest was $250 million to Prudential Insurance  from New Jersey in 2011. But many more states have had to shell out  retention subsidies on a regular basis.</p>
<p>The report  notes that at least 40 states know how to write no-raiding language into  their subsidy programs, because they already have such language banning  intra-state relocations from receiving subsidies under various  programs. However, as far as I know, far fewer states prevent their  cities from giving relocation subsidies to in-state firms, though the  report shows that Maine&#8217;s Employment Tax Increment Financing rules do  provide that.</p>
<p>What is necessary, the report argues and I  wholeheartedly agree, is that states need to tweak their program  language to stop rewarding interstate job relocation as well. They need  to stop efforts to directly poach existing firms, something Texas is  heavily engaged in. The report says there is a &#8220;possible&#8221; federal role  here, to withhold some Department of Commerce monies from states that  engaged in job piracy. I, on the other hand, think that federal action  is the only way it will happen. As I&#8217;ve <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2011/07/new-good-jobs-first-study-shows-micro.html">written before</a>,  voluntary state efforts in the 1980s and 1990s to end job piracy have  been utter failures, and the states clearly need an outside enforcement  mechanism, which can only be provided by the federal government.</p>
<p>With  such extensive documentation of how widespread relocation and retention  subsidies are, hopefully more people can be mobilized to get the  federal action we need.</p>
<p>Cross-posted from <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/">Middle Class Political Economist</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/billions-for-job-piracy-even-as-states-cut-budgets.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
