<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>top 1% &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Ok class, let&#8217;s review before the exam (election)</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/ok-class-lets-review-before-the-exam-election.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/ok-class-lets-review-before-the-exam-election.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2012 15:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2012 elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income equality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[labor economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax cuts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax policy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[top 1%]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[voting]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/ok-class-lets-review-before-the-exam-election.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I&#8217;m sure you are all feeling kind of blah. You have this final exam for this session and I can tell by your performances on the quizzes that you are still confused. The problem solving portions of the quizzes have been very telling. So lets review. You&#8217;re taxes are not too high. It&#8217;s your income [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>I&#8217;m sure you are all feeling kind of blah.  You have this final exam for this session and I can tell by your performances on the quizzes that you are still confused.  The problem solving portions of the quizzes have been very telling.  So lets review.   </div>
<div>  </div>
<div></div>
<div>You&#8217;re taxes are not too high.  It&#8217;s your income that is too low!  Remember this and you will be able to solve enough of the problems to obtain a passing grade and graduate.  And class, no one running today for president gets this.  It is why President Obama looked like such a dufus in the debate.  Romney took a step to his left&#8230; right into Obama&#8217;s policy space.  Where does one go to gain more space when they have walled up the door to the left of them as President Obama has?</div>
<div></div>
<div>Let&#8217;s get something real clear from the beginning.  Unless you are acquiring the majority of your money from money  YOU ARE NOT<a href="https://www.google.com/#hl=en&#038;output=search&#038;sclient=psy-ab&#038;q=define+capitalist&#038;oq=define+&#038;gs_l=hp.1.0.35i39j0l3.735.1657.0.3579.7.6.0.0.0.0.219.938.0j5j1.6.0.les%3B..0.0...1c.1.VPyK4hyLvzM&#038;pbx=1&#038;bav=on.2,or.r_gc.r_pw.r_qf.&#038;fp=f2b10cd80850d317&#038;biw=1024&#038;bih=600" target="_blank"> A CAPITALIST</a> </div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>Second: A MARKET IS NOT AN ECONOMY.</div>
<p><a name="more"></a>
<div></div>
<div>You my fellow students, are citizens living in a particular social structure that can be understood by various groupings of all human interaction that takes place within.  The largest grouping is “society”.    Yes, there is the ultimate grouping known as the human race, but I&#8217;m keeping this discussion and exam limited to the USA society.  (If you pass, you will get to tackle the larger human race grouping in your graduate studies.)  An economy is one such organizational grouping of activity.  A democracy is another.   A “market” is only a labeling of activity.  It is one of many relational activities within an economy and/or a democracy within a society.  An election is another such activity. </div>
<div></div>
<div>Now, this is very important: THERE IS NO HIEARCHY of the various groupings.  There can&#8217;t be.  It&#8217;s impossible as the groupings are not determinate of life and living.   I will tell you that my physiology professor stated that the determinate of life is a membrane.  So, let&#8217;s get off the “market” kick.  Trust me, “market” will not be an answer on the exam.   </div>
<div></div>
<div>If you are not a citizen capitalist, then you are a citizen laborer.  (These are descriptive labels that are not all inclusive of your potential grouping.)   You are acquiring your money mostly via your labor.  Physical labor, cognitive labor  it does not matter because you are using some ratio of both to acquire your money.  You are expending your labor to your personal level of comfort.  Note, I did not say you are expending your labor to the level of market ability or market possibility.  Your labor does not determine your comfort.  Your labor is not interpretative of your comfort.  It is having obtained your level of desired comfort (comfort as defined by you) that will have determined your labor expended.   </div>
<div></div>
<div>Society ultimately determines your value which is based on what society deems of value to it.  Now I know you are thinking I&#8217;ve really put my foot in it here.  I haven&#8217;t.  The market does not determine your value.  The collective of “society” does determine your value and the collective is dynamic though I am not implying any particular velocity of dynamism.  I am not quantifying or qualifying the dynamism.  Elections do the determining.  </div>
<div></div>
<div>Now that we are all on the same page, let me repeat myself: YOUR TAXES ARE NOT TOO HIGH.</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>Your income is too low and no one running for president sees your relationship in this economy in this way.  They don&#8217;t see it because not enough of you see it this way either.  To many are acting as if they are capitalists.  To many are acting as if the market is determinate.  Who the hell is in control here?  YOU or the market?   </div>
<div></div>
<div>So, let me explain your current condition and thus in doing so provide you with what the goal needs to be of any policy (and a focus of your essay) that either of the two presidential candidates propose.  It is working the goal that will allow you to obtain the highest grade on the exam.  Hell, let&#8217;s include the congressional candidates also. They make proposals all the time.  Understand the goal and how you acquire your money and the essay portion (voting) will be a snap.  Original thinking combined with the greatest inclusiveness will get a higher grade.</div>
<div></div>
<div>You are living in the median household.  I know this because, class&#8230; say it with me: I am not a capitalist.   </div>
<div>In 1976 your household had the median income of $12,690.   </div>
<div></div>
<div>Using the magic of the <a href="http://www.measuringworth.com/m/calculators/uscompare/%20" target="_blank">Measuring Worth</a>site  (it is the  only calculator allowed for your final) your household in 2011 has grown to $52,200.00 based on the skilled labor value.   Notice, we are not using the skilled capitalist value (there is none listed).</div>
<div></div>
<div>Unfortunately for you, the census states that your household actually has only $50,054 of income.  The difference of $2146 is the results of your labor not being valued as much as it was in 1976.  Society has decided that what ever it is you are doing it is not of such value as it was in 1976.  In fact, your value is so little that it did not even keep up with inflation.  How ya feeling about that?</div>
<div></div>
<div>Still thinking it&#8217;s that your taxes are too high?   </div>
<div></div>
<div>Well class, here&#8217;s the real pain: $61,629.00.*   This is the number that you would have if society had just kept the dynamics as they were.   For the sensitive students, unfortunately the ever dynamic society just didn&#8217;t keep the same flaming intensity of love for you as it now cherishes for the capitalist.   Sorry class.  Society has changed.  It values the capitalist more.  Thus, society has changed the economy so that the market activities result in more of the income produced going to the capitalist.  Society did this to you.  </div>
<div></div>
<div>Have I made this personal enough for you?  (Remember&#8230;the essay.)   Just in case I haven&#8217;t, recall the earlier part of this review.  You are a part of a collective group called “society”.  </div>
<div></div>
<div>Let&#8217;s recap:  Society.  You are a part of society.  Society is dynamic.  Elections determine.  You are not a capitalist.  &#8220;Economy&#8221; is a grouping.  &#8220;Market&#8221; is not an answer.  Your taxes are not to high.  Your income is to low.    </div>
<div></div>
<div>Here is the major essay question:  <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Fgjfi1DU1mQ" target="_blank">What do you want from life</a>?  I look for original thought and inclusiveness.   Bonus points if you can relate it all to the preamble of the USA societal organizing document.I remove points for facts supported by opinion.</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>*As calculated by using the ratio of the share of income for the non capitalist to capitalist  in 1976 to the time period of around now (like today).</div>
<div></div>
<div>$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>I have published on this confusion many times.  My <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2007/01/how-money-is-made-post-by-divorced-one.html" target="_blank">very first post</a> was on this subject.  Most specifically <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2009/02/more-kissing-income-inequality.htm" target="_blank">here,</a></div>
<div></div>
<div>and <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2008/09/class-war-appropriateness-of-wealthys.html" target="_blank">here</a> and <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2009/01/lets-kiss-income-inequality.html" target="_blank">here</a>.</div>
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/ok-class-lets-review-before-the-exam-election.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Screw the Clinton tax rates. Lets party like it&#8217;s 1936!</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/screw-the-clinton-tax-rates-lets-party-like-its-1936.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/screw-the-clinton-tax-rates-lets-party-like-its-1936.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 28 Jul 2012 05:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Bush tax cuts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income equality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[marginal rates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax rates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[top 1%]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/screw-the-clinton-tax-rates-lets-party-like-its-1936.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Update: *Additional numbers added Digby wrote a few days ago about the“grown-up” people coming to town to save America from the deficit. She listed a few of those people and their annual income. Also, a few days ago the Senate had a vote on the tax cuts. Letting the Bush cuts go (I&#8217;m all for [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div></div>
<div>Update: *Additional numbers added </p>
<p>Digby wrote a few days ago about<a href="http://digbysblog.blogspot.com/2012/07/the-grown-ups-are-planning-coup.html"> the“grown-up” people</a> coming to town to save America from the deficit.  She listed a few of those people and their annual income.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Also, a  few days ago the Senate had a vote on the tax cuts.  Letting the Bush cuts go (I&#8217;m all for it and we can stop the payroll tax cut too as it is all stupid policy when the problem is declining wages/income going to labor) will return us to the Clinton years rates.  People have noted just how little such a rise means to those at the top.     </div>
<div></div>
<div>Well, in keeping with my define rich series and my series looking at the purpose of taxation, I thought wouldn&#8217;t it be interesting to see just what these 1%&#8217;ers might be paying if we went back to the beginning of the last great period of <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/03/defining-rich-vi-1936-tax-tables.html">mass prosperity:  1936</a>.   </div>
<div></div>
<div>Yes indeedy, I say go for the brass ring.  Let&#8217;s show our maturity and actually implement the lesson learned from our history, that period from around <a href="http://www.taxhistory.org/www/website.nsf/Web/THM1901?OpenDocument">1906 to 1932</a> and then 1936 to 1979.   </div>
<div></div>
<div>While we&#8217;re at it, let us stop pretending that global trade is something new with an unknowable to man exotic force that we just have to accept as part of the expression of our DNA.   There is RNA also (look it up).</div>
<div></div>
<p><a name="more"></a>
<div></div>
<div>The following  numbers are based on the gross incomes Digby listed.  Thus we&#8217;ll have to keep in mind that there have been no adjustments made for deductions in my calculations.  So in truth, the tax paid would be less and the purchasing power of the actual non-adjusted income would be much greater.  After all, the deductions represent benefits received from the income that was deducted including the government handout in the form of reduced taxes for various activities taken with one&#8217;s income.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Here is what it looks like:</div>
<div><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-1cMkNPATmc8/UBN2YVEaQKI/AAAAAAAAASw/WiV0pUMcLRU/s1600/Party+like+it+1936+income+tax+chart.jpg" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="177" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-1cMkNPATmc8/UBN2YVEaQKI/AAAAAAAAASw/WiV0pUMcLRU/s320/Party+like+it+1936+income+tax+chart.jpg" width="320"></a></div>
<div>All these men managed to hit the top marginal rate of 79%.  Not one of them paid that amount.  Notice how flat the percentage paid becomes.  They want a flat tax, the got it.  They just had to really, really perform to get to that level of tax nirvana in 1936.  They couldn&#8217;t just pull a <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0102609/">Lawrence Garfield</a>, or should I say a Romney?  They couldn&#8217;t just negotiate payment in stock, whack labor costs to increase the stock value, take that money and buy it&#8217;s competitors to the point of oligopoly and then move on.  They could not just raid a solid company like New England Wire and Cable turning all the assets into cash at the expense of all the other relationships such a company had and justify it by saying “I make you money”.  Greenmail?  Junk Bonds?</div>
<div></div>
<div>I wrote <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/07/wages-driven-down-now-relative-to.html">about Caterpillar </a>and their approach to negotiating with the commodity of labor.  The average yearly income of the labor was $55,000/year.  The multiples of the above net income range from 24.8 to 147.38.  (* Multiples of the gross incomes range from 104.6 to 688.)</div>
<div></div>
<div>Granted, what&#8217;s left for these gentlemen would not allow the purchase of a new Cessna Citation X, but there was a 1999 listed for $5,950,000 when I search google.  I think Mr. Sherill could afford the monthly payment on this.  Though <a href="http://www.cessna.com/citation/mustang.html">Cessna is offering the 4 passenger</a> (the X is 12 passenger) at 0% interest for the first 12 months and Wiki says they list for only $2.65 million!  You know, if buying used just curls your hair.</div>
<div></div>
<div>The point?  There is nothing with the 1936 marginal tax rates that these men can not have other than more of it.  Nothing.   Real grown-ups who developed the 1936 tax table new this along with a lot of other stuff related income how it is actually earned and it&#8217;s social effect.  All you have to do is<a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/03/defining-rich-vi-1936-tax-tables.html"> lookat the tables and graphs</a> to see that the marginal rates were not pulled out of selfish and self serving asses.  They had a desired results in mind, one of which was to prevent “economic royalists”.  I am confident the other desire was to take back rent collected from other peoples collective efforts in proportion to the lack of labor performed as one rises up the economic pyramid.    </div>
<div></div>
<div>Have you heard the one about job creation?  The one that asks: When was the last time a poor person gave you a job?  When was the last time a CEO 1%&#8217;er&#8217;s activity saved the human race?   Four people at least from 1928 to the patent granted in 1948 were involved in<a href="http://inventors.about.com/od/pstartinventions/a/Penicillin.htm"> bring penicillin to the point ofcommercial viability</a>. </div>
<div>It was one woman&#8217;s work that allowed the next step of developing additional antibiotics.  </div>
<div></div>
<div>When was the last time a CEO 1% er&#8217;s activity resulted in a leap of human progress?   I&#8217;m thinking of my favorite non-CEO/Banker/1% example of flight.  No, Gates and Jobs did not do it like the Wright Brothers did it.  </div>
<div></div>
<div>1936.  We responded in a way that attest to a time when we did learn from history and acted on lessons from history.</div>
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/screw-the-clinton-tax-rates-lets-party-like-its-1936.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
