<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Maureen Dowd &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>A Kiss From a Used-Car Salesman—and why it’s important to tie Romney’s “47%” comment directly to his Orwellian lies</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/a-kiss-from-a-used-car-salesman-and-why-its-important-to-tie-romneys-47-comment-directly-to-his-orwellian-lies.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/a-kiss-from-a-used-car-salesman-and-why-its-important-to-tie-romneys-47-comment-directly-to-his-orwellian-lies.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 07 Oct 2012 19:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dodd-Frank]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ezra Klein]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[George Orwell]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Dickerson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mao Tse-tung]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Maureen Dowd]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Krugman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/a-kiss-from-a-used-car-salesman-and-why-its-important-to-tie-romneys-47-comment-directly-to-his-orwellian-lies.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In a terrific article published on Friday, Slate’s John Dickerson asks: Which Mitt Romney DoYou Trust Most? Is he a cold-heartedconservative or a moderate Republican from Massachusetts? How can we know? As for the second of those three questions—Is he a cold-hearted conservative or a moderate Republican from Massachusetts?—I think there’s a third possibility.  I [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>In a terrific article published on Friday, Slate’s John Dickerson asks: <a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/politics/2012/10/mitt_romney_has_moved_from_being_the_conservative_gop_primary_winner_to_a_far_more_moderate_former_governor_of_massachusetts_.html">Which Mitt Romney DoYou Trust Most? Is he a cold-heartedconservative or a moderate Republican from Massachusetts? How can we know?</a>
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>As for the second of those three questions—Is he a cold-hearted conservative or a moderate Republican from Massachusetts?—I think there’s a third possibility.  I think he’s George Orwell.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Or, rather, that he’s <i>channeling</i> George Orwell.  Not Orwell, the person.  Orwell, the writer.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Orwell, of course, is most famous for his book <i>1984</i>, in which politicians and government officials say exactly the opposite of what they mean.  Thus, the term “Orwellian,” which is not limited to politicians’ statements, but which refers to the use of common language terms that have a fixed meaning, and using them to suggest exactly the opposite of what those terms actually mean—and exactly the opposite of what the speaker does mean.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Up means down, left means right, black means white.  You get the picture.  Some people will think that when you say “up,” you mean “up.”  Others will understand that when you say “up,” you mean “down.”  It’s sophistry, con artistry. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>It’s also a key tactic that dictators use to gain or keep power.  Hitler, of course, used it routinely.  But so did Mao Tse-tung.  In fact, another word for “Orwellian” was, during the Mao era, “Mao Speak.”  You just change the definition of common words to mean exactly the opposite of what the words have meant.  That way, you can continue to claim that you’re doing something in particular, or will do something in particular, when you’re actually doing or planning to do the opposite.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>In democracies, when politicians do that, it has another synonym: lie.  Or at least that’s been so until now.  On Wednesday night, Romney changed the meaning of many words and phrases so that they mean the opposite of what they have meant.  Not the least are the words “win” and “debate,” at least as the former normally is applied to the latter, although it was largely the news media that redefined “win,” and of course Jim Lehrer helped with the redefinition of “debate.”
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>But another word that underwent a quick transition Wednesday night from its normal meaning to the opposite of it is “plan.”  As in, he has a plan to cover preexisting medical conditions.  The word “plan” normally means, y’know, a recommendation or intention to <i>change</i> something from its current status.  The phrase “a plan to cover preexisting medical conditions” normally means a requirement that insurance companies provide medical insurance to people who have preexisting medical conditions such as, say, multiple sclerosis or breast cancer, beyond what federal law already requires.  That is, beyond the status quo. </div>
<div><a name="more"></a></div>
<div>Which is that people who have, say, multiple sclerosis or a malignant breast tumor and have had no healthcare insurance within the previous three months can get treated at the emergency room, and then maybe file for bankruptcy if the hospital actually does provide, um, treatment for these medical problems.  Then again, Romney had redefined the word “treatment” even before the Wednesday debate, so I guess we now have to understand the phrase “medical treatment” <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/election-2012/wp/2012/09/24/romney-calls-emergency-room-a-health-care-option-for-uninsured/">to mean </a>something like, “But you have no insurance and you need the sort of medical procedure that isn’t <i>done</i> in emergency rooms.”  Romney already had redefined the word “plan” to mean promised goals rather than the specific, credible means of achieving them. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>But that redefinition had applied only to his economic plan—a plan that he said on Wednesday night might not work, and which—although it escaped the punditry—he seemed to be admitting that he (the successful businessman!) had devised without any actual economic basis for thinking that the revenue/tax-deduction ends could meet as designed.  But this second redefinition of the word “plan” was something else entirely, because by saying that he has a plan to provide healthcare insurance to people who currently are denied it because of a preexisting medical condition, he was telling them that he plans to something <i>specific</i> that he plans <i>not</i> to do.  And it concerns some truly fundamental things, in some cases life or death, in others financial security or instead financial devastation. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>What kind of person stands on a stage speaking to 67 million people, and just plain lies about something of <i>that</i> sort?  Dare I say it—the kind of person who speaks derisively about 47 percent of Americans, none of whom are Bain investors, have overseas bank accounts, hire PriceWaterhouseCoopers to tally their tax returns, and have their IRA accounts in the Cayman Islands.  Nor contribute to Republican PACs or attend Romney fundraisers in Boca Raton.  Or anywhere else.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Maureen Dowd, in her New York Times <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/10/07/opinion/sunday/dowd-two-presidents-smoking-and-scheming.html?_r=1&#038;hp">column today</a>, uses humor to run through many, but by no means all (she’s only allowed a limited number of words per column, after all), of Romney’s bald debate-“winning” lies.  And she includes the preexisting-medical-conditions one.  But I think it’s Paul Krugman who, in his Times column on Friday, titled “<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/10/05/opinion/krugman-romneys-sick-joke.html?partner=rssnyt&#038;emc=rss&#038;gwh=B7234187342E4EBEF3738D0F73F6A7FC">Romney’s Sick Joke</a>,” best highlights that this particular lie is particularly brazen and particularly pernicious.  And Ezra Klein <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/ezra-klein/wp/2012/10/05/romneys-pulling-up-the-ladder-behind-him/">points out</a> that Romney’s mendacity about his plan for healthcare coverage—and in this context it is indeed a plan, as that word is defined the old-fashioned way—runs even deeper. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>It’s been said, accurately, many, many times now that this election will determine the basic nature of American government.  But until now, that’s meant budgetary, taxing and regulatory policy.  It now means something even more fundamental, in addition: Whether or not we allow a redefinition of the word “democracy.”  Romney asks us to believe in America.  It turns out that he means an America of the sort that George Orwell feared.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Or at least one run by a used car salesman.  Read the fine print on that contract.  And on that separate warranty you’ll be charged for. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<p>A kiss <a href="http://www.law.com/corporatecounsel/PubArticleCC.jsp?id=1202573924603&#038;Regarding_DoddFrank_Romneys_Kiss_Isnt_Just_a_Kiss&#038;slreturn=20120907142437">is not a kiss</a> when it’s described as one by someone with a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Forked_tongue">forked tongue</a>.  
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/a-kiss-from-a-used-car-salesman-and-why-its-important-to-tie-romneys-47-comment-directly-to-his-orwellian-lies.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Richard Williamson and John Bolton are Jewish! Recent converts, apparently. [Updated.]</title>
		<link>./../../2012/09/richard-williamson-and-john-bolton-are-jewish-recent-converts-apparently-updated.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/09/richard-williamson-and-john-bolton-are-jewish-recent-converts-apparently-updated.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 17 Sep 2012 22:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[anti-Semitism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dan Senor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dylan Byers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Maureen Dowd]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Max Fisher]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romeny]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[neocons]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New York Times]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politico]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Williamson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Atlantic]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/09/richard-williamson-and-john-bolton-are-jewish-recent-converts-apparently-updated.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Are Richard Williamson and John Bolton—two of Romney’s three main foreign-policy advisors, and reportedly the two most influential—Jewish?  Really? Or are they simply under the influence of Dan Senor and other manipulative neocon Jews?  Sorta like Dick Cheney and Don Rumsfeld were. Oh, please. &#8212;- WARNING: Every word of the above post except the last [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>Are <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_S._Williamson">Richard Williamson</a> and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_R._Bolton">John Bolton</a>—two of Romney’s three main foreign-policy advisors, and reportedly the two most influential—Jewish?  <a href="http://www.politico.com/blogs/media/2012/09/maureen-dowd-meets-antisemitism-charge-135700.html">Really</a>?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Or are they simply under the influence of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dan_Senor">Dan Senor a</a>nd other manipulative neocon Jews?  Sorta like Dick Cheney and Don Rumsfeld were.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Oh, please.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212;-
</p>
</div>
<div>WARNING: Every word of the above post except the last two is said facetiously.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>But this is not: The Dylan Byers Politico post that I link to has this quote:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8220;[The] weirdest part of the anti-semitic tropes on the [Maureen] Dowd column is how lazy they are,&#8221; Max Fisher, an editor at The Atlantic who is leaving to launch a foreign policy blog at the Washington Post, <a href="https://twitter.com/Max_Fisher/status/247375581950402560">tweeted</a>.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Apparently, mimicking Mitt Romney’s pot-calling-the-kettle-black habit has become quite the thing this season among conservatives.  Or maybe Fisher <i>did </i>investigate and has learned that Williamson and Bolton really <i>have</i>converted to Judaism.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Oh, and by the way: I’m Jewish.  Happy <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/local/celebrating-rosh-hashanah/2012/09/16/f3a8cb8c-0045-11e2-9367-4e1bafb958db_gallery.html#photo=1">new year</a>.
</p>
<p>
<div>&#8212;&#8211;
</p>
</div>
<div>UPDATE: Much to my surprise, a link to this post appears on the Jewish American Heritage Month website, at <a href="http://www.jewishamericanheritagemonth.com/jewish/richard-williamson-and-john-bolton-are-jewish-recent-converts.php">http://www.jewishamericanheritagemonth.com/jewish/richard-williamson-and-john-bolton-are-jewish-recent-converts.php</a>.
</p>
</div>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/09/richard-williamson-and-john-bolton-are-jewish-recent-converts-apparently-updated.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rush Limbaugh Says Tax Money Pays For Students’ and Employees’ Jogging Pants As A Welfare Entitlement</title>
		<link>./../../2012/03/rush-limbaugh-says-tax-money-pays-for-students-and-employees-jogging-pants-as-a-welfare-entitlement.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/03/rush-limbaugh-says-tax-money-pays-for-students-and-employees-jogging-pants-as-a-welfare-entitlement.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 04 Mar 2012 18:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Beverly Mann]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bruce Webb]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dana Loesch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Forbes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Maureen Dowd]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rush Limbaugh]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sandra Fluke]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tim Worstall]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/03/rush-limbaugh-says-tax-money-pays-for-students-and-employees-jogging-pants-as-a-welfare-entitlement.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Seriously.  In the rambling press release that he self-styled an apology to Georgetown U. law student Sandra Fluke for calling her a slut and a prostitute, Limbaugh groused: Amazingly, when there is the slightest bit of opposition to this new welfare entitlement being created, then all of a sudden we hate women.  He then explained [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>Seriously.  In the rambling press release that he self-styled an apology to Georgetown U. law student Sandra Fluke for calling her a slut and a prostitute, Limbaugh groused:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Amazingly, when there is the slightest bit of opposition to this new welfare entitlement being created, then all of a sudden we hate women. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>He then explained his position thusly:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I personally do not agree that American citizens should pay for these social activities.  What happened to personal responsibility and accountability? Where do we draw the line? If this is accepted as the norm, what will follow? Will we be debating if taxpayers should pay for new sneakers for all students that are interested in running to keep fit?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>So even as late as yesterday afternoon when he released the statement, he’s claiming that <i>taxpayers</i>would be paying the part of employee and student healthcare premiums that cover contraceptives.  And that taxpayers pay for running pants, shorts and tank tops for employees and students who jog, but don’t pay for the Nikes and Reeboks. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>He apparently doesn’t read Angry Bear (see “Will ‘We’ Really Be Paying Sandra Fluke’s Healthcare Insurance Premiums?”, below.)  He should, though.  Dana Loesch, though, clearly does.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>What? You’ve never heard of Dana Loesch?  Well, you’re in good company.  Mine.  I’d never heard of her until this morning, when I read<a href="http://thecaucus.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/03/03/rush-limbaugh-apologizes-for-verbal-attack/"> the New York Times article</a>about Limbaugh’s statements.  The article says:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>At least one conservative commentator, Dana Loesch, appeared to back Mr. Limbaugh’s original sentiments, writing on Twitter on Saturday, “If you expect me to pay higher insurance premiums to cover your ‘free’ birth control, I can call you whatever I want.”
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>So, whatever the merits of her claim to a right to libel anyone whose medical insurance coverage and use raises “her” insurance premiums, Loesch at least does recognize the difference between private insurance premiums and coverage and taxpayer-funded welfare entitlements.  Limbaugh does not.   
</p>
</div>
<p>
<div>Happily, a mainstream media pundit understands this non-trivial distinction, too, and mentions it.  In her New York Times column today, Maureen Dowd <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/03/04/opinion/sunday/dowd-have-you-no-shame-rush.html">writes</a>:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>[Limbaugh] said insuring contraception would represent another “welfare entitlement,” which is wrong — tax dollars would not provide the benefit, employers and insurance companies would. And women would not be getting paid just “to have sex.” They’d be getting insurance coverage toward the roughly $1,000 annual expense of trying to avoid unwanted pregnancies and abortions, and to control other health conditions.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>So, AB readers, do you think Dowd reads AB?  Nah.  She probably figured it out all by herself. But Loesch probably reads AB.  Okay, or Forbes online. (<a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/timworstall/2012/03/03/rush-limbaugh-sandra-fluke-and-why-is-contraception-part-of-health-insurance-anyway/">Thanks for linking to it, Tim Worstall!)</a> For better or worse.  I mean, I’d hate to be, say, (as Bruce Webb points out in a comment to my earlier post) a skier or mountain climber who works for the same employer that Loesch does, or at least has the same insurance carrier that she has.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Wouldn’t want Loesch to accuse them of having murdered their mother, or something. 
</p>
</div>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/03/rush-limbaugh-says-tax-money-pays-for-students-and-employees-jogging-pants-as-a-welfare-entitlement.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
