<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>disaster relief &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The Public Learns Disaster Relief Was Etched Out of the Sketch. Uh-Oh.</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/the-public-learns-disaster-relief-was-etched-out-of-the-sketch-uh-oh.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/the-public-learns-disaster-relief-was-etched-out-of-the-sketch-uh-oh.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 29 Oct 2012 20:46:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Bill Keller]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[disaster relief]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Etch-A-Sketch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[FEMA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Matthew Yglesias]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New York Times]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/the-public-learns-disaster-relief-was-etched-out-of-the-sketch-uh-oh.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[MITT ROMNEY: &#8220;Every time you have an occasion to take something from the federal government and send it back to the states, that&#8217;s the right direction. And if you can go even further, and send it back to the private sector, that&#8217;s even better. Instead of thinking, in the federal budget, what we should cut, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>MITT ROMNEY: &#8220;Every time you have an occasion to take something from the federal government and send it back to the states, that&#8217;s the right direction. And if you can go even further, and send it back to the private sector, that&#8217;s even better. Instead of thinking, in the federal budget, what we should cut, we should ask the opposite question, what should we keep?&#8221;
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>DEBATE MODERATOR JOHN KING: Including disaster relief, though?&#8221;
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>ROMNEY: We cannot &#8212; we cannot afford to do those things without jeopardizing the future for our kids. It is simply immoral, in my view, for us to continue to rack up larger and larger debts and pass them on to our kids, knowing full well that we&#8217;ll all be dead and gone before it&#8217;s paid off. It makes no sense at all.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212; <i>Republican primary campaign debate last year
</p>
<p></i></div>
<div></div>
<div>Slate’s Matthew Yglesias points to that today <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/moneybox/2012/10/29/romney_s_fema_cuts.html">andcomments</a>:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>More prosaically, though the Romney campaign was understandably <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/10/28/mitt-romney-fema_n_2036198.html" target="_blank">circumspect over the weekend about his spending plans</a> the fact is that his overall budget requires sharp cuts in everything. The central issue is that Romney wants to cap government spending at 20 percent of GDP while boosting military spending to 4 percent of GDP and leaving Social Security harmless. That <a href="http://www.cbpp.org/cms/?fa=view&#038;id=3658" target="_blank">means a 34 percent across-the-board cut in other programs</a> according to the Center on Budget and Policy Priorities. Unless, that is, Medicare is also exempted from the cuts in which case you&#8217;d need a 53 percent cut. …
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>If a storm damages basic physical infrastructure (power lines, bridges) and imperils human life it would be the height of penny-wise, pound-foolish thinking to suppose that the afflicted area should wait months or years to repair the damage. Ultimately, anyplace is going to go back to robust wealth creation faster if basic stuff gets fixed up faster. But that requires financing by an entity capable of rapidly financing expensive projects—i.e., the federal government. Left to its own devices a storm-ravaged Delaware or Louisiana is going to be squeezed between balanced budget rules and falling sales tax receipts and be forced into an increasing state of dilapidation.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>How about a storm-ravaged <i>Florida</i>?  According to current polls, slightly more than half of Florida voters want their state to take over disaster relief, at least until arrangements can be made for the private sector to take it over.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And, about that question Romney asked: What should we KEEP?  Well, in addition to the Bush tax cuts for the wealthy and defense spending for private contractors, what DOES Romney think we should keep?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>We cannot – we cannot afford to do things like disaster relief without jeopardizing the future of our kids.  We CAN, though, afford to give massive additional tax cuts to the wealthy, and huge additional contracts to Republican defense contractors, without jeopardizing the future of our kids.  Right?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>What’s truly unconscionable is that it’s taking Hurricane Sandy to educate the public about the plans Romney and Ryan have stated so clearly.  I’ve been utterly unable to understand why the Obama campaign hasn’t been running video clips of Romney’s primary-campaign statements as the foundation of their ads.  I’ve thought all along that this is all Obama would need to do in order to win.  I think Sandy will prove me right.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And, here’s a shout-out to New York Time columnist Bill Keller for <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/10/29/opinion/keller-the-no-agenda-myth.html?_r=0">exposing for the absurd myth that it is</a> the punditry’s “in” refrain that we don’t know what either of the two candidates would use the office to do in the next four years, because, well, neither has specified sufficiently.  As Keller says, actually <i>both</i> have specified sufficiently. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And Romney’s <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/10/did-romney-begin-to-reverse-etch-sketch.html">already begun to reverse-sketch his etchings</a>.  Suffice it to say that he’s not spent the last week promising “BIG CHANGE” because he plans to etch out of his sketch all those primary-campaign promises. 
</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/the-public-learns-disaster-relief-was-etched-out-of-the-sketch-uh-oh.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Individualism vs. Collectivism: Thanks For the Ammunition, Ann</title>
		<link>./../../2012/08/individualism-vs-collectivism-thanks-for-the-ammunition-ann.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/08/individualism-vs-collectivism-thanks-for-the-ammunition-ann.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 15 Aug 2012 23:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Ann Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ayn Rand]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[crop subsidies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[disaster relief]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[James B. Stewart]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medicare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New York Times]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politico]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/08/individualism-vs-collectivism-thanks-for-the-ammunition-ann.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Ann Romney said in an interview airing Wednesday that her husband has no plans to release additional tax returns, saying “it’ll just give them more ammunition” and insisting that “there’s nothing we’re hiding.” “We have been very transparent to what’s legally required of us. But the more we release, the more we get attacked, the more [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>Ann Romney said in an interview airing Wednesday that her husband has no plans to release additional tax returns, saying “it’ll just give them more ammunition” and insisting that “there’s nothing we’re hiding.”
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>“We have been very transparent to what’s legally required of us. But the more we release, the more we get attacked, the more we get questioned, the more we get pushed. And so we have done what’s legally required and there’s going to be no more, there’s going to be no more tax releases given,” she said in the interview by NBC News. “And there’s a reason for that, and that’s because of how, what happens as soon as we release anything.”
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Romney is releasing two years of his tax returns. Democrats have said what’s he hiding and demanded he make public the last 10 years or more.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Ann Romney also defended Romney’s character and said the “only reason we don’t disclose more is we’ll just become a bigger target.”
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>“Mitt’s financial disclosures when he was governor are huge if people want to really look and see any question they have,” she said. “The other thing they have to understand is that Mitt is as honest — his integrity is just golden. We pay our taxes, we are absolutely — beyond paying our taxes we also give 10 percent of our income to charity.”
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>She also said that the couple has had a blind trust since 2002 before Romney was governor and that they don’t know what’s in it.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>“There’s nothing we’re hiding,” she said, later adding: “I’ll be curious to see what’s in there too.”
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>            &#8212; <i><a href="http://www.politico.com/news/stories/0812/79757.html?hp=l5">Ann Romney: No more tax returns</a></i>, Tomer Ovadia, Politico, today
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>An article published recently by James B. Stewart in the New York Times titled <i><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/08/11/business/in-the-superrich-clues-to-romneys-tax-returns-common-sense.html?pagewanted=all">In Superrich, Clues to What Might Be in Romney’s Returns</a></i>, overlooked because it was published on Saturday, the day on which Romney made his Ryan announcement, explains that 2008 and 2009 were banner tax-break years for a large number of very wealthy people whose main or entire source of income comes from stock dividends and the sale of securities. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The occasion for the article was the IRS’s release last week of “data from the 400 individual income tax returns reporting the highest adjusted gross income, writes Stewart. “This elite ultrarich group,” he says, “earned on average $202 million in 2009, the latest year available.  And buried in the data is the startling disclosure that six of the 400 paid no federal income tax.”
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Which suggestions the likelihood that the Romneys paid no, or almost no, income taxes for 2008 and 2009. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>It does not take a math genius or a tax expert to recognize this.  That’s good, because I am neither.  But I am good enough in math (if barely) to know that 2006, the last year of Romney’s term as governor, ended before 2008 began. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And, thanks to the Romney tax-returns controversy, I know that in 2009 the Department of Justice entered into an agreement with UBS, Switzerland’s largest bank, and other Swiss banks, in which the banks agreed to disclose to the U.S. government the identities of American holders of Swiss bank accounts, and that approximately 34,000 Americans took advantage of an amnesty program that the IRS and Justice Department offered, by which voluntary payment of back taxes and interest and penalties would remove criminal liability and public disclosure. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And I have followed the Romney tax story closely enough during the last few months to know that the Romneys’ 2010 tax returns revealed a bank account with UBS, apparently opened in 2003, was closed sometime during that year and had $3 million in it when it was closed.  And that, according to news reports, Romney did not disclose this account on his Massachusetts financial-disclosure forms—although, unless my math ability (such as it is) fails me, 2003 ended before early 2007, when Romney’s term as governor ended. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And that, also according to news reports, the 2010 returns show that the Romneys have a shell corporation in the tax haven of Bermuda into which they apparently were funneling income from overseas Bain investments, and that one day before Romney was sworn in as governor, the corporation’s shares were transferred to Ann Romney, and the corporation was not disclosed on Romney’s Massachusetts financial-disclosure forms.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>So, yes, Ann, you’re hiding something.  You’re hiding whatever it is that would give your opponent ammunition, whatever it is that would make your husband a bigger target.  And that ammunition is that, whether or not you and he failed to disclose that Swiss account and any other Swiss accounts you held that were closed before 2010 until a gun was held to your heads in 2009, you and he employed tax loopholes and special tax rates that your husband and (even more so) his running mate plan to expand so as to eliminate the very need for offshore tax shelters.  They plan to make this country an overt tax shelter for the wealthy and, especially, for the <i>very</i> wealthy—that is, for people like you and your husband. They have made that central to their policy plans, while desperately trying to deflect scrutiny of those proposals. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Stewart writes in his article, “Tax experts I consulted said these results almost certainly reflected aggressive use of tax-loss carry-forwards from 2008, since the stock market bottomed in March 2009 and rallied strongly during the rest of the year.”  Expressly under Paul Ryan’s plan, there will be no income tax at all on capital gains and on dividends.  <i>Every</i> year will be 2008 and 2009 for the Romneys!  Except, of course, for the need for aggressive use of tax-loss carry-forwards, and the like; no more need for that sort of thing.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>A lot of eyebrows were raised on Sunday when Ryan, sitting next to Romney in an interview, told Bob Schieffer that he wants to end the tax breaks that apply only to the wealthy.  That’s nice, but of no effect.  A seminal part of his tax-and-budget plan, passed this year by the House, is the elimination of <i>all</i> income taxes on capital gains and dividends.  And although this would mean that many very wealthy people will pay no income taxes or estate taxes, and many other very wealthy people would pay income taxes at a single-digit rate, the elimination of these taxes would apply as well to the non-wealthy who have a capital gain or receive stock dividends, however small.  And so—voila!—Ryan’s statement, made with such earnestness, does not apply to the issue of taxes on capital gains and dividends.  Nor, for that matter, to estate taxes, which his plan entirely eliminates; some non-wealthy people leave small estates, after all.  And semantics is the name of their game, the objective of which is the enabling of ever more vast accumulations of wealth, utterly unfettered by tax obligations.  Pure and simple.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>My big fear about the all-Medicare-all-the-time campaign that began last weekend with Romney’s Ryan announcement is that it allows Romney and Ryan to claim the mantle of straight talkers about what they warn is a Medicare-caused fiscal calamity that awaits.  They have yet to explain why, if they fear such a calamity, they propose to reduce federal revenue by trillions of dollars, through their tax-elimination-on-the-wealthy plan.  And when they stress, as they do again and again, that their destroy-Medicare-in-order-to-save-it plan will not end the current program for its current or relatively-imminent recipients (those who are 55 or older), maybe they’ll deign to reveal what programs will be eliminated in order to pay for Medicare for current recipients and baby boomers <i>and</i>—<i>and</i>—the trillions-of-dollars tax cuts for the wealthy.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>My suggestion: Hurricane disaster relief for the southern Atlantic and Gulf Coast states, which will vote for this ticket <i>en force</i>, and crop insurance and drought disaster relief for the plains states, which will vote for them and their budget plan in almost as large percentages. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>In 2005, Ryan now-famously advised his audience when he addressed an Ayn Rand fan club that they should make no mistake: current politics is a clash between “individualism” and “collectivism.”  And indeed it is.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Now, let’s ensure that the public knows the specifics.  
</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/08/individualism-vs-collectivism-thanks-for-the-ammunition-ann.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
