<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>currency pegs &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Retaliating Against Currency Manipulation: A Primer</title>
		<link>./../../2011/10/retaliating-against-currency-manipulation-a-primer.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/10/retaliating-against-currency-manipulation-a-primer.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2011 13:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[China]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[currency pegs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[IMF]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[trade balances]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WTO]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/10/retaliating-against-currency-manipulation-a-primer.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Kash at The Streetlight points us to other aspects of the world, touching upon the WTO and the IMF roles in global trade and China in particular: Retaliating Against Currency Manipulation: A Primer You&#8217;ve probably heard that this week the US Congress has been addressing the issue of how China controls its exchange rate with [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Kash at <em>The Streetlight</em> points us to other aspects of the world, touching upon the WTO and the IMF roles in global trade and China in particular:</p>
<p><a href="http://streetlightblog.blogspot.com/2011/10/retaliating-against-currency.html" target="'_blank">Retaliating Against Currency Manipulation: A Primer</a><br />
<blockquote>You&#8217;ve probably heard that this week the US Congress has been addressing the issue of how China controls its exchange rate with the US dollar. In particular, many have argued that China&#8217;s policy of only allowing the yuan (CNY) to appreciate very gradually against the dollar has kept Chinese products unreasonably cheap to American consumers, and American products unreasonably expensive to Chinese consumers. (See for example Paul Krugman&#8217;s column on <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/03/opinion/holding-china-to-account.html">Monday</a>.)</p></blockquote>
<p>And indicates a source worth reading:<br />
<blockquote><em>if you&#8217;re interested in more details regarding the legal options and implications of possible US retaliation against Chinese currency manipulation, you can&#8217;t do better than this paper by Jonathan Sanford of the Congressional Research Service: &#8220;<a href="http://digital.library.unt.edu/ark:/67531/metadc31498/m1/1/high_res_d/RS22658_2011Jan28.pdf">Currency Manipulation: The IMF and WTO</a>&#8220;.</em></p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/10/retaliating-against-currency-manipulation-a-primer.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>I side with China on this one</title>
		<link>./../../2010/02/i-side-with-china-on-this-one.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/02/i-side-with-china-on-this-one.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2010 11:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[China]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[currency pegs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[exchange rates]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/02/i-side-with-china-on-this-one.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Rebecca Wilder Yes, the renminbi (RMB) is closer to fair value. Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Ma Zhaoxu states: &#8220;Our currency, the RMB, has appreciated more than 20 percent against the U.S. dollar since July 2005, when China moved to a floating exchange rate regime,&#8221; Ma said. Before 2005, the RMB was pegged to the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Rebecca Wilder</p>
<p>Yes, the renminbi (RMB) is closer to fair value. Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman <a href="http://www.gov.cn/misc/2010-02/04/content_1528495.htm">Ma Zhaoxu states</a>:<br />
<blockquote>&#8220;Our currency, the RMB, has appreciated more than 20 percent against the U.S. dollar since July 2005, when China moved to a floating exchange rate regime,&#8221; Ma said. Before 2005, the RMB was pegged to the U.S. dollar at a fixed rate.</p>
<p>&#8220;The RMB exchange rate has drawn close to a reasonable and balanced level, given the international balance of payments and the market supply and demand for foreign exchange,&#8221; Ma said.</p></blockquote>
<p>The <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/02/05/world/asia/05diplo.html">New York Times</a> asserts that China&#8217;s currency is undervalued by 25%-40%. The NY Times, like many politicians and media channels, is entirely too obsessed with China&#8217;s exchange rate; they fail to understand that economic fundamentals are changing.</p>
<p>Contrary to popular belief, the level of the renminbi has become rather inconsequential to Chinese trade flows. Why? Because despite the fact that the renminbi has been pegged against the dollar since July of 2008, imports are surging.<br /><a name="more"></a><br /><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_Et4TQ-a0gGU/S23mU4w6ezI/AAAAAAAAC1Q/3b3rcLtgI5I/s1600-h/trade_trends.png"><img border="0" alt="" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_Et4TQ-a0gGU/S23mU4w6ezI/AAAAAAAAC1Q/3b3rcLtgI5I/s320/trade_trends.png"></a>The chart above illustrates the 3-month annualized growth rate in exports and imports and the renminbi valued against the US dollar. I use the 3-month annualized rate, rather than the year/year rate, to remove the strong base effects from the drop-off in trade last year.<br /><!-- more --><br />The first thing to notice is that while export growth is indeed strong, &#8220;business as usual&#8221; in China, import growth is surely breaking trend. The 3-month annualized growth rate of imports &#8211; a good proxy for domestic demand &#8211; averaged 117% annualized growth per month from April (when it turned positive) to December 2009. Compared to this period in 2006, annualized import growth is up almost 80 percentage-points, while that for exports is up just 5 percentage-points (76.2% average 3-month annualized growth in exports May-December 2009 vs. 71.7% in 2006).</p>
<p>It&#8217;s hard to argue that the Chinese currency is so &#8220;undervalued&#8221; if the import response is this strong.</p>
<p>Another myth is that China is running large current account surpluses. Given the chart above, it won&#8217;t surprise you to know that China&#8217;s current account has dropped markedly since late 2008.</p>
<p><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_Et4TQ-a0gGU/S23o39gQhqI/AAAAAAAAC1Y/fryzIwNzB5g/s1600-h/trade_balance.png"><img border="0" alt="" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_Et4TQ-a0gGU/S23o39gQhqI/AAAAAAAAC1Y/fryzIwNzB5g/s320/trade_balance.png"></a>The thing is: since prices in developed economies have dropped relative to those in key emerging markets (i.e., China), <a href="http://angrybear.blogspot.com/2010/01/inflation-in-china-is-not-necessarily.html">real exchange rates are coming back in-line</a> with a s0-called equilibrium. Therefore, the renminbi, by definition, is closer to whatever an equilibrium would be, despite the fact that it is fixed. Thus, like <a href="http://www.gov.cn/misc/2010-02/04/content_1528495.htm">Ma Zhaoxu</a> says, it&#8217;s at a &#8220;reasonable&#8221; value.</p>
<p>Rebecca Wilder</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/02/i-side-with-china-on-this-one.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
