<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>labor &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>&#034;The Treadmill and the Poor Law are in full vigour, then?”</title>
		<link>./../../2012/02/the-treadmill-and-the-poor-law-are-in-full-vigour-then.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/02/the-treadmill-and-the-poor-law-are-in-full-vigour-then.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2012 18:23:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[labor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[labor force participation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[labor markets]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[run 75441]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/02/the-treadmill-and-the-poor-law-are-in-full-vigour-then.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by run 75441 &#8220;The Treadmill and the Poor Law are in full vigour, then?&#8221; A Christmas Carol, Charles Dickens &#8220;That&#8217;s Baloney&#8221; stated Rep. Micky Hammon, R-Decatur, Alabama; the immigration bill cosponsor, told the Huntsville Times. &#8220;It&#8217;s clear the study over estimates the negative and under estimates the positive to skew the result toward an agenda,&#8221; [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by run 75441</p>
<p><strong>&#8220;<i>The Treadmill and the Poor Law are in full vigour, then</i>?&#8221; A Christmas Carol, Charles Dickens</strong></p>
<p>&#8220;<i>That&#8217;s Baloney</i>&#8221; stated Rep. Micky Hammon, R-Decatur, Alabama; the immigration bill cosponsor, told the Huntsville Times.</p>
<p>&#8220;<i>It&#8217;s clear the study over estimates the negative and under estimates the positive to skew the result toward an agenda</i>,&#8221; Hammon said. &#8220;<i>If 40,000 illegal workers leave the state, they free up jobs that homegrown Alabamians are happy to have.&#8221;</i> <br /> <a href="http://usnews.msnbc.msn.com/_news/2012/02/01/10290742-cost-of-alabama-immigration-law-disputed" target="_blank">The Cost of Alabama Immigration Law (H.B. 56) Disputed</a>.</p>
<p>&#8220;<i>Alabama has the lowest unemployment rate among seven southeastern states,&#8221;</i> the spokeswoman for Governor Robert Bentley said.</p>
<p>I recently completed a quip to Senator Levin of Michigan who was commenting on the fall of the unemployment rate in Michigan and his plan to jump on the deficit reduction bandwagon at the same time. I thought by now most states and the relative &#8220;<i>pols</i>&#8221; would know a drop in U3 state wide or nationally does not necessarily mean an increase in employment. If the Civilian Labor Force drops in numbers because people give up looking for work, than it is possible for U3 to decrease. This is precisely what has happened in Alabama.</p>
<p>&#8220;<i>People are dropping off unemployment rolls because they&#8217;ve become discouraged by not being able to find a job and have stopped looking, according to an analysis by Arise Citizens&#8217; Policy Project. Alabama&#8217;s labor force shrank by more than 6,000 workers in October, and the labor force has been shrinking since June. Economists say a shrinking labor force makes it easier for a state to post an unemployment rate decline, even if job growth is small.&#8221; &#8230;</i>&#8220;<i>Analysis shows a steep drop in the state&#8217;s unemployment rate isn&#8217;t because of Alabama&#8217;s overreaching immigration law&#8221;</i><br /><a href="http://blog.al.com/birmingham-news-commentary/2011/12/our_view_analysis_shows_a_stee.html" target="_blank">Birmingham News</a></p>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />It appears kicking the illegal immigrants out of Alabama doesn&#8217;t do much for getting people back to work. Maybe those UAW jobs which did not require more than a high school education and a good work ethic were not as bad as some Senators made them out to be?</p>
<p>&#8220;Are <i>there no prisons? Are there no workhouses</i>?” A Christmas Carol, Charles Dickens</p>
<p>It appears those students who went to Law School, shelled out $100,000 or more to get the exclusive Juris Doctorate, and as a result expected to make the big bucks. They were sadly disappointed when they could not find a job even with the best of credentials. So what does a newly minted attorney to do? Of course, sue the School of Law which they attended for false advertising.</p>
<p><i>&#8220;Adam Bevelacqua graduated from Brooklyn Law School last year with $100,000 in debt but high hopes for his future. He passed the bar on his first try in New York and had internships to highlight on his resume. And, according to his research, the school’s job placement rate for new graduates was between 90 to 95 percent. But Bevelacqua, 29, is no longer as optimistic.</i></p>
<p><i>“I’ve been looking for work ever since,” Bevelacqua told msnbc.com. “The jobs aren’t really there.”</i><br /><i>On Wednesday, Bevelacqua joined 50 other law school graduates from across the country who sued their alma maters, alleging they were misled about job prospects and burdened with huge amounts of student debt.&#8221;</i><br /><i><a href="http://usnews.msnbc.msn.com/_news/2012/02/02/10302339-law-schools-face-lawsuits-over-job-placement-claims" target="_blank">MSNCB News</a> Law schools face lawsuits over job-placement claims</i></p>
<p>The state of Alabama and Jefferson County are in need of good and cheap attorneys to defend the H.B. 56 law and to process Jefferson County&#8217;s bankruptcy. The going rate right now is $1 million per month or enough to fund a few attorneys. Maybe the law labour has to relocate and go to where the demand is? Any takers???</p>
<p><i>&#8220;Please Sir, I want some more.&#8221; </i>Oliver,&#8221; Charles Dickens</p>
<p>The Center for Progressive Studies Looks at  <a href="http://www.americanprogress.org/issues/2012/01/child_tax_credit_numbers.html">&#8220;<em>Immigrants and the Child Tax Credit&#8221;</em></a><em> </em><br />In order to fund the Payroll Tax Credit and instead of whacking the 1% of the taxpayers making > $500,000 annually; Congress has decided to whack the children of immigrants. Parents claiming a tax credit using the ITIN must now provide a Social Security number. Most likely, they do not have a legitimate SS number. Isn&#8217;t this like the feudal wars? Knights on horseback slaughtering the serfs and the peasants (Bruce?).</p>
<p><strong>Benefits of the Child Tax Credit</strong></p>
<p><a href="http://www.cbpp.org/cms/index.cfm?fa=view&#038;id=2989">2.3 million</a>: The number of people, including 1.3 million children, who were kept out of poverty by the child tax credit in 2009.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.treasury.gov/tigta/auditreports/2011reports/201141061fr.html">$1,800</a>: The average amount claimed in child tax credits by ITIN filers in 2010.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.cnpp.usda.gov/Publications/FoodPlans/2011/CostofFoodNov2011.pdf">3</a>: The number of months for which a family of four with two children could put food on the table using the average child tax credit refund under the Department of Agriculture’s “Thrifty Food Plan.”</p>
<p><a href="http://www.economy.com/dismal/article_free.asp?cid=224641&#038;tid=F0851CC1-F571-48DE-A136-B2F622EF6FA4&#038;src=MZ">$1.38</a>: The amount of economic growth that results from every $1 spent on child tax credits. Not all tax cuts are created equal, though. The payroll tax holiday results in $1.25 of economic growth for every $1 spent, while making the Bush tax cuts permanent would result in $0.35 per dollar.</p>
<p><a href="http://thinkprogress.org/justice/2011/12/15/389244/house-republicans-target-the-american-children-of-immigrants-in-punishing-payroll-tax-bill/">4 million</a>: The number of U.S.-born children whose families would be affected by the proposed offset.</p>
<p>20 percent: The amount of the payroll tax holiday extension that would be offset by raising taxes on lower-income immigrant parents of American children. The payroll tax holiday extension is worth $120 billion. The proposed legislation to offset the tax cut, however, will, by conservatives’ own calculations, save a total of only $24 billion over 10 years.</p>
<p><a href="http://immigrationimpact.com/2011/12/13/just-in-time-for-the-holidays-congress-moves-4-million-children-closer-to-poverty/">About $100 billion</a>: The amount of payroll taxes that will be contributed by ITIN filers over the next 10 years. These taxes contribute to the trust funds for Medicare and Social Security—programs from which immigrants will never recoup benefits because of their status.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.politico.com/news/stories/0112/71370.html">$21,240</a>: The average household income for ITIN filers claiming additional child tax credit refunds in 2010. This is less than half of the 2010 median household income in the United States of $49,445, and would mean that a family of four with two children was living below the poverty line. Latino children are more likely to be living in poverty than any other racial or ethnic group in the United States.</p>
<p>&#8220;<i>But injustice breeds injustice; the fighting with shadows and being defeated by them necessitates the setting up of substances to combat.&#8221;</i> <strong>Bleak House, Charles Dickens</strong>; February 7th . . . belated Happy Birthday!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/02/the-treadmill-and-the-poor-law-are-in-full-vigour-then.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>For the Ones Who Haven&#8217;t Been Stars Since Jeffrey Maier</title>
		<link>./../../2011/09/for-the-ones-who-havent-been-stars-since-jeffrey-maier.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/09/for-the-ones-who-havent-been-stars-since-jeffrey-maier.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2011 21:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[baseball]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[labor]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/09/for-the-ones-who-havent-been-stars-since-jeffrey-maier.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[(cross-posted from Skippy)]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>(cross-posted from Skippy)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/09/for-the-ones-who-havent-been-stars-since-jeffrey-maier.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Volunteering</title>
		<link>./../../2011/09/volunteering.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/09/volunteering.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2011 07:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[labor]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/09/volunteering.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Mike Kimel Can someone explain to me why people volunteer at for-profit hospitals? I can understand volunteering at a not-for-profit hospital, but how is volunteering at a for-profit hospital different from, say, volunteering at Exxon-Mobil or Wal-Mart?]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Mike Kimel</p>
<p>Can someone explain to me why people volunteer at for-profit hospitals?  I can understand volunteering at a not-for-profit hospital, but how is volunteering at a for-profit hospital different from, say, volunteering at Exxon-Mobil or Wal-Mart?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/09/volunteering.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Cost of Labor</title>
		<link>./../../2011/09/the-cost-of-labor.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/09/the-cost-of-labor.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2011 22:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[capital labor ratio]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[compensation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[human capital]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[labor]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/09/the-cost-of-labor.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The standard model of Economic Development is Romer’s (1989, JPE 1990) adaptation* of Solow’s (1956, 1957) Model.  Basically, became Y = AKα(HL)(1-α) where the H stands for “human capital,” which multiplies the ability of labor. (Think high-skills labor—construction work, plumbing, teaching—where the worker continually “learns by doing” [op cit., Arrow, 1962]. The additional “human capital” [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The standard model of Economic Development is Romer’s (1989, JPE 1990) adaptation* of Solow’s (1956, 1957) Model.  Basically,<br />
<blockquote>
<p><img alt="Y=AK^aL^{1-a}\," src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/math/4/8/1/481e35d4e18ad0ca6715fd78d109e75e.png"></p>
</blockquote>
<p>became</p>
<blockquote><p>Y = AK<sup>α</sup>(HL)<sup>(1-α)</sup></p>
</blockquote>
<p>where the H stands for “human capital,” which multiplies the ability of labor. (Think high-skills labor—construction work, plumbing, teaching—where the worker continually “learns by doing” [op cit., Arrow, 1962]. The additional “human capital” multiples the effect of the labor.</p>
<p>One central question is how much of α is attributable to capital and how much is attributable to labor.  Standard Macroeconomics and Economic Development courses teach varying values for α, ranging from around 25% to about 1/3 (33.3%): that is, the mixture is between 3 and 4 parts of Labor to every one part of Capital.</p>
<p>How does the compensation go?  Well, not quite that way:</p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="http://lh3.ggpht.com/-PysKeU2Pmzw/TmVL_rVfokI/AAAAAAAAAh4/nB1bAuxL2e8/s1600-h/COE%25255B3%25255D.png"><img title="COE" border="0" alt="COE" src="http://lh3.ggpht.com/-bnXdQM5N2wM/TmVL_7BiAtI/AAAAAAAAAh8/o0NtNlO8Abs/COE_thumb%25255B1%25255D.png?imgmax=800" width="644" height="443"></a> </p>
<p>The banded area is the estimate of actual allocations of capital and labor.  The bars show the compensation to labor (and, therefore, the area above that to 100% are the portion of GDP that is being allocated to capital).</p>
<p>Economic theory tells us that if something is receiving excessive rents—as capital is clearly doing in the United States—there is suboptimal growth occurring across the economy. The standard method of adjusting for that is to reduce the excessive rents through either the introduction of competition (preferred if possible) or through taxation and redistribution.  Following are the tax rates on Capital v. Labor:</p>
<div align="center">
<table border="1" cellpadding="0" align="center">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td valign="top" width="100">
<p>Labor Tax Bracket</p>
</td>
<td valign="top" width="100">
<p>Capital Gains, Short Term</p>
</td>
<td valign="top" width="100">
<p>Capital Gains, Long Term</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top">
<p>10%</p>
</td>
<td valign="top">
<p>10%</p>
</td>
<td valign="top">
<p>0%</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top">
<p>15%</p>
</td>
<td valign="top">
<p>15%</p>
</td>
<td valign="top">
<p>0%</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top">
<p>25%</p>
</td>
<td valign="top">
<p>25%</p>
</td>
<td valign="top">
<p>15%</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top">
<p>28%</p>
</td>
<td valign="top">
<p>28%</p>
</td>
<td valign="top">
<p>15%</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top">
<p>33%</p>
</td>
<td valign="top">
<p>33%</p>
</td>
<td valign="top">
<p>15%</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top">
<p>35%</p>
</td>
<td valign="top">
<p>35%</p>
</td>
<td valign="top">
<p>15%</p>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
<p>Note also that labor is not necessarily allowed to exclude its “depreciation” above the value of the “standard deduction” ($8,500 for an individual, $11,600 for a married couple). This is clearly a skewed incentive, with preferable tax treatment given to the overvalued resource (capital) at the expense of the undervalued one (labor).</p>
<p>Happy Labor Day!</p>
<p>*NBER subscribers can access paper w3173.  Others can just type “Human Capital and Growth: Theory and Evidence” and probably find an ungated copy somewhere.  The uncurious are referred to Wikipedia.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/09/the-cost-of-labor.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Unemployment, Unemployment Benefits and Severance Packages: A Modest Thought Experiment</title>
		<link>./../../2011/08/unemployment-unemployment-benefits-and-severance-packages-a-modest-thought-experiment.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/08/unemployment-unemployment-benefits-and-severance-packages-a-modest-thought-experiment.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2011 17:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[employment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[labor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[unemployment benefits]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/08/unemployment-unemployment-benefits-and-severance-packages-a-modest-thought-experiment.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Mike Kimel Most economists believe that unemployment benefits increase the unemployment rate. The idea is that even having a relatively small income coming in (from unemployment) can encourage people to stay jobless just a little while longer. And no doubt there are people who play the unemployment compensation game fairly well. Now, consider severance [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by <strong>Mike Kimel</strong></p>
<p>Most economists believe that unemployment benefits increase the unemployment rate.  The idea is that even having a relatively small income coming in (from unemployment) can encourage people to stay jobless just a little while longer.  And no doubt there are people who play the unemployment compensation game fairly well.</p>
<p>Now, consider severance packages.  These days they aren&#8217;t uncommon.  There are differences in how different states treat severance packages, but as I understand it, in general, if a jobless worker received a severance package equivalent to X weeks of pay in lump sum form, that makes the worker ineligible to receive unemployment benefits for what would otherwise be the first X weeks worth of claims.  Which, would imply that for an unemployed worker, there is zero incentive to be jobless during the first X weeks of unemployment, but a jump in the incentive to be jobless beginning in week X + 1.  One presumes, therefore, a greater probability of people turning down proffered job offers in weeks X-1 or X (when unemployment benefits are imminent) than in week 1 or 2 (when there is a much longer wait to get unemployment benefits).  </p>
<p>If this solves the problem of anyone looking for a thesis topic at a Freshwater school, your thanks are all the payment I need but I do appreciate cookies.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/08/unemployment-unemployment-benefits-and-severance-packages-a-modest-thought-experiment.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Wisconsin, Have you Met L. Paul Bremer?</title>
		<link>./../../2011/02/wisconsin-have-you-met-l-paul-bremer.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/02/wisconsin-have-you-met-l-paul-bremer.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Feb 2011 20:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Iraq]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[labor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[unions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wisconsin]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/02/wisconsin-have-you-met-l-paul-bremer.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[By Daniel Becker Now that the story is getting out that Governor Walke et al&#8217;s bill is about more than just busting unions, a little bell went off in the back of my head. Yes, I read Shock Doctrine. Yes, I understand the true concept of fascism. I read What would Jefferson do. I read [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By Daniel Becker</p>
<p>
<div>Now that the story is getting out that Governor Walke et al&#8217;s bill is about more than just busting unions, a little bell went off in the back of my head. Yes, I read Shock Doctrine. Yes, I understand the true concept of fascism. I read What would Jefferson do. I read C &#038; L, AB, Hullabaloo, Glen Greenwald, watch Rachel, Ed, Cspan, etc, etc, etc. And, there are some people pointing out the connections between some of all these perspectives. However, Wisconsin&#8217;s current event just seemed too familiar. Deja vue familiar. More familiar than all the reading and listening would allow. It is experiencingly familiar and I don&#8217;t mean Egypt. </div>
<div></div>
<div>I mean, we can all see (or at least a majority are now seeing) the thread of connection to all the seemingly disjointed liberal/progressive commentary about what has been happening in America since around 1981. We even are accepting that Clinton et al&#8217;s governing time was part of the thread. It&#8217;s economic. It&#8217;s societal structure, it&#8217;s civil rights, it&#8217;s power (always is since the constitutional convention). </div>
<div></div>
<div>But, where&#8217;s the beef. Show me the money. Where is the materialization most recently that it all came together as to the implementation of the play book that Governor Walker et al are using such that I know this is real&#8230;this is really and honestly currently America&#8230;American?</div>
<div></div>
<div>Folks&#8230;I give you <a href="http://www.middle-east-online.com/english/?id=41829">Iraq: 10/10/2010</a></div>
<p><a name="more"></a>
<div></div>
<blockquote><div>The political deadlock in Baghdad, which has prevented the formation of an Iraqi government more than six months after the parliamentary elections in March, has not prevented the administration of Nuri Kamal al-Maliki from opening the southern oilfields to the world&#8217;s giant corporations. <strong>Nor has it stopped the US Embassy and Commerce Department from reinvigorating the Bush-era program of selling the country&#8217;s public assets to corporate buyers.</strong> And because Iraqi unions have organized opposition to privatization since the start of the occupation, the Maliki administration is enforcing with a vengeance Saddam Hussein&#8217;s prohibition of public sector unions. </div>
<div></div>
<div>The United States may have withdrawn its combat brigades, but it is not leaving Iraq. And while Washington may have scaled back its dreams of nation-building, it has not given <strong>up on a key aspect of the economic agenda behind that project: encouraging corporate investment by sacrificing the rights of Iraqi workers.</strong></div>
<div></div>
<div>June demonstrations over blackouts, supported by the union &#8212; <strong>the first national union led by a woman, Hashmeya Muhsin &#8212; were put down by police,</strong> who killed one protester and injured several others</div>
<div></div>
<div>Also in June, longshoremen protesting the prohibition of unions in ports south of Basra <strong>were surrounded by troops, and the union&#8217;s leaders were transferred hundreds of miles from their homes. </strong></div>
<div></div>
<div>In January <strong>the government threw the president of Basra&#8217;s Iraqi Teachers Union in jail.</strong> According to Nasser al-Hussain, an executive board member, the government seeks to establish control over an organization it views as far too independent.</div>
<div></div>
<div>After the 2003 invasion, occupation czar Paul Bremer decided to keep on the books Saddam&#8217;s Law 150, which bans public sector unions. Each succeeding Iraqi administration continued the prohibition. </div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div>Wisconsin is not Egypt nor the rest of the protesting that is going on in the middle east other than that there is protesting. Not at all. Wisconsin is Iraq for one big, monstrous, sledge hammer to the head reason: Iraq&#8217;s oppression and thus resistance by the unions is all American. The union busting to the benefit of capital (big, huge money for the rest of you, as in Rockefeller&#8217;s Standard Oil time) in Iraq is purely American. We own it. Yes, we have propped up dictators such as in Egypt. What is singularly different in the protesting of Egypt/Mid East is freedom. They protested for freedom. Now we&#8217;ll see if they get unions. However, Wisconsin and Iraq are free. American style free in that Iraq is American made. <a href="http://upsidedownworld.org/iraqiunions.htm">They also have/had unions</a>. </div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<blockquote><div>At the end of World War I, Iraqi workers wasted no time in forming oil, railway and dockworker unions in the fragmented country that Churchill had carved out of the desert, connecting the oil fields of three Ottoman provinces–Mosul, Baghdad, and Basra. Their hold on the terrain already tenuous, the British occupiers responded with force. Repeated strikes were quashed, often violently. </div>
<div></div>
<div>Under Qasim&#8217;s watch, unions along with civic groups swelled in rank and number. By 1959, 250,000 workers had joined unions in Iraq; peasants had formed 3,000 village associations for 200,000 peasants; the Iraqi Women&#8217;s League boasted 20,000 members and the Democratic Youth Federation 84,000 youngsters. </div>
<div>Qasim&#8217;s &#8220;progressive&#8221; autocracy was fleeting, however, and in February of 1963, <strong>the Baath party, in alliance with a sect of the nationalist armed forces, and with the help of the CIA, overthrew Qasim.</strong></div>
<div></div>
<div>When Saddam Hussein seized control in 1979, he built upon the Baathist tradition of usurping the unions as an instrument of state power. As part of his brutal purge of all leaders and activists refusing to pledge total allegiance to the Baath party, he eradicated all non-Baathist unions. In 1987, the Baathist unions fully backed Saddam&#8217;s Orwellian decree: &#8220;From now on, the title &#8216;worker&#8217; is abolished and all workers shall become official employees by the State&#8230;<strong>As everybody is now a government employee, there is no more need for trade unions.&#8221;</strong> Interestingly, Saddam did tolerate private sector unions, albeit with certain laws circumscribing their powers. The exception appears irrelevant, because, since the 1970&#8217;s through the fall of Saddam, no strikes are known to have occurred in Iraq, according to Political Risk Services, a well-respected corporate consultancy firm.</div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>If you think Obama&#8217;s recent commentary is hopeful for unions, <a href="http://www.middle-east-online.com/english/?id=41829">guess again</a>:</div>
<div></div>
<blockquote><div>When questioned by reporters about the union bans, an official at the US Embassy, the world&#8217;s largest, said mildly, &#8220;We&#8217;re looking into it. We hope that everybody resolves their differences in an amicable way.&#8221; The Obama White House has not spoken out, and the latest <strong>State Department report on human rights plays down the oppression of Iraqi unionists, calling their situation a &#8220;limited exercise of labour rights.&#8221;</strong></div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>Can you say Public Option? I knew you could.  However, start asking you gen X&#8217;ers and younger if they have heard of the &#8220;<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=O93YpTYCWRk">labor wars</a>&#8220;.  You might be surprised, and not pleasantly.  Just like the term &#8220;<a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2009/05/define-rich-part-ii-rat-race-and.html">rat race</a>&#8220;.  Remember that one?  You need to.   </div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/02/wisconsin-have-you-met-l-paul-bremer.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Wisconsin, fiscal responsibility, and power (plants?)</title>
		<link>./../../2011/02/wisconsin-fiscal-responsibility-and-power-plants.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/02/wisconsin-fiscal-responsibility-and-power-plants.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Feb 2011 13:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Koch brothers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[labor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wisconsin]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/02/wisconsin-fiscal-responsibility-and-power-plants.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Have you heard about 16.896? &#8220;&#8230;with or without solicitation of bids, for any amount that the department determines to be in the best interest of the state.&#8221; Who knew behind the scenes it was also power plants? From rortybomb at the link above: The fight in Wisconsin is over Governor Walker’s 144-page Budget Repair Bill. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a target="_blank" href="http://rortybomb.wordpress.com/2011/02/21/the-less-discussed-part-of-walkers-wisconsin-plan-no-bid-energy-assets-firesales/">Have you heard about 16.896?</a>   <br />&#8220;&#8230;with or without solicitation of bids, for any amount that the department determines to be in the best interest of the state.&#8221;  Who knew behind the scenes it was also power plants? From <strong>rortybomb</strong> at the link above:</p>
<blockquote><p>The fight in Wisconsin is over <a target="_blank" href="http://legis.wisconsin.gov/2011/data/JR1SB-11.pdf">Governor Walker’s 144-page Budget Repair Bill</a>. The parts everyone is focusing on have to do with the right to collectively bargain being stripped from public sector unions (except for the unions that <a target="_blank" href="http://voices.washingtonpost.com/postpartisan/2011/02/scrooge-ism_in_wisconsin_part.html?hpid=opinionsbox1">supported Walker running for Governor</a>). Focusing on this misses a large part of what the bill would do. Check out this language, from the same bill (my bold):</p>
<p><strong>16.896</strong> Sale or contractual operation of state−owned heating, cooling, and power plants. (1) Notwithstanding ss. 13.48 (14) (am) and 16.705 (1), the department may sell any state−owned heating, cooling, and power plant or may contract with a private entity for the operation of any such plant, <strong>with or without solicitation of bids, for any amount that the department determines to be in the best interest of the state</strong>. Notwithstanding ss. 196.49 and 196.80, no approval or certification of the public service commission is necessary for a public utility to purchase, or contract for the operation of, such a plant, and <strong>any such purchase is considered to be in the public interest and to comply with the criteria for certification of a project under s. 196.49 (3) (b).</strong></p></blockquote>
<p>(Update:  Dan here&#8230;see also <a target="_blank" href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2011/02/krugman-on-union-busting.html">Linda Beale&#8217;s post</a> on the same issue via Mark Thoma.  <a target="_blank" href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2011/02/wisconsins-walker-joins-government-asset-giveaway-club-and-is-rahm-soon-to-follow.html">Yves Smith</a> adds her comments.)<br /><a name="more"></a></p>
<blockquote><p>The bill would allow for the selling of state-owned heating/cooling/power plants without bids. This excellent catch is from <a target="_blank" href="http://www.ginandtacos.com/2011/02/21/stand-and-deliver/">Ed at ginandtacos.com</a> (who, speaking of Madison, took me to the Essen Haus on my 21st birthday, where the night began to go sideways). Ed correctly notes:</p>
<p>&#8220;If this isn’t the best summary of the goals of modern conservatism, I don’t know what is. It’s like a highlight reel of all of the tomahawk dunks of neo-Gilded Age corporatism: privatization, no-bid contracts, deregulation, and naked cronyism. Extra bonus points for the explicit effort to <strong>legally redefine </strong>the term “public interest” as “whatever the energy industry lobbyists we appoint to these unelected bureaucratic positions say it is.”</p>
<p><strong>&#8230;</strong></p>
<p>It’s important to think of this battle as a larger one over the role of the state. The attempt to break labor is part of the same continuous motion as saying that the crony, corporatist selling of state utilities to the Koch brothers and other energy interests is the new “public interest.” </p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/02/wisconsin-fiscal-responsibility-and-power-plants.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Hey anti socialist! You really don&#8217;t want to sit on UHC, Cigna, Microsoft, Walmart, Koch brother&#8217;s, GE, Boeing or Buffet&#8217;s corporate boards?</title>
		<link>./../../2011/01/hey-anti-socialist-you-really-dont-want-to-sit-on-uhc-cigna-microsoft-walmart-koch-brothers-ge-boeing-or-buffets-corporate-boards.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/01/hey-anti-socialist-you-really-dont-want-to-sit-on-uhc-cigna-microsoft-walmart-koch-brothers-ge-boeing-or-buffets-corporate-boards.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2011 18:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Germany]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[labor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[policy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[socialism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/01/hey-anti-socialist-you-really-dont-want-to-sit-on-uhc-cigna-microsoft-walmart-koch-brothers-ge-boeing-or-buffets-corporate-boards.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[By Daniel Becker Just thought, being the new year, we might want to start it off with some actual new thinking about how to make our economic system better. I have been meaning to purchase the book: Were you born on the wrong Continent. I&#8217;m just a very slow reader though and have to finish [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By Daniel Becker</p>
<p>Just thought, being the new year, we might want to start it off with some actual new thinking about how to make our economic system better. I have been meaning to purchase the book: <strong><em>Were you born on the wrong Continent</em></strong>. I&#8217;m just a very slow reader though and have to finish what I have. So, I found this <a href="http://www.booktv.org/Watch/11911/Were+You+Born+on+the+Wrong+Continent+How+the+European+Model+Can+Help+You+Get+a+Life.aspx">Book TV interview</a> to satisfy my “should I buy it” meter. Yes I should, and will.</p>
<blockquote><p>Here in this country, it&#8217;s unthinkable that you would have a high school graduate on the corporate board of a major corporation. And there it happens, I don&#8217;t want to say routine, it happens a lot. You know, at least in terms of the supervisory board. </p>
<p>My favorite example, which I give in the book is, is this ah, nascent global bank which was just starting up and I asked a young banker there about co-determination, how it worked and he said well ah, “I&#8217;ll tell you how it works. The guy who brought us the plants, around the bank building, he&#8217;s on the corporate board.” Well what do you think about? “Well I think it&#8217;s very funny.” He said “the other thing I think about, is that they can&#8217;t hold the meetings in English” which is the global language &#8230; because this guy only speaks German. Everybody has to go at the pace of the gardener on the&#8230; corporate board.</p></blockquote>
<p>Imagine that! Mr. Smith actually does go to Washington. As a lobbyist.  Daily even, if he were a German citizen. <br /><a name="more"></a><br />The author, Mr Geoghegan goes on to say that Germany was punished for the conception and implementation of co-determination by the boycott of international capital. The Financial Times, the Economist all editorialized against it. Thus, their people have to be on guard for those who want to bring it down. However, he notes that the post 1945 constitutions that were adopted came out of the New Deal, consequently they have in stone rights to healthcare, employment and education. Things our New Deal could not get constitutionally in-scripted. Under their constitution the courts have to look at whether the law will help or hurt the family. Is education free or not free? </p>
<p>Ultimately, Mr. Geoghegan sees Germany having an advantage in their system because the people are pulled into the system and thus are responsible for the results of their decisions. He notes that in the US we have no real power (at least as it relates to economic outcomes via labor) which allows one to talk irresponsibly about power. Remember that gardener? He is at the table of economic policy decisions. Kind of makes you realize just what we&#8217;re about to experience now that the Tea Party is calling some major shots. All of a sudden a group of people who have been able to sit on the outside in their own circle of reality is at the table of the worlds circle of reality. Think there is not going to be some major crashes? Even Carl Rove understood the danger in O&#8217;Donnell&#8217;s limited understanding of power because of lack of exposure and all it experiences. The issue we should all have with Rove et al though, is that he does not want to helper her learn about real power and thus truly be able to make decisions that enhances her life and reduces the risk of living. </p>
<p>In Germany, because of their system that makes it hard for even the least educated to sit on the outside, and the most powerful to ignore or leverage the least knowledgeable for their own gain, they have a better chance of surviving those who would create the world in their own vision. </p>
<p> One caution when asked what the down side is of the German system? The least knowledgeable being employed. Here, we have a service economy as the solution. That is personal service to those who have the where for all to buy personal service. This leads to a crack in the foundation of an egalitarian mind set and thus the policy that follows.   </p>
<p>Truth is, not everyone is born to go and get a traditional BS type college education.  Germany obviously is going to struggle as we have with making sure the lowest common denominator and not the highest is the the standard for acceptable earning capacity.  Sure, promote being the best you can be.  Great as an individual motto, but not as a minimum standard for policy setting.  We need to understand that the best for some is simple manual labor.  If we don&#8217;t, then we are only left with welfare policy, which I have no problem with if that is what we choose.  One way or the other, people who for what ever luck in life they have or have not been blessed with have to be able to receive enough money to live in the society we have set up.  Either we allow this to happen by assuring &#8220;living wages&#8221; for the lowest work society needs accomplished or we do it by welfare.  Preferably not the penal kind of welfare we seem to be choosing.  It cost the most to society and not just in money.</p>
<p>Besides, is it not what made us the model for and the envy of the world that we had created an economy which allowed such capacity to be considered valuable enough to earn the basic American Dream of a house, car, education and retirement without being broke or broken? </p>
<p>Do watch the interview.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/01/hey-anti-socialist-you-really-dont-want-to-sit-on-uhc-cigna-microsoft-walmart-koch-brothers-ge-boeing-or-buffets-corporate-boards.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Paying better wages and profit sharing another way to success?</title>
		<link>./../../2010/11/paying-better-wages-and-profit-sharing-another-way-to-success.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/11/paying-better-wages-and-profit-sharing-another-way-to-success.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 26 Nov 2010 16:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[labor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[labor share]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[profit sharing]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/11/paying-better-wages-and-profit-sharing-another-way-to-success.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Higher Wages, Profit Sharing and Greater Flexibility Benefit All Employees &#8212; And the Company Bottom Line Too(link repaired) Costco is so certain that its policy is sound that it has kept paying better wages than rivals, even as Wall Street has pressured the company to conform to industry standards. As the economy slowly recovers, it&#8217;s [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.alternet.org/story/148975/higher_wages%2C_profit_sharing_and_greater_flexibility_benefit_all_employees_--_and_the_company_bottom_line_too" target="_blank"><strong>Higher Wages, Profit Sharing and Greater Flexibility</strong> Benefit All Employees &#8212; And the Company Bottom Line Too</a><br />(link repaired)</p>
<blockquote><p>Costco is so certain that its policy is sound that it has kept paying better wages than rivals, even as Wall Street has pressured the company to conform to industry standards. </p>
<p>As the economy slowly recovers, it&#8217;s no secret that companies would like to boost productivity and profits. Many think the best way to do so is to slash costs. As an entrepreneur and business owner, though, I&#8217;d like to suggest another idea: Pay your employees more.</p>
<p>That&#8217;s not as crazy as it sounds. A growing body of evidence is revealing that companies that pay fair wages, and offer flexibility and training to even entry-level and lower-skilled employees, do better than those that don&#8217;t. A vast number of businesses mistakenly assume that their lowest-wage workers are easily replaced or not worth investing in, but those that do the right thing soon find that they&#8217;re doing the right thing for their bottom lines. It&#8217;s time that this becomes a business norm.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/11/paying-better-wages-and-profit-sharing-another-way-to-success.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Preface to a Thought-Experiment on Labor, Capital, and Income Distribution</title>
		<link>./../../2010/11/preface-to-a-thought-experiment-on-labor-capital-and-income-distribution.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/11/preface-to-a-thought-experiment-on-labor-capital-and-income-distribution.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 23 Nov 2010 04:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Business Philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[labor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mark Thoma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[microeconomic theory]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/11/preface-to-a-thought-experiment-on-labor-capital-and-income-distribution.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Mark Thoma goes to something called the Business Ethics Blog for an economics thought-experiment: A Montreal accessories company has taken its policy of using no animal products beyond the rack and has forbidden its staff from eating meat and fish at work. A former employee says the policy violated her rights as a non-vegetarian…. It’s [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://economistsview.typepad.com/economistsview/2010/11/can-employers-tell-employees-what-to-eat.html" target="_blank">Mark Thoma</a> goes to something called the Business Ethics Blog for <a href="http://businessethicsblog.com/2010/11/21/can-employers-tell-employees-what-to-eat/" target="_blank">an economics thought-experiment</a>:<br />
<blockquote>
<p>A Montreal accessories company has taken its policy of using no animal products beyond the rack and has forbidden its staff from eating meat and fish at work.</p>
<p>A former employee says the policy violated her rights as a non-vegetarian….</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It’s an interesting experiment for many reasons, none of which deal directly with economics as it is currently taught.  For one thing, it is a dictated change in a contract with workers.  As a standard microeconomics problem, there is a negotiation, the worker’s preferences are examined, and the student is asked to find an economic balance that will satisfy the worker, with the implication that the employer desiring the change with provide compensation. (Note that the standard intermediate or graduate-level microeconomics problem merely teaches math, with dollars and preferences substituted for widgets and variables.)</p>
<p>For another, there is insufficient information to discuss externalities. (Aside to Brad DeLong: it’s not only, or even most importantly, Irving Fisher who is forgotten; Alfred Marshall appears to have been stripped from the curriculum as it transmogrified into a Libertarian Wet Dream.)  Absent evidence, we cannot know if the company had a legitimate reason for banning meat eating. Perhaps chemicals used in their processes combine with some proteins and produce a marginally higher level of cancer in those exposed for long periods. Perhaps the maintenance crew has discovered multiple rat nests because the workers have not been attentive to clean-up requirements, leaving enough pieces of pork, chicken, beef, and tripe around to make the building a desirable habitat. We do not have sufficient information.</p>
<p>We do, however, know that bars that permit smoking produce lung, throat, and other cancers in even the non-smoking bartenders and wait staff.  It may be unlikely that the aggressive hormone and radiation treatment given to meat these days produces a similar effect—radiation and drug treatment, after all, are both perfectly safe—but it is also possible that the company has seen recent research that indicates otherwise and fears for its future health-care costs.</p>
<p>We also do not know whether the company provides eating areas for its staff, or under what conditions it does.  Is there a company cafeteria (or eating spaces on various floors) that provides napkins and utensils to those who bring their own food? Is eating at one’s desk permitted? (I have worked places where it is not.) In such a case, we cannot even model the type of microeconomics problem referenced above, because we do not know the extent to which the workers are being told to give up something. (Smokers having to leave the building has positive externalities for them, such as work breaks others do not get and social networking opportunities that provide compensation.)  We cannot, in short, know the value of the widgets or the identities of the variables.</p>
<p>The question then becomes whether this is an economics problem at all.  And, if we assume it is, what does that mean for other. more standard, problems?  On the Next Rock: capital, labor, and taxation.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/11/preface-to-a-thought-experiment-on-labor-capital-and-income-distribution.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
