<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>House energy debate &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Unused oil drilling permits: 9300</title>
		<link>./../../2008/05/unused-oil-drilling-permits-9300.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/05/unused-oil-drilling-permits-9300.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2008 19:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[House energy debate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[liquid gold]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[oil]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[permits]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/05/unused-oil-drilling-permits-9300.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Watching Cspan at lunch of the House debt on taxes and energy Rep Emanual stated there are currently 9300 unused oil drilling permits in the US. The counter to the statement was from Rep McCrery: There must be a reason for them being unused. Yes, obviously if they are unused there is a reason. Any [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Watching Cspan at lunch of the House debt on taxes and energy Rep Emanual stated there are currently 9300 unused oil drilling permits in the US.  The counter to the statement was from Rep McCrery: There must be a reason for them being unused.</p>
<p>Yes, obviously if they are unused there is a reason.  Any guess?  Of course, that they are unused McCrery noted is the reason why we need to drill in ANWR and all 3 coasts; East, West, Gulf.  Rep </p>
<p>McCrery seems to imply here that the permits are unusable.  Well, if they are unusable, then why are they still open?  Why have they not been returned as unusable and thus the ares of permit removed from the list of viable drilling property.  </p>
<p>Fascinating.  Being that we are not opening up any new refineries which is blamed on all sorts of things (usually those tree hugger types) where would all this oil, whether from the republican wish list of holes in the ground or the current 9300 ok&#8217;d potential holes in the ground be refined?  If not here, then we are exporting crude.  Will that offset our import costs?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/05/unused-oil-drilling-permits-9300.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
