<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Matthew Yglesias &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Paul Ryan Is the Joe McCarthy of Our Era. Maybe the Mainstream Media Finally Will Recognize That. Then Again, Maybe It Won’t.</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/paul-ryan-is-the-joe-mccarthy-of-our-era-maybe-the-mainstream-media-finally-will-recognize-that-then-again-maybe-it-wont.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/paul-ryan-is-the-joe-mccarthy-of-our-era-maybe-the-mainstream-media-finally-will-recognize-that-then-again-maybe-it-wont.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2013 16:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Edward R. Murrow]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Joe MCarthy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mainstream news media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Matthew Yglesias]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Walter Cronkite]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/paul-ryan-is-the-joe-mccarthy-of-our-era-maybe-the-mainstream-media-finally-will-recognize-that-then-again-maybe-it-wont.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Paul Ryan is, in effect, the Joe McCarthy of our era.  He consistently spews outlandishly false statements of fact, never offers actual evidence in support of them and never refutes factual challenges using actual and full facts, and tries as a matter of routine to obfuscate his specific and broader objectives and therefore to trick [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Paul Ryan is, in effect, the Joe McCarthy of our era.  He consistently spews <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/moneybox/2013/03/12/paul_ryan_currency_debasement.html">outlandishly false statements of fact</a>, never offers actual evidence in support of them and never refutes factual challenges using actual and full facts, and <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/moneybox/2013/03/12/class_war_budgeting_paul_ryan_and_house_gop_want_more_money_for_the_rich.html">tries <i>as a matter of routine</i> to obfuscate his specific and broader objectives </a>and therefore to trick the public.  </p>
<p>He is a serious nutcase.  And yet he has garnered mainstream media attention as though what he puts out is credible.  We have a mainstream media that treats this nutjob as though he were a legitimate policy wonk. And that acts as though facts are legitimately in the eye of the beholder.  </p>
<p>If only Obama were more like Ike.  And if only there were an Edward R. Murrow around now, although a Walter Cronkite would do, too.  If only.  </p>
<p>Broadcast news, of course, no longer has nearly the power and audience it once had, but we now have the veritable <i>reverse</i> of what this country once had in its highest-profile journalists.  and we have a president who cowers in the face of whatever media juggernaut is currently saying &#8220;boo.&#8221;  </p>
<p>True, Ike was buoyed, not hindered, by the mainstream press when he helped end the McCarthy stranglehold.  And McCarthy and Eisenhower were, technically anyway, members of the same political party, so there was no insistence that Eisenhower humor McCarthy in the name of bipartisanship.  But there&#8217;s also no law that requires the president, this one or any other, to mindlessly do the mainstream media&#8217;s bidding if that bidding is in the name of bipartisanship.  At least not when bipartisanship means delegating fiscal policy to a rightwing faction of a minority party that a majority of voters recently pretty-darned-clearly  rejected.</p>
<p>This is getting really, really scary.  </p>
<p>&#8212;-<br /><i>The links are to two Matthew Yglesias posts in Slate this morning.</i></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/paul-ryan-is-the-joe-mccarthy-of-our-era-maybe-the-mainstream-media-finally-will-recognize-that-then-again-maybe-it-wont.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>THREAT-LEVEL-GATE©: Bob Woodward’s Awful Hope-Y’All-Won’t-Notice-Ryan-Lizza’s-Report Ploy</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/threat-level-gate-bob-woodwards-awful-hope-yall-wont-notice-ryan-lizzas-report-ploy.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/threat-level-gate-bob-woodwards-awful-hope-yall-wont-notice-ryan-lizzas-report-ploy.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2013 21:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Alexandra Petri]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bob Woodward]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gene Sperling]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Matthew Yglesias]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ryan Lizza]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The New Yorker]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the sequester]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Washington Post]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[THREAT-LEVEL-GATE]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/threat-level-gate-bob-woodwards-awful-hope-yall-wont-notice-ryan-lizzas-report-ploy.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Bob Woodward, the legendary Watergate reporter turned reliable chronicler of insider accounts of political events, has made a series of bizarre assertions over the past week. &#8212; Matthew Yglesias, Bob Woodward Trolls the World, Slate, today Yglesias then summarizes last weekend’s exciting Woodward-related events, and then updates us: Things moved into the absurd Wednesday night [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">Bob Woodward, the legendary Watergate reporter turned reliable chronicler of insider accounts of political events, has made a series of bizarre assertions over the past week.</div>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; Matthew Yglesias,<a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/moneybox/2013/02/28/bob_woodward_vs_gene_sperling_veteran_reporter_trolls_washington.html#article_comment_box"> Bob Woodward Trolls the World</a>, Slate, today</div>
<p>Yglesias then summarizes<a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/02/bob-woodwards-seriously-stupid.html"> last weekend’s exciting Woodward-related events</a>, and then updates us:</p>
<div dir="ltr">Things moved into the absurd Wednesday night when it was revealed that National Economic Council director Gene Sperling had concluded an email disagreement with Woodward with the observation that in Sperling&#8217;s view Woodward would come to regret clinging so tenaciously to an untenable position.</div>
<div dir="ltr"></div>
<div dir="ltr">As if determined to prove Sperling right,<a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/weigel/2013/02/28/the_nature_of_the_threat.html"> Woodward chose to start talking around town about how Sperling had threatened him</a>—a ridiculous interpretation that the ridiculous conservative media has been running with—rather than sticking with the obvious interpretation that Woodward&#8217;s reputation among journalists is going to suffer from flagrant wrongness. It would be interesting to see Woodward try to hash this out with, say, fellow Post-ie Ezra Klein, but instead he&#8217;s going the full wingnut and<a href="http://themoderatevoice.com/177366/woodward-says-white-house-threatened-him-will-appear-on-sean-hannitys-fox-show/"> will be appearing on Sean Hannity&#8217;s show</a> Thursday night to advance the agitprop agenda. In retrospect, this whole affair was foreshadowed by the release of<a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1451651104/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&#038;camp=1789&#038;creative=390957&#038;creativeASIN=1451651104&#038;linkCode=as2&#038;tag=slatmaga-20"> Woodward&#8217;s latest book last fall</a>. It made much less of a splash than many other Woodward books. Most well-informed observers<a href="http://www.newrepublic.com/book/review/bob-woodward-price-of-politics"> agreed with Noam Scheiber that it was marred by anti-Obama bias</a>, but under the circumstances of the time, it didn&#8217;t get the right geared up either. By essentially doubling down on the worst qualities of that book, Woodward has managed to make himself the center of attention again.</div>
<p>Surprisingly, though, Yglesias doesn’t mention that earlier this week, New Yorker writer Ryan Lizza published<a href="http://www.newyorker.com/reporting/2013/03/04/130304fa_fact_lizza#ixzz2MCuygBWh"> a journalistic scoop</a> that undermined the thing about Woodward being a reliable chronicler of insider accounts of political events.  Lizza quoted none other than Eric Cantor, who conceded that Boehner, at Cantor’s urging, reneged on the 2011 grand bargain deal at the last minute, for political reasons.  </p>
<p>Uh-oh.   </p>
<p>So, do you think Woodward might have decided to ratchet up the off-the-rails stuff a-few-fold yesterday because yesterday (or maybe the day before) was the day when Ryan Lizza’s New Yorker story broke?  Yeah?  You think?</p>
<p>Yes, that&#8217;s right.  Bob Woodward, the legendary Watergate reporter had turned a reliable chronicler of insider accounts of political events, and has now been exposed as a reliable and gullible tool of Republican insiders.  But he hopes no one will notice that.</p>
<p>What I find interesting about this is that apparently the Washington Post has pulled the plug on Woodward’s unfettered use of it as a forum in which to spread false statements of fact. Thus he was relegated to seeking out Politico<a href="http://www.politico.com/story/2013/02/exclusive-the-woodward-sperling-emails-revealed-88226.html?hp=t2_3"> as his venue</a> for the “breaking news” this time.</p>
<p>Progress.</p>
<p>I can&#8217;t help wondering, though, whether Sperling was right that Woodward might come to regret his flagrantly false reporting on what the sequester agreement is.  He hasn&#8217;t yet, though. He&#8217;s still cowering with fear from that threat, but determined to press on nonetheless. </p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />By the way, you really, really need to see Alexandra Petri’s <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/compost/wp/2013/02/28/how-to-threaten-bob-woodward/?hpid=z3">threat-level piece </a>on this. Seriously.  (Just be sure you’re not eating anything you might choke on when you do.)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/threat-level-gate-bob-woodwards-awful-hope-yall-wont-notice-ryan-lizzas-report-ploy.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>FOLLOW-UP to, “Do ‘Right to work’ Laws Violate the Constitution&#8217;s Contracts Clause?”</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/follow-up-to-do-right-to-work-laws-violate-the-constitutions-contracts-clause.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/follow-up-to-do-right-to-work-laws-violate-the-constitutions-contracts-clause.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 13 Dec 2012 19:07:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Contracts Clause]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Matthew Yglesias]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[PJS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Right-to-Work laws]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sec. 10]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Seth Ackerman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Supreme court]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Taft-Hartley Act]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/follow-up-to-do-right-to-work-laws-violate-the-constitutions-contracts-clause.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Last night, in a comment to my post from Tuesday, “Do‘Right to Work’ Laws Violate the Constitution Contracts Clause?”, reader PJR wrote: To a non-lawyer, it kinda looks like SCOTUS rejected the contracts argument in 1949, so unions would have to find someway to get the court(s) to reconsider&#8211;or is this wrong? If wrong, why [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>Last night, in a comment to my post from Tuesday, “<a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/12/do-right-to-work-laws-violate.html?utm_source=feedburner&#038;utm_medium=feed&#038;utm_campaign=Feed%3A+blogspot%2FHzoh+%28Angry+Bear%29">Do‘Right to Work’ Laws Violate the Constitution Contracts Clause?</a>”, reader PJR wrote:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>To a non-lawyer, it kinda looks like SCOTUS rejected the contracts argument in 1949, so unions would have to find someway to get the court(s) to reconsider&#8211;or is this wrong? If wrong, why the heck haven&#8217;t unions tried this? ( http://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/335/525/case.html)
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I began writing a response that I planned to post in the Comments section, but then realized that the post would be too long (wayyy too long) for that, and that the issue was important enough to post directly as a blog post, in follow-up to the initial post.  So, here’s the follow-up in response to PJS’s comment:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212;-
</p>
</div>
<div>Hmm.  The opinion PJS links to, <i>Lincoln Union v. Northwestern Co</i>., from 1949, says that the Court earlier decided that the ‘right to work’ laws at issue in that case don’t violate the Contracts clause, but the opinion doesn’t elaborate except to cite, without comment, to a 1934 opinion, <i>Home Building &#038; Loan Assn. v. Blaisdell</i>.  
</p>
</div>
<div>But <i>Home Building &#038; Loan Assn</i>. had nothing to do with labor contracts.  In that case, the Court upheld the constitutionality of a Minnesota law that required mortgage holders to grant homeowners longer periods of time to begin again to repay their mortgages after missing payments, before the mortgage company could foreclose on the house.  The Court said this didn’t violate the Contracts clause because states must be allowed to address severe emergencies by requiring an altered “remedy” for completion of the contract—in that case, a longer time in which to repay the mortgage—as long as the legislation didn’t alter the ultimate amount owed. 
</p>
</div>
<div>The opinion recites the economic devastation of the Depression, and says that the Contracts clause must be interpreted to allow states some leeway to protect the state’s residents as long as the leeway wasn’t so great as to deprive the mortgage holder permanently of a property right—the right to eventual full payment of the mortgage. Then, after discussing two 1870s Supreme Court opinion that interpret the Contracts clause as absolute, the opinion says that it really is not, as long as the change is just temporary and in response to a real emergency.  (This is apart from the state’s right to permanently bar contracts or provisions in contracts that violate criminal or civil law—a separate “public policy” exemption that has existed since the founding; people (including corporate people) can’t simply contract away the criminal law or certain types of civil law.  Although lately the Supreme Court, in a series of 5-4 opinions, does pretty much allow <i>corporate</i> people to do <i>exactly</i> that.)  
</p>
</div>
<div>Yet, in <i>Home Building &#038; Loan Assoc</i>., the Court interpreted <i>Lincoln Union</i> as allowing states to declare exempt from the Contracts clause pretty much anything it wants, simply by declaring it public policy in the interest of the state’s citizens.  Here’s the extent of what that opinion says about the Contract clause issue:
</p>
</div>
<div>Second. There is a suggestion though not elaborated in briefs that these state laws conflict with Art. I, 10, of the United States Constitution, insofar as they impair the obligation of contracts made prior to their enactment. That this contention is without merit is now too clearly established to require discussion. See <i>Home Bldg. &#038; Loan Ass&#8217;n v. Blaisdell</i>, <a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?court=us&#038;vol=290&#038;invol=398#436">290 U.S. 398, 436 </a>-439, 239, 240, 88 A.L.R. 1481, and cases <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766" name="532">[335 U.S. 525 , 532] </a>  there cited. And also <i>Veix v. Sixth Ward Building &#038; Loan Ass&#8217;n</i>, <a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?navby=case&#038;court=us&#038;vol=310&#038;invol=32#38">310 U.S. 32, 38 </a>, 794; East New York Savings Bank v. Hahn, <a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?navby=case&#038;court=us&#038;vol=326&#038;invol=230#232">326 U.S. 230, 232 </a>, 70, 160 A.L.R. 1279.
</p>
</div>
<div>After “seeing” <i>Home Building</i>, I can say that that conclusory statement is clearly a deeply distorted interpretation of <i>Lincoln Union</i>.  Read <i>Home Building</i>.  You be the justice, er, the judge, about what it says.
</p>
</div>
<div>Ditto, and then some, for the other two referenced opinions.  <i>Veix v. Sixth Ward Building &#038; Loan Assoc</i>., decided in 1940, begins:
</p>
</div>
<div>In 1928 and 1929 appellant purchased prepaid shares of the appellee, a New Jersey building and loan association, paying the pay value of $200 per share. At that time the applicable New Jersey statutes provided that shares in such an association could be withdrawn by giving such written notice as the constitution or by-laws of the association provided, not to exceed 30 days; that withdrawals should be paid in the order in which notices were received, with not more than one-half of the receipts of any month being required to be used for payment of withdrawals, without the consent of the board of directors, until the oldest unpaid claim of withdrawal had been on file for six months; that no payment should be postponed for longer than six months from the date of notice; and that any member who had given notice could sue and recover the withdrawal value if it was not paid within six months of the notice. <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766" name="t1"></a><a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?navby=case&#038;court=us&#038;vol=310&#038;invol=32#f1">1 </a> 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>On April 22, 1932, these statutes were amended in four respects: (1) &#8216;total receipts&#8217; of an association, one-half of which were required to be used for the payment of withdrawals and which had not been previously defined, were defined as income on authorized investments, dues on shares of the association which were pledged with it to secure loans, and repayments from loans; (2) if in any one month the funds required to be payable for withdrawals were insufficient to pay all requested withdrawals, withdrawing members were to receive $500 each in the order of priority until the fund for withdrawals was exhausted; (3) no withdrawals were to be paid if the funds available for payment of matured shares were insufficient to pay all matured shares, the payment of which had been requested within thirty days after maturity; (4) so long as the funds of an association were applied as required by the amendment, no member who had filed his withdrawal notice should have a right to sue for the withdrawal value of his shares. <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766" name="t2"></a><a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?navby=case&#038;court=us&#038;vol=310&#038;invol=32#f2">2 </a>  In 1935 another amendment was passed providing that one-third of the &#8216;net receipts&#8217; of an association were to be payable for withdrawals, with &#8216;net receipts&#8217; defined as monies, other than borrowed monies, received by the association less operating expenses, payments on creditor obligations, payments for protecting the property of the association and reserves for any of these purposes. At the same time payments of withdrawals in the order in which notices had been received was continued but the payments were limited to $50 per member.
</p>
</div>
<div>And here’s its holding, and the explanation for it:
</p>
</div>
<div>In <i>Home Building &#038; Loan Association v. Blaisdell </i> <a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?navby=case&#038;court=us&#038;vol=310&#038;invol=32#f12">10</a> this Court considered the authority retained by the state over contracts &#8216;to safeguard the vital interests of its people.&#8217; The rule that all contracts are made subject to this paramount authority was there reiterated. Such authority is not limited to health, morals and safety. <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766" name="t11"></a><a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?navby=case&#038;court=us&#038;vol=310&#038;invol=32#f11">11 </a> It extends to economic needs as well. <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766" name="t12"></a><a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?navby=case&#038;court=us&#038;vol=310&#038;invol=32#f12">12 </a>Utility rate contracts give way to this power,  <a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?navby=case&#038;court=us&#038;vol=310&#038;invol=32#f12">13 </a> as do contractual arrangements between landlords and tenants. <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766" name="t"></a><a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?navby=case&#038;court=us&#038;vol=310&#038;invol=32#f">14 </a> </div>
<div>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The cases cited in the preceding paragraph make repeated reference to the emergency existing at the time of the enactment of the questioned statutes. Many of the enactments were temporary in character. We are here considering a permanent piece of legislation. So far as the contract clause is concerned, is this significant? We think not. &#8216;Emergency does not create (constitutional) power, emergency may furnish the occasion for the exercise of power.&#8217; <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766" name="t15"></a><a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?navby=case&#038;court=us&#038;vol=310&#038;invol=32#f15">15 </a>We think of emergencies as suddenly arising and quickly passing. The emergency of the depression may have caused the 1932 legislation, but the weakness in the financial system brought to light by that emergency remains. If the legislature could enact the legislation as to withdrawals to protect the associations in that emergency, we see no reason why the new status should not continue. When the 1932 act was passed commercial and savings banks, insurance companies and building and loan associations were suffering heavy withdrawals. The liquid portion of their assets were being rapidly drained off by their customers, leaving the long term investments and depreciated assets as an inadequate source for payment of the remaining liabilities. An acceleration or a continuance of this tendency to withdraw available funds threatened a quick end to the ability of the institutions to meet even normal demands. Such threatened insolvency demands legislation for its control in the same way that liquidation after insolvency does. Such legislation may be classed as emergency in one sense but it need not be temporary. <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766" name="t16"></a><a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?navby=case&#038;court=us&#038;vol=310&#038;invol=32#f16">16 </a> 
</p>
</div>
<div>And <i>East New York Savings Bank v. Hahn</i>, issued in 1945, pretty much sums it up:
</p>
</div>
<div>Since <i>Home Bldg. &#038; L. Ass&#8217;n v. Blaisdell</i>, <a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?court=us&#038;vol=290&#038;invol=398">290 U.S. 398 </a>, 54 S.Ct. 231, 88 A.L.R. 1481, there are left hardly any open spaces of controversy concerning the constitutional restrictions of the Contract Clause upon moratory legislation referable to the depression. The comprehensive opinion of Mr. Chief Justice Hughes in that case cut beneath the skin of words to the core of meaning. After a full review of the whole course of decisions expounding the Contract Clause-covering almost the life of this Court-the Chief Justice, drawing on the early insight of Mr. Justice Johnson2 in <i>Ogden v. Saunders</i>, 12 Wheat. 213, 286, as reinforced by later decisions cast in more modern terms, e.g., <i>Manigault v. Springs</i>, <a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?court=us&#038;vol=199&#038;invol=473#480">199 U.S. 473, 480 </a>, 26 S.Ct. 127, 130; <i>Marcus Brown Co. v. Feldman</i>, <a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?court=us&#038;vol=256&#038;invol=170#198">256 U.S. 170, 198 </a>, 41 S.Ct. 465, 466, put the Clause in its proper perspective in our constitutional framework. The <i>Blaisdell </i>case and decisions rendered since (e.g., <i>Honeyman v. Jacobs,</i> <a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?court=us&#038;vol=306&#038;invol=539">306 U.S. 539 </a>, 59 S.Ct. 702; <i>Veix v. Sixth Ward Ass&#8217;n</i>, <a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?court=us&#038;vol=310&#038;invol=32">310 U.S. 32 </a>, 60 S.Ct. 792; <i>Gelfert v. National City Bank</i>, <a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?court=us&#038;vol=313&#038;invol=221">313 U.S. 221 </a>, 61 S.Ct. 898, 133 A.L.R. 1467; <i>Faitoute Co. v. Asbury Park</i>, <a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?court=us&#038;vol=316&#038;invol=502">316 U.S. 502 </a>, 62 S.Ct. 1129), yield this governing constitutional principle: when a widely diffused public interest has become enmeshed in a network of multitudinous private arrangements, the authority of the State &#8216;to safeguard the vital interests of its people,&#8217; 290 U.S. at page 434, 54 S. Ct. at page 239, 88 A.L.R. 1481, is not to be gainsaid by abstracting one such arrangement from its public context and treating it as though it were an isolated private contract constitutionally immune from impairment.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The formal mode of reasoning by means of which this &#8216;protective power of the state,&#8217; 290 U.S. at page 440, 54 S.Ct. at page 241, 88 A.L.R. 1481, is acknowledged is of little moment. It may be treated as an implied condition of every contract and, as such, as much part of the contract as though it were written into it, whereby the State&#8217;s exercise of its power enforces, and does not impair, a contract. A more candid statement is to recognize, as was said in<i> Manigault v. Springs</i>, supra, that the power &#8216;which, in its various ramifications, is known as the police power, is an exercise of the sovereign right of the government to protect the &#8230; general welfare of the people, and is paramount to any rights under contracts  between individuals.&#8217; 199 U.S. at page 480, 26 S.Ct. at page 130. Once we are in this domain of the reserve power of a State we must respect the &#8216;wide discretion on the part of the legislature in determining what is and what is not necessary.&#8217; Id. So far as the constitutional issue is concerned, &#8216;the power of the State when otherwise justified,&#8217; <i>Marcus Brown Co. v. Feldman</i>, <a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?court=us&#038;vol=256&#038;invol=170#198">256 U.S. 170, 198 </a>, 41 S.Ct. 465, 466, is not diminished because a private contract may be affected.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>In other words, a state can use what is in essence its police power to limit the state the absolute right to freely contract, but only “to safeguard the vital interests of its people.”  Suffice it to say that none of those three opinions gave any indication, much less outright held, that a vital interest of the people of any state was to be able to avoid payment of union dues, much less to avoid payment of lower union-administration fees, as a union-beneficiary employee in a union shop. 
</p>
</div>
<div>In any event, <i>Lincoln Union</i>, in pretending that <i>Home Building</i> and the other two New Deal era opinions say things contrary to what they actually say, dealt only with compulsory union <i>membership</i>, not with required non-union-member administrative fees paid to unions.  That case was decided two years after passage of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taft%E2%80%93Hartley_Act">Taft-Hartley Act</a>.  And Taft-Hartley itself bars required union membership, while also requiring that unions negotiate compensation and working conditions on behalf of all the employees within unionized categories, irrespective of whether the employee has chosen to join the union., and also requires the union to represent those employees in controversies between the individual employee and the employer other just as they do for union members in other words, to provide all the union benefits even to employees who opted out of union membership.
</p>
</div>
<div>In return, that law does allow the non-union employees to be required as a provision of the collective-bargaining agreement to pay union-administration fees.
</p>
</div>
<div>I don’t think the administrative-fee requirement is “materially” (a legalese term of art) the same as the pre-Taft-Hartley contractual agreements that barred employers from hiring people who will refuse to join the union. And, certainly, it does not involve addressing severe long-term emergency that even remotely brings it within the reach of the <i>Home Building &#038; Loan Assoc</i>. public-policy exemption from a narrow Contracts Clause interpretation. So, best as I can tell—and I am NOT an expert in labor law—the Supreme Court has never actually held that state ‘right to work’ laws do not violate the Contracts Clause.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>That said, although the rightwing justices normally are all for upholding the right of contract, when the shoe is on the pro-Democratic Party foot rather than the pro-Republican one (or is it the reverse? I’m not sure), they probably would not uphold that right in this circumstance.  These people are the ultimate hypocrites.  And stunningly, unabashedly so.  And they hold a bare majority on the Court.  </div>
<div></div>
<div>For now.
</p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />COOL UPDATE, <a href="http://jacobinmag.com/2012/12/the-shift-from-the-unions/">here</a>.  H/T <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/moneybox/2012/12/13/the_shift_away_from_unions_organized_labor_s_inevitable_terminal_decline.html">Matthew Yglesias</a>.</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/follow-up-to-do-right-to-work-laws-violate-the-constitutions-contracts-clause.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Do ‘Right to Work’ Laws Violate the Constitution&#8217;s Article I Contracts Clause? [Updated]*</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/do-right-to-work-laws-violate-the-constitutions-article-i-contracts-clause-updated.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/do-right-to-work-laws-violate-the-constitutions-article-i-contracts-clause-updated.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2012 04:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[constitution]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Matthew Yglesias]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Right-to-Work laws]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/do-right-to-work-laws-violate-the-constitutions-article-i-contracts-clause-updated.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[No State shall enter into any Treaty, Alliance, or Confederation; grant Letters of Marque and Reprisal; coin Money; emit Bills of Credit; make any Thing but gold and silver Coin a Tender in Payment of Debts; pass any Bill of Attainder, ex post facto Law, or Law impairing the Obligation of Contracts, or grant any [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>No State shall enter into any Treaty, Alliance, or Confederation; grant Letters of Marque and Reprisal; coin Money; emit Bills of Credit; make any Thing but gold and silver Coin a Tender in Payment of Debts; pass any Bill of Attainder, ex post facto Law, or Law impairing the Obligation of Contracts, or grant any Title of Nobility.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212; Article I, Section 10, Constitution of the United States<br /><!--[if !supportLineBreakNewLine]--><br /><!--[endif]-->
</p>
</div>
<div>No, I didn’t post this to highlight the prohibition against states’ granting any title of nobility.  I posted it to highlight the prohibition against states’ enacting a law impairing the obligation of contracts—which the Supreme Court has interpreted as a guarantee of the right to freely enter into contracts.  </div>
<div></div>
<div>That guarantee does have exceptions, of course, none of which includes the type of contract that state so-called ‘right to work’ laws bar.  Including the ones passed today by the Michigan legislature, after springing out of nowhere last week.  (Although maybe the proponents of these laws think these statutes come within this exception created by the current Supreme Court’s majority: any law that helps corporations is constitutional.  It’s a corollary to the majority’s maxim that any federal statute, such as ones concerning compelled contractual arbitration, or labor unions, or federal-court jurisdiction, be distorted beyond plausible recognition of the statute’s actual language, if necessary, to favor corporations.  This is known by them as “originalism” and “textualism.”  And known by others, not all of whom are justices, as cute, pick-and-choose gimmickry.)
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>But as Slate’s Matthew Yglesias <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/moneybox/2012/12/11/right_to_work_laws_stunning_hypocrisy.html">points out</a> today, what these bills do is use the force of law—state law—to interfere with the right of contract between two private parties: labor unions and private employers.  In Michigan, the legislature actually passed two separate laws today: one pertaining to labor contracts between labor unions and private employers, the other pertaining to contracts between labor unions and public employers (i.e., state and local governments).  But as a constitutional matter, this doesn’t matter.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Yglesias points out what does matter, although he argues it only as a matter of hypocrisy, not as a possible violation of constitutional law.  After saying that the concrete economic impact of these statutes is murky—something that Paul Krugman and most Angry Bears would dispute (and have disputed)—he hits the nail on the head about the actual nature of these laws:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>[What is] not murky is the absurd hypocrisy that has to go into making the case for right-to-work legislation.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The way this works is that if there&#8217;s a labor union at a given business establishment that&#8217;s bargaining for some higher pay or benefits or better work-rules or whatever it&#8217;s rapidly going to find that there&#8217;s a free rider problem. Everyone in the relevant class of workers gets the benefits whether or not they join the union. So something the union is often going to want to bargain for is some kind of rule stating that everyone hired in the relevant class has to join the union, or has to pay dues to the union, or something else along those lines.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Now naturally an employer&#8217;s not going to want to agree to that. But he&#8217;s not going to want to agree to higher pay or more vacation days either. That&#8217;s why it&#8217;s a negotiation. A right-to-work law is a law <em>banning</em> employers from making that concession.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The impact, obviously, is to make it hard to form strong unions in a given jurisdiction and thus make it a more business-friendly jurisdiction. But note that this same trick works across the board. You could just ban pay raises in general. Any one firm, after all, faces a dilemma. On the one hand it would be more profitable to pay people less. On the other hand, it&#8217;s also unprofitable to have everyone quit to go work for some other higher-paying company. So a law against pay raises would make everyone more profitable, spurring crazy business investment and job creation. Except nobody does that because it would be (a) insane and (b) obviously unfair. And yet the proponents of right-to-work laws are generally <em>exactly</em> the people most inclined to stand up for freedom of contract under other circumstances.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And yet the proponents of right-to-work laws are generally <em>exactly</em> the people most inclined to stand up for freedom of contract under other circumstances, indeed.  They do this standing up in legislatures, think tanks, and lobbying firms.  And in court, including the Supreme one.  Some of them doing this standing from the black-robes-wearing, comfortable-leather-chair-sitting side of the courtroom bench.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Now that the gauntlet has been thrown, labor should pick it up and take it to court.  There is, I think, little doubt that these laws impair the obligation of <i>current</i> labor contracts and also impinge upon the right to freely enter into contracts.  The proponents of these laws will defend them on the ground that state laws impairing the obligation of this particular type of contract isn’t what the framers had in mind.  And undoubtedly they’re right; it’s a historical fact that the Washington, Madison, and the others considered union organizing <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/the_slatest/2012/10/05/justice_scalia_the_textualist_scotus_justice_explains_stance_on_abortion_gay_rights_.html">right up there with sodomy and murder</a> as unprotected by the Fourteenth Amendment, which they foresaw would be added to the Constitution a few decades later, or by the clause in Article 1, Section 10, prohibiting states from impairing the obligation of contracts. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>But labor unions still should challenge the constitutionality of these laws, even if they have to try to convince the courts, and eventually <i>the </i>Court, that the laws are Letters of Marque and Reprisal. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Which, at least regarding the Reprisal part, sounds about right. 
</p>
<p>&#8212;-</p>
<p>UPDATE: Excellent, thorough article by Rick Ungar in Forbes today, titled “<a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/rickungar/2012/12/11/right-to-work-laws-explained-debunked-demystified/">‘</a><a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/rickungar/2012/12/11/right-to-work-laws-explained-debunked-demystified/">Right-to-Work’ Laws Explained, Debunked &#038; Demystified.</a>&#8221;  Don&#8217;t miss it.</p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />*I just posted a lengthy follow-up post, <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/12/follow-up-to-do-right-to-work-laws.html">here</a>.</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/do-right-to-work-laws-violate-the-constitutions-article-i-contracts-clause-updated.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Public Learns Disaster Relief Was Etched Out of the Sketch. Uh-Oh.</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/the-public-learns-disaster-relief-was-etched-out-of-the-sketch-uh-oh.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/the-public-learns-disaster-relief-was-etched-out-of-the-sketch-uh-oh.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 29 Oct 2012 20:46:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Bill Keller]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[disaster relief]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Etch-A-Sketch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[FEMA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Matthew Yglesias]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New York Times]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/the-public-learns-disaster-relief-was-etched-out-of-the-sketch-uh-oh.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[MITT ROMNEY: &#8220;Every time you have an occasion to take something from the federal government and send it back to the states, that&#8217;s the right direction. And if you can go even further, and send it back to the private sector, that&#8217;s even better. Instead of thinking, in the federal budget, what we should cut, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>MITT ROMNEY: &#8220;Every time you have an occasion to take something from the federal government and send it back to the states, that&#8217;s the right direction. And if you can go even further, and send it back to the private sector, that&#8217;s even better. Instead of thinking, in the federal budget, what we should cut, we should ask the opposite question, what should we keep?&#8221;
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>DEBATE MODERATOR JOHN KING: Including disaster relief, though?&#8221;
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>ROMNEY: We cannot &#8212; we cannot afford to do those things without jeopardizing the future for our kids. It is simply immoral, in my view, for us to continue to rack up larger and larger debts and pass them on to our kids, knowing full well that we&#8217;ll all be dead and gone before it&#8217;s paid off. It makes no sense at all.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212; <i>Republican primary campaign debate last year
</p>
<p></i></div>
<div></div>
<div>Slate’s Matthew Yglesias points to that today <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/moneybox/2012/10/29/romney_s_fema_cuts.html">andcomments</a>:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>More prosaically, though the Romney campaign was understandably <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/10/28/mitt-romney-fema_n_2036198.html" target="_blank">circumspect over the weekend about his spending plans</a> the fact is that his overall budget requires sharp cuts in everything. The central issue is that Romney wants to cap government spending at 20 percent of GDP while boosting military spending to 4 percent of GDP and leaving Social Security harmless. That <a href="http://www.cbpp.org/cms/?fa=view&#038;id=3658" target="_blank">means a 34 percent across-the-board cut in other programs</a> according to the Center on Budget and Policy Priorities. Unless, that is, Medicare is also exempted from the cuts in which case you&#8217;d need a 53 percent cut. …
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>If a storm damages basic physical infrastructure (power lines, bridges) and imperils human life it would be the height of penny-wise, pound-foolish thinking to suppose that the afflicted area should wait months or years to repair the damage. Ultimately, anyplace is going to go back to robust wealth creation faster if basic stuff gets fixed up faster. But that requires financing by an entity capable of rapidly financing expensive projects—i.e., the federal government. Left to its own devices a storm-ravaged Delaware or Louisiana is going to be squeezed between balanced budget rules and falling sales tax receipts and be forced into an increasing state of dilapidation.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>How about a storm-ravaged <i>Florida</i>?  According to current polls, slightly more than half of Florida voters want their state to take over disaster relief, at least until arrangements can be made for the private sector to take it over.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And, about that question Romney asked: What should we KEEP?  Well, in addition to the Bush tax cuts for the wealthy and defense spending for private contractors, what DOES Romney think we should keep?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>We cannot – we cannot afford to do things like disaster relief without jeopardizing the future of our kids.  We CAN, though, afford to give massive additional tax cuts to the wealthy, and huge additional contracts to Republican defense contractors, without jeopardizing the future of our kids.  Right?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>What’s truly unconscionable is that it’s taking Hurricane Sandy to educate the public about the plans Romney and Ryan have stated so clearly.  I’ve been utterly unable to understand why the Obama campaign hasn’t been running video clips of Romney’s primary-campaign statements as the foundation of their ads.  I’ve thought all along that this is all Obama would need to do in order to win.  I think Sandy will prove me right.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And, here’s a shout-out to New York Time columnist Bill Keller for <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/10/29/opinion/keller-the-no-agenda-myth.html?_r=0">exposing for the absurd myth that it is</a> the punditry’s “in” refrain that we don’t know what either of the two candidates would use the office to do in the next four years, because, well, neither has specified sufficiently.  As Keller says, actually <i>both</i> have specified sufficiently. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And Romney’s <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/10/did-romney-begin-to-reverse-etch-sketch.html">already begun to reverse-sketch his etchings</a>.  Suffice it to say that he’s not spent the last week promising “BIG CHANGE” because he plans to etch out of his sketch all those primary-campaign promises. 
</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/the-public-learns-disaster-relief-was-etched-out-of-the-sketch-uh-oh.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Yglesias Misses the Point. Again. [with correction]</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/yglesias-misses-the-point-again-with-correction.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/yglesias-misses-the-point-again-with-correction.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 17 Jul 2012 16:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Bain Capital]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Matthew Yglesias]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[offshoring]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/yglesias-misses-the-point-again-with-correction.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Rules requiring firms to restrict employment to their country of origin would be hideously inefficient if applied on a global basis, and they would be every bit as devastating to American employees of foreign firms as offshoring by American firms is to workers who lose their jobs here. (One might also ask where the borders [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>Rules requiring firms to restrict employment to their country of origin would be hideously inefficient if applied on a global basis, and they would be every bit as devastating to American employees of foreign firms as offshoring by American firms is to workers who lose their jobs here. (One might also ask where the borders of corporate patriotism ought to be. If it’s wrong for a Michigan-based car company to have a supply chain that extends to Mexico, why is Ohio OK? After all, it hardly makes a difference to a laid-off worker where exactly his job went—the bad news is that he lost his job.)
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Over the long run, we’re all going to be more prosperous if we live in a world where firms are allowed to locate work where it’s most efficient to locate it. This is exactly why, <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ud3mMj0AZZk" target="_blank">despite some tough ads</a>, the Obama administration has not proposed any policies to restrict firms’ freedom to shift work across state or national boundaries.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Romney’s unwillingness to make the case for outsourcing reflects, in part, political timidity. But more broadly, it underscores that although he’s been an eager participant in contemporary capitalism, he’s not willing to mount a policy response to its vicissitudes.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212; <i><a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/business/moneybox/2012/07/romney_and_offshoring_why_won_t_he_defend_bain_capital_s_record_.html#comments">Offshoring Is Fine. Why won’t Mitt Romney defend Bain’s record?</a></i>Matthew Yglesias, Slate, yesterday afternoon.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>It’s surely true that rules requiring firms to restrict employment to their country of origin would be hideously inefficient if applied on a global basis, and they would be every bit as devastating to American employees of foreign firms as offshoring by American firms is to workers who lose their jobs here. </p>
<p>But, to my knowledge, the only one who’s equated the absence of* government policy (of necessity on this issue, statutes) that would restrict corporate employment to the country of the corporation’s origin, and a private equity firm’s investment in companies that specialize in assisting American corporations with offshoring employment, is Yglesias.  Even Romney apparently recognizes the distinction. Not sure why Yglesias doesn’t.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a>It’s one thing to argue that utterly unfettered globalization of employment by corporations worldwide ultimately has a positive effect on the American economy—as Yglesias does. But it&#8217;s another thing entirely to actually convince a majority of the public that this is so even in light of current trends and actual facts. </div>
<div></div>
<div>And it’s one thing to argue that laws that forbid companies from relocating jobs from the company’s home country to another one would have a negative side to it because of possible retaliatory laws in other countries, and another thing to equate that with decisions by corporations themselves about whether to offshore or not. (And, setting aside the obvious constitutional bar to prohibiting a corporation’s relocation of jobs from one state to another, it’s a lot easier for families to relocate from Michigan to Ohio than from Michigan to Mexico.)</p>
<p>The thing that Yglesias doesn’t get is that Romney’s claiming that his private-sector career demonstrates his ability to create not just wealth for investors but jobs <i>en masse</i> for the public. There’s really no way for him to make that claim persuasively, because it plainly isn’t true. He can defend offshoring as a corporate strategy, but corporate strategy is a different matter than economic strategy.</p>
<p>Unless, of course, Romney wants to argue that encouraging offshoring by American corporations is good government policy. Hope he does.  But then, I&#8217;m a Democrat.
</p>
<p>*<i>Sentence corrected to insert the words &#8220;the absence of&#8221;.</i></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/yglesias-misses-the-point-again-with-correction.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Matthew Yglesias, Slate’s Boy With a Little Curl</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/matthew-yglesias-slates-boy-with-a-little-curl.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/matthew-yglesias-slates-boy-with-a-little-curl.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 16 Jul 2012 15:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[ACA litigation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[legislative logrolling]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Matthew Yglesias]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[offshoring]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Supreme court]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/matthew-yglesias-slates-boy-with-a-little-curl.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Lost in the shuffle here is the question of what it is Romney is denying he&#8217;s responsible for. Stipulate that Romney somehow had nothing to do with running a company of which he was the CEO and sole shareholder. Does he think, in retrospect, that his subordinates did something wrong by offshoring jobs? Clearly he [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>Lost in the shuffle here is the question of what it is Romney is denying he&#8217;s responsible for. Stipulate that Romney somehow had nothing to do with running a company of which he was the CEO and sole shareholder. Does he think, in retrospect, that his subordinates did something wrong by offshoring jobs? Clearly he didn&#8217;t, which highlights the absurdity of his claims not to have been responsible. It&#8217;s true that he wasn&#8217;t running the country [<i>sic</i>] on a day-to-day basis, but he really was titular CEO and had Bain been doing something he deemed outrageous he could and should have stepped in to stop them. But he doesn&#8217;t believe that. And what&#8217;s more,<i> </i><em>all indications are that Barack Obama also doesn&#8217;t think Bain was doing anything wrong</em>. [Emphasis in original.] As president he&#8217;s made no moves to make it illegal for companies to shift production work abroad and has publicly associated himself with a wide range of American firms—from GE to Apple and beyond—who&#8217;ve done just that to varying extents. And we all remember what happened to Obama&#8217;s promise to renegotiate NAFTA after taking office, right?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>In my view both Obama and Romney are quite right about this. I&#8217;ll say more on this during the workweek, but one quick test is do you think there&#8217;s something immoral about the fact that Toyota and BMW have manufacturing facilities located in the United States? Should the Japanese and German governments be stopping Japan- and Germany-based firms from locating production offshore?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212;<i><a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/moneybox/2012/07/14/bain_outsourcing_neither_obama_nor_romney_think_it_s_wrong_so_what_are_we_arguing_about_.html">The Fake Headlines: Neither Obama Nor Romney Is Against Offshoring</a></i>, Matthew Yglesias, Slate, Jul. 14
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I posted a comment to it, saying:
</p>
</div>
<div><a name="more"></a></div>
<div>Well, when Obama starts claiming that one of his key qualifications for reelection is that he’s helped create jobs in China—or when Romney starts saying that Bain invested in companies that specialized in moving jobs overseas in exchange for promises by German and Japanese companies to open, or keep, factories in this country—Yglesias’s equivalency argument might be less ridiculous. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>One of Obama’s spot-on arguments against Romney’s claim that his Bain experience was a successful jobs-creation experience rather than merely a successful wealth-creation-for-investors experience is that there’s a huge difference between experience in creating wealth for private investors, by any means available and at whatever expense to others, and creating good for the country’s overall economy and general welfare.  This offshoring issue is a classic case in point. Setting aside whether the federal government has the legal authority to prohibit private companies from offshoring—and I don’t think the government has any such legal authority, except in certain limited national security or foreign policy circumstances—there’s an obvious critical difference between not trying to stop this country’s companies from offshoring, for fear of retribution by other countries’ companies, similar to trying to avoid a tariff war, and aggressively aiding offshoring by American companies irrespective of any up-side for the general American economy. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Add to that that, as several other commenters have pointed out, the German and Japanese companies that offshore in this country do so mainly in manufacturing products or parts for products that will be sold in North America, mostly in this country.  GM, Ford, Chrysler and some U.S. auto-components manufacturing companies have factories in Europe, but the products and components made there are sold in Europe.  Like the German and Japanese auto companies that Yglesias equates with Bain’s offshoring-specialist companies, the American auto-industry companies continue to make the parts and cars sold in their home country in factories in their home country. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Which, of course, would not be the case any longer had the Bush and Obama administrations taken Romney’s advice and let Detroit fail.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>That said—and for the same reasons—Yglesias is wrong in saying that unless Romney thinks there’s something wrong with offshoring, it’s absurd for him to deny responsibility for Bain’s investments in offshoring-specialist companies during the three-year period beginning in early 1999.  If in fact Romney was no longer associated with Bain during that period, he would have every right to correct the record, whether or not he thinks there was anything wrong with what Bain did during that time.  But the question of whether Bain did anything wrong in investing in offshoring-specialist companies—during the period between 1993 and 1999, when (at least as I understand it) it apparently was doing so at Romney’s clear behest, or during the following three years—depends on what is meant by “wrong.” 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>It was not illegal.  But many voters think that, while it clearly was helpful to Bain’s investors and to Romney (who has continued since then to receive large payments from Bain), it was not helpful to the larger American economy and to the middle class.  It did not create jobs in this country; instead, it eliminated them.  And Romney is running for president virtually entirely on his claimed credential of being a jobs creator and of knowing how to create jobs—in America.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I’m <a href="http://www.destinyland.org/when_she_was_good.htm">hesitant to be too critical of Yglesias</a> for his rather obvious conflations here.  He was, after all, not just the first pundit but also one of the very few even yet to point out a stunning, absolutely <i>jaw-dropping</i>proposition of law stated by <i>four of the nine</i> Supreme Court justices in their joint dissent late last month in the Affordable Care Act case, the part of the dissent concerning the issue of the severability of the part of the Medicaid provision in the Act that the Court’s majority struck down, in which the dissenters, while claiming that the majority was rewriting the Medicaid provision in order to save much of it, wanted to rewrite, rather dramatically, the Constitution’s separation of powers between Congress and the Court. Only four hours after the release of the opinion, when almost no one except the journalists covering the Court had yet read the dissent, Yglesias <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/moneybox/2012/06/28/why_the_dissenters_thought_dentist_deregulation_was_unconstitutional.html">wrote</a>:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>As I&#8217;ve noticed previously, there&#8217;s lots of other stuff in the Affordable Care Act besides the new regulation of insurance companies, including a move to <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/moneybox/2012/06/26/the_affordable_care_act_vs_the_dentists_cartel.html">deregulate dental services</a>. So I was curious to see why the dissenters in the Supreme Court thought that not only was the individual mandate and the provisions related to the individual mandate unconstitutional, but also all this other stuff.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The answer is that they appear to have made up a new Christmas Tree Doctrine under which legitimate acts of Congress are held null and void if Antonin Scalia thinks they were part of some kind of unseemly horse-trading:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Some provisions, such as requiring chain restaurants to display nutritional content, appear likely to operate as Congress intended, but they fail the second test for severability. There is no reason to believe that Congress would have enacted them independently. The Court has not previously had occasion to consider severability in the context of an omnibus enactment like the ACA, which includes not only many provisions that are ancillary to its central provisions but also many that are entirely unrelated—hitched on because it was a quick way to get them passed despite opposition, or because their proponents could exact their enactment as the quid pro quo for their needed support. When we are confronted with such a so called “Christmas tree,” a law to which many nongermane ornaments have been attached, we think the proper rule must be that when the tree no longer exists the ornaments are superfluous. We have no reliable basis for knowing which pieces of the Act would have passed on their own. It is certain that many of them would not have, and it is not a proper function of this Court to guess which.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>That all seems fine except I would have thought it was the prelude to the <i>opposite</i> ruling. It&#8217;s not the proper function of the court to guess why different provisions were enacted, just to rule on the constitutionality of laws. Since there&#8217;s plainly no constitutional problem with regulating interstate chain restaurants, the law is the law until Congress repeals the law. Instead, Justices Scalia, Alito, Kennedy, and Thomas have decided that rather than pick and choose it would be better to strike everything.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>
</div>
<div>This is far, far more newsworthy than the teensy bit of attention it has received suggests.  Four Supreme Court justices think legislative <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logrolling">logrolling</a> is improper and that therefore the Court can strike down full pieces of legislation that a majority of justices don’t like whenever they decide that some provision, however small, in the full piece of legislation is unconstitutional.  After all, y’know, maybe the rest of the legislation would not have been enacted without the <i>quid pro quo</i> votes.  Presumably, this also would apply to state laws as well as to federal laws—but, of course, as with federal laws, only to laws that the conservatives don’t like.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<p>I’d been meaning to write about this truly radical part of the dissent in the ACA case, but hadn’t gotten around to it.  Now I have.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/matthew-yglesias-slates-boy-with-a-little-curl.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Does Uncompensated Care Raise Prices for the Insured?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/does-uncompensated-care-raise-prices-for-the-insured.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/does-uncompensated-care-raise-prices-for-the-insured.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 08 Jul 2012 15:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Matthew Yglesias]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Robert Waldmann]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/does-uncompensated-care-raise-prices-for-the-insured.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Lifted from Robert&#8217;s Stochastic Thoughts comes this comment on Matt Yglesias: by Robert Waldmann Matthew Yglesias asks  (Does Uncompensated Care Raise Prices for the Insured?). I am having trouble with moneybox comments so I comment here. OK first I have to note that a philosophy concentrator half my age is doing pretty well to make [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Lifted from Robert&#8217;s Stochastic Thoughts comes this comment on Matt Yglesias: </p>
<p>by Robert Waldmann</p>
<p>Matthew Yglesias <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/moneybox/2012/07/05/does_uncompensated_care_raise_prices_for_the_insured_.html#article_comment_box">asks</a>  (<a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766">Does Uncompensated Care Raise Prices for the Insured?)</a><br /><a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766"><br /></a><br />. I am having trouble with moneybox comments so I comment here. OK first I have to note that a philosophy concentrator half my age is doing pretty well to make me think about economics. Yglesias&#8217;s willingness to think and write about technical subjects is a valuable national resource. This is also true of field specialists can respond to his arguments.   <br />His argument<br />
<blockquote>Think about the CVS downstairs from my office. It charges prices that it believes are profit-maximizing. Now suppose some indigent person comes in and burns all the magazines on their magazine rack for fun. The guy&#8217;s got no money, so CVS can&#8217;t recoup its losses. Does this force CVS to raise prices on Diet Coke to make up for the cost? No—CVS was already charging profit-maximizing prices, and past losses are irrelevant to determining optimal forward-looking pricing strategy.</p></blockquote>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Hmm logically this implies that people who live in high crime neighborhoods in which people do stuff like that don&#8217;t pay more for goods. But they do. So what is missing ?<br />    <br />Well first the thought experiment considers an unanticipateable cost and one repetition of which is not likely. Uncompensated health care isn&#8217;t like that at all.<br />    <br />Even a totally profit oriented for profit hospital chain will consider the forecast rate of unconmpensated care when deciding whether to invest in building new hospitals. A cost which doesn&#8217;t affect the marginal cost of a good or service and doesn&#8217;t in itself effect the elasticity of demand will affect entry, which depends on forecast average cost and not on marginal cost.<br />    <br />This will affect prices. The reason is that with higher unavoidable costs a higher ratio of price to marginal cost is required to convinced firms to enter.<br />    <br />Let&#8217;s imagine a socially useful application of Yglesias&#8217;s theory (if it were valid). Stealing from CVS and giving the the stolen goods to the median citizen would be a distortion free transfer from CVS shareholders to people on average poorer than CVS shareholders. This would cause increased welfare. I don&#8217;t think Yglesias thinks this would be a good approach.<br />    <br />I don&#8217;t think he thought the problem through to the end (oops I mean to the beginning &#8212; entry of firms).</p>
<p>slightly edited from <a href="http://rjwaldmann.blogspot.com/2012/07/does-uncompensated-health-care-raise.html">Stochastic Thoughts</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/does-uncompensated-care-raise-prices-for-the-insured.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sorta Interesting … (Updated!)*</title>
		<link>./../../2012/06/sorta-interesting-updated.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/06/sorta-interesting-updated.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Jun 2012 14:16:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[ACA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Matthew Yglesias]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obamacare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Orin Kerr]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ruth Bader Ginsburg]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Supreme court]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Volokh Conspiracy]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/06/sorta-interesting-updated.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Thought y’all would enjoy this post, on one of THE BIG DEAL law-profs’ blogs.  It’s bloggers are right- to center-right libertarians, all (or at least most) of them former law clerks to one of the conservative Supreme Court justices. Ah. And this is even moreinteresting.  Woo-hoo! &#8212;&#8211;UPDATE: Welll.  Hmmm.  As I said earlier today in a [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>Thought y’all would enjoy <a href="http://www.volokh.com/2012/06/19/foolishly-reading-the-tea-leaves-of-justice-ginsburgs-speech-at-the-acs/">this post</a>, on one of THE BIG DEAL law-profs’ blogs.  It’s bloggers are right- to center-right libertarians, all (or at least most) of them former law clerks to one of the conservative Supreme Court justices.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Ah. And <a href="http://hosted.ap.org/dynamic/stories/U/US_AP_POLL_HEALTH_CARE?SITE=AP&#038;SECTION=HOME&#038;TEMPLATE=DEFAULT">this </a>is even <i>more</i>interesting.  Woo-hoo!
</p>
<p>&#8212;&#8211;<br />UPDATE: <a href="http://www.npr.org/blogs/thetwo-way/2012/06/20/155434549/survey-former-supreme-court-clerks-think-court-will-strike-healthcare-mandate?ft=1&#038;f=1001">Welll</a>.  Hmmm.  As I said earlier today in a comment in response to JackD’s comment about my post, I was surprised to read the original law-prof blogger’s interpretation of Ginsburg’s weekend comments, because on Monday I had concluded the opposite after reading a quote from Ginsburg’s speech. 
<div>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The quote was:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>As one may expect, many of the most controversial cases remain pending. So it is likely that the sharp disagreement rate will go up next week and the week after.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>As I noted in my comment to Jack, “Sharp disagreement,” in Supreme Court coverage, usually means 5-4 decisions, although sometimes it means “fractured,” as in, there were a zillion separate concurring and dissenting opinions, and no one can actually figure out what the hell the actual result was. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>As I also said, the ACA case, of course, isn’t the only high-profile case the Court will decide in the next 10 days or so.  But I still read that comment as suggesting a 5-4 result in the ACA case.  The CW is that if the ACA is stricken down, it will be 5-4, but that if it’s upheld it will be 6-3.  But Kerr could be right.  Ginsburg might have just been sending out a red herring.  Who knows?  Or: Oh, what the hell.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Ooooh.  This is more nerve-wracking than betting on your Kentucky Derby favorite, who’s no one else’s favorite; your odds are even <i>worse</i>. And there’s no “place” or “show” here.  Unless ….
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>As I also said in responding to comments to my post—JackD’s and run’s—the impact of the poll I linked to in the last sentence of my post is, I think, that it suggests that, contrary to the CW of the last two years, the healthcare-insurance issue could be a big positive, rather than a negative, for the Dems in November, if the Court does strike down the entire ACA or the mandate part of it.  (And even if it doesn’t, since by the election most people finally will actually know what’s in the law, what’s not in the law, and what the purpose of the mandate is and how it relates to the preexisting-conditions provision.)  The Repubs want the status quo.  The Dems and a substantial majority of the public don’t.</p>
<p>&#8212;&#8211;<br />*In response to a comment by Gary, in the Comments to this post, asking what “CW” is, I wrote:</p>
<p>
<div>
</div>
<div>Conventional wisdom.  I&#8217;m sorry.  I did exactly what I hate when other people do that.  Especially mainstream-media bloggers like Matthew Yglesias, who regularly drops names of people I&#8217;ve never heard of, and the like, on his blog on Slate.  I guess now I qualify to blog on Slate.    <br /> <br />Again, sorry.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Beverly, 6/21
</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/06/sorta-interesting-updated.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Bain Capital vs. Berkshire Hathaway**</title>
		<link>./../../2012/05/bain-capital-vs-berkshire-hathaway.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/05/bain-capital-vs-berkshire-hathaway.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 21 May 2012 18:09:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Bain Capital]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Berkshire Hathaway]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cory Booker]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Matthew Yglesias]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/05/bain-capital-vs-berkshire-hathaway.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Matthew Yglesias channels … me! Yep, that&#8217;s right.  And now that, as Yglesias discusses, Newark Mayor Cory Booker has given the Obama campaign permission to explain the differences between the various types of venture capital “models” (as Yglesias calls them), conceding that, yes, that may really be more relevant to the key issues in the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>Matthew Yglesias <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/05/steven-rattner-misses-point-romneys-and.html">channels … me</a>!
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Yep, <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/moneybox/2012/05/21/with_walkback_corey_booker_has_it_right_on_private_equity.html">that&#8217;s right</a>.  And now that, as Yglesias discusses, Newark Mayor Cory Booker has given the Obama campaign permission to explain the differences between the various types of venture capital “models” (as Yglesias calls them), conceding that, yes, that may really be more relevant to the key issues in the campaign than Obama’s earlier relationship with Jeremiah Wright, I strongly urge the Obama campaign to do that—in detail, with as much specificity as is necessary to illustrate it. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>In my earlier post, I mentioned the distinction between, say, the funding-of-Silicon-Valley-startups venture capital model and the leveraged-buyout-to-extract-value-and-then-close-the-company model that Bain engaged in (apparently) regularly when Romney headed it.  Yglesias doesn’t mention the former but contrasts the latter with the genuine-turnaround model, which is the model that Bain and Romney claim was (and Bain claims, is)** theirs. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Yglesias is right to point out that the genuine-turnaround model is distinct from the extract-value-and-then-close-the-company one.  But I think there’s also a distinction between the leveraged-buyout-to-extract-value-and-then-close-the-company model that Bain engaged (and, I assume, still engages) in, in which the intent is to “flip” the company as soon as possible, and the (to my knowledge) Berkshire Hathaway model, in which the venture capital firm, fund or holding company invests in companies, long-term, including buying some companies outright with the intent to actually own them for the foreseeable future.  (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berkshire_Hathaway">From Wikipedia</a>: “Berkshire Hathaway Inc. … is an American multinational conglomerate holding company headquartered in Omaha, Nebraska, United States, that oversees and manages a number of subsidiary companies.”)</div>
<div></div>
<div>Surely there are differences between the decisions a Bain-like company makes <i>vis-à-vis</i> the businesses it acquires in order to flip quickly for large profits and a Berkshire Hathaway-like firm whose interest in the acquired business is long-term, because the very purpose of the investment is different.  Those differences matter.  A lot, I would think.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>As for Booker, his short-term interest seems analogous to the Bain venture-capital model.  Yglesias says he&#8217;s receiving quite a bit of campaign funding from finance types. Including, presumably, those of the Bain model.  (Or maybe Booker just doesn&#8217;t recognize the distinction.)*</p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />*This parenthetical was added after the original posting.</p>
<p>**This parenthetical was corrected for clarity.</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/05/bain-capital-vs-berkshire-hathaway.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
