<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>federal reserve &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Release of transcripts of 2007 Fed meetings</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/release-of-transcripts-of-2007-fed-meetings.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/release-of-transcripts-of-2007-fed-meetings.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 16 Jan 2013 15:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2007]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[federal reserve]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/release-of-transcripts-of-2007-fed-meetings.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[A note from Wonkblog For anybody who cares about how the country ended up in this precarious economic state, a very big day is coming soon, as information that has been under lock and key for the past five years will be shared with the world.  The Federal Reserve keeps transcripts of its meetings to [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/wonkblog/wp/2013/01/15/secrets-of-the-crisis-revealed-what-to-expect-from-transcripts-of-2007-fed-meetings/">A note from Wonkblog</a><br />
<blockquote>For anybody who cares about how the country ended up in this precarious economic state, a very big day is coming soon, as information that has been under lock and key for the past five years will be shared with the world. </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><div><a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/wonkblog/files/2013/01/fomc-1.jpg"><img alt="The FOMC had a big year in 2007! (Federal Reserve photo)" height="133" src="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/wonkblog/files/2013/01/fomc-1.jpg" width="200"></a></div>
<p>The Federal Reserve keeps transcripts of its meetings to set monetary policy, and releases them with a five year delay. It does not announce in advance when they will be released, but if the past is a guide, any day now we will be getting full transcripts of the 2007 meetings of the Federal Open Market Committee. Transcripts of all eight regularly scheduled meetings, plus three special emergency sessions to respond to the earliest ripples of the financial crisis, will be posted to the <a href="http://www.federalreserve.gov/">Federal Reserve’s Web site</a>.  (The FOMC had a big year in 2007! (Federal Reserve photo)</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/release-of-transcripts-of-2007-fed-meetings.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>One question for Ben Bernanke</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/one-question-for-ben-bernanke.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/one-question-for-ben-bernanke.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 03 Oct 2012 02:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[federal reserve]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[monetary policy]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/one-question-for-ben-bernanke.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Mike Kimel The other day Ben Bernanke gave a speech in which he asked and answered five questions about the Fed: 1. What are the Fed&#8217;s objectives, and how is it trying to meet them?2. What&#8217;s the relationship between the Fed&#8217;s monetary policy and thefiscal decisions of the Administration and the Congress?3. What is the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Mike Kimel</p>
<p>The other day Ben Bernanke gave a speech in which he <a href="http://www.federalreserve.gov/newsevents/speech/bernanke20121001a.htm">asked and answered five questions about the Fed</a>:<br />
<blockquote>1. What are the Fed&#8217;s objectives, and how is it trying to meet them?<br />2. What&#8217;s the relationship between the Fed&#8217;s monetary policy and the<br />fiscal decisions of the Administration and the Congress?<br />3. What is the risk that the Fed&#8217;s accommodative monetary policy will<br />lead to inflation?<br />4. How does the Fed&#8217;s monetary policy affect savers and investors?<br />5. How is the Federal Reserve held accountable in our democratic<br />society?</p></blockquote>
<p>I&#8217;d have asked only one question, similar to his first, albeit with a bit of prefacing.  This is what I&#8217;d love to ask Bernanke.</p>
<blockquote><p>The Fed has a very close relationship with the financial sector.  Simple examples of this include:</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>a.  Of the three advisory committees that advise the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve directly, even in theory only one, the Consumer Advisory Council, has a non-zero number of members who don&#8217;t directly work for the financial sector.   Regional Federal Reserve Banks are also, ahem, advised by similar committees made up entirely or almost entirely by financial institutions and/or their representatives.<br />b.  By design, every one of the Fed&#8217;s methods for raising and lowering the money supply require direct interactions between the Fed and financial institutions.  None of these methods even allow for any direct interactions between the Fed and members of the public.  (Note that raising and lowering the money supply does not in any way constitute &#8220;regulating the banks.&#8221;)<br />c.  Federally chartered banks and some state chartered banks are designated &#8220;members&#8221; of the Federal Reserve system &#8211; no similar appellation or roles apply to the public at large.<br />d.  Federal Reserve banks serve as repository institutions for member banks, but none of the services performed by the Fed for banks are<br />available to the public at large.<br />e.  And of course, there is something of a revolving door between the Fed and the financial sector.</p>
<p>Given all of this, what would the Fed&#8217;s objectives be, and how would it be trying to meet those objectives, if the interests of the public were given equal weight to the interests of the financial sector?</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/one-question-for-ben-bernanke.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
