<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Economist&#8217;s View &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Not All Economists are to Blame, But Some Are</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/not-all-economists-are-to-blame-but-some-are.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/not-all-economists-are-to-blame-but-some-are.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 17 Jul 2012 13:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Economist's View]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mark Thoma]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/not-all-economists-are-to-blame-but-some-are.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Mark Thoma notes the discrepancy between pretty much standard economics and what the popular discussion considers &#8216;economics&#8217; : Not All Economists are to Blame, But Some Are  A defense of some, but not all economists: Why Some Economists Failed  I assert that some economists got things mostly right about the recession and what was needed to [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div></div>
<p><a href="http://economistsview.typepad.com/economistsview/2012/07/not-all-economists-are-to-blame-but-some-are.html">Mark Thoma</a> notes the discrepancy between pretty much standard economics and what the popular discussion considers &#8216;economics&#8217; :</p>
<blockquote><p><a href="http://economistsview.typepad.com/economistsview/2012/07/not-all-economists-are-to-blame-but-some-are.html">Not All Economists are to Blame, But Some Are</a> </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>A defense of some, but not all economists:</p>
<p><a href="http://www.thefiscaltimes.com/Columns/2012/07/17/Bubbles-and-Bailouts-Why-Some-Economists-Failed.aspx#page1">Why Some Economists Failed</a> </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p><a href="http://www.thefiscaltimes.com/Columns/2012/07/17/Bubbles-and-Bailouts-Why-Some-Economists-Failed.aspx#page1"></a>I assert that some economists got things mostly right about the recession and what was needed to fix it, but they have been ignored in policy discussions. Conversely, those who got things mostly wrong were given prominent seats at the policy-setting table where they continued to make errant forecasts even as the evidence piled up against them. One attempt at rebuttal is, I suppose, is to ask how we know who was correct? The answer is that unlike the economists who continue to promote austerity, fear of inflation, and so on, the assertion is based upon the empirical evidence on these issues. [<a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/07/16/on-the-curious-persistence-of-inflationary-obsession/">See</a> Paul Krugman for a related issue, why fear of inflation, deficits, and so on &#8220;resonates with a lot of people no matter how often and how badly the worldview fails in practice.&#8221; Part of my point is that I don&#8217;t think economists are free of blame for this.]</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/not-all-economists-are-to-blame-but-some-are.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Republicans Want to Repeal Resolution Authority</title>
		<link>./../../2012/04/republicans-want-to-repeal-resolution-authority.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/04/republicans-want-to-repeal-resolution-authority.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2012 13:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Economist's View]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mark Thoma]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/04/republicans-want-to-repeal-resolution-authority.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Mark Thoma points us to Republicans Want to Repeal Resolution Authority the House Republicans on the Financial Services Committee just voted to repeal &#8220;resolution authority.&#8221; Let&#8217;s review the history. When the crisis hit, the government bailed out many financial firms &#8212; shadow banks as they are known. That&#8217;s not what it does when an ordinary [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://economistsview.typepad.com/economistsview/2012/04/republicans-want-to-repeal-resolution-authority.html">Mark Thoma</a>   points us to<br />
<blockquote><a href="http://economistsview.typepad.com/economistsview/2012/04/republicans-want-to-repeal-resolution-authority.html">Republicans Want to Repeal Resolution Authority</a> </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>
<blockquote>the House Republicans on the Financial Services Committee just voted to repeal &#8220;resolution authority.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>Let&#8217;s review the history. When the crisis hit, the government bailed out many financial firms &#8212; shadow banks as they are known. That&#8217;s not what it does when an ordinary bank fails. When ordinary banks fail, the government takes over the bank, puts the good assets in one pile, the bad assets in another, then repackages the good assets into a new bank that is sold back to the private sector as soon as possible.  </p></blockquote>
<p>
<blockquote>This has many advantages, including the ability to replace managers of failed firms instead of rewarding them with a bailout. So why wasn&#8217;t this approach adopted during the financial crisis? The Treasury argues that it did not have the legal authority to take over large shadow banks &#8212; these banks fell outside of the existing regulatory umbrella (there is dispute on this point, some people claim the government regulators could have twisted existing regulation to allow this, but government regulators insist otherwise). Thus, government regulators believed there were only two (bad) choices. Let too big to fail banks fail and suffer the economic consequences, or to bail them out, including bailing out the owners and managers who had led the banks to disaster. If it had resolution authority &#8212; the ability to step in take over when banks fail &#8212; the rewards to management could have been avoided, and taxpayers could have been better protected in other ways, but limits on legal authority gave regulators only two bad options. Do nothing, or bail the banks out. </p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/04/republicans-want-to-repeal-resolution-authority.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
