<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>boomers &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Boomer life experience</title>
		<link>./../../2010/11/boomer-life-experience.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/11/boomer-life-experience.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 26 Nov 2010 16:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[boomers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[EEOC]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/11/boomer-life-experience.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[EEOC offers this information: The Commission heard testimony from a number of experts on the impact of the economic crisis on older workers, the legal issues surrounding age discrimination today, and best practices to retain older workers. Dr. William Spriggs, Assistant Secretary for Policy, U.S. Department of Labor, testified that the rate of unemployment for [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a target="_blank" href="http://www.eeoc.gov/eeoc/newsroom/release/11-17-10.cfm">EEOC</a> offers this information:</p>
<blockquote><p> The Commission heard testimony from a number of experts on the impact of the economic crisis on older workers, the legal issues surrounding age discrimination today, and best practices to retain older workers.  Dr. William Spriggs, Assistant Secretary for Policy, U.S. Department of Labor, testified that the rate of unemployment for people age 55 and over “rose from a pre-recession low of 3.0 percent (November 2007) to reach 7.3 percent in August, 2010, <strong>making the past 22 months the longest spell of high unemployment workers in this age group have experienced in 60 years</strong>.”  Older workers also spend far more time searching for work and are jobless for far longer periods of time compared to workers under 55.</p></blockquote>
<p>(bolding mine)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/11/boomer-life-experience.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
