<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>campaign financing &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Supreme Court faces pressure to reconsider Citizens United</title>
		<link>./../../2012/05/supreme-court-faces-pressure-to-reconsider-citizens-united.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/05/supreme-court-faces-pressure-to-reconsider-citizens-united.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2012 13:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Beverly Mann (Supreme court)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[campaign financing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Citizens United]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Supreme court]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/05/supreme-court-faces-pressure-to-reconsider-citizens-united.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Lifted from an e-mail by Beverly Mann in response to an inquiry of mine on a Washington Post article: Hi Dan. The key paragraphs in a Washington Post article earlier this week, called Supreme Court faces pressure to reconsider Citizens United ruling say: The Supreme Court has already blocked the Montana decision, and the justices [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Lifted from an e-mail by Beverly Mann in response to an inquiry of mine on a Washington Post article:</p>
<p>Hi Dan. The key paragraphs in a Washington Post article earlier this week, called <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/supreme-court-faces-pressure-to-reconsider-citizens-united-ruling/2012/05/20/gIQAOdoqdU_print.html." target="_blank">Supreme Court faces pressure to reconsider Citizens United ruling</a> say:</p>
<blockquote><p>The Supreme Court <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/two-justices-suggest-citizens-united-ruling-should-be-reconsidered-in-montana-case/2012/02/17/gIQAJ07kKR_story.html">has already blocked the Montana decision</a>, and the justices may simply set their counterparts in Helena straight by summarily reversing the finding. But pressure is being applied — by members of Congress and nearly half the states, not to mention Justices Ruth Bader Ginsburg and Stephen G. Breyer — to at least let Montana make its argument.</p>
<p>The Montana Supreme Court acknowledged a conflict <a href="http://brennan.3cdn.net/7dc7086b8c35cd518d_uym6i2f0t.pdf">when it voted 5 to 2</a> to uphold the state law, created by voters in 1912 to combat the power of the so-called Copper Kings who controlled state politics. It said the state’s characteristics, including a dependence on agriculture and mining and low campaign costs, made it “especially vulnerable” to corporate control.</p>
<p>Those urging the court to grant a full hearing of the Montana case take aim at the<a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/01/21/AR2010012101724.html"> most important finding of <em>Citizens United</em>.</a> That was the declaration in Justice Anthony M. Kennedy’s majority opinion that “we now conclude that independent expenditures, including those made by corporations, do not give rise to corruption or the appearance of corruption.”</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>“That cannot be so,” the new bipartisan team of <a href="http://brennan.3cdn.net/a0b38399089c014ffb_ffm6bn6qy.pdf">Sens. John McCain (R-Ariz.) and Sheldon Whitehouse (D-R.I.) told the court</a>. “Whether independent expenditures pose dangers of corruption or apparent corruption depends on the actual workings of the electoral system; it is a factual question, not a legal syllogism.”</p>
<p>The court under Chief Justice John G. Roberts Jr. has incrementally undermined McCain’s landmark campaign finance act by saying it doesn’t meet First Amendment requirements. McCain has in turn been dismissive of a court — without a single member who has ever run for public office — that he says is hopelessly naive about how campaign finance affects the political process.</p></blockquote>
<p>The most stunning part of the <i>Citizens United</i> opinion was that declaration of fact was made out-of-the-blue and that most people recognize is plainly false. I wrote about this a couple of times on AB, including last January, shortly after the Montana Supreme Court issued its opinion.</p>
<p>I think that, although the rightwing majority would love to just summarily reverse the Montana Supreme Court on the basis of that declaration of purported fact in <i>Citizens United</i>, they’re under enough pressure now to not do that; the dissents from any such opinion would be devastatingly scathing and would get a lot of attention. I think they’ll agree to hear the case, and will schedule the oral argument for after the election. I think that, when they do decide the case, the wingnut majority probably will say that, whether or <i>not</i> “independent expenditures pose dangers of corruption or apparent corruption depends on the actual workings of the electoral system,” the First Amendment interest in “free speech” outweighs it. </p>
<p>But, who knows? Another possibility is that they’ll say that their opinion in Citizens United stated that it was based on the presumption of transparency about who is actually funding these Super PACs, and on the basis that, supposedly, these Super PACs do operate independently of the candidates’ campaigns, and that unless both of these presumptions actually are true, laws like Montana’s are constitutional.<br />Beverly</p>
<p>And Beverly added later:</p>
<p>In my opinion, the only newsworthy part is the amicus brief from McCain and Whitehouse,  because of MCain&#8217;s participation and because these two senators are saying that  as a matter of fact the Citizens United opinion&#8217;s declaration of fact is  erroneous, and that they, not the justices, have the actual facts.  That&#8217;s the  argument made by Montana&#8217;s attorney general, but having two senators say  outright that in their experience, the Supreme Court&#8217;s statement of fact is  flatly wrong is a big deal.  But I don&#8217;t have any more insight into what will  happen than what I wrote in the email and what&#8217;s in the Washington Post article.   
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/05/supreme-court-faces-pressure-to-reconsider-citizens-united.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Secret Money is Shifting to 501c4s</title>
		<link>./../../2012/02/the-secret-money-is-shifting-to-501c4s.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/02/the-secret-money-is-shifting-to-501c4s.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2012 12:36:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2012 Presidential elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[campaign financing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[super pacs]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/02/the-secret-money-is-shifting-to-501c4s.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Rick Hasen at Election Law Blog instructs us on super pacs and 501c4s: These days, I probably spend more time speaking to reporters (from as far away as Brazil and Italy) about Super PACs than about any other election law subject. There is a lot of misinformation floating out there about what Super PACs are, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://electionlawblog.org/?p=28973" target="_blank">Rick Hasen at Election Law Blog</a> instructs us on super pacs and 501c4s:<br />
<blockquote>These days, I probably spend more time speaking to reporters (from as far away as Brazil and Italy) about Super PACs than about any other election law subject.  There is a lot of misinformation floating out there about what Super PACs are, where they came from, the relationship to Citizens United, and the ability of super PACs to coordinate with candidates without running afoul of the FEC disclosure rules.  For those looking for basic information from what I’ve written, I point reporters to my <a href="http://www.cnn.com/2012/01/09/opinion/hasen-super-pacs/index.html?eref=rss_topstories&#038;utm_source=feedburner&#038;utm_medium=feed&#038;utm_campaign=Feed%3A%20rss%2Fcnn_topstories%20%28RSS%3A%20Top%20Stories%29">recent CNN oped</a>, <a href="http://electionlawblog.org/?p=28207">this blog post</a> on whether <em>Citizens United</em> created Super PACs, and t<a href="http://electionlawblog.org/?p=28617">his blog post</a> which highlights the kinds of coordination which are currently permissible under FEC rules.<br /><strong>&#8230;</strong><br /><strong>. The Secret Money is Shifting to 501c4s, and It Demands a Legislative Response. </strong>Last night ace election lawyer Rob Kelner <a href="https://twitter.com/#">tweeted</a>: “Biggest story today: Crossroads’ c4 raised more than its Super PAC. Confirming that media is missing the boat by focusing on Super PACs.”</p></blockquote>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />
<blockquote> My big concern before yesterday was that we would see a lot of transfers of money from 501c4s to affiliated Super PACs to shield the identity of donors to Super PACs. I’m still trying to get a handle on how much of this took place (apparently less than I thought). But the reason these transfers are not taking place is that it appears the 501c4s are engaging in much more <em>direct </em>election-related activity than they have in the past. That is, we are seeing some 501c4s becoming pure election vehicles. The relation of 501c4s to super pacs is now like the past relation between 527s and pacs—these are now the vehicles of questionable legality to influence elections. While <a href="http://www.mediteerenian.salon.com/2012/01/31/congress_can_fix_the_super_pac_problem/singleton/">Adam Skaggs</a> is rightly focused on fixing the coordination rules for Super PACs, this seems to be fighting yesterday’s war already. The key is to stop 501c4s from becoming shadow super PACs. Yes, campaign finance reform community, it has become this bad: I want <em>more</em> super PACs, because the 501c4 alternative is worse&#8230;</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/02/the-secret-money-is-shifting-to-501c4s.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
