<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Obama&#8217;s speech &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Obama&#8217;s State of the Union vs Romney&#8217;s Tax Returns</title>
		<link>./../../2012/01/obamas-state-of-the-union-vs-romneys-tax-returns.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/01/obamas-state-of-the-union-vs-romneys-tax-returns.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2012 02:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2012 Presidential elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linda Beale (Tax law)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obama's speech]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Romney]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/01/obamas-state-of-the-union-vs-romneys-tax-returns.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Beale Obama&#8217;s State of the Union vs Romney&#8217;s Tax Returns Obama took the high ground in his state of the union address, where he pointedly noted the importance of applying fair tax rules to ensure that millionaires pay taxes at rates more similar to those paid by secretaries and firefighters. He wants a [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Linda Beale</p>
<p>Obama&#8217;s State of the Union vs Romney&#8217;s Tax Returns</p>
<p>  Obama took the high ground in his state of the union address, where he pointedly noted the importance of applying fair tax rules to ensure that millionaires pay taxes at rates more similar to those paid by secretaries and firefighters. He wants a 30% rate on those with incomes of a million or more. <br />
<blockquote>We can either settle for a country where a shrinking number of people do really well, while a growing number of Americans barely get by,” Obama said in his address to a joint session of Congress. “Or we can restore an economy where everyone gets a fair shot, everyone does their fair share and everyone plays by the same set of rules.” STeven Sloan, Obama Says High-Earners Should Pay at least 30% of Income as Tax, Bloomberg.com, Jan 24, 2011.</p></blockquote>
<p>That would mean that Romney wouldn&#8217;t enjoy the exceptionally low rate of tax he had in 2010 after Congress enacted Obama&#8217;s suggested reforms. Romney released his tax returns on Tuesday. See this handy <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2012/01/24/us/politics/2011-romney-tax-returns.html">link on the New York Times</a> at which the 2010 and 2011 returns and accompanying documents are available, including links showing where Romney earned his $528,871 in speaking fees, etc.. Romney paid only 13.9% on $21.6 million of income, benefitting enormously from the low preferential capital gains rate of 15% that he paid on his returns from his investment of capital. Romney benefitted, too, from investments in the Cayman Islands, a well-known tax haven. And he is still earning &#8220;carried interest&#8221; from Bain Capital to the tune of multiple millions a year&#8211;that&#8217;s a share of the profits of a partnership he managed, treated as though it were a return on an investment of capital though it is paid for services. Romney is most definitely one of the 1%&#8211;actually in an even more rarefied class cluster of the top 0.006% of multimillionaires with lots of very low taxed income. See Kevin McCoy, <a href="http://www.usatoday.com/news/politics/story/2012-01-24/mitt-romney-tax-return/52780230/1">Romney tax returns show he&#8217;s no average multipmillionaire</a>, USA Today (Jan. 24, 2011) (noting that only 8274 returns out of 140 million filed had income of $10 million or more in 2009); Lori Montgomery et al, <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2012/01/23/gIQAj5bUMQ_story.html">Mitt Romney&#8217;s Tax Returns shed some light on his investment wealth</a>, Washington Post (Jan. 24, 2012); Nicholas Confessore, <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/01/25/us/politics/romneys-tax-returns-show-21-6-million-income-in-10.html">Romney&#8217;s Tax Returns Show $21.6 Million Income in &#8217;10</a>, New York Times (Jan. 24, 2012).</p>
<p>As the Times story puts it:</p>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />
<blockquote>What Mr. Romney’s returns illustrated, instead, was the array of perfectly ordinary ways in which the United States tax code confers advantages on the rich, allowing Mr. Romney to amass wealth under rules very different from those faced by most Americans who take home a paycheck.</p></blockquote>
<p>Obama&#8217;s proposals sound reasonable. But I&#8217;d extend the basic concepts to the corporate tax. Every corporation that is making book profits of more than some amount ($5 million? $10 million) ought to be held to a similar minimum tax rate on those book profits. </p>
<p>Funny, that is what the original Alternative Minimum Tax (for individuals, and one for corporations) was supposed to achieve&#8211;to ensure that everybody paid at least a reasonable rate on their income, even if they could cumulate lots of preferences like mortgage interest deductions, state income taxes, property taxes, and similar deductions. Over time, the AMT has eroded&#8211;too many exceptions made, too many taxpayer friendly amendments, and then the Bush tax cut bills that lowered rates so that the AMT rates aren&#8217;t really working well as a &#8220;broader base but lower rate&#8221; tax that ensures that even high-flying income recipients pay a more reasonable tax rate on their income. <br /><a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2012/01/obamas-state-of-the-union-vs-romneys-tax-returns.htm" title="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2012/01/obamas-state-of-the-union-vs-romneys-tax-returns.htm">http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2012/01/obamas-state-of-the-union-vs-romneys-tax-returns.htm</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/01/obamas-state-of-the-union-vs-romneys-tax-returns.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>A reminder from Obama&#8217;s February 2009 speech</title>
		<link>./../../2011/08/a-reminder-from-obamas-february-2009-speech.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/08/a-reminder-from-obamas-february-2009-speech.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2011 15:36:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[debt ceiling]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[debt limit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economic crisis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obama economic policy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obama's speech]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[recession]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/08/a-reminder-from-obamas-february-2009-speech.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[By: Daniel Becker In answer to the generic question regarding President Obama&#8217;s actions regarding the debt ceiling, I am re-posting this from 2/25/09.  In comments of the original I stated that cutting the deficit by 1/2 seemed to &#8220;optimistic&#8221; for me.*************************** Ok, here are my basic issues with the substance of President Obama&#8217;s speech. First, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By: Daniel Becker </p>
<p>In answer to the generic question regarding President Obama&#8217;s actions regarding the debt ceiling, I am re-posting this from 2/25/09.  In comments of the original I stated that cutting the deficit by 1/2 seemed to &#8220;optimistic&#8221; for me.<br />***************************</p>
<p>Ok, here are my basic issues with the substance of President Obama&#8217;s speech. First, may I remind everyone<br />that as of 11/08 I declared my divorce successful.  Has it become my mission accomplish moment?</p>
<p>I heard this:<br />
<blockquote>“And we will expand our commitment to charter schools. but as a father when I say that responsibility for our children&#8217;s education must begin at home.” </p></blockquote>
<p>And thought: 2 tier education system/vouchers, no thank you.  Education begins at home when home means one parent has the time to spend at home oppose to both working.</p>
<p>I heard this:<br />
<blockquote>“And we must also begin a conversation on how to do the same for Social Security, while creating tax-free universal savings accounts for all Americans.”</p></blockquote>
<p>And thought: Are you freak&#8217;n kidding me!  In this time of financial collapse we&#8217;re still going to talk about turning an insurance for the masses against the follies of finance into some form to include finance?  The entire reason we want to create jobs is because we have suddenly realized that the vast, vast majority do not earn their money from money.  Tax free?  Has he not heard of 401K, IRA and all it&#8217;s versions, HSA, higher education accounts?  Italy?</p>
<p>I heard this:<br />
<blockquote>“Yesterday, I held a fiscal summit where I pledged to cut the deficit in half by the end of my first term in office.”</p></blockquote>
<p>And thought: Yeah, how&#8217;d that work for the last administration who made such a declaration?  Did he have to say “in half”?  Has his advisors not taught him about the blip during the FDR recovery?  Only one way I can think of doing this: Raise taxes where the money is and whack the defense budget in half and I mean take a swipe at all moneys related to security.  Are we really $1 trillion dollars worth of paranoid?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/08/a-reminder-from-obamas-february-2009-speech.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>DOLB&#8217;s Punditry on Obama&#8217;s speech</title>
		<link>./../../2009/02/dolbs-punditry-on-obamas-speech.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/02/dolbs-punditry-on-obamas-speech.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2009 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[economic crisis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economic stimulus]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obama's speech]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/02/dolbs-punditry-on-obamas-speech.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by divorced one like Bush Ok, here are my basic issues with the substance of President Obama&#8217;s speech. First, may I remind everyone that as of 11/08 I declared my divorce successful. Has it become my mission accomplish moment? I heard this: “And we will expand our commitment to charter schools. but as a father [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by divorced one like Bush</p>
<p>Ok, here are my basic issues with the substance of President Obama&#8217;s speech. First, may I remind everyone that as of 11/08 I declared my divorce successful.  Has it become my mission accomplish moment?</p>
<p>I heard this:<br />
<blockquote>“And we will expand our commitment to charter schools. but as a father when I say that responsibility for our children&#8217;s education must begin at home.” </p></blockquote>
<p>And thought: 2 tier education system/vouchers, no thank you.  Education begins at home when home means one parent has the time to spend at home oppose to both working.</p>
<p>I heard this:<br />
<blockquote>“And we must also begin a conversation on how to do the same for Social Security, while creating tax-free universal savings accounts for all Americans.”</p></blockquote>
<p>And thought: Are you freak&#8217;n kidding me!  In this time of financial collapse we&#8217;re still going to talk about turning an insurance for the masses against the follies of finance into some form to include finance?  The entire reason we want to create jobs is because we have suddenly realized that the vast, vast majority do not earn their money from money.  Tax free?  Has he not heard of 401K, IRA and all it&#8217;s versions, HSA, higher education accounts?  Italy?</p>
<p>I heard this:<br />
<blockquote>“Yesterday, I held a fiscal summit where I pledged to cut the deficit in half by the end of my first term in office.”</p></blockquote>
<p>And thought: Yeah, how&#8217;d that work for the last administration who made such a declaration?  Did he have to say “in half”?  Has his advisors not taught him about the blip during the FDR recovery?  Only one way I can think of doing this: Raise taxes where the money is and whack the defense budget in half and I mean take a swipe at all moneys related to security.  Are we really $1 trillion dollars worth of paranoid?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/02/dolbs-punditry-on-obamas-speech.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
