<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>MERS issues &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Systematic document forgery and fabrication</title>
		<link>./../../2012/11/systematic-document-forgery-and-fabrication.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/11/systematic-document-forgery-and-fabrication.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2012 14:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dept. of Justice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MERS issues]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Yves Smith]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/11/systematic-document-forgery-and-fabrication.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Yves Smith at continues to point us in the direction of property ownership and the fallout from the widespread disregard of law in establishing title to property in her post Systematic document forgery and fabrication at Naked Capitalism: The Department of Justice and the state of Missouri have each announced criminal plea bargains with one [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/11/justice-in-america-systematic-document-forgery-and-fabrication-yields-one-criminal-plea-bargain.html">Yves Smith</a> at continues to point us in the direction of property ownership and the fallout from the widespread disregard of law in establishing title to property in her post <i>Systematic document forgery and fabrication</i> at <i>Naked Capitalism</i>:</div>
<p>
<blockquote>The Department of Justice and the state of Missouri have each announced criminal plea bargains with one Lorraine Brown, former chief executive of DocX, the Lender Processing subsidiary best known for its <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2010/10/4closurefraud-posts-docx-mortgage-document-fabrication-price-sheet.html">price sheet for fabricating the mortgage documents</a> a servicer, or frankly, anyone would need to claim they had standing to foreclose on your home. Funny how that particular DocX product was mentioned no where in the plea deals.<br /><strong>…</strong></p>
<p>Brown admitted guilt to perpetrating a six-year scheme, from 2003 to 2009 to forge and falsify over a million signatures, including now-infamous practices such as “surrogate signing”, in which other employees, typically temps, would forge the signatures of robosigners. The federal penalties are up to five years in prison plus $250,000 in fines; the Missouri penalties re two to three years in prison.</p></blockquote>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />
<blockquote>Several things are striking about this deal. First is that it appears that the Missouri suit against Brown goaded the Feds to join. It’s hardly unheard of for state regulators to embarrass their Federal counterparts into action, and the DoJ probably could not afford to sit out a successful prosecution on its beat, particularly after all the noise the Obama Administration has made about its new, improved anti mortgage fraud efforts. But that makes the second item more striking: how the “statement of facts” presents Brown as deceiving Lender Processing Services about her illegal actions. Brown is thus a rogue executive whose misdeeds presumably don’t have bigger implications for LPS or the industry. It’s nauseating to see the filings take that position and contain statements like this:<br />When hiring DocX to sign documents, servicers typically issued special corporate resolutions delegating document execution authority to specific, authorized, and trained personnel at DocX. The DocX employees who were given express signing authority from DocX’s clients and who, as represented by Brown, were purportedly trained to ensure that the clients’ documents were properly created, signed, and notarized were called “Authorized Signers.” These documents were then generally recorded by DocX with the appropriate local property recorders’ offices throughout the country.<br />Read more at <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/11/justice-in-america-systematic-document-forgery-and-fabrication-yields-one-criminal-plea-bargain.html#KsHfMdUvXWFQf1X3.99">Naked Capitalism</a></p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/11/systematic-document-forgery-and-fabrication.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Massachusetts Home Seizures Threatened in Loan Case: Mortgages</title>
		<link>./../../2012/02/massachusetts-home-seizures-threatened-in-loan-case-mortgages.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/02/massachusetts-home-seizures-threatened-in-loan-case-mortgages.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2012 21:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[home ownership]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MA Supreme Court]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MERS issues]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/02/massachusetts-home-seizures-threatened-in-loan-case-mortgages.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Yves at Naked Capitalism  comments on this Bloomberg article about the Eaton v. Federal National Mortgage Association case before the MA Supreme Court in the article  Massachusetts Home Seizures Threatened in Loan Case: Mortgages: This is super important &#8230; The highly respected Massachusetts Supreme Judicial Court is going to rule on whether the mortgage (the lien) can be [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/02/links-22112.html">Yves at <i>Naked Capitalism</i></a>  comments on this Bloomberg article about the <i>Eaton v. Federal National Mortgage Association</i> case before the MA Supreme Court in the article  <a href="http://news.businessweek.com/article.asp?documentKey=1376-LZKAUN0D9L3501-5TCTU8KVHPVUOQ034TMUOK0029">Massachusetts Home Seizures Threatened in Loan Case: Mortgages</a>:  <br />
<blockquote>This is super important &#8230; The highly respected Massachusetts Supreme Judicial Court is going to rule on whether the mortgage (the lien) can be separated from the note (the borrower IOU). Since the US Supreme Court over 100 years ago said the lien was a mere accessory to the mortgage, the odds are high they will say no. That means they might invalidate the foreclosure at issue, putting many other FCs under a cloud (but even if they rule for the borrower, I’d expect them to award damages rather than undo the FC; there is a lot of other law that treats sales out of bankruptcies and foreclosures as final). But a ruling in favor of the borrower would also deliver a fatal blow to MERS. </p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/02/massachusetts-home-seizures-threatened-in-loan-case-mortgages.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Gleaning more insights on MERS issues</title>
		<link>./../../2010/11/gleaning-more-insights-on-mers-issues.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/11/gleaning-more-insights-on-mers-issues.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Nov 2010 17:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[MERS issues]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/11/gleaning-more-insights-on-mers-issues.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I want to point to Linda Beale&#8217;s post with Naked Capitalism, where additional commentary is added from Yves Smith and a few others. Worth a visit for sure.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I want to point to <a target="_blank" href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2010/11/mortgage-loan-foreclosure-mess-yves.html">Linda Beale&#8217;s post</a> with <a target="_blank" href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2010/11/the-mortgage-loan-foreclosure-mess-the-banks-gluttony-problems-with-mers-and-sloppy-securitizations.html">Naked Capitalism</a>, where additional commentary is added from Yves Smith and a few others.  Worth a visit for sure.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/11/gleaning-more-insights-on-mers-issues.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
