<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>softball &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Yves Smith, Matt Taibbi, and Bill Moyers talk on the financial &#034;Follies of Big Banks and Government&#034;</title>
		<link>./../../2012/06/yves-smith-matt-taibbi-and-bill-moyers-talk-on-the-financial-follies-of-big-banks-and-government.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/06/yves-smith-matt-taibbi-and-bill-moyers-talk-on-the-financial-follies-of-big-banks-and-government.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 25 Jun 2012 20:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Jamie Dimon]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Senate Banking Committee]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[softball]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/06/yves-smith-matt-taibbi-and-bill-moyers-talk-on-the-financial-follies-of-big-banks-and-government.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Yves Smith, Matt Taibbi, and Bill Moyers talk on the financial Follies of Big Banks and Government Matt Taibbi:The question I wanted to ask is, was, really more about the criminality. I mean, none of the members in either the House or the Senate really got into the issue of all the different offenses that [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Yves Smith, Matt Taibbi, and Bill Moyers talk on the financial <i>Follies of Big Banks and Government</i></p>
<p>
<blockquote>Matt Taibbi:<br />The question I wanted to ask is, was, really more about the criminality. I mean, none of the members in either the House or the Senate really got into the issue of all the different offenses that these banks have committed in the last few years. You know, or, an ordinary person, if he commits welfare fraud, never gets a food stamp again in his life.</p>
<p>So given that these banks have systematically and repeatedly committed fraud, repeatedly been caught, you know, in situations like Jefferson County, municipal bid rigging, why should we still give them billions and billions of dollars in emergency lending from the Fed, bailouts, all of this aid from the government? How come there&#8217;s no consequences for them and there are consequences for ordinary people?</p>
<p>Yves Smith: I would have asked questions more having to do with what&#8217;s the justification for complex banking at all? That why do we need, why shouldn&#8217;t banks be run on the utility basis? Why should we have people like Dimon and his, the members of the CIO unit, most of which he&#8217;s fired, what the justification for literally that hundreds of millions of bonuses were paid collectively to those people.</p>
<p>And now he says they didn&#8217;t know what they were doing. There&#8217;s no justification for this, the sort of level of compensation that we generally have on Wall Street. And I would like to see that myth starting to be punctured in more public places.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/06/yves-smith-matt-taibbi-and-bill-moyers-talk-on-the-financial-follies-of-big-banks-and-government.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
