<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>state interventions &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>David Cay Johnson and taxed by the boss</title>
		<link>./../../2012/05/david-cay-johnson-and-taxed-by-the-boss.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/05/david-cay-johnson-and-taxed-by-the-boss.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 May 2012 12:22:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[David Cay Johnson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[local economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[state interventions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax subsidies]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/05/david-cay-johnson-and-taxed-by-the-boss.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Reuters brings us a post from David Cay Johnson on a less well known funding mechanism from state coffers to private businesses. Granted there are a lot of others as well. See this post by Kenneth Thomas    (link repaired) on how competition between government is different than between private businesses: Across the United States more [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://blogs.reuters.com/david-cay-johnston/2012/04/12/taxed-by-the-boss/" target="_blank">Reuters</a> brings us a post from David Cay Johnson on a less well known funding mechanism from state coffers to private businesses.  Granted there are a lot of others as well. See <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/04/guest-post-greg-mankiw-doesn-understand.html" target="_blank">this post by Kenneth Thomas  </a>  (link repaired) on how competition between government is different than between private businesses:</p>
<blockquote><p>Across the United States more than 2,700 companies are collecting state income taxes from hundreds of thousands of workers – and are keeping the money with the states’ approval, says an eye-opening report published on Thursday.</p>
<p>The report from Good Jobs First, a nonprofit taxpayer watchdog organization funded by Ford, Surdna and other major foundations, identifies 16 states that let companies divert some or all of the state income taxes deducted from workers’ paychecks. None of the states requires notifying the workers, whose withholdings are treated as taxes they paid.</p>
<p>General Electric, Goldman Sachs, Procter &#038; Gamble, Chrysler, Ford, General Motors and AMC Theatres enjoy deals to keep state taxes deducted from their workers’ paychecks, the report shows. Foreign companies also enjoy such arrangements, including Electrolux, Nissan, Toyota and a host of Canadian, Japanese and European banks, Good Jobs First says.<br /><a name="more"></a><br />Why do state governments do this? Public records show that large companies often pay little or no state income tax in states where they have large operations, as this column has documented. Some companies get discounts on property, sales and other taxes. So how to provide even more subsidies without writing a check? Simple. Let corporations keep the state income taxes deducted from their workers’ paychecks for up to 25 years.</p></blockquote>
<p>The snappier <a href="http://youtu.be/4sZzQQLX-AI" target="_blank">You tube version is here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/05/david-cay-johnson-and-taxed-by-the-boss.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>To ban contraception to married couples too?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/01/to-ban-contraception-to-married-couples-too.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/01/to-ban-contraception-to-married-couples-too.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2012 19:07:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[privacy rights]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[state interventions]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/01/to-ban-contraception-to-married-couples-too.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In the New Yorker comes this note lost in the shuffle of the NH primary. I sense a pervasive theme of bigger government interference: Since Ronald Reagan, Republican Presidents (and Presidential nominees) have been committed to overturning Roe v. Wade, the Supreme Court’s abortion-rights landmark from 1973. But as the debates last weekend in New [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/comment/2012/01/the-republicans-lost-privacy.html#ixzz1jAq4oTdw" target="_blank">In the New Yorker</a> comes this note lost in the shuffle of the NH primary.  I sense a pervasive theme of bigger government interference:<br />
<blockquote>Since Ronald Reagan, Republican Presidents (and Presidential nominees) have been committed to overturning Roe v. Wade, the Supreme Court’s abortion-rights landmark from 1973. But as the debates last weekend in New Hampshire suggested, the G.O.P. appears to have taken a more extreme step in terms of rolling back the Constitutional right to privacy.</p>
<p>Since the first time Mitt Romney ran for President, four years ago, he’s been on record reversing his previous support for abortion rights. However, when pressed by George Stephanopoulos in the debate Saturday night, Romney went beyond mere opposition to Roe. He said he thought Griswold v. Connecticut, the 1965 case that first made explicit the right to privacy, was also wrong. “I don’t believe they decided that correctly,” Romney said. In this, the front-runner was eagerly seconded by Rick Santorum, who said the Justices “created through a penumbra of rights a new right to privacy that was not in the Constitution.”<br /><a name="more"></a><br />In Griswold, the Court ruled that a Connecticut law banning the sale of contraceptives, even to married couples, was unconstitutional. In the most famous passage from that opinion (which Santorum alluded to) Justice William O. Douglas said, “Specific guarantees in the Bill of Rights have penumbras, formed by emanations from those guarantees that help give them life and substance. Various guarantees create zones of privacy.” Later, Douglas said, “We deal with a right of privacy older than the Bill of Rights—older than our political parties, older than our school system.”</p>
<p>Roe has long been controversial, of course. But Griswold, largely, has not. For example, while John Roberts and Samuel Alito were cagey in their references to Roe in their confirmation testimony before the Senate Judiciary Committee, both of them readily embraced Griswold as a settled precedent of the Court. This is understandable. It is chilling to believe that the Constitution could allow a state to ban married couples from buying birth control. (A few years after Griswold, in a 1972 case called Eisenstadt v. Baird, the Court said states could not ban unmarried people from buying birth control, either.)</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/01/to-ban-contraception-to-married-couples-too.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
