<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>debates &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Strategic Lying as Political Art</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/strategic-lying-as-political-art.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/strategic-lying-as-political-art.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2012 03:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2012 Presidential elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[debates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jazzbumpa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romeny]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Republican]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/strategic-lying-as-political-art.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[If you listen to Randi Rhodes, you know she is still livid over Romney being declared the &#8220;winner&#8221; in last week&#8217;s &#8211; we&#8217;ll call it a &#8220;debate&#8221; for the nonce. Alas, though, the reason he won is that poll numbers have moved in his favor.  Whether that bounce is robust remains to be seen.  But [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you listen to Randi Rhodes, you know she is still livid over Romney being declared the &#8220;<i>winner</i>&#8221; in last week&#8217;s &#8211; we&#8217;ll call it a &#8220;debate&#8221; for the nonce.</p>
<p>Alas, though, the reason he won is that <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2012/oct/08/romney-gains-lead-obama-poll">poll numbers have moved in his favor</a>.  Whether that bounce is robust remains to be seen.  But it did gain Romney some sort of advantage, at least in the near term.</p>
<p>Randi&#8217;s  objection is that Romney lied, repeatedly, and about almost  everything.  In the process, he flatly repudiated some of the major  planks in his platform &#8211; the destruction of Medicare as we know it, the  $5 Trillion dollar tax cut, the reduction of tax share paid by high  income people, and an insurance plan not covering pre-existing  conditions stand out in that regard.   And these are but a few of the <a href="http://thinkprogress.org/politics/2012/10/04/958801/at-last-nights-debate-romney-told-27-myths-in-38-minutes/">27  debate lies that can easily be recognized and refuted</a>.</p>
<p>Indeed,  the one rare moment of lucid candor came when he eagerly, gleefully  announced that he would send Big Bird to the unemployment line in order  to avoid borrowing money from China.  Big NPR whoop!  To put this in  perspective, for CY 2012, the Federal Government, via the Corp. for  Public Broadcasting, is contributing $26.65 million in support of PBS,  or 0.0007% of total Federal expenditures ($3.77 Trillion) for 2012.     In fact, the entire Federal contribution to CPB is $445.2 million, or  0.0118% of total expenditures. That&#8217;s sure going to help balance $5  Trillion in tax cuts over ten years. (CPB data from <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Corporation_for_Public_Broadcasting#Funding_of_and_by_the_corporation">Wikipedia</a>, current expenditure data from the <a href="http://research.stlouisfed.org/fred2/series/FGEXPND">St. Louis Fed</a>.)   Romney isn&#8217;t lying about our creditor position with China, but he was certainly misleading.  According to <a href="http://www.foxnews.com/politics/2012/09/04/who-do-owe-most-that-16-trillion-to-hint-it-isnt-china/">Fox News</a> (!) &#8220;<i>China, it turns out, holds less than 8 percent of the money our government has borrowed over the years</i>.&#8221;</p>
<p>OK,  I get where Randi is coming from &#8211; to have a totally unprincipled  opportunist in charge of running the world&#8217;s greatest super power is not  a recipe for any kind of enduring success, either for the U.S.A.  specifically, or for the world at large.  There are many historical  examples one could cite, but we really needn&#8217;t go back any further than  the &#8220;compassionate conservatism&#8221; of unprosecuted war criminal and  would-be social security privatizer George W. Bush to make the point.</p>
<p>But  what Randi refuses to acknowledge is that what we witnessed last week  was not a debate, by any recognizable definition of the term.  Lying  will get you disqualified in a real debate &#8211; right?  This was <i>political theater</i> &#8211; and what is theater but staged fiction?  </p>
<p>And there is nothing unusual here.  I&#8217;ve been saying for years that <a href="http://jazzbumpa.blogspot.com/2010/04/you-cant-fool-all-of-kentucky-all-of.html">all Republicans do is lie</a>, and then lie about their lies. (I might have gotten that phrase from Randi &#8211; the memory is foggy.)  Here is a four-year-old exposé of some of Romney&#8217;s shape shifting.  (H/T to <a href="http://www.lawyersgunsmoneyblog.com/2012/10/catch-this-guy-on-the-right-day-and-hes-che-frickin-guevara">Dave Brockington at LGM</a>.)</p>
<p>A more insidious kind of lie is simply denying  reality, as characterized by birtherism, New Deal and global warming  denialism, and Friday&#8217;s epidemic of <a href="http://m.apnews.com/ap/db_289563/contentdetail.htm?contentguid=dkjMKAA6">conspiracy theories surrounding the latest favorable jobs report</a>.   But I digress.</p>
<p>Here is my point.  <a href="http://delong.typepad.com/sdj/2012/10/george-hw-bush-press-secretary-in-1984-lying-during-debates-is-a-republican-strategy.html">Brad Delong points</a> us to a 1984 Fay Joyce  article in the N. Y. Times uncovered by <a href="http://delong.typepad.com/sdj/2012/10/george-hw-bush-press-secretary-in-1984-lying-during-debates-is-a-republican-strategy.html">Michael Moore</a>.   It turns out that lying during a debate is a time honored Republican  strategy.  Even 28 years ago, when there was some chance of the main  stream media doing actual journalism, they were confident in their lying  strategy.</p>
<blockquote><p>The Republicans are unabashed in their discussion of their ability to use the television medium. &#8220;You can say anything you want during a debate and 80 million  people hear it,&#8221; observed Peter Teeley, press secretary to Vice  President Bush. If reporters then document that a candidate spoke  untruthfully, &#8221;so what?&#8221; </p>
<p> &#8221;Maybe 200 people read it or 2,000 or 20,000,&#8221; he said.</p></blockquote>
<p>Now,  they have honed it into an art form.  And it&#8217;s worth remembering the  one reason that always accounts for every person&#8217;s lie: their agenda is  not compatible with the truth.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/strategic-lying-as-political-art.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Debate with only frames</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/debate-with-only-frames.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/debate-with-only-frames.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 07 Oct 2012 15:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2012 Presidential elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[debates]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/debate-with-only-frames.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Via Salon, here is a short note on an art history textbook students apparently were forced to buy: Kyle Chayka, Hyperallergenic What is this, October!? According to a blog post published by a disgruntled parent of a student, the Ontario College of Art and Design (OCAD) is forcing students to buy an art history book [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Via Salon, here is a short note on an art history textbook students apparently were forced to buy: <a href="http://www.salon.com/writer/kyle_chayka/">Kyle Chayka</a>, <a href="http://hyperallergic.com/">Hyperallergenic</a>  </p>
<blockquote><p>What is this, <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/October_%28journal%29">October</a></em>!? According to <a href="http://www.ashleyit.com/blogs/brentashley/2012/09/16/copyright-and-the-pictureless-art-history-textbook/">a blog post</a> published by a disgruntled parent of a student, the Ontario College of Art and Design (OCAD) is forcing students to <a href="http://gawker.com/5944240/art-schools-expensive-art-history-textbook-contains-no-actual-art">buy an art history book</a> for $180 — which wouldn’t be unheard of, but the catch is that the publishers of this book didn’t get any of the image rights for the artwork it includes. To reiterate, that’s an art history survey without any pictures.</p></blockquote>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<blockquote><p>Instead of having pictures of artwork, the book, “<a href="http://www.ashleyit.com/blogs/brentashley/2012/09/17/its-as-bad-as-that-and-worse/">Global Visual and Material Culture: Prehistory to 1800</a>“ (so named for the course it goes with), instead just has placeholders with instructions to see a digital version for the actual image. It’s like a website with only broken image links. Just check out this hilarious sample page from the book:</p></blockquote>
<p><img alt="" height="722" src="http://hyperallergic.wpengine.netdna-cdn.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/09/textbook-example1.png" title="textbook-example1" width="600"></p>
<p>This little bit of news seemed to parallel our election process/debate.  I think we have sort of prepaid the whole $800 for the content for art history texbooks instead of the discounted $180, tax not included.  Google for answers on your own are the instructions.  Sort of like the first debate.</p>
<p>(<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/10/03/us/politics/transcript-of-the-first-presidential-debate-in-denver.html?pagewanted=all&#038;_r=1&#038;">Transcript of the debate from the NYT</a>)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/debate-with-only-frames.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
