<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Canadian healthcare system &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Why Doesn’t Rachel Zubay Know That Most Provisions of Obamacare Won’t Start Until 2014?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/09/why-doesnt-rachel-zubay-know-that-most-provisions-of-obamacare-wont-start-until-2014.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/09/why-doesnt-rachel-zubay-know-that-most-provisions-of-obamacare-wont-start-until-2014.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 23 Sep 2012 15:17:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Canadian healthcare system]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Joel Auchenbach]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Michelle Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obamacare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rachel Zubay]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Washington Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/09/why-doesnt-rachel-zubay-know-that-most-provisions-of-obamacare-wont-start-until-2014.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Rachel Zubay, 32, works as a waitress at Abdalla’s Steak House, in the shadow of a recently idled coal-fired power plant. She’s got two kids, is in the middle of a divorce, has no medical insurance and is paying $50 a month on a $15,000 surgical bill after she injured her ankle and foot in [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>Rachel Zubay, 32, works as a waitress at Abdalla’s Steak House, in the shadow of a recently idled coal-fired power plant. She’s got two kids, is in the middle of a divorce, has no medical insurance and is paying $50 a month on a $15,000 surgical bill after she injured her ankle and foot in a nasty fall. She figures she’ll have it paid off in five or 10 years.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>She’ll probably vote for Romney. What about the president’s health-care plan, which is supposed to help people afford medical insurance? “Obviously it hasn’t helped me at all,” Zubay says. “I’d be better off moving to Canada.”
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212; <i><a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/national/health-science/in-ohio-county-electorate-is-hardened-and-fractured/2012/09/22/3a848108-03da-11e2-91e7-2962c74e7738_print.html">In Ohio county, electorate is hardened and fractured</a></i>, <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/joel-achenbach/2011/02/24/AB5edOJ_page.html">Joel Achenbach</a>, Washington Post, today
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Michelle Obama gave a lovely, effective speech earlier this month at the Democratic convention.  But in my opinion, her best moment came two days later, while making a particular comment during a taped clip that was part of the little film played before her husband delivered his acceptance speech.  In one seemingly unscripted moment, at the end of brief comments about Obamacare, she said something about hospitals and physicians sending bills for hundreds of thousands of dollars to, say, a single mothers with hourly-wage jobs—and doing so “with a straight face.”  What was most effective were not even her words but the spontaneous, pained, incredulous look on her face as she said “with a straight face.”
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I’d love to see the Obama campaign use that clip in an ad that also makes clear that the part of Obamacare that will help Ms. Zubay by the time she’s 34, and her young children, and millions of others too, won’t start until 2014.  If it starts at all.  Which, Romney/Ryan, if elected, will do their best to keep it from doing.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Seriously.  It probably didn’t occur to Obama that some people think that Obamacare’s main provisions have started but have just failed to help <i>them</i>.  But now, he knows.  And Ms. Zubay probably isn’t the only one who’s planning to vote for Romney, in part because of that evil Obamacare, who recognizes the benefits, healthcare-wise, of living in Canada.  Or Germany.  Or Taiwan.  Or Israel. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>What some of them don’t recognize, I guess, is that if they injure a foot two years from now, they won’t have to pay $50 a month for the next several decades.  They’ll be able instead to use that $50 a month for other things.</div>
<div>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/09/why-doesnt-rachel-zubay-know-that-most-provisions-of-obamacare-wont-start-until-2014.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
