<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>subsidies &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Discussing Tax Increment Financing on TV</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/discussing-tax-increment-financing-on-tv.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/discussing-tax-increment-financing-on-tv.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 31 Oct 2012 12:18:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Eurozone]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kenneth Thomas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[subsidies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax increments]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/discussing-tax-increment-financing-on-tv.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Kenneth Thomas Discussing Tax Increment Financing on TV I recently appeared on a local public access TV show, Conversation with Lee Presser, discussing tax increment financing and European Union subsidy control regulations. It&#8217;s a great format, just an almost 30-minute discussion without interruption, which allowed me to explain the problems with TIF as it [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Kenneth Thomas</p>
<p>Discussing Tax Increment Financing on TV</p>
<p> I recently appeared on a local public access TV show, <i>Conversation with Lee Presser</i>, discussing tax increment financing and European Union subsidy control regulations. It&#8217;s a great format, just an almost 30-minute discussion without interruption, which allowed me to explain the problems with TIF as it has been used in Missouri in great detail. We also had a shorter conversation about EU regulations to control investment incentives and other subsidies, which covered the basics of transparency, maximum subsidy rates that vary by how rich the region is, and the reduction in those rates for large projects. Many thanks to Lee Presser for having me on. If you are interested in economic development issues, I think you will enjoy the program.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vZxbCr6YcXA">(&#8220;A Conversation with Kenneth Thomas &#8211; UMSL Professor of Political Science &#8211; 10/23/12&#8221;</a>)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/discussing-tax-increment-financing-on-tv.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>David Cay Johnston has noticed a tax giveaway through FERC</title>
		<link>./../../2010/06/david-cay-johnston-has-noticed-a-tax-giveaway-through-ferc.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/06/david-cay-johnston-has-noticed-a-tax-giveaway-through-ferc.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Jun 2010 12:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[FERC]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[subsidies]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/06/david-cay-johnston-has-noticed-a-tax-giveaway-through-ferc.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Beale David Cay Johnston has noticed a tax giveaway through FERC [hat tip to Tax Prof; edited to correct typo and provide links] David Cay Johnston, writing in Tax Notes, has focused on a tax giveaway that most of us have missed&#8211;a provision that permits partnerships that own pipelines to charge consumers for [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>by Linda Beale</strong></p>
<p><a target="_blank" href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2010/06/david-cay-johnston-has-noticed-a-tax-giveaway-through-ferc.html"><strong>David Cay Johnston has noticed a tax giveaway through FERC</strong></a></p>
<p>[hat tip to Tax Prof; edited to correct typo and provide links]</p>
<p>David Cay Johnston, writing in Tax Notes, has focused on a tax giveaway that most of us have missed&#8211;a provision that permits partnerships that own pipelines to charge consumers for a tax that they don&#8217;t actually pay, resulting in considerable profits for the partners of the partnerships with little or no accompanying tax liability. See Master LImited Partnerships: Paying Other People&#8217;s Taxes, 129 Tax Notes 1393 (Jun. 21, 2010), available for free at tax.com, <a target="_blank" href="http://tax.com/taxcom/taxblog.nsf/Permalink/UBEN-86LJ4E?OpenDocument">here</a>. There&#8217;s also a brief explanatory video by Johnston, <a target="_blank" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=V9SwDUNG8S0">here</a>. This pipeline policy stems from the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission and a 2007 court decision upholding the shift. ExxonMobil Oil Corp v. FERC, 487 F.3d 945 (DC Cir. 2007).</p>
<p>As Johnston explains:</p>
<blockquote><p>For a traditional corporate owned pipeline, these costs include the corporate income tax on company profits. However, the income taxes ofn individual investors have never before counted as a cost of providing service. &#8230;. [But] even though the MLP does not pay the corporate income tax, FERC lets MLP pipelines include income tax in the rates charged to customers. FERC policy assumes the top marginal rate. Since the only income tax paid is by individual owners, this means that the rates include the individual income tax the MLP investors owe. In other words, you are forced to pay the income taxes of the MLP investors when you buy natural gas or petroleum products that were transported on [a publicly traded partnership&#8217;s] pipeline. Id.</p></blockquote>
<p>In fact, Johnston notes, the consumers pay the partners&#8217; income taxes &#8220;even if they are only &#8216;potential&#8217; taxes.&#8221; The result is incredible profits for partners in the partnership owning the pipelines.</p>
<blockquote><p>The math here is stunning. When rates include a tax that does not exist, the investors make out like, well, bandits. Investors in an MLP pocket 75 percent more inn after-tax profits than they would if they invested in a traditional corporation owning a pipeline. Id.</p></blockquote>
<p>FERC lost the originall BP West Coast case, so then it just issued a statement of policy, with private meetings between commissioners and lobbyists to agree to a general rule allowing a maximum tax to be in included in the rate calculation, even if there were no business level tax to affect business profits (and only individual investor taxes, which are not costs of any business). The court allowed this new policy to survive, based on extraordinary deference to the agency, even for an arbitrary and capricious standard of review. Isn&#8217;t it clear that allowing an agency to decide that companies that operate through non-taxed partnerships can nonetheless increase their rates by a non-paid tax is an arbitrary and capririous decision that is unfair to regulated entities as well as to consumers&#8211;especially when the order of magnitude is considered&#8211;$1.6 billion a year for gas pipelines and $1.3 billion a year for petroleum pipelines. Johnston notes that such pipelines consequently have rent-like profits of 42% of revenues, four times the typical margin for the 12,000 largest corporations.</p>
<p>Further, this tax shifting is inflated by FERC&#8217;s own regulatory practices.</p>
<blockquote><p>FERC has acknowledged that there is some over-collection by oil pipelines and yet it continues to grant rate hikes based not on costs, but on an index. &#8230;[T]he overcollection is pure profit except for the income tax burden, which is shifted to customers. Id. at 1395</p></blockquote>
<p>Johnston makes two important points (paraphrased here): </p>
<p>1.   Every industry has an incentive to get this treatment, since the &#8220;tax&#8221; is hidden from consumers and goes directly to industry investors&#8217; bottom lines, resulting in a small charge to everybody and a huge gain to the industry investors<br />It would be very simple for Congress to pass this advantage along to more industries, just by a minor change to the loophole exempting industries from the publicly traded partnership provisions intended result (treating publicly traded partnerships like corporations subject to the corporate tax). </p>
<p>2.   And he notes that such treatment of monoplies is disturbing as a matter of principle, violating &#8220;two long-standing principles of rate regulation that are fundamental to fairness and integrity&#8221;&#8211;that owners be entitled to recover costs and earn a reasonable return on equity and that customers only be charged for actdual expenses. This is a trend towards &#8220;corporate socialism, under which profits are concentrated through government action and losses are socialized through bailouts.&#8221;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/06/david-cay-johnston-has-noticed-a-tax-giveaway-through-ferc.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>What Policies Cause High Food Prices?</title>
		<link>./../../2008/07/what-policies-cause-high-food-prices.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/07/what-policies-cause-high-food-prices.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2008 12:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[food]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[subsidies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[trade]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/07/what-policies-cause-high-food-prices.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Tom Bozzo Over at his FT blog, Willem Buiter sensibly calls for an end to biofuel subsidies and mandated levels of biofuel use, and suggests that the money be spent on environmentally friendlier renewable energy research instead. He delivers a great bit of wonk snark after reciting various biofuel targets, then saying: All this [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Tom Bozzo</p>
<p>Over at his FT blog, Willem Buiter <a href="http://blogs.ft.com/maverecon/2008/07/lets-stop-subsidising-the-production-and-use-of-bio-fuels/">sensibly calls for an end</a> to biofuel subsidies and mandated levels of biofuel use, and suggests that the money be spent on environmentally friendlier renewable energy research instead.  He delivers a great bit of wonk snark after reciting various biofuel targets, then saying:<br />
<blockquote>All this will have to go.  It is part of a process called ‘learning’.  More governments and official institutions should try it.</p></blockquote>
<p>Buiter does deliver a &#8220;<a href="http://www.prospect.org/csnc/blogs/beat_the_press_archive?month=07&#038;year=2008&#038;base_name=how_do_cheap_food_exports_rais">Paging Dr. Baker</a>&#8221; moment in adding a more general call for agriculture liberalization in the rich world to the pitch:<br />
<blockquote>End all policies to subsidise or protect agriculture as well as all policies to restrict agricultural production through set-asides (paying farmers not to grow stuff) and other idiocies.</p></blockquote>
<p>Do subsidies <i>and</i> restrictions on production both affect price in the same direction?  (Not all set-asides are &#8220;idiocies&#8221; either, notably those on the margins of waterways.)</p>
<p>Agriculture subsidies is one of those areas that tends to unite economists against politicians; the elimination of them seems to offer benefits across the political spectrum — a little expansion of the &#8220;free&#8221; market for the right, a little reduction in corporate welfare for the left, say.  Much as I might be receptive to both under the right circumstances, this is not enough reason to pursue the near-total liberalization of ag markets.</p>
<p>It can be argued that there are goods where we should be willing to trade some efficiency of provision for reliability and/or affordability, which favors the intervention of the visible hand; I&#8217;d argue that food staples are among them.  To the extent this is the policy aim, then economists should be more aware than most that there&#8217;s no theoretical reason to expect free markets to provide them reliably or affordably for all, or even all important, values of &#8220;reliable&#8221; and &#8220;affordable.&#8221;  It&#8217;s part of a process called &#8216;learning,&#8217; natch!</p>
<p>It&#8217;s necessary to actually make the case that subsidies aren&#8217;t warranted, or at least that the effects of existing as opposed to ideal subsidy programs in total are worse than whatever could be reasonably expected under liberalization, and that&#8217;s a tough one to make categorically.  Even Buiter is willing to countenance subsidies for production of staple crops in poor and underdeveloped countries.  The question is whether that should be the limit of them, and there isn&#8217;t a simple answer.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/07/what-policies-cause-high-food-prices.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Friend of small business??? Not!!!</title>
		<link>./../../2008/03/friend-of-small-business-not.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/03/friend-of-small-business-not.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2008 19:17:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[farm]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[subsidies]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/03/friend-of-small-business-not.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The NYT carries this article. (Hat tip to dmarek) IF you’ve stood in line at a farmers’ market recently, you know that the local food movement is thriving, to the point that small farmers are having a tough time keeping up with the demand.But consumers who would like to be able to buy local fruits [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/03/01/opinion/01hedin.html?_r=1&#038;em&#038;ex=1204520400&#038;en=1850d11a7a2d5f01&#038;ei=5087%0A&#038;oref=slogin">The NYT</a> carries this article. (Hat tip to dmarek)</p>
<blockquote><p>IF you’ve stood in line at a farmers’ market recently, you know that the local food movement is thriving, to the point that small farmers are having a tough time keeping up with the demand.<br />But consumers who would like to be able to buy local fruits and vegetables not just at farmers’ markets, but also in the produce aisle of their supermarket, will be dismayed to learn that the federal government works deliberately and forcefully to prevent the local food movement from expanding. And the barriers that the United States Department of Agriculture has put in place will be extended when the farm bill that House and Senate negotiators are working on now goes into effect.<br />As a small organic vegetable producer in southern Minnesota, I know this because my efforts to expand production to meet regional demand have been severely hampered by the Agriculture Department’s commodity farm program. As I’ve looked into the politics behind those restrictions, I’ve come to understand that this is precisely the outcome that the program’s backers in California and Florida have in mind: they want to snuff out the local competition before it even gets started.<br />&#8230;<br />Who pays the price for this senselessness? Certainly I do, as a Midwestern vegetable farmer. But anyone trying to do what I do on, say, wheat acreage in the Dakotas, or rice acreage in Arkansas would face the same penalties. Local and regional fruit and vegetable production will languish anywhere that the commodity program has influence.<br />Ultimately of course, it is the consumer who will pay the greatest price for this — whether it is in the form of higher prices I will have to charge to absorb the government’s fines, or in the form of less access to the kind of fresh, local produce that the country is crying out for.<br />Farmers need the choice of what to plant on their farms, and consumers need more farms like mine producing high-quality fresh fruits and vegetables to meet increasing demand from local markets — without the federal government actively discouraging them.</p></blockquote>
<p><strong>Update:</strong>  MG points out I missed this part of the article&#8230;I did in my scanning.  Thanks.</p>
<blockquote><p>&#8220;The commodity farm program effectively forbids farmers who usually grow corn or the other four federally subsidized commodity crops (soybeans, rice, wheat and cotton) from trying fruit and vegetables. Because my watermelons and tomatoes had been planted on “corn base” acres, the Farm Service said, my landlords were out of compliance with the commodity program. </p>
<p>I’ve discovered that typically, a farmer who grows the forbidden fruits and vegetables on corn acreage not only has to give up his subsidy for the year on that acreage, he is also penalized the market value of the illicit crop, and runs the risk that those acres will be permanently ineligible for any subsidies in the future. (The penalties apply only to fruits and vegetables — if the farmer decides to grow another commodity crop, or even nothing at all, there’s no problem.)&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p><strong>Update 2</strong>:  Hat tip to Noni in the comment section as well under cactus&#8217;s children post.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/03/friend-of-small-business-not.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
