<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>New Years resolution &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Resolution</title>
		<link>./../../2010/01/resolution.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/01/resolution.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2010 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[New Years resolution]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/01/resolution.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I&#8217;ve made it already, and it&#8217;s one I can &#8212; and will &#8212; keep. by Noni Mausa For me, salmon and tuna have always been at opposite ends of my food spectrum &#8212; cheap staple versus delicacy. I&#8217;m a boomer, and I am sure I&#8217;m not alone in having a mother who used tuna as [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;ve made it already, and it&#8217;s one I can &#8212; and will &#8212; keep.</p>
<p>by Noni Mausa</p>
<p>For me, salmon and tuna have always been at opposite ends of my food spectrum &#8212; cheap staple versus delicacy.</p>
<p>I&#8217;m a boomer, and I am sure I&#8217;m not alone in having a mother who used tuna as a tasty way to feed seven or more of us on a budget.  Make a cream sauce, open 3 cans of tuna and a tin of green peas, and pour it over toast &#8212; that was the comfort food of my childhood and adulthood too.</p>
<p>And heaped up tuna sandwiches with mayonnaise and little chopped gherkins &#8230; pasta salad with cheese, peas and more gherkins &#8230; tuna casserole with onion rings on top &#8230;  well, you can tell I <a href="http://www.amazon.com/How-Talk-Minnesotan-Visitors-Guide/dp/0140092846">grew up in Minnesota</a>.  </p>
<p>I miss them already, and it&#8217;s only been a few weeks.</p>
<p>At my parent&#8217;s table tuna was the rule, not the exception.  We must have eaten a school of tunas in my school years.  Oh, tinned salmon showed up now and then also, but I never got to know the delights of broiled salmon till I grew up.</p>
<p>But this autumn I decided I couldn&#8217;t have either of them anymore.</p>
<p>Eating a tuna isn&#8217;t like eating a cow.  Cows are grazing animals, but tuna, silvery streamlined and one of the fastest fish in the sea, is a peak predator.  Eating tuna is like eating cheetahs &#8212; yummy, endangered carnivores, in cream sauce.</p>
<p>At the other end of my delicacy spectrum we have the beautiful wild ocean relative of the trout, the salmon.  The wild ones, as are tuna, are endangered.</p>
<p>But I can&#8217;t eat the farmed salmon either &#8212; it&#8217;s now certain they act as a reservoir for disease and parasites for the wild ones, and there are other problems too numerous to detail here.</p>
<p><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_MSuZ1riS9qU/Sz02jjBl3II/AAAAAAAAAYQ/1TcI5bDjJzc/s1600-h/fish+tins.jpg"><img src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_MSuZ1riS9qU/Sz02jjBl3II/AAAAAAAAAYQ/1TcI5bDjJzc/s320/fish+tins.jpg" border="0" alt=""></a>So earlier this autumn I had my last tin of tuna (creamed with a sprinkle of curry powder &#8211; very un-Minnesotan) and my last tin of salmon (can&#8217;t remember what I did with that.)  There is a single salmon steak still in the freezer.  Then that&#8217;s it.  Those last two tins hang from my cedar tree now, clinking gently in the wind, to remind me.  But so far I haven&#8217;t been tempted at all.</p>
<p>Maybe someone else will eat the last tuna, or the last salmon.  But it won&#8217;t be me.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/01/resolution.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>19</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
