<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Chris Hayes &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>$1 trillion to be spent on direct hiring&#8230;that&#8217;s the ticket!</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/1-trillion-to-be-spent-on-direct-hiring-thats-the-ticket.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/1-trillion-to-be-spent-on-direct-hiring-thats-the-ticket.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2013 03:36:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[budget deficits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chris Hayes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economic recovery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[new deal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the sequester]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/1-trillion-to-be-spent-on-direct-hiring-thats-the-ticket.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[With all this stalemate posturing in Washington, today Chris Hayes has come up with the best idea I have heard yet to move the players. And, in my opinion actually solve our economic depression. One trillion dollars to be spent on direct hiring by the government along with debt forgiveness.  A solution right out of [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>
<p>With all this stalemate posturing in Washington, today Chris Hayes has come up with the best idea I have heard yet to move the players.  And, in my opinion actually solve our economic depression.</div>
<div></div>
<div>One trillion dollars to be spent on direct hiring by the government along with debt forgiveness.  A solution right out of the New Deal program.  Unfortunately for Chris, Obama does not have the language within his vocabulary to recognize such an approach and thus in Obama&#8217;s <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/ref/us/politics/21seelye-text.html" target="_blank">own words</a>: “&#8230;put us on a fundamentally different path because the country was ready for it.”</div>
<div></div>
<div>In fact, not only does he not have the language within his vocabulary to recognize a solution from history, he thinks the <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/ref/us/politics/21seelye-text.html" target="_blank">60&#8217;s and 70&#8217;s</a> were full of excesses (while noting Kennedy moved the nation in a new direction&#8230;right into the excesses of the 60&#8217;s?)*</div>
<div></div>
<p>
<div>Visit NBCNews.com for <a href="http://www.nbcnews.com/">breaking news</a>, <a href="http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/3032507">world news</a>, and <a href="http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/3032072">news about the economy</a> </div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>Do you think anyone who remembers what it meant to be a leader in the Democratic Party was watching?   </div>
<div></div>
<div>*“I do think that, for example, the 1980 election was different. I think Ronald Reagan changed the trajectory of America in a way that, you know, Richard Nixon did not and in a way that Bill Clinton did not.”</div>
<div>&#8220;He put us on a fundamentally different path because the country was ready for it. I think they felt like, you know, with all the excesses of the 60s and the 70s, and government had grown and grown, but there wasn&#8217;t much sense of accountability in terms of how it was operating. I think people just tapped into &#8212; he tapped into what people were already feeling, which was, we want clarity, we want optimism, we want a return to that sense of dynamism and entrepreneurship that had been missing.”  </div>
<div></div>
<div><i>Don&#8217;t get me going on the people wanting &#8220;clarity&#8221; (security state that even the congress can&#8217;t get info on) and &#8220;optimism&#8221; (the audacity!).</i></div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/1-trillion-to-be-spent-on-direct-hiring-thats-the-ticket.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
