<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Walter Cronkite &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Paul Ryan Is the Joe McCarthy of Our Era. Maybe the Mainstream Media Finally Will Recognize That. Then Again, Maybe It Won’t.</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/paul-ryan-is-the-joe-mccarthy-of-our-era-maybe-the-mainstream-media-finally-will-recognize-that-then-again-maybe-it-wont.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/paul-ryan-is-the-joe-mccarthy-of-our-era-maybe-the-mainstream-media-finally-will-recognize-that-then-again-maybe-it-wont.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2013 16:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Edward R. Murrow]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Joe MCarthy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mainstream news media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Matthew Yglesias]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Walter Cronkite]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/paul-ryan-is-the-joe-mccarthy-of-our-era-maybe-the-mainstream-media-finally-will-recognize-that-then-again-maybe-it-wont.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Paul Ryan is, in effect, the Joe McCarthy of our era.  He consistently spews outlandishly false statements of fact, never offers actual evidence in support of them and never refutes factual challenges using actual and full facts, and tries as a matter of routine to obfuscate his specific and broader objectives and therefore to trick [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Paul Ryan is, in effect, the Joe McCarthy of our era.  He consistently spews <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/moneybox/2013/03/12/paul_ryan_currency_debasement.html">outlandishly false statements of fact</a>, never offers actual evidence in support of them and never refutes factual challenges using actual and full facts, and <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/moneybox/2013/03/12/class_war_budgeting_paul_ryan_and_house_gop_want_more_money_for_the_rich.html">tries <i>as a matter of routine</i> to obfuscate his specific and broader objectives </a>and therefore to trick the public.  </p>
<p>He is a serious nutcase.  And yet he has garnered mainstream media attention as though what he puts out is credible.  We have a mainstream media that treats this nutjob as though he were a legitimate policy wonk. And that acts as though facts are legitimately in the eye of the beholder.  </p>
<p>If only Obama were more like Ike.  And if only there were an Edward R. Murrow around now, although a Walter Cronkite would do, too.  If only.  </p>
<p>Broadcast news, of course, no longer has nearly the power and audience it once had, but we now have the veritable <i>reverse</i> of what this country once had in its highest-profile journalists.  and we have a president who cowers in the face of whatever media juggernaut is currently saying &#8220;boo.&#8221;  </p>
<p>True, Ike was buoyed, not hindered, by the mainstream press when he helped end the McCarthy stranglehold.  And McCarthy and Eisenhower were, technically anyway, members of the same political party, so there was no insistence that Eisenhower humor McCarthy in the name of bipartisanship.  But there&#8217;s also no law that requires the president, this one or any other, to mindlessly do the mainstream media&#8217;s bidding if that bidding is in the name of bipartisanship.  At least not when bipartisanship means delegating fiscal policy to a rightwing faction of a minority party that a majority of voters recently pretty-darned-clearly  rejected.</p>
<p>This is getting really, really scary.  </p>
<p>&#8212;-<br /><i>The links are to two Matthew Yglesias posts in Slate this morning.</i></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/paul-ryan-is-the-joe-mccarthy-of-our-era-maybe-the-mainstream-media-finally-will-recognize-that-then-again-maybe-it-wont.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>My answer to the question, “So is Brian Williams really an idiot, or does he just play one on TV?”</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/my-answer-to-the-question-so-is-brian-williams-really-an-idiot-or-does-he-just-play-one-on-tv.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/my-answer-to-the-question-so-is-brian-williams-really-an-idiot-or-does-he-just-play-one-on-tv.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2013 17:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Brian Williams]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[debt ceiling]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jason Stanley]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NBC Nightly News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New York Times]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Puppy Bowl]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Walter Cronkite]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/my-answer-to-the-question-so-is-brian-williams-really-an-idiot-or-does-he-just-play-one-on-tv.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In the Comments thread to my post yesterday about a comment that Brian Williams made the day before indicating that he apparently does not know what “the debt ceiling” actually means, reader SW asked: “So, is he really an idiot or does he just play one on the tv?” I answered: I hadn’t thought of [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the Comments thread to <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/02/brian-williams-thinks-raising-debt.html">my post yesterday about</a> a comment that Brian Williams made the day before indicating that he apparently does not know what “the debt ceiling” actually means, reader SW asked: “So, is he really an idiot or does he just play one on the tv?”</p>
<p>I answered:</p>
<div dir="ltr">I hadn’t thought of Williams as a lightweight before, which is one reason I was so shocked that he apparently doesn’t know what “the debt ceiling” actually means.  I rarely watch the network evening news shows anymore, but when I do, It’s his show that I watch.  The CBS and ABC ones seem to have made a concerted effort to play to conservatives, I guess because the audience for these shows these days is so largely white elderly folks.  </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">There was a good Opinionator piece in the NYT yesterday by a Philosophy prof. named Jason Stanley, called “<a href="http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/01/31/philosopher-kings-and-fiscal-cliffs/">Philosopher Kings and Fiscal Cliffs,</a>” about how the misleading language used to discuss these things&#8211;which actually are specific facts&#8211;leads to dangerously false analogies and misunderstandings by the public, fed by deliberate misrepresentations by pols. (The article engages in a misrepresentation of sorts, itself, by equating Repub misrepresentations with Dem ones, but, oh, well.)  But Williams isn’t any old member of the general public. How can the main news anchor for NBC Nightly News not know what the debt ceiling is, and think it’s something that it’s not?</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Williams’ <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brian_Williams">Wikipedia bio</a> is surprisingly sparse about his professional background, but my guess is that he’s never been a hard-news reporter on anything really complicated.  He apparently came to prominence by covering Hurricane Katrina for NBC News&#8211;hardly a complicated news event requiring knowledge beyond what the general public has.  But it just really surprises me that he apparently doesn’t even read the NYT or the Washington Post on major, complex stories such as the debt ceiling thing.  </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Oh, well. This isn’t the era of Walter Cronkite.  So, what else is new?</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">I watched [Williams&#8217;] show again last night, and near the end he did a wonderful story on something dear to my heart: <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/lifestyle/style/the-puppy-bowl-behind-the-scenes-of-tvs-cutest-show/2013/01/25/f7fe46f4-6642-11e2-93e1-475791032daf_gallery.html?tid=ts_carousel">The Puppy Bow</a>l.  The dogs all are rescues, up for adoption. Again, nothing complicated.  But, at least in my opinion, important. </div>
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/my-answer-to-the-question-so-is-brian-williams-really-an-idiot-or-does-he-just-play-one-on-tv.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
