<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Dodd-Frank &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>A Kiss From a Used-Car Salesman—and why it’s important to tie Romney’s “47%” comment directly to his Orwellian lies</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/a-kiss-from-a-used-car-salesman-and-why-its-important-to-tie-romneys-47-comment-directly-to-his-orwellian-lies.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/a-kiss-from-a-used-car-salesman-and-why-its-important-to-tie-romneys-47-comment-directly-to-his-orwellian-lies.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 07 Oct 2012 19:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dodd-Frank]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ezra Klein]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[George Orwell]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Dickerson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mao Tse-tung]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Maureen Dowd]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Krugman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/a-kiss-from-a-used-car-salesman-and-why-its-important-to-tie-romneys-47-comment-directly-to-his-orwellian-lies.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In a terrific article published on Friday, Slate’s John Dickerson asks: Which Mitt Romney DoYou Trust Most? Is he a cold-heartedconservative or a moderate Republican from Massachusetts? How can we know? As for the second of those three questions—Is he a cold-hearted conservative or a moderate Republican from Massachusetts?—I think there’s a third possibility.  I [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>In a terrific article published on Friday, Slate’s John Dickerson asks: <a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/politics/2012/10/mitt_romney_has_moved_from_being_the_conservative_gop_primary_winner_to_a_far_more_moderate_former_governor_of_massachusetts_.html">Which Mitt Romney DoYou Trust Most? Is he a cold-heartedconservative or a moderate Republican from Massachusetts? How can we know?</a>
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>As for the second of those three questions—Is he a cold-hearted conservative or a moderate Republican from Massachusetts?—I think there’s a third possibility.  I think he’s George Orwell.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Or, rather, that he’s <i>channeling</i> George Orwell.  Not Orwell, the person.  Orwell, the writer.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Orwell, of course, is most famous for his book <i>1984</i>, in which politicians and government officials say exactly the opposite of what they mean.  Thus, the term “Orwellian,” which is not limited to politicians’ statements, but which refers to the use of common language terms that have a fixed meaning, and using them to suggest exactly the opposite of what those terms actually mean—and exactly the opposite of what the speaker does mean.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Up means down, left means right, black means white.  You get the picture.  Some people will think that when you say “up,” you mean “up.”  Others will understand that when you say “up,” you mean “down.”  It’s sophistry, con artistry. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>It’s also a key tactic that dictators use to gain or keep power.  Hitler, of course, used it routinely.  But so did Mao Tse-tung.  In fact, another word for “Orwellian” was, during the Mao era, “Mao Speak.”  You just change the definition of common words to mean exactly the opposite of what the words have meant.  That way, you can continue to claim that you’re doing something in particular, or will do something in particular, when you’re actually doing or planning to do the opposite.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>In democracies, when politicians do that, it has another synonym: lie.  Or at least that’s been so until now.  On Wednesday night, Romney changed the meaning of many words and phrases so that they mean the opposite of what they have meant.  Not the least are the words “win” and “debate,” at least as the former normally is applied to the latter, although it was largely the news media that redefined “win,” and of course Jim Lehrer helped with the redefinition of “debate.”
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>But another word that underwent a quick transition Wednesday night from its normal meaning to the opposite of it is “plan.”  As in, he has a plan to cover preexisting medical conditions.  The word “plan” normally means, y’know, a recommendation or intention to <i>change</i> something from its current status.  The phrase “a plan to cover preexisting medical conditions” normally means a requirement that insurance companies provide medical insurance to people who have preexisting medical conditions such as, say, multiple sclerosis or breast cancer, beyond what federal law already requires.  That is, beyond the status quo. </div>
<div><a name="more"></a></div>
<div>Which is that people who have, say, multiple sclerosis or a malignant breast tumor and have had no healthcare insurance within the previous three months can get treated at the emergency room, and then maybe file for bankruptcy if the hospital actually does provide, um, treatment for these medical problems.  Then again, Romney had redefined the word “treatment” even before the Wednesday debate, so I guess we now have to understand the phrase “medical treatment” <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/election-2012/wp/2012/09/24/romney-calls-emergency-room-a-health-care-option-for-uninsured/">to mean </a>something like, “But you have no insurance and you need the sort of medical procedure that isn’t <i>done</i> in emergency rooms.”  Romney already had redefined the word “plan” to mean promised goals rather than the specific, credible means of achieving them. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>But that redefinition had applied only to his economic plan—a plan that he said on Wednesday night might not work, and which—although it escaped the punditry—he seemed to be admitting that he (the successful businessman!) had devised without any actual economic basis for thinking that the revenue/tax-deduction ends could meet as designed.  But this second redefinition of the word “plan” was something else entirely, because by saying that he has a plan to provide healthcare insurance to people who currently are denied it because of a preexisting medical condition, he was telling them that he plans to something <i>specific</i> that he plans <i>not</i> to do.  And it concerns some truly fundamental things, in some cases life or death, in others financial security or instead financial devastation. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>What kind of person stands on a stage speaking to 67 million people, and just plain lies about something of <i>that</i> sort?  Dare I say it—the kind of person who speaks derisively about 47 percent of Americans, none of whom are Bain investors, have overseas bank accounts, hire PriceWaterhouseCoopers to tally their tax returns, and have their IRA accounts in the Cayman Islands.  Nor contribute to Republican PACs or attend Romney fundraisers in Boca Raton.  Or anywhere else.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Maureen Dowd, in her New York Times <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/10/07/opinion/sunday/dowd-two-presidents-smoking-and-scheming.html?_r=1&#038;hp">column today</a>, uses humor to run through many, but by no means all (she’s only allowed a limited number of words per column, after all), of Romney’s bald debate-“winning” lies.  And she includes the preexisting-medical-conditions one.  But I think it’s Paul Krugman who, in his Times column on Friday, titled “<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/10/05/opinion/krugman-romneys-sick-joke.html?partner=rssnyt&#038;emc=rss&#038;gwh=B7234187342E4EBEF3738D0F73F6A7FC">Romney’s Sick Joke</a>,” best highlights that this particular lie is particularly brazen and particularly pernicious.  And Ezra Klein <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/ezra-klein/wp/2012/10/05/romneys-pulling-up-the-ladder-behind-him/">points out</a> that Romney’s mendacity about his plan for healthcare coverage—and in this context it is indeed a plan, as that word is defined the old-fashioned way—runs even deeper. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>It’s been said, accurately, many, many times now that this election will determine the basic nature of American government.  But until now, that’s meant budgetary, taxing and regulatory policy.  It now means something even more fundamental, in addition: Whether or not we allow a redefinition of the word “democracy.”  Romney asks us to believe in America.  It turns out that he means an America of the sort that George Orwell feared.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Or at least one run by a used car salesman.  Read the fine print on that contract.  And on that separate warranty you’ll be charged for. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<p>A kiss <a href="http://www.law.com/corporatecounsel/PubArticleCC.jsp?id=1202573924603&#038;Regarding_DoddFrank_Romneys_Kiss_Isnt_Just_a_Kiss&#038;slreturn=20120907142437">is not a kiss</a> when it’s described as one by someone with a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Forked_tongue">forked tongue</a>.  
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/a-kiss-from-a-used-car-salesman-and-why-its-important-to-tie-romneys-47-comment-directly-to-his-orwellian-lies.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Spain. Please, Mr. Obama, talk about Spain. Please.</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/spain-please-mr-obama-talk-about-spain-please.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/spain-please-mr-obama-talk-about-spain-please.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 04 Oct 2012 14:49:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dodd-Frank]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jim Lehrer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Krugman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spain]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[taxes]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/spain-please-mr-obama-talk-about-spain-please.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[ROMNEY: Look, the revenue I get is by more people working, getting higher pay, paying more taxes. That’s how we get growth and how we balance the budget. But the idea of taxing people more, putting more people out of work, you’ll never get there. You’ll never balance the budget by raising taxes. Spain &#8212; [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div></div>
<div>ROMNEY: Look, the revenue I get is by more people working, getting higher pay, paying more taxes. That’s how we get growth and how we balance the budget. But the idea of taxing people more, putting more people out of work, you’ll never get there. You’ll never balance the budget by raising taxes.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Spain &#8212; Spain spends 42 percent of their total economy on government. We’re now spending 42 percent of our economy on government. I don’t want to go down the path to Spain. I want to go down the path of growth that puts Americans to work with more money coming in because they’re working.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>LEHRER: But &#8212; but Mr. President, you’re saying in order to &#8212; to get the job done, it’s got to be balanced. You’ve got to have&#8230;
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>(CROSSTALK)
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212; <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/decision2012/2012-presidential-debate-president-obama-and-mitt-romneys-remarks-in-denver-on-oct-3-running-transcript/2012/10/03/24d6eb6e-0d91-11e2-bd1a-b868e65d57eb_print.html">Last night</a>
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Romney doesn’t want to go down the path to Spain?  Oh?  Well, since, actually, the percent of Spain’s total economy that they spend on government has nothing at all to do with Spain’s situation now, and instead has <i>everything</i>to do with the fact that they had a huge, huge housing bubble, worse even than ours, and since their housing bubble is—like ours—the main cause of their economic problems, and since Romney wants to repeal the Dodd-Frank Wall Street and Mortgage-lending regulations and replace them with regulations that favor Wall Street … then, yes, Romney does want to go down the path of Spain. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Or at least down the path we took during our deregulation juggernaut.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>OK, here’s the thing: Romney and his campaign aides recognized that that debate forum would present a <i>perfect</i> opportunity for him to just rattle off statements without any challenge.  Just a steady stream of nonsense, without any real risk of being confronted with actual challenges to any of it.  They knew, as I did, that Lehrer—I still remember his nauseating role in the first Bush/Gore debate in 2000—does nothing but ask the candidates to state their positions on whatever.  Open-ended questions in which each one is supposed to state his policy proposal on, say, taxes, or “jobs.” There’s no actual questioning <i>about</i> the proposal.  None.  None.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>So, Romney gets to state, <i>free and clear</i>, a completely false inference of fact about the cause of Spain’s economic problems.  And he gets to say, <i>free and clear</i>:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Look, the revenue I get is by more people working, getting higher pay, paying more taxes. That’s how we get growth and how we balance the budget. But the idea of taxing people more, putting more people out of work, you’ll never get there. You’ll never balance the budget by raising taxes.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Really?  You’ll never balance the budget by raising taxes?  Oh? Didn’t we do exactly that during the Clinton administration?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And, the revenue he gets is by more people working, getting higher pay, paying more taxes?  Oh? Through the same policies as George W. Bush did?  Really?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And so forth. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Like, that Romney is going to cut tax rates <i>across the board</i> by 20%.  But he’s not going to lower tax revenue from the wealthy at all.  And so forth.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>What Obama needs to do—really, really <i>needs</i> to do—is put up a series of ads juxtaposing Romney’s earlier statements with his gibberish from last night. (I strongly urge using a clip from Romney’s speech to the Detroit Economic Club in February, and a similar speech that same week in Arizona; Michigan and Arizona had their primaries on the same Tuesday.)  But rather than just suggesting that Romney is a slippery liar who’s trying to trick voters into putting into office a team that would put in place drastic, basic changes that he knows a substantial majority of the public <i>doesn’t want</i>, Obama should pretend that Romney just doesn’t know the facts and can’t do simple math.  He is, in other words, not very smart, or at least not very well-informed. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The public, of course, will recognize that Romney’s a sleaze bucket. But Obama can just say, for example, that if Romney doesn’t know that during the Clinton years, we had a balanced budget, he’s too ill-informed to be president.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And, about that Spain thing: The final debate will be about foreign policy.  Which, Obama should point out, requires some knowledge of such things as what <i>actually</i>caused Spain’s economy to crash. And then he should educate the public about it.  He can do that in two or three sentences of medium length.  If he wants to see how it&#8217;s done, he can read any one of several Paul Krugman columns in which Krugman did exactly that.  It’s not rocket science.  It’s not even economic science.  It’s simple, established fact.  Of exactly the sort that not long ago Romney’s pollster said the Romney campaign wouldn’t trouble itself about, and that it would instead continue to make up its own facts.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Speaking of good way for the Obama campaign to get a message across in an ad ….
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The bottom line: Obama can easily turn Romney’s performance last night into a plus. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Easily.  Really.
</p>
<p>&#8212;-<br /><i>Typo-corrected 10/5.</i></div>
<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/spain-please-mr-obama-talk-about-spain-please.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>GOP wants to repeal Dodd-Frank: instead they should listen to Nassim Taleb</title>
		<link>./../../2011/11/gop-wants-to-repeal-dodd-frank-instead-they-should-listen-to-nassim-taleb.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/11/gop-wants-to-repeal-dodd-frank-instead-they-should-listen-to-nassim-taleb.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2011 14:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[bank regulations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dodd-Frank]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[incentives]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linda Beale (Tax law)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[long tail events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[risk management]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/11/gop-wants-to-repeal-dodd-frank-instead-they-should-listen-to-nassim-taleb.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Beale GOP wants to repeal Dodd-Frank: instead they should listen to Nassim Taleb Nassim Taleb, the author of the book on long-tail events, suggests in a Nov. 6, 2011 op-ed in the New York Times that &#8220;it is only a matter of time before private risktaking leads to another giant bailout like the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Linda Beale</p>
<p>GOP wants to repeal Dodd-Frank: instead they should listen to Nassim Taleb
<p>Nassim Taleb, the author of the book on long-tail events, suggests in a Nov. 6, 2011 op-ed in the New York Times that &#8220;it is only a matter of time before private risktaking leads to another giant bailout like the ones the United States was forced to provide in 2008.&#8221; </p>
<p>That&#8217;s pretty strong language, and should be cause for worry among those GOP debaters who have been in a pissing contest over how much legislation they can suggest for repeal, like Dodd-Frank, health care reform, and environmental protection.  Instead of defending big banks, the GOP should start thinking about how to break them up.  Instead of suggesting that we need to repeal Dodd-Frank and end regulation of banks, Taleb says we do need  regulation but can&#8217;t depend on it alone: &#8220;Supervision, regulation, and other forms of monitoring are necessary, but insufficient.&#8221;</p>
<p> <a name="more"></a>
<p>And instead of defending risk-taking bankers as innovators and entrepreneurs, Congress should be considering measures to undo the incentives for risk taking.  Taleb says&#8211;<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/11/08/opinion/end-bonuses-for-bankers.html">End Bonuses for Bankers</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p>[I]t&#8217;s time for a fundamental reform:  Any person who works for a company that, regardless of its current financial health, would require a taxpayer-financed bailout if it failed, should not get a bonus, ever.  In fact, all pay at systemically important financial institutions&#8211;big banks, but also some insurance companies and even huge hedge funds&#8211;should be strictly regulated.</p>
<p>***</p>
<p>Bonuses are particularly dangerous because they invite bankers to game the system by hiding the risks of rare and hard-to-predict but consequential blow-ups, which I have called &#8216;black swan&#8217; events. </p>
</blockquote>
<p>Seems like sound advice.  Bonuses encourage risktaking, and risktaking encourages breakdowns of TBTF banks.  Breakdowns lead to taxpayer bailouts.  To break the chain, deny the bonuses.</p>
<blockquote><p>The asymmetric nature of the bonus (an incentive for success without a corresponding disincentive for failure) causes hidden risks to accmumlate in the financial system and become a catalyst for disaster.  This violates the fundamental rules of capitalism:  Adam Smith himself was wary of the effect of limiting liability, a bedrock principle of the modern corporation.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Here Taleb touches on a factor in the expanding risk of our economy&#8211;and the expanding immunity of the manager class from the risk they cause.  Corporations provide limited liability to their owners.  And innovations over the last few decades have expanded limited liability to almost all investors even in pass-through entities that pay no entity-level tax, through the limited liability company and the limited liability partnerships. That is one of the reasons I have argued for Congress to enact legislation to restrain the availability of tax-free mergers and reorganizations.  The combination of easily attained limited liability plus easily attained consolidation of entities has been a factor in the growth of the corporatist state.</p>
<p>Taleb has a good point about the incidence of bonuses in the US market system as well.</p>
<blockquote><p>We trust military and homeland secrutiy personnel with our lives, yet we don&#8217;t give them lavish bonuses.  They get promotions and the honor of a job well done if they succeed, and the severe disincentive of shame if they fail.  For bankers, it is the opposite: a bonus if they make short-term profits and a bailout if they go bust.</p>
</blockquote>
<p> Eliminating bonuses would make banking boring again, like it was before the repeal of the Glass-Steagall Act.  Boring, in this case, is good.  Congress should consider what kind of legislation could be designed to make bonuses in banking less likely, through tax disincentives or other means.</p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2011/11/gop-wants-to-repeal-dodd-frank-maybe-they-should-listen-to-nassim-taleb-.html">http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2011/11/gop-wants-to-repeal-dodd-frank-maybe-they-should-listen-to-nassim-taleb-.html</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/11/gop-wants-to-repeal-dodd-frank-instead-they-should-listen-to-nassim-taleb.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
