<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Clarence Thomas &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The Rightwing Supreme Court Justices&#8217; Fair-Weather &#034;State Sovereignty” Canard</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/the-rightwing-supreme-court-justices-fair-weather-state-sovereignty-canard.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/the-rightwing-supreme-court-justices-fair-weather-state-sovereignty-canard.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 04 Jan 2013 17:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Anthony Kennedy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Clarence Thomas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[federalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[George Orwell]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Roberts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mad Hatter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Maoism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Supreme court]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/the-rightwing-supreme-court-justices-fair-weather-state-sovereignty-canard.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Two days ago, Dan posted an entry by run75441 titled “SCOTUS Chastises Congress and the Executive Branch.”  The post’s title wasn’t quite accurate; run’s post was about Chief Justice John Roberts’ annual state-of-the-judicial-branch report, in which he was writing in his capacity as administrative head of that branch, not in his actual judicial capacity, and [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Two days ago, Dan posted an entry by run75441 titled “<a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/01/scotus-chastises-congress-and-executive.html">SCOTUS Chastises Congress and the Executive Branch</a>.”  The post’s title wasn’t quite accurate; run’s post was about Chief Justice John Roberts’ <a href="http://articles.washingtonpost.com/2012-12-31/politics/36103796_1_federal-courts-congressional-leaders-fiscal-cliff">annual state-of-the-judicial-branch report</a>, in which he was writing in his capacity as administrative head of that branch, not in his actual judicial capacity, and not for the other justices.  </p>
<p>Run (who didn’t title the post; Dan did) deeply criticized Roberts for bragging about the austerity of the federal courts in recent years, including his own court, which, he also bragged, had decided on 64 cases in its last term.  That was down from, I think, 70 the term before, and the main reason for that reduction was that the ACA case consumed a full week of oral-argument slots&#8211; the full week at issue normally consisting of arguments in six&#8211;count ‘em, six!&#8211;cases; some full weeks consist of four arguments, leaving the justices slightly less exhausted than they are after the six-argument work weeks.  </p>
<p>Roberts implied&#8211;he did not say so, expressly, but he did imply&#8211;that Congress and the White House take a cue from the justices and force the federal government to make do with less money.  To which I suggest that the justices really lead by example, and get rid of their four-justices-apiece law clerks, who do most of their work for them and start doing their legally-mandated jobs themselves.  After all, the federal government at least doesn’t pay salaries to congressional lobbyists&#8211;the equivalent of Supreme Court law clerks.</p>
<p>Anyway, I posted a comment to run’s post, and then asked Dan to add it as an update to run’s post, which he did.  My comment said:</p>
<div dir="ltr">The Supreme Court is rarely in session.  It’s seasonal, part-time work.  They usually hear argument in 10 cases a month, seven months a year.  In December, they didn’t hear even that many.</div>
<div dir="ltr">There’s really sooo much that can, and should, be said about the issue of (virtually universal lack of) access to the Supreme Court, and its repercussions.  Roberts’ bizarre, cutesy annual report is … oh … I don’t know …characteristically hubristic? </div>
<p>Run responded to my comment, and I then responded to his, writing:</p>
<p><a name="more"></a>
<div dir="ltr">What’s especially outrageous is the type of situation you’re talking about [a federal habeas corpus case challenging the constitutionality of aspects of the proceedings in a state-court criminal case]: The Supreme Court almost never agrees to hear cases on “direct appeal” (a legal term of art) from state supreme courts, in criminal or civil cases, with the major exception that they do often agree to do so in criminal cases when it is the state (i.e., the prosecution) that is asking them to hear hear the case in order to overrule a (rare) state supreme court ruling in favor of the criminal defendant. In state-court criminal cases, when it is the defendant who is asking the Supreme Court to hear the case in order to overturn a conviction, on constitutional grounds, the Supreme Court seems to figure that the criminal defendant can file a habeas corpus petition in a lower federal court. </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Which they can, but the Supreme court has made that right an all-but-empty one&#8211;just a shell game, really&#8211;by interpreting a 1996 “jurisdictional” statute in a way that bars the lower federal courts from throwing out the state-court conviction on constitutional grounds in almost every case. With each passing Supreme Court term, the right to federal habeas review becomes even narrower, a seeming impossibility until it happens. In the last two years, the Supreme Court has treated that right as all but nonexistent. So the almost-total lack of access to the Supreme Court on direct appeal by state-court criminal defendants effectively removes access to constitutional review in federal court. </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">This is even truer in civil cases [including some that involve incredibly important, truly fundamental rights of the sort protected under international human rights laws, although they have nothing at all to do with, say, prison inmates; really&#8211;trust me on this], thanks to a set of perverse, gimmicky Supreme Court-created “jurisdictional” doctrines, which the Supreme Court has stood by and watched metastasize to remove any access to federal court in order to make a constitutional challenge, except for ExxonMobil, which asked the Supreme Court to limit the doctrine at issue, which the Court did, so narrowly as to apply in almost no other case, especially since the other, related doctrine actually bars access in the circumstance in which ExxonMobil was allowed to have it. (Sort of like Bush v. Gore.)</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Anthony Kennedy, the leader of this state-courts-have-sovereignty-and-dignity! juggernaut, likes to say this is done in the name of liberty. (Isn’t everything the rightwing wants done in the name of liberty?!) Which reminds me of a political science class I once took on Maoism. [Maoism] included, basically, the routine use of Orwellian language, in which everything is the opposite of what its name or description indicates. </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Of course, the current Supreme Court’s goal&#8211;the goal of the legal right since the early 1980s&#8211;is to turn the law into nothing but circuitous yellow-brick-road procedure: a dead-end labyrinth whose very purpose is its circuitry and fruitlessness. They’ve come incredibly close to succeeding.</div>
<p>There’s a whole lot more about this that can, and should, be said, and I plan to write in more depth about it.  Which will make me the only one writing for public consumption about it; the general news media covers only “substantive” legal issues (“substantive” being another legal term of art; legal issues are either “substantive” or “procedural.”)  And rarely covers even substantive issues that aren’t part of the culture wars debate.  Which is really nice for the legal right, because their justices and judges can, and do, do just about anything they want, completely under the radar. </p>
<p>But for now, I’ll just add that the judicial right, lead on this by Kennedy and Clarence Thomas, conflate state sovereignty with freedom, but, at least regarding those two and their wingy three colleagues and some (but not all of their lower-court compadres), do so only with respect (pun most definitely intended) to state courts.  To them, state legislative- and executive-branch actions (e.g., state statutes) are fair game for constitutional challenges, and they harbor no inhibition whatsoever about impinging upon state “sovereignty” in recognizing the Constitution’s <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Supremacy_Clause">Supremacy Clause</a> when striking down as unconstitutional state statutes that the political right doesn’t care much for; Texas’s colleague-admissions affirmative action law, say.  (Sit tight for the upcoming oral argument there in that case.)  And their summary reversal of the Montana Supreme Court’s ruling late last year upholding the constitutionality of Montana’s longstanding campaign-finance statute is another example that comes (very) quickly to mind.  My mind, anyway.</p>
<p>To be fair to Kennedy, and certainly to his credit, he&#8211;and he alone, among the Fab Five&#8211;does extend this principle to state statutes that liberals don’t like.  Texas’s criminal anti-sodomy statute is one example, but there are other important ones as well.  </p>
<p>But, in what appears to me to be nothing more than just <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Professional_courtesy">old-fashioned professional courtesy</a>, Kennedy effectively exempts state judicial branches from Supremacy Clause mandates to honor constitutional rights of individuals.  And state courts violate individual procedural and substantive rights, in criminal cases and in certain types of civil cases, with absolute abandon, comfortable in the knowledge that they can.  The result, far, far more often than not, is the very antithesis of freedom.  Except in the Matter Hatter-esque language that the legal right has found so useful.</p>
<p>So, next time Kennedy or Thomas writes an opinion singing the praises of state sovereignty&#8211;by which they almost always just mean state-court sovereignty&#8211;as advancing “freedom,” ask them (rhetorically, of course; they won’t actually hear you unless you retain <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Clement">Paul Clement</a> to speak to them for you, which was basically run75441’s point) whether they think that, say, German Jews in the mid- and late 1930s were freer because Germany was a sovereign state.  <br />I will, anyway.  Or maybe I’ll just ask the Mad Hatter.  Orwell lives.  These days, though, in this country it&#8217;s called &#8220;federalism.&#8221;</p>
<p>&#8212;-</p>
<p>Occasionally, one of my AB posts goes viral (relatively speaking), racking up a couple thousand views on statcounter.  This is one that I hope does.  Actually, I hope it gets a million hits. </p>
<p>Yeah.  A million hits would be good.</p>
<p>Is there such a thing as hitting the Supreme Court in effigy?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/the-rightwing-supreme-court-justices-fair-weather-state-sovereignty-canard.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Clarence and Ginny Thomas, the Go-To Folks for Liberty</title>
		<link>./../../2011/03/clarence-and-ginny-thomas-the-go-to-folks-for-liberty.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/03/clarence-and-ginny-thomas-the-go-to-folks-for-liberty.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2011 01:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Clarence Thomas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Supreme court]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Supreme court ethics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/03/clarence-and-ginny-thomas-the-go-to-folks-for-liberty.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Lifted from an e-mail in reaction to two links here and here I sent to Beverly Mann concerning Judge Clarence Thomas. (e-mail slightly revised for clarity) by Beverly Mann Clarence and Ginny Thomas, the Go-To Folks for Liberty Hi Dan, I’m obviously very supportive of the political goals of both of the organizations whose web [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Lifted from an e-mail in reaction to two links  <br /><a target="_blank" href="http://visitor.benchmarkemail.com/c/v?e=AF1A8&#038;c=7187&#038;email=70J%2BdTjI2cv%2B4t3dS5BmEXnlkRjLUbPe&#038;relid=C6EC164">here</a> and <a target="_blank" href="http://www.protectourelections.org/">here</a> I sent to Beverly Mann concerning Judge Clarence Thomas. (e-mail slightly revised for clarity)</p>
<p>by <strong>Beverly Mann</strong>
<p>Clarence and Ginny Thomas, the Go-To Folks for Liberty</p>
<p>Hi Dan,</p>
<p>I’m obviously very supportive of the political goals of both of the organizations whose web sites you’ve pointed me to and asked my opinion about concerning their efforts against Clarence Thomas.  But the petition demanding impeachment of Thomas for ruling in favor of Citizens United because in 1991 that organization sponsored television commercials urging Thomas’s confirmation by the Senate strikes me as ridiculous. And not just because the House, which would have initiate an impeachment process and then vote articles of impeachment, is in Republican control.</p>
<p><em>The problem with Thomas’s participation in the Citizens United case isn’t that the organization that filed the lawsuit challenging the constitutionality of some of the McCain-Feingold election-law restrictions happened to be Citizens United. Citizens United actually challenged a regulation in that law that had nothing to do with campaign contributions. It was the Court itself (the five-member majority, obviously) that reached out on its own to address the constitutionality of the restrictions on corporate campaign contributions. </em><br /><a name="more"></a><br />The problem is that Koch Industries, the most prolific and pervasive of corporate campaign contributors in federal and state election campaigns, and the Koch brothers, were huge players in this controversy. The purpose of the Koch campaign contributions is to affect the outcome of elections in order to affect enactment, repeal or enforcement of a vast array of environmental laws and regulations that impact their immense oil, gas, manufacturing, ranching, finance and commodities trading businesses. (I got those listings from Wikipedia.) Scalia and Thomas attended and spoke at Koch-sponsored four-day law conferences at luxury resorts. Their expenses were paid by the rightwing bar group, the Federalist Society, which receives substantial donations from Koch Industries and which may have actually received dedicated funds for those expenses from Koch Industries. If so, Scalia and Thomas may not have known of this.</p>
<p>In any event, the decision by these two to participate in the Citizens United decision is not an impeachable offense. What might be an impeachable offense, in my opinion, is Thomas’ failure to comply the disclosure statute; he lied on his disclosure statement, for at least six years, in what I think is a significant respect. As I wrote last week, that may violate a criminal statute, although that is not my area of expertise and I don’t know whether it does or not. And if it does, I hope he is eventually prosecuted for it.</p>
<p>The information that Thomas withheld was that his wife was paid a very substantial amount of money during those six years by rightwing interests. Comments he made in a speech at a Federalist Society function last weekend hint, if I understand the comments correctly, that he withheld that information in contravention of federal statute as part of what he considers his and his wife’s crusade for Liberty in the name of the Constitution, and that he believes—and he made this clear in that speech, as the speech was reported—that he and his wife are the True Arbiters of the meaning of that word as the Constitution intends it; no one else need apply. They are the liberty messiahs, so they are entitled to violate the law, and certainly ethics codes, in the service of their holy mission. And make no mistake. This is a holy mission.</p>
<p>Here are quotes from a <a target="_blank" href="http://dyn.politico.com/printstory.cfm?uuid=98FB7622-57C3-4BBF-8F77-83BDD2822C8F">Politico story about the speech</a>:</p>
</p>
<blockquote><p>Thomas spoke in vague, but ominous, terms about the direction of the country and urged his listeners to “redouble your efforts to learn about our country so that you’re in a position to defend it.”   <br />He also lashed out at his critics, without naming them, asserting they “seem bent on undermining” the High Court as an institution. Such criticism, Thomas warned, could erode the ability of American citizens to fend off threats to their way of life.    <br />“You all are going to be, unfortunately, the recipients of the fallout from that – that there’s going to be a day when you need these institutions to be credible and to be fully functioning to protect your liberties,” he said, according to a partial recording of the speech provided to POLITICO by someone who was at the meeting.    <br />“And that’s long after I’m gone, and that could be either a short or a long time, but you’re younger, and it’s still going to be a necessity to protect the liberties that you enjoy now in this country.” …
<p>At one point Thomas recognized his wife in the audience and suggested she was being targeted for her beliefs, telling the audience, according to the recording, “my bride is with me, Virginia Thomas. And some of you may know her. But the reason I bring that – specifically bring it – up is there is a price to pay today for standing in defense of your Constitution.”</p>
<p>Thomas said his wife “started her organization to give 24/7 every day in defense of liberty,” and said he shared her principles.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>
<p>Yes, that’s right. Thomas thinks it’s his critics who seem bent on undermining the Court as an institution and that could erode the ability of American citizens to fend off threats to their way of life.</p>
<p>Beverly maintains her own blog <a target="_blank" href="http://annarborist.blogspot.com/">The Annarborist</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/03/clarence-and-ginny-thomas-the-go-to-folks-for-liberty.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
