<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>inferior goods &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Non-Hormel Spam is also an Inferior Good, and there are also Inferior Enablers</title>
		<link>./../../2008/11/non-hormel-spam-is-also-an-inferior-good-and-there-are-also-inferior-enablers.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/11/non-hormel-spam-is-also-an-inferior-good-and-there-are-also-inferior-enablers.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2008 01:36:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[inferior goods]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[technology]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/11/non-hormel-spam-is-also-an-inferior-good-and-there-are-also-inferior-enablers.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Why Yahoo! e-mail may be worth using again, non-Jerry Yang edition: Security researchers, anti-spam groups and the whole security community in general were taken by surprise yesterday when reports of a sudden drop in junk mail activity started flowing in. This was the result of ISPs depeering McColo Corp., a U.S. based company offering web [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Why Yahoo! <a href="http://news.softpedia.com/news/Severe-Decrease-in-Spam-Activity-97737.shtml">e-mail may be worth using again</a>, non-Jerry Yang edition:<br />
<blockquote> Security researchers, anti-spam groups and the whole security community in general were taken by surprise yesterday when reports of a sudden drop in junk mail activity started flowing in. This was the result of ISPs depeering McColo Corp., a U.S. based company offering web hosting services to many international cybercrime organizations.</p></blockquote>
<p>First, there was the gathering of evidence:<br />
<blockquote> McColo Corp. is based in San Jose, California and offers web hosting solutions. Nothing bad so far, but according to many reports and an important amount of evidence, a large number of their clients are shady at best. Security experts estimate that the spam generated by the illegal activities hosted by McColo amounts for a whooping 75% of the junk mail sent everyday on a global level.</p></blockquote>
<p>Then it was presented to the companies that could do something about it.<br />
<blockquote>Brian Krebs, reputable journalist at The Washington Post, informed on the <a href="http://voices.washingtonpost.com/securityfix/2008/11/major_source_of_online_scams_a.html">Security Fix blog</a> that he was involved with forwarding evidence of the criminal activity to Global Crossing and Hurricane Electric, McColo&#8217;s two major Internet service providers. “For the past four months, Security Fix has been gathering data from the security industry about McColo Corp. [&#8230;] On Monday, Security Fix contacted the Internet providers that manage more than 90 percent of the company&#8217;s connection to the larger Internet, sending them information about badness at McColo as documented by the security industry,” he writes.</p></blockquote>
<p>Then it was left to two companies to examine the evidence. Compare and contrast:<br />
<blockquote>According to Krebs, while the response from Global Crossing was rather evasive, Hurricane Electric was a lot more responsive to the abuse report and even quick to act about it. &#8220;We looked into it a bit, saw the size and scope of the problem you were reporting and said &#8216;Holy cow! Within the hour we had terminated all of our connections to them,&#8221; Benny Ng, the Freemont-based ISP&#8217;s Director of Marketing, told Krebs.</p></blockquote>
<p>And the result was <a href="http://news.softpedia.com/newsImage/Severe-Decrease-in-Spam-Activity-3.jpg">immediately clear</a>.<br />Go <a href="http://news.softpedia.com/news/Severe-Decrease-in-Spam-Activity-97737.shtml">read the whole thing</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/11/non-hormel-spam-is-also-an-inferior-good-and-there-are-also-inferior-enablers.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
