<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>marginal rates &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Screw the Clinton tax rates. Lets party like it&#8217;s 1936!</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/screw-the-clinton-tax-rates-lets-party-like-its-1936.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/screw-the-clinton-tax-rates-lets-party-like-its-1936.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 28 Jul 2012 05:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Bush tax cuts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income equality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[marginal rates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax rates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[top 1%]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/screw-the-clinton-tax-rates-lets-party-like-its-1936.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Update: *Additional numbers added Digby wrote a few days ago about the“grown-up” people coming to town to save America from the deficit. She listed a few of those people and their annual income. Also, a few days ago the Senate had a vote on the tax cuts. Letting the Bush cuts go (I&#8217;m all for [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div></div>
<div>Update: *Additional numbers added </p>
<p>Digby wrote a few days ago about<a href="http://digbysblog.blogspot.com/2012/07/the-grown-ups-are-planning-coup.html"> the“grown-up” people</a> coming to town to save America from the deficit.  She listed a few of those people and their annual income.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Also, a  few days ago the Senate had a vote on the tax cuts.  Letting the Bush cuts go (I&#8217;m all for it and we can stop the payroll tax cut too as it is all stupid policy when the problem is declining wages/income going to labor) will return us to the Clinton years rates.  People have noted just how little such a rise means to those at the top.     </div>
<div></div>
<div>Well, in keeping with my define rich series and my series looking at the purpose of taxation, I thought wouldn&#8217;t it be interesting to see just what these 1%&#8217;ers might be paying if we went back to the beginning of the last great period of <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/03/defining-rich-vi-1936-tax-tables.html">mass prosperity:  1936</a>.   </div>
<div></div>
<div>Yes indeedy, I say go for the brass ring.  Let&#8217;s show our maturity and actually implement the lesson learned from our history, that period from around <a href="http://www.taxhistory.org/www/website.nsf/Web/THM1901?OpenDocument">1906 to 1932</a> and then 1936 to 1979.   </div>
<div></div>
<div>While we&#8217;re at it, let us stop pretending that global trade is something new with an unknowable to man exotic force that we just have to accept as part of the expression of our DNA.   There is RNA also (look it up).</div>
<div></div>
<p><a name="more"></a>
<div></div>
<div>The following  numbers are based on the gross incomes Digby listed.  Thus we&#8217;ll have to keep in mind that there have been no adjustments made for deductions in my calculations.  So in truth, the tax paid would be less and the purchasing power of the actual non-adjusted income would be much greater.  After all, the deductions represent benefits received from the income that was deducted including the government handout in the form of reduced taxes for various activities taken with one&#8217;s income.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Here is what it looks like:</div>
<div><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-1cMkNPATmc8/UBN2YVEaQKI/AAAAAAAAASw/WiV0pUMcLRU/s1600/Party+like+it+1936+income+tax+chart.jpg" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="177" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-1cMkNPATmc8/UBN2YVEaQKI/AAAAAAAAASw/WiV0pUMcLRU/s320/Party+like+it+1936+income+tax+chart.jpg" width="320"></a></div>
<div>All these men managed to hit the top marginal rate of 79%.  Not one of them paid that amount.  Notice how flat the percentage paid becomes.  They want a flat tax, the got it.  They just had to really, really perform to get to that level of tax nirvana in 1936.  They couldn&#8217;t just pull a <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0102609/">Lawrence Garfield</a>, or should I say a Romney?  They couldn&#8217;t just negotiate payment in stock, whack labor costs to increase the stock value, take that money and buy it&#8217;s competitors to the point of oligopoly and then move on.  They could not just raid a solid company like New England Wire and Cable turning all the assets into cash at the expense of all the other relationships such a company had and justify it by saying “I make you money”.  Greenmail?  Junk Bonds?</div>
<div></div>
<div>I wrote <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/07/wages-driven-down-now-relative-to.html">about Caterpillar </a>and their approach to negotiating with the commodity of labor.  The average yearly income of the labor was $55,000/year.  The multiples of the above net income range from 24.8 to 147.38.  (* Multiples of the gross incomes range from 104.6 to 688.)</div>
<div></div>
<div>Granted, what&#8217;s left for these gentlemen would not allow the purchase of a new Cessna Citation X, but there was a 1999 listed for $5,950,000 when I search google.  I think Mr. Sherill could afford the monthly payment on this.  Though <a href="http://www.cessna.com/citation/mustang.html">Cessna is offering the 4 passenger</a> (the X is 12 passenger) at 0% interest for the first 12 months and Wiki says they list for only $2.65 million!  You know, if buying used just curls your hair.</div>
<div></div>
<div>The point?  There is nothing with the 1936 marginal tax rates that these men can not have other than more of it.  Nothing.   Real grown-ups who developed the 1936 tax table new this along with a lot of other stuff related income how it is actually earned and it&#8217;s social effect.  All you have to do is<a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/03/defining-rich-vi-1936-tax-tables.html"> lookat the tables and graphs</a> to see that the marginal rates were not pulled out of selfish and self serving asses.  They had a desired results in mind, one of which was to prevent “economic royalists”.  I am confident the other desire was to take back rent collected from other peoples collective efforts in proportion to the lack of labor performed as one rises up the economic pyramid.    </div>
<div></div>
<div>Have you heard the one about job creation?  The one that asks: When was the last time a poor person gave you a job?  When was the last time a CEO 1%&#8217;er&#8217;s activity saved the human race?   Four people at least from 1928 to the patent granted in 1948 were involved in<a href="http://inventors.about.com/od/pstartinventions/a/Penicillin.htm"> bring penicillin to the point ofcommercial viability</a>. </div>
<div>It was one woman&#8217;s work that allowed the next step of developing additional antibiotics.  </div>
<div></div>
<div>When was the last time a CEO 1% er&#8217;s activity resulted in a leap of human progress?   I&#8217;m thinking of my favorite non-CEO/Banker/1% example of flight.  No, Gates and Jobs did not do it like the Wright Brothers did it.  </div>
<div></div>
<div>1936.  We responded in a way that attest to a time when we did learn from history and acted on lessons from history.</div>
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/screw-the-clinton-tax-rates-lets-party-like-its-1936.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Peter Diamond, Emmanuel Saez, Paul Krugman and Me!! Looking at Optimal Tax Rates</title>
		<link>./../../2011/11/peter-diamond-emmanuel-saez-paul-krugman-and-me-looking-at-optimal-tax-rates.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/11/peter-diamond-emmanuel-saez-paul-krugman-and-me-looking-at-optimal-tax-rates.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 23 Nov 2011 13:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[marginal rates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Presimetrics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[top marginal rates]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/11/peter-diamond-emmanuel-saez-paul-krugman-and-me-looking-at-optimal-tax-rates.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Mike Kimel Peter Diamond, Emmanuel Saez, Paul Krugman and Me!! Looking at Optimal Tax Rates Via Paul Krugman, I learned of this paper by Peter Diamond and Emmanuel Saez. Diamond, of course, is a Nobel Laureate. I will be shocked if Saez isn&#8217;t one too in ten or fifteen years. Long story made very [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Mike Kimel</p>
<p>Peter Diamond, Emmanuel Saez, Paul Krugman and Me!!  Looking at Optimal Tax Rates</p>
<p>Via <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/22/taxing-job-creators/">Paul Krugman</a>, I learned of <a href="http://pubs.aeaweb.org/doi/pdfplus/10.1257/jep.25.4.165">this paper</a> by Peter Diamond and Emmanuel Saez.  Diamond, of course, is a Nobel Laureate.  I will be shocked if Saez isn&#8217;t one too in ten or fifteen years.</p>
<p>Long story made very short, Diamond and Saez jump through a lot of hoops and find that the optimal top marginal income tax rate (all in, that is, including federal, state and local), which they define as maximizing social welfare, is about 73%.  </p>
<p>Now, long time readers may recall I&#8217;ve been doing this sort of analysis for years, though of course I&#8217;ve been looking at tax rates that maximize real GDP growth.  Simply put, you cannot maximize long run social welfare if you aren&#8217;t maximizing economic growth.  <br /><a name="more"></a><br />My approach is much simpler than that followed by Diamond and Saez.  I like to think its much more intuitive and easier to explain.  I note that US data shows a simple quadratic relationship between real GDP growth from one year to the next and tax rates:</p>
<p>growth in real GDP, t to t+1 = f(top marginal tax rate, top marginal tax rate squared, other variables)</p>
<p>One recent post on the topic is <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2010/12/top-marginal-income-tax-rate-should-be.html">here</a>.   (<a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2011/10/laffer-curve-and-kimel-curve.html">Unlike the Laffer curve</a>, the coefficients come out statistically significant and with the right signs.)  </p>
<p>I mention all this to note that no matter what I throw into the equation, I find that the top marginal tax rate that maximizes economic growth is somewhere around 65%.  Of course, I&#8217;ve focused only on federal tax rates&#8230; add in state and local it comes pretty close to what Diamond and Saez have found.</p>
<p>As I noted above, my approach is somewhat simpler, and easier to follow than that of Diamond and Saez.  Part of the reason is that they come at it from a point of view of elasticities.  But with all due respect to my betters (Diamond and Saez, and Krugman as well considering the explanation in his post) I think this is the wrong way to consider the problem.  It requires all sorts of assumptions and generalizations about people&#8217;s behavior, some of which are both false and create resistance from folks on the right.  </p>
<p>For example, there is a notion that raising tax rates will reduce people&#8217;s willingness to work&#8230; which is only true above certain thresholds.  (That threshold, of course, varies per individual.)  As anyone who has ever had a business will tell you (when they&#8217;re not busy demanding tax reductions), you don&#8217;t pay taxes on income from the business if you turn around and reinvest that income.  (An accountant would talk to you about decreasing your tax liability by increasing expenses which amounts to the same thing.)  You only pay taxes on that income you take that income out, presumably for consumption purposes.</p>
<p>So to simplify, consider an example&#8230;.  is a successful businessperson more likely to take money out of the business if his/her tax rate is 70% or if its 25%?  In general, a person is more likely to take that money at 25%, as there&#8217;s less of a penalty.  At 70% tax rates, there is more of an incentive to reinvest in the business, creating more growth in the business in subsequent years, and more economic growth thereafter.  70% tax rates are more likely to generate faster economic growth than 25% tax rates precisely because people are self-interested and the higher tax rates induce people to continue investing in things they do well.</p>
<p>(Of course, tax rates can get too high.  At 95%, people will reinvest almost every dime&#8230; even if they have exhausted every good investment opportunity they have.  Thus, to avoid taxes they&#8217;ll be making lousy investments which in turn slow economic growth.)  </p>
<p>Still, its gratifying to see others who are more, er, credentialed doing similar work.  If I might end on a digression, though, I can think of a number of examples of work being done on blogs by people who are essentially hobbyists which is somewhat ahead of the academic literature.  However, to a large extent, if something wasn&#8217;t published in the academic literature, for all practical purposes it didn&#8217;t happen.  Which is a shame, because most of us who aren&#8217;t academics don&#8217;t have time or the resources required for such publication (such as access to econlit).  That inevitably slows economic development three ways:</p>
<p>1.  the lack of recognition discourages hobbyists who have the potential and otherwise would have the willingness to improve on the existing literature<br />2.  should such hobbyists persist and do the research, that research will not be widely disseminated even if it is an improvement over the academic literature<br />3.  it maintains an insular attitude among those who are not hobbyists.  As smart as Diamond, Saez, and Krugman all are, none of them are thinking the way someone running a business thinks of they&#8217;d have realized immediately how people who are running a business react to higher and lower tax rates.  I have read a lot of academic papers on taxation and have yet to stumble on one that gets it right.</p>
<p>&#8212;</p>
<p>Thanks to Steve Roth of <a href="http://www.asymptosis.com/">Asymptosis</a> and Jazzbumpa of <a href="http://jazzbumpa.blogspot.com/">Retirement Blues</a> for notifying me of Krugman&#8217;s post.  </p>
<p>And since I always offer&#8230;  if anyone wants any spreadsheets showing the quadratic relationship between tax rates and economic growth or anything else I&#8217;ve done, drop me a line.  I&#8217;m at my first name (mike) then a period then my last name (kimel &#8211; with one m only!!!) at gmail.com.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/11/peter-diamond-emmanuel-saez-paul-krugman-and-me-looking-at-optimal-tax-rates.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>John Taylor in Favor of Higher Marginal Income Tax Rates? If Not, Why Not?</title>
		<link>./../../2011/04/john-taylor-in-favor-of-higher-marginal-income-tax-rates-if-not-why-not.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/04/john-taylor-in-favor-of-higher-marginal-income-tax-rates-if-not-why-not.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2011 05:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Income tax]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[marginal rates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Presimetrics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/04/john-taylor-in-favor-of-higher-marginal-income-tax-rates-if-not-why-not.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Mike Kimel John Taylor in Favor of Higher Marginal Income Tax Rates? If Not, Why Not? A couple of weeks ago, John Taylor posted a graph showing that since 1990, there has been a negative correlation between the Investment to GDP ratio and unemployment. There&#8217;s been some back and forth between Taylor and some [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by <strong>Mike Kimel</strong></p>
<p><strong>John Taylor in Favor of Higher Marginal Income Tax Rates?  If Not, Why Not?</strong></p>
<p>A couple of weeks ago, John Taylor <a href="http://johnbtaylorsblog.blogspot.com/2011/01/higher-investment-best-way-to-reduce.html">posted a graph</a> showing that since 1990, there has been a negative correlation between the Investment to GDP ratio and unemployment.   </p>
<p>There&#8217;s been some back and forth between Taylor and some of the other big boys (some of it summarized at <a href="http://economistsview.typepad.com/economistsview/2011/04/graph-fight.html">Mark Thoma&#8217;s Economists View</a>, and even <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/03/30/more-on-unemployment-and-investment/">Krugman</a> has weighed in).<br /><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Lots of fun is being had by all, but it seems everyone, especially John Taylor, is missing a key point.  If, as he states in his post, &#8220;the most effective way to reduce unemployment is to raise investment as a share of GDP&#8221; and if we want to reduce unemployment, then we should be <a href="http://www.presimetrics.com/blog/?p=301">raising the top marginal tax rate.</a>.  After all, going back to 1929 (that&#8217;s as far back as the Bureau of Economic Analysis has data), there&#8217;s a quadratic relationship between the top marginal income tax rate and the ratio of private investment to private consumption.</p>
<p>As I note in the post in which that analysis is done (complete with a nice graph):</p>
<blockquote><p>correlation between the top marginal tax rate the ratio of investment to consumption for top marginal tax rates below 50% is 55%. That is to say, an increase in tax rates increases the ratio of investment to consumption when tax rates are below 50%.</p></blockquote>
<p>So&#8230;  raise top marginal rate &#8212;> more investment &#8212;> lower unemployment.  I imagine John Taylor&#8217;s endorsement of higher marginal tax rates should come any moment now.</p>
<p>&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8211;<br />Cross-posted at the <a href="http://www.presimetrics.com/blog/?p=412">Presimetrics blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/04/john-taylor-in-favor-of-higher-marginal-income-tax-rates-if-not-why-not.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
