<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>g5 &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>g7-vs-g5-in-charts</title>
		<link>./../../2009/10/g7-vs-g5-in-charts.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/10/g7-vs-g5-in-charts.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Oct 2009 13:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[g5]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[g7]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[global economies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Globalization]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[international]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/10/g7-vs-g5-in-charts.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by RebeccaCross posted from Newsneconomics These are interesting times in global economics, especially from the policy perspective. And although there was a sense of global urgency across the G7 (Canada, France, Germany, Japan, Italy, UK, and US) and the G5 (Brazil, People&#8217;s Republic of China, India, Mexico, and South Africa) late in 2008 and early [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Rebecca<br />Cross posted from <a target="_blank" href="http://www.newsneconomics.com/2009/10/g7-vs-g5-in-charts.html"> Newsneconomics</a></p>
<div>These are interesting times in global economics, especially from the policy perspective. And although there was a sense of global urgency across the G7 (Canada, France, Germany, Japan, Italy, UK, and US) and the G5 (Brazil, People&#8217;s Republic of China, India, Mexico, and South Africa) late in 2008 and early in 2009, policy makers now face very different economic circumstances. The global downturn was (mostly) ubiquitous, but the upswing will not be. The G5 are likely to initiate explicit exit strategies before the G7, as growth, domestic demand, and inflation rebound first.</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<p>
<div>
<div>The downturn in the developed world was very severe, as illustrated by the sharp contraction of GDP of the G7 countries. And across the G5, some countries experienced similar declines, however given the nose-dive that was global trade, the economic resilience via expansionary policy in India and China has been rather remarkable.  </div>
<div><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_RPTAaOI4RN8/SstFIu_ru3I/AAAAAAAAAmw/FNn7ruH6BLU/s1600-h/g5_gdp.png" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_RPTAaOI4RN8/SstFIu_ru3I/AAAAAAAAAmw/FNn7ruH6BLU/s200/g5_gdp.png"></a> 
<div><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_RPTAaOI4RN8/SstHCyyvk-I/AAAAAAAAAnA/0qYbhKwc6J8/s1600-h/g7_gdp.png" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_RPTAaOI4RN8/SstHCyyvk-I/AAAAAAAAAnA/0qYbhKwc6J8/s200/g7_gdp.png"></a></div>
<p>Domestic demand, underpinned by robust fiscal and monetary policy pushed auto sales forward in the G5 and simply offset some of the decline in retail sales in the G7 (see charts below). I used auto sales in the G5 as a proxy for retail sales, as I could not access a retail sales in India (not even sure they offer the statistic). Impressively, though, retail sales remained strong in the UK. Auto sales in China, Brazil, and India have been hot &#8211; the real question here is: what is the underlying demand for goods and services in these countries, especially in China.
<div><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_RPTAaOI4RN8/SstII85Ve1I/AAAAAAAAAnQ/nj0CPupjBnk/s1600-h/g5_auto.png" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_RPTAaOI4RN8/SstII85Ve1I/AAAAAAAAAnQ/nj0CPupjBnk/s200/g5_auto.png"></a><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_RPTAaOI4RN8/SstH7napyVI/AAAAAAAAAnI/Hw72ZZuMhCI/s1600-h/g7_retail.png" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_RPTAaOI4RN8/SstH7napyVI/AAAAAAAAAnI/Hw72ZZuMhCI/s200/g7_retail.png"></a></div>
<p>Monetary policy &#8211; driving down interest rates in order to stimulate consumption via the credit markets &#8211; was very successful in the G5, but much less so in the ailing G7.</p>
<p>And finally, inflation has been quite resilient in some countries, notably in the UK and India. As such, the Bank of England has a real trade-off with which to contend: inflation (as measured by the CPI), 1.6% over the year, remains sticky and remarkably close to target, 2.0%. The Reserve Bank of India is seeing food prices drive inflation steadily upward. http://online.wsj.com/article/SB125439928727956013.html?mod=googlenews_wsjSome expect India to be one of the first emerging markets to start tightening (The Bank of Israel was the first).</div>
</div>
<div></div>
<div><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_RPTAaOI4RN8/SstIcnPWWqI/AAAAAAAAAnY/zuLfEG42n7U/s1600-h/g7_inflation.png" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_RPTAaOI4RN8/SstIcnPWWqI/AAAAAAAAAnY/zuLfEG42n7U/s200/g7_inflation.png"></a></div>
<div><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_RPTAaOI4RN8/SstI_6VJYjI/AAAAAAAAAng/VripFQoYyKc/s1600-h/g5_inflation.png" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_RPTAaOI4RN8/SstI_6VJYjI/AAAAAAAAAng/VripFQoYyKc/s200/g5_inflation.png"></a></div>
<p>
<div>There are a lot of question marks right now &#8211; the biggest is when central banks and fiscal authorities start to pull back. Especially in the G7, too early and one risks the feared W, but too late, and inflation becomes an issue.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Across the G7, rate hikes are unlikely to occur until well-into 2010, and maybe even 2011 for some. Across the G5, however, late 2010 is more likely an upper limit, however, some countries like Mexico are seriously struggling and policy will remain loose for some time. (See RGE Monitor Nouriel Roubini&#8217;s latest, &#8220;Thoughts on Where We Are&#8221; &#8211; unfortunately, a subscription is required.)</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/10/g7-vs-g5-in-charts.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
