<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>run 75441 &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Geithner&#8217;s Baa Humbug to Jobs and Labor</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/geithners-baa-humbug-to-jobs-and-labor.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/geithners-baa-humbug-to-jobs-and-labor.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 09 Feb 2013 17:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Main Street]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[run 75441]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Timothy Giethner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wall street]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/geithners-baa-humbug-to-jobs-and-labor.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Dan here&#8230;Taking a look back to 2009: Geithner&#8217;s Baa Humbug to Jobs and Labor 12/25/2009 (h/t Run75441) &#8220;Ebenezer: Since you ask me what I wish sir, that is my answer. I help to support the establishments I have named; those who are badly off must go there.&#8221; Daniel Gross at Slate interviews Tim Geithner here: [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Dan here&#8230;Taking a look back to 2009:<br />
<h4><a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2009/12/geithners-baa-humbug-to-jobs-and-labor.html">Geithner&#8217;s Baa Humbug to Jobs and Labor</a> 12/25/2009</h4>
<p>(h/t Run75441)</p>
<p>&#8220;Ebenezer: Since you ask me what I wish sir, that is my answer. I help to support the establishments I have named; those who are badly off must go there.&#8221;</p>
<p>Daniel Gross at Slate interviews Tim Geithner here: <a href="http://www.slate.com/id/2239552/pagenum/all/#p2">“We Will Be Judged on How We Dealt with the Things that were Broken”</a> Some rather revealing statements by Tim Geithner to Daniel Gross&#8217;s questions:    </p>
<p>GROSS: There&#8217;s a perception that you regard your portfolio narrowly, as primarily focused on the health of Wall Street, with Main Street a distant second.  </p>
<p>GEITHNER: &#8220;My first and essential responsibility was to fix and reform the financial system. That was necessarily going to be the principal part of what people saw. About half my time from the beginning has been spent on the design of the broader economic strategy. The idea that we did not do much for the broader challenges facing the country is completely unjustified. The Recovery Act itself was not just a sweeping, essential force for growth but included a bunch of targeted investments in education, energy, environment, health care that will have huge long-term benefits.&#8221;</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>(Run here: Geithner misses the point or makes the point that finance is the number one concern over Main Street, even though Main Street is financing the rescue of W$. The constituency doesn&#8217;t want charity in targeted investments in education, energy, education, and environment when it can pay for those investments itself if they are working. Main Street wants jobs? Main street is still waiting for that tsunami of job creation which is one of the broader challenges of any administration and no administration has put into play any package to stimuli it or companies to do more. Jobs are left to free market influences which is content with investing profits elsewhere other than job creating infrastructure.)    </p>
<p>GROSS: So you don&#8217;t think the bailouts were too friendly to Wall Street? </p>
<p>GEITHNER: “The idea that the strategy was unfair and has principally benefited a small number of institutions in New York is a mischaracterization of the design and result of the strategy. I thought people would have understood this after the failure of Lehman Bros. But when you do too little and you leave the system with real fear that everything is going to fall apart, like any financial crisis, it hurts the poorest most. A just and fair strategy, even if it is politically hardest to explain and justify, is to use well-designed but massive force to stabilize the system.“   </p>
<p>(Run here: Over at Naked Capitalism, they are debating whether Goldman Sachs drove the collapse of AIG by calling for the mark down of CDO by companies holding too many of them thereby forcing AIG to raise collateral after it was downgraded and eventually paying off on CDO that never were expected to payoff. While AIG is at fault for seeing too many pie in the sky dollars in risk and having too little collateral to cover it, one has to wonder why Goldman Sachs should have received 100% on the dollar on its CDS for its risk with AIG and not knowing how over leveraged AIG was at the time. Goldman Sachs certainly benefited by Geithner&#8217;s negotiated settlement of AIG&#8217;s liabilities at 100% on the dollar.)</p>
<p>GROSS: The biggest downside surprise?<br />  <br />GEITHNER: &#8220;The [high] level of unemployment relative to what was happening in the economy as a whole. I&#8217;m not an economist, but almost all forecasters missed that. And that&#8217;s hugely consequential, because it&#8217;s the prism through which most people view basic economic health.&#8221; </p>
<p>(Run here:He is kidding right? During every economic downturn, it has consistently been Main Street that has been shown the street from their jobs or homes.)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/geithners-baa-humbug-to-jobs-and-labor.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Healthcare Reform; Socialism or Fascism?</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/healthcare-reform-socialism-or-fascism.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/healthcare-reform-socialism-or-fascism.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 20 Jan 2013 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[health care reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[healthcare thoughts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[run 75441]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/healthcare-reform-socialism-or-fascism.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Run75411 Healthcare Reform; Socialism or Fascism? Whole Foods CEO John Mackey in 2009 originally called President Obama&#8217;s healthcare plan a form of Socialism while writing an op-ed for the Wall Street Journal: &#8220;The problem with socialism is that eventually you run out of other people&#8217;s money.&#8221; Margaret Thatcher&#8221; and added to Thatcher&#8217;s statement: &#8220;While [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Run75411</p>
<p> Healthcare Reform; Socialism or Fascism?</p>
<p>Whole Foods CEO John Mackey in 2009 originally called President Obama&#8217;s healthcare plan a form of Socialism while writing an op-ed for the Wall Street Journal:</p>
<blockquote><p><i>&#8220;The problem with socialism is that eventually you run out of other people&#8217;s money.&#8221;</i> <i>Margaret</i> <i>Thatcher&#8221;</i></p></blockquote>
<p>and added to Thatcher&#8217;s statement:</p>
<blockquote><p><i>&#8220;While we clearly need health-care reform, the last thing our country needs is a massive new health-care entitlement that will create hundreds of billions of dollars of new unfunded deficits and move us much closer to a government takeover of our health-care system,&#8221; he wrote.</i></p></blockquote>
<p>Mackey joins other CEO&#8217;s (Papa Johns, Olive Garden, Applebees, etc.) (<a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/12/raising-price-of-pizza-10-to-14-cents.html"><i>Raising the Cost of Pizza 10 to 14 cents</i></a>); who refuse to understand the need for healthcare reform, support a commercial healthcare insurance and industry solution even though both have done little to voluntarily rein in costs, are willing to penalize their employees for the PPACA, and ignore the results of doing nothing and associated increased costs. Since Hillarycare (1994), the industry has ignored increasing costs and has not provided solutions to mitigate them. As shown in Figure 1 annual healthcare cost has grown much faster than inflation. Figure 4 shows the increase in House hold expenditures since 1994 when Hillarycare was considered.<i></i></p>
<div><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-c-GJxlk8UzQ/UPrc-bnrVHI/AAAAAAAABbY/PtRATj7wSK0/s1600/hillarycare.PNG" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="263" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-c-GJxlk8UzQ/UPrc-bnrVHI/AAAAAAAABbY/PtRATj7wSK0/s400/hillarycare.PNG" width="400"></a></div>
<p><a href="http://www.americanprogress.org/wp-content/uploads/issues/2009/01/pdf/1994_health_memo.pdf"><i>&#8220;American Healthcare since 1994&#8221; Center for American Progress</i></a></p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Recently during an NPR interview, John Mackey changed his opinion calling the PPACA fascism instead of Socialism:</p>
<blockquote><p><i>&#8220;Technically speaking, it&#8217;s more like fascism. Socialism is where the government owns the means of production. In fascism, the government doesn&#8217;t own the means of production, but they do control it — and that&#8217;s what&#8217;s happening with our health care programs and these reforms.&#8221; </i><a href="http://www.newsmax.com/TheWire/whole-foods-obamacare-facist-socialist/2013/01/16/id/471765">Obamacare Is Fascist, Not Socialist</a></p></blockquote>
<p>In a short period after labeling the PPACA as fascism, John Mackey reconsiders his words after a public uproar and retracted his name-calling of President Obama as a fascist and the PPACA as fascism. All of this from a Liberal now turned Libertarian.</p>
<blockquote><p>&#8220;<i>The term fascism today stirs up too much negative emotion with its horrific associations in the 20th century,&#8221; he said.</i> </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p><i>&#8220;I believe that, if the goal is universal health care, our country would be far better served by combining free enterprise capitalism with a strong governmental safety net for our poorest citizens and those with preexisting conditions, helping everyone to be able to buy insurance. This is what Switzerland does and I think we would be much better off copying that system than where we are currently headed in the United States.</i>&#8221; <a href="http://www.nbcnews.com/business/whole-foods-ceo-regrets-comparing-obamacare-fascism-1B8022914">Whole Foods CEO Regrets . . .&#8221;</a></p></blockquote>
<p>It has only been since the passage of the PPACA (see S&#038;P Healthcare Indices) has the healthcare industry begun to rein in costs as reflected in Medicare, Medicaid, and SCHPS through efficiencies. Much of this is due to the healthcare industry rapidly preparing for the 2014 final implementation of the PPACA. More will come after 2014.</p>
<p>You would think this would be enough? At the same time, the Republicans are calling for cuts to the three programs to lower deficit spending; the President is offering to consider modest cuts and shows willingness to sell-out the citizens to achieve his Grand Deal. Cuts in any of the programs will do nothing to lower healthcare industry cost as these programs are a reflection of the industry. In the end, such a Grand Deal will lay the burden of healthcare costs on the elderly, the poor and the children of this nation. The &#8220;I Made This&#8221; John Mackeys of the world who became rich as a result his customers buying from Whole Foods will absolve themselves of any social responsibility.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/healthcare-reform-socialism-or-fascism.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>SCOTUS Chastises Congress and the Executive Branches</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/scotus-chastises-congress-and-the-executive-branches.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/scotus-chastises-congress-and-the-executive-branches.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Jan 2013 18:23:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[run 75441]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SCOTUS]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/scotus-chastises-congress-and-the-executive-branches.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by run 75411Update:  Beverly Mann adds this note lifted from comments: The Supreme Court is rarely in session. It’s seasonal, part-time work. They usually hear argument in 10 cases a month, seven months a year. In December, they didn’t hear even that many.There’s really sooo much that can, and should, be said about the issue [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by<strong> run 75411</strong><br /><strong><br /></strong><strong></strong><br />Update:  Beverly Mann adds this note lifted from comments:</p>
<blockquote><p>The Supreme Court is rarely in session.  It’s seasonal, part-time work.  They usually hear argument in 10 cases a month, seven months a year.  In December, they didn’t hear even that many.<br />There’s really sooo much that can, and should, be said about the issue of (virtually universal lack of) access to the Supreme Court, and its repercussions.  Roberts’ bizarre, cutesy annual report is … oh … I don’t know …characteristically hubristic?  </p></blockquote>
<p><strong><br /></strong><strong><br /></strong><strong>SCOTUS Chastises Congress and the Executive Branches</strong><br /><strong><br /></strong>A pencil and piece of paper was all Clarence Earl Gideon needed to state his case of being denied council in court after being accused of robbery and sentenced to prison. Gideon did get a review of his case under a violation of his 6th Amendment rights to council. Today it is near to impossible for the same to occur and the probability of achieving a review by SCOTUS would be akin to a grain of sand on a Florida beach. The highest court in the nation reviews issues and issues opinions for an ~85 cases/year few of which would be of the same stature as Gideon&#8217;s. It is all about who gains access to the court. Filing a petition is no easy task and the cost of which runs ~$3,000 for a dozen or so copies. The days of Gideon are long gone.</p>
<p>Why would I bring this up on an Economics board? Most recently Chief Justice Roberts got into the Congressional/Executive fray and their battle over finding a solution to the hypothetical fiscal cliff. </p>
<blockquote><p>“<i>Our country faces new challenges, including the much-publicized ‘fiscal cliff’ and the longer-term problem of a truly extravagant and burgeoning national debit,” he wrote. “No one seriously doubts that the country’s fiscal ledger has gone awry. The public properly looks to its elected officials to craft a solution.” </i></p></blockquote>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Chief Justice Prods Congress to Resolve Budget Talks and Control National Debt, http://www.nytimes.com/2013/01/01/us/chief-justice-roberts-prods-congress-on-fiscal-matters.html?_r=0<br />Roberts goes on to add;<br />
<blockquote><i>The federal judiciary makes do with a budget appropriation of about $7 billion, he wrote, “a mere two-tenths of 1 percent of the United States’ total budget of $3.7 trillion.”<br /></i><i>“Yes,” he went on, “for each citizen’s tax dollar, only two-tenths of one penny goes toward funding the entire third branch of government!” </i></p></blockquote>
<p><i></i><br /><i><br /></i><i></i><br />That is notable cost control and Roberts cites how much it costs each citizen to have access to SCOTUS. The Robert&#8217;s SCOTUS saw an ~ 64 cases last year which is down from the typical 75-85 cases seen yearly and down even further from the 1963 cases reviewed by SCOTUS. By reviewing fewer cases, the Roberts SCOTUS controls costs and further reduces the probably of another Gideon achieving review. This is not true cost control, his waxing elegantly on how SCOTUS achieves reduced costs is suspect, and comes at the expense of the citizenry. Instead of working 8 hour days (if they were hourly), SCOTUS now works 7 hour days and produces less.</p>
<p>Less throughput and a selective one at best.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/scotus-chastises-congress-and-the-executive-branches.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Raising the Price of Pizza 10 to 14 cents. . .</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/raising-the-price-of-pizza-10-to-14-cents.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/raising-the-price-of-pizza-10-to-14-cents.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 02 Dec 2012 21:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Health care costs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health care reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Maggie Mahar]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obamacare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[run 75441]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/raising-the-price-of-pizza-10-to-14-cents.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Bill aka run75441 Raising the Price of Pizza 10 to 14 cents. . . Will pizza and food prices really have to increase to cover healthcare costs for the mostly young employees of the Olive Garden&#8217;s, Denny&#8217;s, and Papa John&#8217;s restaurants? A 10 to 14 cents increase per pizza is being proposed by Papa [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by <strong>Bill aka run75441</strong><a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766" name="_top"></a></p>
<p>Raising the Price of Pizza 10 to 14 cents. . .</p>
<p> Will pizza and food prices really have to increase to cover healthcare costs for the mostly young employees of the Olive Garden&#8217;s, Denny&#8217;s, and Papa John&#8217;s restaurants? </p>
<p>A 10 to 14 cents increase per pizza is being proposed by Papa Johns&#8217; to pay for the PPACA. At the same time, Papa John&#8217;s is advertising a 2 million-pizza giveaway with the help of Peyton Manning <a href="file:///C:/Users/Owner/AppData/Local/Microsoft/Windows/Temporary%20Internet%20Files/Content.IE5/XVMSONN6/#_top"><i>&#8220;Two Million Free Pizzas&#8221;</i></a> (must be a freebie?). Not sure myself how I might decide to account for the cost; but, here is a try; free pizza for 2 million NFL fans to increase sales, . . . cut employee hours to avoid the PPACA and keep the price, . . . raise prices 10 to 14 cents per pizza to have healthcare insurance for the restaurant staff, . . . or maybe a kind of half cheese/half sausage combo. . . healthcare and free pizzas with Peyton Manning promoting the social responsibility of Papa John&#8217;s? </p>
<p>Maggie Mahar at The Health Beat Blog <a href="http://www.healthbeatblog.com/2012/11/can-u-s-businesses-afford-obamacare-2/"><i>&#8220;Can US Businesses Afford Obamacare?&#8221;</i></a> points to an interesting article by John Padua of <i>Managed Care Matters </i>discussing who bears the healthcare reform cost if restaurant owners opt out<i> </i>while Forbes Caleb Melby runs the numbers and questions the increased costs suggested by Papa&#8217;s John&#8217;s CEO<i> </i><a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/calebmelby/2012/11/12/breaking-down-centi-millionaire-papa-john-schnatters-obamacare-math/"><i>&#8220;Papa John&#8217;s Obamacare Math&#8221;</i></a><i> .</i><br /><i><br /></i> The issue(s): <i>The Affordable Care Act dictates that full-time employees (30 hours or more per week) at companies with more than 50 workers need to be provided health insurance. CEO John Schnatter has further claimed that some employers will cut employee hours to avoid providing them with healthcare. </i><br /><i></i><br />The Cost: <i>John Schnatter estimates that Obamacare will end up costing his company $5-8 million annually.</i><br /><i></i><br />The Price Increase: <i>10 to 14 cents per pizza</i><br /><strong><br /></strong> <strong>Checking John Schnatter’s Math: </strong><i>Last year, Papa John’s International captured $1.218 billion in revenue. Total operating expenses were $1.131 billion. If Schnatter’s math is accurate (Obamacare will cost his company $5-8 million more annually), then new regulation translates into a .4% to .7% expense increase. It is difficult to set that ratio against the proposed pie increase and across all sizes given size and topping differentials, but many of their large specialty pizzas run for $16. Remarkably, a 10-14 cent increase on a $16 pizza falls in a comparable range of .6% to .9%; but, the cost transference becomes less equitable if you are looking at medium pizzas which run closer to $12, meaning a .8% to 1.15% price increase.</i><br /><i><br /></i> <i>Lets say that Papa John’s sells exactly half medium/half large specialty pizzas. Averaging the ranges for both sizes, then averaging that product yields a .86% price increase — well outside the range of what Schnatter says Obamacare will cost him.</i><br /><i><br /></i> <i>So how much would prices go up, under these 50/50 conditions, if they were to fairly reflect the increased cost of doing business onset by Obamacare? Roughly 3.4 to 4.6 cents a pie.</i><br /><i></i></p>
<p>3.4 to 4.6 cents does not seem like such a huge increase to bear by either customer or the business and if the advertising is done right; it might prove more positive than giving away 2 million freebie pizzas during the NFL season . . . a little like Schooner Tuna in the movie &#8220;<i>Mr. Mom,</i>&#8216;<i>we are in this together for the long haul.'&#8221;</i> What customer would not buy into this?</p>
<p>The Issue(s): From the annals of I made this;<i> &#8220;Everyone is looking for a way &#8216;</i>not<i>&#8216; to provide insurance for their employees. It is essentially a huge tax on all us business people,&#8221; </i>declares <a href="http://thinkprogress.org/health/2012/11/15/1197431/dennys-obamacare/?mobile=nc"><i>Denny&#8217;s RREMC Franchise Owner CEO John Metz</i></a><i> </i>on Fox News. To offset costs further, John adds; &#8220;<strong><i>he also will slash most of the </i></strong><strong><i>staff’s time to fewer than 30 hours per week</i></strong>&#8221; to start January 2014.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Talk about giving a long notice for plant closures to employees. What happens if franchise owner sidesteps the insurance provision of the PPACA and cuts hours to fewer than 30? John Padua of <i>Managed Care Matters </i>says the cost falls back on the US citizenry, employees, and customers of these restaurants. </p>
<p><strong>&#8220;<i>If companies do not provide insurance for low-paid workers, we taxpayers have to.</i></strong><i> That is the way Obamacare works; folks with incomes below 400% of the FPL can get subsidized coverage. If restaurants cut workers’ hours so as not to insure employees, all of us taxpayers get to pay for their health insurance. These companies are avoiding their responsibility and increasing our tax burden. </i><i><a href="http://www.joepaduda.com/2012/11/the-cost-obamacare-14-cents-per-pizza/">&#8220;The Cost of Obamacare -14 cents per pizza&#8221;</a></i><i></i></p>
<p>The Cost: Maggie Mahar raises the question in her <i>&#8220;Can They Afford It???&#8221;</i> post. Metz employs 1,200 associates at his Denny&#8217;s RREMC franchise. Taking the extreme case of all 1200 employees going into the state exchange and being subsidized up to 400% of FPL; by slashing everyone&#8217;s hours to 28, Metz avoids the $2,000 penalty (~$2.34 million in total) for those going into the state exchange.</p>
<p>The Price Increase: 5% surcharge to all meals in 40 Denny&#8217;s in Georgia, Florida and Virginia. (note: I wonder how that will appear on the bill?)</p>
<p>Checking The Math: The CBO (which forever appears to be anti-healthcare reform) found in a recent study, 2014 comprehensive healthcare insurance could be had at $3,400 for an employee up to 30 years of age and single. Understanding we are not talking about writing off Metz&#8217;s employee expenses from his corporate income tax yet and knowing the PPACA requires an employer to pay 65% of the employee&#8217;s healthcare insurance, the $3,400 per person (down from a projected $6,700 without the PPACA) now becomes $2,210 per person. </p>
<p>Denny&#8217;s franchise owner Metz is angry with Obama, the PPACA, and his employees. Granted, the example is as much an extreme as Metz&#8217;s knee jerk reactions and posturing; but, it points to the overall fallacy in the too-much-healthcare- cost is a drag on my business argument. Both of these entrepreneurs did take grief for their stances. Denny&#8217;s CEO John Miller did call john Metz to discuss his stance and John Schnatter has been called out in various blogs and is the subject of multiple boycotts.</p>
<p>Much of this sounds like sour grapes starting with SCOTUS affirming the PPACA and is carryover from the re-election of Barack Obama to the Presidency. Some have protested the validity of the PPACA claiming it was immoral to force business owners to pay for employee healthcare insurance. In an email exchange, John Paduca answers:</p>
<p><i>&#8220;In response to your query as to when it became an employers’ responsibility to provide health insurance, that would have occurred when PPACA was passed, signed into law, and upheld by the Supreme Court. Laws run this country, not morals. If &#8216;morals&#8217; did, we never would have invaded Iraq or water-boarded prisoners or interned Japanese Americans or overturned legitimate governments in Africa and Central America or supported the Shah of Iran. &#8216;Morals&#8217; are personal; laws are societal.&#8221;</i><br /><i><br /></i> Maybe it is just Republicans having to cancel their airline tickets to Boston for the celebration on November 7th which has placed both Johns in a bad mood. Or could it be pent up anger with the very people who elected Barack to The White House for a second term? You know, those 47 percenters who might make up the bulk of the restaurant workers. </p>
<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/raising-the-price-of-pizza-10-to-14-cents.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>New Report on Getting the Best Care</title>
		<link>./../../2012/09/new-report-on-getting-the-best-care.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/09/new-report-on-getting-the-best-care.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2012 13:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Health care costs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[run 75441]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/09/new-report-on-getting-the-best-care.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Run 75441 New Report on Getting the Best Care Both Matthew Yglesias at Slate and Sarah Kliff at WonkBlog and a host of other sites have posted some interesting results coming out of a recent study by the Institute of Medicine  Best Care at Lower Cost: The Path to Continuously Learning Health Care in [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Run 75441</p>
<p>New Report on Getting the Best Care</p>
<p>Both Matthew Yglesias at Slate and Sarah Kliff at WonkBlog and a host of other sites have posted some interesting results coming out of a recent study by the Institute of Medicine  <a href="http://iom.edu/~/media/Files/Report%20Files/2012/Best-Care/Best%20Care%20at%20Lower%20Cost_Recs.pdf">Best Care at Lower Cost: The Path to Continuously Learning Health Care in America</a>. </p>
<p>Unfortunately as a lowly and unpaid (99% of the time) blogger, I do not have access to the entire report. What I do have is a abstract of what the report is about and some of the charts placed on <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/ezra-klein/wp/2012/09/07/we-spend-750-billion-on-unnecessary-health-care-two-charts-explain-why/">Wonkblog</a>.</p>
<p>We spend $750 billion on unnecessary health care. Two charts explain why. This report documents much of the whys to a much needed Healthcare Reform in the numeric of it. Phillip Longman in his book  <i>The Best Care Anywhere</i>  touches upon a similar transition in the VA administration and the experiences of his and Timothy Noah&#8217;s wives in being treated for cancer. Unfortunately, the best named hospitals and the best insurance does not guarantee the best care. Too much is spent inefficiently on the wrong type of care.</p>
<p><a href="http://lh6.ggpht.com/-nmEYytaUnt4/UEyU4-02oYI/AAAAAAAABAQ/NZ5WB2Ry20o/s1600-h/clip_image002%25255B3%25255D.jpg"><img alt="clip_image002" border="0" src="http://lh5.ggpht.com/-gWO_1R8_LwQ/UEyU5MOIJII/AAAAAAAABAY/DhgNPBzveDo/clip_image002_thumb.jpg?imgmax=800" title="clip_image002"></a></p>
<p>The second series of chart is an accounting of how some of these expenditures are made within the system. Again, this is something which Phillip Longman touched upon with his book on the VA and how they overcame the inefficiencies. Sarah Kliff at Wonkblog calls it creating an environment in which it is easy to create waste. When healthcare and its associated industries were not the monsters in cost, no one paid attention to the cost, loss of efficiency, and the lack of quality outcome in treating patients. We spent for the services and not the outcome with the results being a higher cost.</p>
<p><a href="http://lh6.ggpht.com/-t6BCYKvXfgQ/UEyU5v2z9uI/AAAAAAAABAg/Ip6xXZHa_RM/s1600-h/clip_image004%25255B3%25255D.jpg"><img alt="clip_image004" border="0" height="150" src="http://lh5.ggpht.com/-WVkHKxG-csU/UEyU5_8NAGI/AAAAAAAABAo/P2jJ3KfoqJw/clip_image004_thumb.jpg?imgmax=800" title="clip_image004" width="500"></a></p>
<p>Constantly targeted within today&#8217;s healthcare system is the cost of treating the elderly. While it is true as we grow older, the costs of treating us increase due to our aging and failure to care for ourselves. Within the system it is easy to have increased waste as treatments and records may not be logged to computer leading to duplicate treatments and a lack of coordination amongst way to many doctors in treating patients. It has happened where a group of consulting doctors can be describing treatments when the oncologist knows there is little more to be done.</p>
<p>What does the IOM recommend? I will leave you with Sarah Kliff&#8217;s post on Wonk Blog to find out. <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/ezra-klein/wp/2012/09/07/we-spend-750-billion-on-unnecessary-health-care-two-charts-explain-why/"><i>What&#8217;s Possible for Healthcare</i></a></p>
<p>Getting back to today&#8217;s politics between Romney and Ryan vs Obama, would you want more of the same? More of today&#8217;s private market with its rising healthcare cost is precisely what is being advocated by Mitt Romney and Paul Ryan. More to come.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/09/new-report-on-getting-the-best-care.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Elephants are Still Thirsty</title>
		<link>./../../2012/08/the-elephants-are-still-thirsty.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/08/the-elephants-are-still-thirsty.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 31 Aug 2012 18:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[medicare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medicare costs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[run 75441]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/08/the-elephants-are-still-thirsty.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Run 75411 The Elephants are Still Thirsty In my earlier post on Carrying Water for Elephants I explained how the $716 billion in planned reductions to Medicare was calculated, who it impacted, and from where it originated. The $716 billion is far larger than the initial $449 billion first reported. In 2010, the CBO arrived [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Run 75411</p>
<p> The Elephants are Still Thirsty</p>
<p> In my earlier post on <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/08/medicare-cuts-what-is-fight-about.html">Carrying Water for Elephants</a> I explained how the $716 billion in planned reductions to Medicare was calculated, who it impacted, and from where it originated.</p>
<blockquote><p><i>The $716 billion is far larger than the initial $449 billion first reported. In 2010, the CBO arrived at an estimate of savings of ~$449 billion starting from 2012 onwards and covered 6- 7 years from when the bill takes full effect in 2014 to 2019. The second estimate of savings was the result of John Boehner&#8217;s request for a review of the costs and gains realized from the repeal the ACA in its entirety. The second review covered the period from 2014 to 2022 and resulted in the $716 billion.</i> &#8220;Medicare Cuts: What is the Fight About?&#8221; <a href="http://www.brookings.edu/blogs/up-front/posts/2012/08/15-medicare-cuts-galston">Brookings Institute</a></p></blockquote>
<p>Above the explanation of how the $716 billion calculated; I presented Ezra Klein&#8217;s pie chart explaining where the reductions were made. Not one of the reductions comes from reductions in Medicare benefits to recipients which as I also explained is denied the PPACA. In last night&#8217;s Republican Convention Paul Ryan again claimed the reductions to providers are actually cuts in benefits to Medicare recipients and the reductions are being used to fund the PPACA. Neither statement is true; but then, Paul Ryan is a Republican VP candidate who hopes to confuse the voters with supposition and conjecture. Paul should be made to explain what he will do with the reductions achieved from similar reductions he has proposed for Medicare . . . maybe more tax breaks for the 1 percenters???</p>
<p>There is no amount of water Paul Ryan or Mitt Romney can carry to quench the thirst of this elephant of misrepresentation.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/08/the-elephants-are-still-thirsty.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Medicare Cuts: What is the Fight About?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/08/medicare-cuts-what-is-the-fight-about.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/08/medicare-cuts-what-is-the-fight-about.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2012 01:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[ACA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cbo projections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[run 75441]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/08/medicare-cuts-what-is-the-fight-about.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Run75411 &#8220;Water For Elephants&#8221; &#8220;carrying water for elephants&#8221; is a phrase that means carrying a heavy load, much like carrying a secret that you can&#8217;t tell even someone you love wholeheartedly, just as in the end Jacob does for his wife.An elephant drinks 25-75 gallons of water a day far more than any man [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Run75411</p>
<p> &#8220;Water For Elephants&#8221;</p>
<p> &#8220;<i>carrying water for elephants&#8221; is a phrase that means carrying a heavy load, much like carrying a secret that you can&#8217;t tell even someone you love wholeheartedly, just as in the end Jacob does for his wife</i><br /><i>.</i><br /><i>An elephant drinks 25-75 gallons of water a day far more than any man would be able to carry at any given time. </i><a href="http://angela-michelle.hubpages.com/hub/Water-For-Elephants"><i>http://angela-michelle.hubpages.com/hub/Water-For-Elephants</i></a><i> &#8220;Water for Elephants&#8221; </i><i>Sometimes when you get older . . . things you think on and wish on start to seem real. And then you believe them, and before you know it they&#8217;re part of your history.&#8221;</i><br /><i><br /></i> Most recently former NY Lt. Governor Betsy McGaughey in the WSJ (August 8th) commented on the ACA in “<i>ObamaCares’s Phoney Deficit Reduction</i>” choosing to carry water for the Republican candidates Romney and Ryan with the hope she can convince voters that President Obama&#8217;s ACA will not reduce the cost of Medicare and instead will rob the Medicare TF. By her words alone, Ms. McGaughey cannot change the numeric of Medicare expected and occurring reduced growth and costs resulting from the passage of ACA. In her, Romney and Ryan&#8217;s mines the logic of how the robbery of benefits and the Medicare is all too real even when the proof of the opposite is self-evident. The three will have to do double time if they are to provide enough water to conflate the ACA to the public if in fact they are to make them believe the illusion.</p>
<p>Ms. McGaughey critiques CBO Director Elmendorf&#8217;s and the JCT&#8217;s analysis (letter to House Leader John Boehner) on the impact of repealing the ACA, what it means to the country in increased costs, and then conflates the cuts to the Advantage Program and other parts of Medicare as actual cuts in benefits to Medicare recipients. The ACA states Medicare benefits cannot be reduced for Medicare recipients. </p>
<p>As operated by commercial insurance companies, the Advantage Program intent was to provide competition to Medicare and separate from Medicare. As Betsy believes and everyone else imagines, private commercial insurance can provide similar benefits at a lower cost and more efficiently. Except the Advantage Program did not do so and has out spent Medicare by an average of $1000 or 7% to 18% (dependent on who you read) more and in total for similar Medicare benefits. </p>
<div><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-wlg41Jc0W4M/UDY_EFHZbHI/AAAAAAAAA-o/5q2gKenImug/s1600/haskell1.png" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="231" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-wlg41Jc0W4M/UDY_EFHZbHI/AAAAAAAAA-o/5q2gKenImug/s320/haskell1.png" width="320"></a></div>
<p>
<div></div>
<div>                                        Ezra Klein , “Romney’s right: Obamacare cuts Medicare by $716 billion. Here’s how.”  <br />                                  Note: HMO is health maintenance organization; PPO is preferred provider organization.<br />   <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/ezra-klein/wp/2012/08/14/romneys-right-obamacare-cuts-medicare-by-716-billion-heres-how/">http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/ezra-klein/wp/2012/08/14/romneys-right-obamacare-cuts-medicare-by-716-billion-heres-how/</a> </div>
<p>                   </p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>The very same CBO Director who wrote about the impact of repealing the ACA to House Leader John Boehner and the resulting increased costs was also a part of the CBO team which pounded the final nail into the &#8220;Hillarycare&#8221; coffin resulting in its demise in Congress. Healthcare then was 20% of the cost of what it is today. I doubt Director Elmendorf has lost any of his boldness since Clinton. So, who is right?</p>
<p>The best way to counter supposition and conjecture by Romney, Ryan, and Ms. McGaughey is to present detail about the cuts and to what they are related , the same as the actual cost of the Advantage program in relation to Medicare. The planned reduction in Medicare costs come from three areas, which also include the government sponsored Advantage program. </p>
<p>
<div><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-AZI2vM2YAQM/UDY-9CwM83I/AAAAAAAAA-g/YXJDPLHnllg/s1600/haskell.jpg" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="245" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-AZI2vM2YAQM/UDY-9CwM83I/AAAAAAAAA-g/YXJDPLHnllg/s320/haskell.jpg" width="320"></a></div>
<div>                                SOURCE: Medicare Payment Advisory Commission Report to Congress, March 2008.</div>
<div>                               &#8220;Medicare Advantage&#8221;; Kaiser Foundation http://www.kff.org/medicare </div>
<p>30.2% of the planned reduction in Medicare costs will come from the elimination of Advantage subsidies as I stated above. The ACA also applies the same rules to the Advantage insurance programs it applies to hospitals by tying reimbursement (or fees) to quality of outcomes instead of a fee for the number of services provided.</p>
<p>34.8% of the reduction in cost comes from revised calculations in the reimbursement of hospitals for provided services. Hospitals not only give up the pay-for-services cost model to embrace better quality outcomes for services cost model; but, they move to electronic record keeping (which proved to be cost effective with the VA, Longman &#8220;<i>Best Care Anywhere</i>&#8220;), and the bundling of payments eliminating multiple billings and forcing a split of the total compensation. Knowing the increase in patients coming from the addition of the uninsured, there is also the influx of an aging baby-boomer population, which also influenced hospitals to accept the changes.</p>
<p>35% of the reduction result from a combination of smaller cuts in extra funds ( ~5%) given to hospitals to cover the uninsured (not needed as more people will be covered), reductions in homecare providers (~8%), fraud reduction, etc..</p>
<p>The $716 billion is far larger than the initial $449 billion first reported. In 2010, the CBO arrived at an estimate of savings of ~$449 billion starting from 2012 onwards and covered 6- 7 years from when the bill takes full effect in 2014 to 2019. The second estimate of savings was the result of John Boehner&#8217;s request for a review of the costs and gains realized from the repeal the ACA in its entirety. The second review covered the period from 2014 to 2022 and resulted in the $716 billion. http://www.brookings.edu/blogs/up-front/posts/2012/08/15-medicare-cuts-galston &#8220;<i>Medicare Cuts: What is the Fight About?&#8221;</i><br /><i><br /></i> <i></i><br />And what of other things implied?</p>
<p>&#8211; Healthcare spending was 17.9% of GDP in 2010 and will rise to 19.6% in 2021. Neglected and a part of the article from which this snippet of CMS information was pulled is this: <i>&#8220;</i><i> Current projections also do not include potential drops in spending through health care delivery reforms, such as the accountable care organizations and medical homes being promoted by the health law.&#8221; </i>In other words, the author projections of $ and % are being made as if the ACA did not exist. The author of this particular article is an MBA and not an economist or a doctor. Quelle Surprise?</p>
<p>&#8211; &#8220;<i>Repeal also would reduce government spending, lower taxes, and undo the evisceration of Medicare; all good results.</i>&#8221; I guess it is still unclear how Medicare is to be eviscerated under the ACA when Obama will plow the results back into Medicare, and the CMS has lengthen the TF out to 2024-2029. Comparing this to Romney wishing to end Medicare and Ryan wanting to keep the very same reductions as the ACA and take the savings for tax breaks, who is eviscerating what?</p>
<p>Healthcare Costs have been decreasing for years? Maybe not so long and since 2009/2010 at the earliest?</p>
<div><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-ujMS2GY8Bjc/UDY_JmpJJ4I/AAAAAAAAA-w/fLBevXKyZk0/s1600/haskell2.jpg" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="189" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-ujMS2GY8Bjc/UDY_JmpJJ4I/AAAAAAAAA-w/fLBevXKyZk0/s320/haskell2.jpg" width="320"></a></div>
<p>Secretary of Heath Kathy Sebelius made the comment in an article that a family of 4 paid ~$6,000 for private insurance in 2000 and ~$12,000 for similar insurance in 2009. http://www.voxxi.com/kathleen-sebelius-affordable-care-act/ &#8220;<i>Public Needs To Get Their Facts Straight</i>&#8221; Part of this is due to increased administrative costs and much more is a reflection of increased healthcare care costs which insurance and Medicare reflects.</p>
<p>Medicare has had slower growth because it has taken the necessary actions to control much of the costs associated with healthcare through pilot programs, negotiations, etc. The results of its actions are clear in the S&#038;P Indices. The increase in enrollment of healthier patients over the last two recessions has contributed to the slow down; however, it is the ACA which started hospitals and doctors to begin to plan for full implementation and take the steps necessary to meet ACA goals for commercial insurance.</p>
<p>&#8220;<i>spending per enrollee slowed to 4.2% annually, as compared with 4.5% among private payers. After large increases in enrollment due to two recessions and the increasing numbers of Americans with disabilities are accounted for, growth of Medicaid spending per enrollee was relatively slow (less than 3% per… http://www.nationaljournal.com/healthcare/both-obama-and-romney-medicare-plans-fail-to-solve-the-cost-problem-20120816</i> &#8220;<i>Medicare and Medicaid Spending Trends and the Deficit Debate&#8221;</i><br /><i><br /></i> &#8211; And the Pink Cadillac Tax? The ACA does impose a tax on plans exceeding $27,000 and typically carried by executives in the rarefied levels of management. They can always shuck it off and go to one of the insurance exchanges for a cheaper plan with no tax. There is also an excise tax on plans with premiums exceeding $10,200 for individuals or $27,500 for a family tax Other taxes include Increase Medicare tax rate by .9% and impose added tax of 3.8% on unearned income for high-income taxpayers.</p>
<p>So what is the Fight About? It is about whether Romney/Ryan can eliminate Medicare and repeal the ACA, and keep the same proposals President Obama put in play for Medicare but using the savings from it elsewhere (tax breaks &#8211; think SS surplus) rather than within Medicare, as both are opposed to Obama plowing the savings back into Medicare. http://www.brookings.edu/blogs/up-front/posts/2012/08/15-medicare-cuts-galston &#8220;<i>Medicare Cuts: What is the Fight About?&#8221;</i><br /><i><br /></i> References:<i> </i></p>
<p><i></i><br /><i>Maggie Mahar Health Beat Blog</i><br /><i></i><br /><a href="http://www.cbpp.org/cms/index.cfm?fa=view&#038;id=3161">http://www.cbpp.org/cms/index.cfm?fa=view&#038;id=3161</a> Federal Government Will Pick Up Nearly All Costs of Health Reform’s Medicaid Expansion<br /><i></i><br />http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/ezra-klein/wp/2012/08/14/romneys-right-obamacare-cuts-medicare-by-716-billion-heres-how/ &#8221; Romney’s right: Obamacare cuts Medicare by $716 billion. Here’s how<br />http://www.drugchannels.net/2011/08/cms-bright-future-for-drug-spending-in.html CMS Bright Future for Spending . . .<br />http://www.cms.gov/apps/docs/ACA-Update-Implementing-Medicare-Costs-Savings.pdf<br />Affordable Care Act Update: Implementing Medicare Cost Savings<br />http://www.ajhp.org/content/69/5/405.abstract Projecting future drug expenditures—2012<br />http://www.brookings.edu/blogs/up-front/posts/2012/08/15-medicare-cuts-galston Medicare Cuts: What Is the Fight About?<br />http://www.kff.org/medicare/upload/2052-11.pdf Medicare Advantage<br />http://factcheck.org/2012/06/romney-obama-uphold-health-care-falsehoods/ Romney, Obama Uphold Health Care Falsehoods<br />http://www.voxxi.com/kathleen-sebelius-affordable-care-act/ Public Needs . . . <br />http://www.reuters.com/article/2012/06/12/us-usa-healthcare-spending-idUSBRE85B1DI20120612 Government forecasts modest health spending growth<br />http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052702303768104577462731719000346.html?mod=WSJ_hps_LEFTTopStories &#8221; Steep Rise in Health Costs Projected&#8221;<br />http://www.nejm.org/doi/pdf/10.1056/NEJMp1204899 &#8220;<i>Medicare and Medicaid Spending Trends and the Deficit Debate&#8221;</i><br />http://www.urban.org/UploadedPDF/412419-Containing-the-Growth-of-Spending-in-the-US-Health-System.pdf &#8220;<i>Containing the Growth of Spending in the U.S. Health System&#8221;</i></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/08/medicare-cuts-what-is-the-fight-about.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Repeal the ACA and Lower Costs for Citizens</title>
		<link>./../../2012/08/repeal-the-aca-and-lower-costs-for-citizens.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/08/repeal-the-aca-and-lower-costs-for-citizens.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Aug 2012 12:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Maggie Mahar]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medical expenses]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medical inflation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medical loss ratio]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[run 75441]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/08/repeal-the-aca-and-lower-costs-for-citizens.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Run75441 Repeal the ACA and Lower Costs for Citizens&#8230; Chicken Little, Courtesy of &#8220;EW.Com Entertainment Weekly&#8221;What presidential candidate Romney has vowed to repeal is showing more benefit than harm in driving down the cost of healthcare for individuals, groups, and commercial insurance. If repealed by Romney, the results could cost more than leaving it [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Run75441</p>
<p>Repeal the ACA and Lower Costs for Citizens&#8230;</p>
<p><a href="http://lh4.ggpht.com/-weEj05JSuSE/UCMcsAt0UGI/AAAAAAAAA7M/GliXXgbogbY/s1600-h/clip_image001%25255B3%25255D.jpg"><img alt="clip_image001" border="0" height="184" src="http://lh3.ggpht.com/-_ZCh4rvYJQM/UCMcsgiFTVI/AAAAAAAAA7U/Y6wM-70vatY/clip_image001_thumb.jpg?imgmax=800" title="clip_image001" width="244"></a><br /><a href="http://img2.timeinc.net/ew/dynamic/imgs/061212/16047__little_l.jpg">Chicken Little</a>, Courtesy of<i> &#8220;EW.Com Entertainment Weekly&#8221;</i><br /><i><br /></i>What presidential candidate Romney has vowed to repeal is showing more benefit than harm in driving down the cost of healthcare for individuals, groups, and commercial insurance. If repealed by Romney, the results could cost more than leaving it in place.</p>
<p>The most recent projections of the CBO and JCT reflect a decrease in the insurance cost coverage provision of the ACA over the 11-year period 2012-2022, a decrease of ~$86 billion from the initial projection of $1.252 trillion to $1.1.68 trillion. The projected decrease does not include other aspects of the ACA which in the aggregate will drive the reduction in healthcare cost further. http://www.cbo.gov/publication/43473 , July 24, 2012.</p>
<p>In the same report, the CBO addresses a letter from House Speaker Boehner asking about the benefits of repealing the ACA. Speaker of the House Boehner and he House Republicans have floated a bill which would repeal the ACA. In a separate CBO letter to John Boehner, the CBO estimates the repeal would reduce outlays by ~$890 billion and revenues by $1 trillion. Over the same period 2012 &#8211; 2021, the repeal would increase deficits by ~$109 billion. This estimate does not include the hidden costs of people not being insured if the ACA is repealed.</p>
<p>Over at Maggie Mahar&#8217;s Health Beat, Maggie touches upon the decreasing cost of healthcare <a href="http://www.blogger.com/%3Ci%3Ehttp://www.healthbeatblog.com/2012/08/breaking-the-curve-of-health-care-inflation/#comment-15066%3C/i%3E"><i>Breaking The Curve of Healthcare Inflation</i></a> and what the intent is of the ACA:<br /><i></i><br /><a name="more"></a><i><br /></i><i></i><br /><i>&#8220;- The ACA told insurers that they would no longer be able to shun the sick by refusing to cover those suffering from pre-existing conditions. They also won’t be allowed to cap how much they will pay out to a desperately ill patient over the course of a year –or a lifetime.&#8221;</i><br /><i><br /></i><i></i><br /><i>&#8220;- insurance companies selling policies to individuals and small companies will have to reimburse for all of the “essential benefits” outlined in the ACA–benefits that are not now covered by most policies and if they hope to stay in business, they will have to find a way to ”manage” the cost of care–but they won’t be able to do it by denying needed care.&#8221;</i><br /><i><br /></i><i></i><br /><i>&#8220;providers too will be under pressure. A growing number will no longer be paid &#8216;fees for service that rewarding them for &#8216;volume&#8217; or for &#8216;doing more.&#8217; Bonuses will depend on better outcomes, and keeping patients out of the hospital–which means doing a better job of managing chronic illnesses.&#8221;</i><br /><i><br /></i><i></i><br />But, what of the overall program results?</p>
<p>&#8211; &#8220;<em>From 2000 through 2009, Medicare’s outlays climbed by an average of 9.7 percent a year. By contrast, since the beginning of 2010,</em> Medicare spending has been rising<em> by less than 4 percent a year.</em>” It is now ~2.5%.</p>
<p>&#8211; &#8220;<i>Zeke Emanuel (an oncologist and former special adviser for health policy to White House OMB director Peter Orszag) to Maggie</i>: <i>providers are &#8216;<em>anticipating </em>the Affordable Care Act kicking in. They can’t wait until the end of 2013: They have to act today. Everywhere I go, &#8216;Emanuel, added, &#8216;medical schools and hospitals are asking me, How can we cut our costs by 10 to 15 percent?'&#8221;</i><br /><i><br /></i><i></i><br /><i>&#8211; &#8220;Rather than have Medicare set prices for lab tests and medical devices we should put all such purchases out for competitive bidding. &#8216;In 2011,&#8217; he (Peter Orzag) pointed out, &#8216;bidding reduced Medicare spending on wheel chairs and other equipment by more than 40 percent.'&#8221;</i><br /><i><br /></i><i></i><br />And for the average person, what are and what were the paybacks? Exploring Maggie&#8217;s article further, this chart can be found on the US Department of Health detailing the amounts of rebates in total, by state, and by Healthcare Insurance Company. <i>&#8220;The 80/20 Rule&#8221;</i> http://www.healthcare.gov/law/resources/reports/mlr-rebates06212012a.html</p>
<p><a href="http://lh6.ggpht.com/-n7JrTXwK0Sk/UCMctNzaVXI/AAAAAAAAA7c/y9wmNfzDLkw/s1600-h/clip_image003%25255B3%25255D.gif"><img alt="clip_image003" border="0" height="35" src="http://lh4.ggpht.com/-v-Lgt9ATHPA/UCMctbBDqAI/AAAAAAAAA7k/GKMUki1XL5M/clip_image003_thumb.gif?imgmax=800" title="clip_image003" width="240"></a></p>
<p>To take this a step further and look up your own insurance company, a pivot table at the Healthcare.gov site will allow you to look up insurance companies by state and what the average rebate is if called for from the application of the MLR. <a href="http://companyprofiles.healthcare.gov/RateReviewInfo"><i>Your Insurance Company and Cost of Coverage</i></a><br /><i><br /></i><i> </i>How successful the MLR<i> </i>has been can be measured by the impact of the MLR in measuring administrative costs of insurance companies against benefits, providing rebates to citizens, and giving states the ability to review requests for insurance increases through greater access to information. There are fewer double digit increases requested, more decreases in insurance rate requested, and reversals in rates at the state level due to greater information provided to states. <a href="http://www.healthcare.gov/law/resources/reports/rate-review03222012a.html"><i>2012 Progress Report: Health Reform is Opening the Insurance Market and Protecting Consumer</i></a><br /><i><br /></i><i></i><br />Early on, the ACA is having a tremendous impact on controlling and reducing costs providing better value for the money and reducing the inflationary impact of the overall healthcare industry.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/08/repeal-the-aca-and-lower-costs-for-citizens.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Second Verse, the Same as The First</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/second-verse-the-same-as-the-first.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/second-verse-the-same-as-the-first.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 16 Jul 2012 12:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2012 Presidential elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[boehner]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[run 75441]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/second-verse-the-same-as-the-first.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Run 75441“Second Verse, the Same as The First&#8221;The story never seems to change . . . When you say that the high income earners, the top 20 percent, pay 90 percent of the taxes, what should they pay, 99 percent? These are the people who have enough money to invest in businesses and to [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><i>by Run 75441</i><br /><i><br /></i><br />“Second Verse, the Same as The First&#8221;<br /><i><br /></i><br /><i>The story never seems to change . . .</i><br /><i><br /></i><br />
<blockquote>When you say that the high income earners, the top 20 percent, pay 90 percent of the taxes, what should they pay, 99 percent? These are the people who have enough money to invest in businesses and to create jobs.” The tax increase that Obama is proposing “falls directly on those job creators,” Senator Kyl said.&#8221; <i><a href="http://nbcpolitics.msnbc.msn.com/_news/2012/07/15/12753063-can-us-economy-tolerate-a-tax-increase-in-2013?lite">Can U.S. economy tolerate a tax increase in 2013?</a></i></p></blockquote>
<p>The vast majority of the upper quintile in Household Taxable Income does not make >$250,000 in AGI. Yet since 2001, the Republicans would have us believe that 3% of the taxpayers are the same as 20% of the taxpayers and that quintile makes > than $250,000. It is a lie and Senator Kyl needs to retract his blathering. </p>
<p>What is laughable about Senator Kyl statement is the Speaker of the House repudiates his statement here:<br />BOB SCHIEFFER: Do you quarrel with that figure? Is that a right figure or a wrong figure? </p>
<p>BOEHNER: Well, it may be three percent, but it&#8217;s half of small business income. Because, obviously, the top three percent have half of the gross income for those companies that we would term small businesses. And this is why you don&#8217;t want to punish these people at a time when you have a weak economy. <i></i><a href="http://voices.washingtonpost.com/plum-line/2010/09/boehner_concedes_only_three_pe.html"><i>Boehner concedes only three percent of small businesses affected by extending tax cuts.</i></a></p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>3% = 20%? Not likely and this is another example of the Republicans attempting to confuse the taxpayers. Even &#8220;<i>Joe- The-Plumber</i>&#8221; got it wrong; but then, why would a plumber have any greater knowledge then a Senator? At least there is an excuse for Joe.</p>
<p>So would taxing the upper 3% of the Taxable Household Incomes more hurt the economy? Not likely and it would correct the 2001/2003 skewing of taxes to this income group by President George Bush. What Bush did is without precedent in political history and is something not even Hoover attempted.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/second-verse-the-same-as-the-first.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Same as MA Healthcare Premiums, the ACA Premiums are too Costly . . .</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/the-same-as-ma-healthcare-premiums-the-aca-premiums-are-too-costly.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/the-same-as-ma-healthcare-premiums-the-aca-premiums-are-too-costly.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 11 Jul 2012 11:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[ACA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Incidental Economist]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[run 75441]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/the-same-as-ma-healthcare-premiums-the-aca-premiums-are-too-costly.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Run75441 The Same as MA Healthcare Premiums, the ACA Premiums are too Costly . . . Chicken Little, Courtesy of &#8220;EW.Com Entertainment Weekly&#8221;I have listened to many  stating the MA subsidies do not go far enough in alleviating the costs of healthcare for a family not covered by an Employer Subsidized Healthcare plan. Even [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Run75441</p>
<p>The Same as MA Healthcare Premiums, the ACA Premiums are too Costly . . .</p>
<p><a href="http://lh5.ggpht.com/-CPDv_9UZutA/T_rZb5ObVOI/AAAAAAAAA5w/eMCNEukUbzc/s1600-h/clip_image001%25255B3%25255D.jpg"><img alt="clip_image001" border="0" height="184" src="http://lh4.ggpht.com/-sqzLsgCq5SA/T_rZcYaQJSI/AAAAAAAAA54/P4NMJi6rzwo/clip_image001_thumb.jpg?imgmax=800" title="clip_image001" width="244"></a><br /><a href="http://img2.timeinc.net/ew/dynamic/imgs/061212/16047__little_l.jpg">Chicken Little</a>, Courtesy of<i> &#8220;EW.Com Entertainment Weekly&#8221;</i><br /><i><br /></i><br />I have listened to many  stating the MA subsidies do not go far enough in alleviating the costs of healthcare for a family not covered by an Employer Subsidized Healthcare plan. Even with my pointing out the subsidies in the ACA exceed that of the MA plan, there still has been quite a bit of doubt.</p>
<p>Maggie Mahar at the resurrected Health Beat Blog http://www.healthbeatblog.com/2012/07/what-will-the-supreme-courts-decision-mean-for-the-november-election-part-1/ <i></i>pointed to a new Kaiser Family Foundation subsidy calculator in her article as well as other informative points; &#8220;<i>What Will the Supreme Court Decision Mean In November?&#8221; </i>The ACA Premium Calculator is found here: <a href="http://healthreform.kff.org/Home/KHS/SubsidyCalculator.aspx?source=FS" target="_blank"><i>Healthcare Reform Subsidy Calculator.</i></a><br /><i></i><br /><a name="more"></a><i><br /></i><br />Using the KFF Calculator, a person can calculate what they will pay in premiums under the ACA in 2014. Further on down this post, there is a short discussion of the Mandate and a link to another KFF site to determine what the mandated penalty might be per year for an individual and a family. The last chart by &#8220;The Incidental Economist&#8221; touches upon the relative size of the Mandate in comparison to taxes historically. As a mandated penalty, Obamacare is a middle of the pack tax. </p>
<p>With the KFF calculator, assuming we are discussing Median Household Income, and making an addition assumption Household Median Income increases from the ~$51,000 in 2011 to ~$55,000 in 2013, this is what a family of 4 might pay in 2014:</p>
<p>&#8211; Income (family of 4) $55,000 (235% of Poverty)<br />&#8211; Policyholder Age: 45<br />&#8211; ESI: None Available<br />&#8211; Regional Cost Factor: Median<br />&#8211; Unsubsidized Healthcare Premium: $14,425<br />&#8211; Government Tax Credit: $10,110<br />&#8211; Out of Pocket Premium: $4,125<br />&#8211; 2014 Maximum Out of Pocket Expenses: $6,250</p>
<p>Mandate/Tax Penalty is huge? And what if an individual does not buy insurance from the state insurance exchanges; the individual would pay a Mandate Penalty in 2014 of $95/adult and $47.50 per child (or 1% of income, whichever is greater). In 2016, the mandate would be $695/adult and 50% for children (or 2.5% of income, whichever is greater). http://healthreform.kff.org/the-basics/Requirement-to-buy-coverage-flowchart.aspx <i>&#8220;The Requirement to Buy Healthcare Coverage&#8221; </i>For those who wish to argue Mandate versus Tax, please remember all laws are open to interpretation which does not change the initial intent of the Act passed by Congress.</p>
<p>ACA is the Biggest Tax Ever? It does not even come close to the tax Truman passed to cover WWII costs or even the Reagan Tax Increases of 1982. http://theincidentaleconomist.com/wordpress/obamacare-is-the-biggest-tax-increase-in-history-if-you-ignore-history/ Incidental Economist <i>&#8220;Obamacare is the Biggest Tax Ever, If You Ignore History&#8221;</i><br /><i><br /></i><br /><a href="http://lh6.ggpht.com/-cT38JaKQ4mI/T_rZcorpFxI/AAAAAAAAA6A/99MqShSW6HA/s1600-h/clip_image003%25255B3%25255D.jpg"><img alt="clip_image003" border="0" height="169" src="http://lh6.ggpht.com/-EEpuzxeEJBA/T_rZc21wnpI/AAAAAAAAA6I/pl6HsN8qyCg/clip_image003_thumb.jpg?imgmax=800" title="clip_image003" width="244"></a></p>
<p>Austin Frakt, The Incidental Economist,<a href="http://theincidentaleconomist.com/wordpress/obamacare-is-the-biggest-tax-increase-in-history-if-you-ignore-history/"><i>Obamacare is the biggest tax increase in history … if you ignore history</i></a></p>
<p>Maybe the sky is not falling with SCOTUS declaring the ACA is constitutional?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/the-same-as-ma-healthcare-premiums-the-aca-premiums-are-too-costly.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
