<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Yves Smith &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Innovation and production</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/innovation-and-production.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/innovation-and-production.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2013 13:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[global trade]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[global trade imbalances]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[production]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Yves Smith]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/innovation-and-production.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[ Yves Smith points to a MIT study on how much bigger the conversation should be than the political arguments of offshoring and outsourcing suggest.  And the complexities of applying &#8216;just in time&#8217; sorts of global production systems through a complicated supply chain. From that post is this excerpt: And a new report by MIT on innovation [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p> <a href="https://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766" target="_blank"></a><a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2013/03/as-dow-sprints-to-new-high-the-middle-class-and-manufacturing-languish.html" target="_blank">Yves Smith</a> points to a MIT study on how much bigger the conversation should be than the political arguments of offshoring and outsourcing suggest.  And the complexities of applying &#8216;just in time&#8217; sorts of global production systems through a complicated supply chain. </p>
<p>From that post is this excerpt:</p>
<p>And a <a href="http://web.mit.edu/press/images/documents/pie-report.pdf">new report</a> by MIT on innovation and production (hat tip Marcy Wheeler) has an almost desperate undertone. It starts by pointing out how the data understate how bad the competitive erosion is:<br />
<blockquote>One of the key danger points identified in these reports is the declining weight of the U.S. in the global economy. Even though the U.S. share of world manufactured output has held fairly steady over the past decade, economists have pointed out that this reflects good results in only a few industrial sectors. And even in those sectors, what appear to be productivity gains may be the result of underestimating the value of imported components. A close look at the composition of a worsening trade deficit shows that even in high-tech sectors the U.S. has a deteriorating picture. While the output of U.S. high tech manufacturing is still the largest in the world and accounted for $390 billion of global value added in high-tech manufacturing in 2010, U.S. share of this world market has been declining, from 34 percent in 1998 to 28 percent in 2010, as other countries made big strides ahead into this market segment.<br />Jobs are another huge concern. The great spike in unemployment over the past five years was disproportionately due to loss of manufacturing jobs. And as the economy revived, such jobs were very slow to return. In fact it is clear that many of them never will.</p></blockquote>
<p>It makes clear how far hollowing out has gone in the manufacturing sector, and how the economy has lost so many components critical to innovation that it isn’t clear how to restore them. The researchers went beyond the venture capital darlings to find what it called “Main Street Manufacturers.” It found they were at a serious disadvantage due to the lack of firms with complimentary know-how in their ecosystem. After quoting the experience of one firm, the authors noted:</p>
<p>Read more at <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2013/03/as-dow-sprints-to-new-high-the-middle-class-and-manufacturing-languish.html#ljmE5kup6AHLQY2B.99">Naked Capitalism</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/innovation-and-production.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>New Ruling on Mortgage Putbacks a Potential Huge Win for Banks</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/new-ruling-on-mortgage-putbacks-a-potential-huge-win-for-banks.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/new-ruling-on-mortgage-putbacks-a-potential-huge-win-for-banks.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Jan 2013 13:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[mortgage regulation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Yves Smith]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/new-ruling-on-mortgage-putbacks-a-potential-huge-win-for-banks.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Yves Smith discusses New Ruling on Mortgage Putbacks a Potential Huge Win for Banks Even though, for most people, the housing crisis is a thing of the past, the fight over who should bear the cost of sloppy and openly fraudulent mortgage origination and securities sales continues to grind through the courts. We’ve written now [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Yves Smith discusses <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2013/01/new-ruling-on-mortgage-putbacks-a-potential-huge-win-for-banks.html">New Ruling on Mortgage Putbacks a Potential Huge Win for Banks</a></p>
<blockquote><p>Even though, for most people, the housing crisis is a thing of the past, the fight over who should bear the cost of sloppy and openly fraudulent mortgage origination and securities sales continues to grind through the courts.</p>
<p>We’ve written now and again about mortgage putback cases, which are also called representation and warranty, or “rep and warranty” litigation. Investors in mortgage-backed securities were not quite as dumb as the crisis aftermath had made them look. The sponsors of the securitizations made promises in the offering documents (called representations and warranties) about the quality of the loans. It turns out they lied.</p>
<p>Normally, when a loan is found to be worse than the sponsors promised, the remedy is a putback. The originator is required to take the bad loan back and replace it, either with cash or buy replacing it with a loan that was of the quality that the investors were promised. However, the mortgage securitizations put hurdles in front of the investors: it took a minimum level of investors (usually 25%) to demand putbacks and it was hard for any investor to know who else had bought a particular deal. Even then, the trustee (who was the party who was responsible for putting back the loan) almost always ignored and fought investor putback requests. They have ongoing relationships with the sponsors, so they don’t want to ruffle big meal tickets, plus the margins for acting as a mortgage securitization trustee are thin, so they don’t lift a finger unless they absolutely have to&#8230;</p></blockquote>
<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/new-ruling-on-mortgage-putbacks-a-potential-huge-win-for-banks.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Is the $8.5 billion Foreclose and Fraud Settlement Enough of a Penalty?</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/is-the-8-5-billion-foreclose-and-fraud-settlement-enough-of-a-penalty.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/is-the-8-5-billion-foreclose-and-fraud-settlement-enough-of-a-penalty.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 09 Jan 2013 05:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[OCC]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SCOTUS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Yves Smith]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/is-the-8-5-billion-foreclose-and-fraud-settlement-enough-of-a-penalty.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by run75411 Update: Besides not prosecuting particulars who promulgated much of 2008, what makes this settlement bad is letting banks off the hook: &#8220;In the settlement announced Monday between the Federal Reserve, the Comptroller of the Currency and ten of the largest banks and other mortgage providers, the government gives up the right to prosecute banks [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by run75411</p>
<p>Update: Besides not prosecuting particulars who promulgated much of 2008, what makes this settlement bad is letting banks off the hook:</p>
<p><em>&#8220;In the settlement announced Monday between the Federal Reserve, the Comptroller of the Currency and ten of the largest banks and other mortgage providers, the government gives up the right to prosecute banks for past wrongful foreclosures. In exchange, the banks part with another $8.5 billion, of which $5.2 billion is for loan modifications and $3.3 billion is for people whose mortgages were wrongfully foreclosed.</em><br /><em></em> <br /><em>It’s a pittance. With 3.8 million homeowners covered by the settlement, that works out to less than $2,000 per homeowner.&#8221; </em><a href="http://prospect.org/article/banks-win-again" target="_blank"><em>http://prospect.org/article/banks-win-again</em></a><em> &#8220;</em>The Banks Win Again&#8221;</p>
<p>$2,000 per homeowner in many cases might be two months of a mortgage payment. The settlement hardly qualifies as major.<br /> Is the $8.5 billion Foreclose and Fraud Settlement Enough of a Penalty?</p>
<p> Are The Federal Reserve and the OCC acting in good faith in letting banks off the hook for their past predatory lending practices? Yves Smith at Naked Capitalism labels it a sellout at the expense of mortgage holders: <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2013/01/8-5-billion-foreclosure-fraud-settlement-yet-another-loss-for-homeowners-touted-as-a-victory.html#comment-1010312" target="_blank">$8.5 billion Foreclosure Fraud Settlement: Yet Another Loss for Homeowners Touted as a Victory</a>.</p>
<p>When compared to TARP and other programs created to save TBTF and STBB (soon to be banks) plus the trillions pumped into the economy as a result the failures of banks and Wall Street, the $8.5 billion does seem paltry in comparison. Rather than taking the lead and closely auditing the review of wrongfully foreclosed mortgages and past practices, the OCC once again lets banks off the hook by giving them the ability to independently review both issues. Haven&#8217;t we come this way before? Banks will not do it or will be selective in what they choose to disclose. Besides the history of banks failing to act in good faith, there is also a history of government agencies and branches failure to provide consumer protection. </p>
<p>It appears the dogs causing much of this debacle are kicking back their hind legs in an attempt to hide the droppings left behind because of their failures. Frankly, it is amazing the OCC is still in that mode of protecting thrifts and national banks, which caused much of the issue in the last decade after they were identified as the culprits who failed to regulate. For those who may not be familiar with the OCC&#8217;s lack of supervision, I would offer Columbia&#8217;s &#8220;The Audit&#8221; as a refresher: <a href="http://www.cjr.org/the_audit/sleeping_watchdogs.php?page=all">Let Sleeping Dogs Lie</a>.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>To finalize and give strength to the OCC limited supervision (2007) of National banks and thrifts, SCOTUS over ruled states attempting to fill the void in regulating predatory bank lending practices. In a 5-3 ruling, SCOTUS tied the hands of states which attempted to regulate banks supervised by OCC. Michigan was joined by numerous states in an effort to control predatory bank lending.( <a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=newsarchive&#038;sid=ahTRNjftAoOU" target="_blank">Banks Win Shield From State Regulation at High Court</a>)</p>
<p>A mixed bag of conservative and liberal justices ruled on <i>Watters vs Wachovia Bank</i> in the same manner as over turning State Usury Laws in Marquette Nat. Bank of Minneapolis v. First of Omaha Service Corp in 1978. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marquette_Nat._Bank_of_Minneapolis_v._First_of_Omaha_Service_Corp" target="_blank">SCOTUS cited the National Banking Act</a> to give the OCC the capability to regulate national banks and thrifts over turn state regulations. . The irony is Congress moving quickly to repeal Glass Steagall and change the National Banking Act to allow Citibank to merge with Travelers Insurance; but, Congress saw no need to act to allow states to continue the regulation of national banks. Both actions by SCOTUS and the failure of Congress to pass new legislation have contributed much to the issues we have today. Always look to the money . . .</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/is-the-8-5-billion-foreclose-and-fraud-settlement-enough-of-a-penalty.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Bruce Bartlett and Yves Smith on Overhyping the Fiscal Cliff</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/bruce-bartlett-and-yves-smith-on-overhyping-the-fiscal-cliff.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/bruce-bartlett-and-yves-smith-on-overhyping-the-fiscal-cliff.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 21 Dec 2012 18:36:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Bruce Bartlett]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cliff economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fiscal cliff]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Yves Smith]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/bruce-bartlett-and-yves-smith-on-overhyping-the-fiscal-cliff.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This video featuring Bruce Bartlett and Yves Smith on Overhyping the Fiscal Cliff is worth watching. Independent political and economic analysts Bruce Bartlett and Yves Smith join Bill in a discussion that&#8217;s become as rare as it is necessary &#8212; why are Washington insiders talking about the deficit crisis and not the jobs crisis? Bartlett, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This video featuring <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766" target="_blank">Bruce Bartlett and Yves Smith on Overhyping the Fiscal Cliff</a> is worth watching.</p>
<blockquote><p>Independent political and economic analysts Bruce Bartlett and Yves Smith join Bill in a discussion that&#8217;s become as rare as it is necessary &#8212; why are Washington insiders talking about the deficit crisis and not the jobs crisis? Bartlett, former advisor to Presidents Ronald Reagan and George H. W. Bush, got into hot water with fellow conservatives when he aired concerns about the direction of their ideology and wrote critically of the second George Bush. His most recent book is The Benefit and The Burden: Tax Reform &#8212; Why We Need It, and What It Will Take. Yves Smith, who spent more than 25 years in the financial services industry, is the founder and editor of the popular blog Naked Capitalism, and runs a successful management consulting firm. Published on Dec 14, 2012</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/bruce-bartlett-and-yves-smith-on-overhyping-the-fiscal-cliff.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Systematic document forgery and fabrication</title>
		<link>./../../2012/11/systematic-document-forgery-and-fabrication.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/11/systematic-document-forgery-and-fabrication.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2012 14:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dept. of Justice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MERS issues]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Yves Smith]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/11/systematic-document-forgery-and-fabrication.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Yves Smith at continues to point us in the direction of property ownership and the fallout from the widespread disregard of law in establishing title to property in her post Systematic document forgery and fabrication at Naked Capitalism: The Department of Justice and the state of Missouri have each announced criminal plea bargains with one [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/11/justice-in-america-systematic-document-forgery-and-fabrication-yields-one-criminal-plea-bargain.html">Yves Smith</a> at continues to point us in the direction of property ownership and the fallout from the widespread disregard of law in establishing title to property in her post <i>Systematic document forgery and fabrication</i> at <i>Naked Capitalism</i>:</div>
<p>
<blockquote>The Department of Justice and the state of Missouri have each announced criminal plea bargains with one Lorraine Brown, former chief executive of DocX, the Lender Processing subsidiary best known for its <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2010/10/4closurefraud-posts-docx-mortgage-document-fabrication-price-sheet.html">price sheet for fabricating the mortgage documents</a> a servicer, or frankly, anyone would need to claim they had standing to foreclose on your home. Funny how that particular DocX product was mentioned no where in the plea deals.<br /><strong>…</strong></p>
<p>Brown admitted guilt to perpetrating a six-year scheme, from 2003 to 2009 to forge and falsify over a million signatures, including now-infamous practices such as “surrogate signing”, in which other employees, typically temps, would forge the signatures of robosigners. The federal penalties are up to five years in prison plus $250,000 in fines; the Missouri penalties re two to three years in prison.</p></blockquote>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />
<blockquote>Several things are striking about this deal. First is that it appears that the Missouri suit against Brown goaded the Feds to join. It’s hardly unheard of for state regulators to embarrass their Federal counterparts into action, and the DoJ probably could not afford to sit out a successful prosecution on its beat, particularly after all the noise the Obama Administration has made about its new, improved anti mortgage fraud efforts. But that makes the second item more striking: how the “statement of facts” presents Brown as deceiving Lender Processing Services about her illegal actions. Brown is thus a rogue executive whose misdeeds presumably don’t have bigger implications for LPS or the industry. It’s nauseating to see the filings take that position and contain statements like this:<br />When hiring DocX to sign documents, servicers typically issued special corporate resolutions delegating document execution authority to specific, authorized, and trained personnel at DocX. The DocX employees who were given express signing authority from DocX’s clients and who, as represented by Brown, were purportedly trained to ensure that the clients’ documents were properly created, signed, and notarized were called “Authorized Signers.” These documents were then generally recorded by DocX with the appropriate local property recorders’ offices throughout the country.<br />Read more at <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/11/justice-in-america-systematic-document-forgery-and-fabrication-yields-one-criminal-plea-bargain.html#KsHfMdUvXWFQf1X3.99">Naked Capitalism</a></p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/11/systematic-document-forgery-and-fabrication.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The CBO Wants to Discuss Healthcare and the Deficit?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/11/the-cbo-wants-to-discuss-healthcare-and-the-deficit.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/11/the-cbo-wants-to-discuss-healthcare-and-the-deficit.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2012 14:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[CBO]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cbo projections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health care costs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health care reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Yves Smith]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/11/the-cbo-wants-to-discuss-healthcare-and-the-deficit.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The CBO Wants to Discuss Healthcare and the Deficit?(from run75411) Someone struck a nerve, &#8220;The Lady Doth Protest Too Much: CBO Director Asks for A Chat . . .&#8221;. Yves Smith at Naked Capitalism received an interesting email after a voice mail from the Associate Director of Communications for the CBO: Greetings, Susan.I am following [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The CBO Wants to Discuss Healthcare and the Deficit?<br />(from run75411)</p>
<p>Someone struck a nerve, <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/11/the-lady-doth-protest-too-much-cbo-director-asks-for-a-chat-regarding-our-post-on-their-questionable-health-cost-increase-model.html">&#8220;The Lady Doth Protest Too Much: CBO Director Asks for A Chat . . .&#8221;</a>. Yves Smith at Naked Capitalism received an interesting email after a voice mail from the Associate Director of Communications for the CBO:<br /><i><br /></i> <i>Greetings, Susan.</i><br /><i></i><br /><i>I am following up on my voicemail to see if we can arrange a time either today or sometime this week for you to speak with our director, Doug Elmendorf. He wanted to speak with you about your blog post </i><a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/11/fed-budgetary-experts-demolish-cbo-health-cost-model-the-lynchpin-of-budget-hysteria.html">&#8220;Fed Budgetary Experts Demolish CBO Health Models, the Lynch Pin of Budget Hysteria&#8221;</a><i> that appeared Sunday on Naked Capitalism regarding CBO.</i><br /><i></i><br /><i>I am copying Brianne Hutchinson, Doug’s executive assistant, who will work with you to find a convenient time for the call. You can reach Brianne by e-mail or directly at: 202-226-2700.</i><br /><i>We look forward to hearing back from you at your convenience.</i><br /><i></i><br /><i>Kind regards,</i><br /><i>Deborah</i><br /><i>Deborah Kilroe     <br />Associate Director for Communications      <br />Congressional Budget Office      <br />2nd and D Streets, SW      <br />Washington, DC 20515</i><br /><i></i><br />Recently, Dan posted some of my earlier conversation with Yves and other participants on her post&#8217;s thread <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/11/yves-smith-at-naked-capitalism-brings.html">&#8220;Healthcare Spending Growth in the US&#8221;</a> at Naked Capitalism . Yves&#8217;s post pointed to a recent paper completed by Glen Follette and Louise Sheiner examining and challenging the CBO analysis of healthcare costs as a percentage of GDP <a href="http://www.bancaditalia.it/studiricerche/convegni/atti/fiscal_sustainability/session_3/Follette%20Sheiner.pdf">An Examination of Health-Spending Growth in the US</a>. Simplified, what the study is found Healthcare growth as a percentage of GDP is sustainable at 1% which is precisely what Obama and even Romney used in their limiting factor for healthcare costs.</p>
<p>Read more at   <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/11/yves-smith-at-naked-capitalism-brings.html" target="_blank">Health spending growth in the US</a>  at <i>Angry Bear</i>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/11/the-cbo-wants-to-discuss-healthcare-and-the-deficit.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Yves Smith on Wall Street ethics</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/yves-smith-on-wall-street-ethics.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/yves-smith-on-wall-street-ethics.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Oct 2012 10:43:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Wall Street ethics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Yves Smith]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/yves-smith-on-wall-street-ethics.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[You can&#8217;t say Wall Street has no ethics&#8230;but you can say what kind:]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>You can&#8217;t say Wall Street has no ethics&#8230;but you can say what kind:</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/yves-smith-on-wall-street-ethics.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Project S.H.A.M.E. on Megan McArdle&#8230;</title>
		<link>./../../2012/09/project-s-h-a-m-e-on-megan-mcardle.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/09/project-s-h-a-m-e-on-megan-mcardle.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2012 17:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Megan McArdle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Yves Smith]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/09/project-s-h-a-m-e-on-megan-mcardle.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Angry Bear has had a history of disagreement with Megan McArdle via her Atlantic magazine posts (starting in 2007), at one point being called Mike and his merry madmen in print by Megan McArdle (in exasperation?). Still. the madmen included Mike, Dan Crawford, Spencer England, Ken Houghton, Robert Waldmann, and other notables brought in to [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Angry Bear has had a history of disagreement with Megan McArdle via her Atlantic magazine posts (starting in 2007), at one point being called <i>Mike and his merry madmen</i> in print by Megan McArdle (in exasperation?).  Still. the madmen included Mike, Dan Crawford, Spencer England, Ken Houghton, Robert Waldmann, and other notables brought in to help.  I will have a history up later when I can sort them out.  </p>
<p>It is with feeling some real vindication publicly when I saw <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/09/project-s-h-a-m-e-on-megan-mcardle-portrait-of-a-taxpayer-subsidized-libertarian.html" target="_blank">Yves Smith</a> post an entire column from <a href="http://shameproject.com/" target="_blank">Project Shame</a> on Megan McArdle well worth reading.  It begins:<br />
<blockquote>Megan McArdle is a Koch-trained conservative activist working as a business journalist and pundit. She earned her MBA from the University of Chicago, received journalism training at the Kochs’ flagship libertarian think-tank, the Institute for Humane Studies, and has used her position at The Atlantic and, most recently, Newsweek/The Daily Beast, to run cover for and promote Koch interests and the Republican Party agenda. In early 2009, a GOP outfit backed by the Kochs hailed McArdle for her “leadership role in … re-branding the Republican party.” McArdle continues to conceal the extent of her deeply conflicted relationships with the Koch influence-peddling machine.</p></blockquote>
<p>Read more at <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/09/project-s-h-a-m-e-on-megan-mcardle-portrait-of-a-taxpayer-subsidized-libertarian.html#VokgGsGRrcmriKJU.99" target="_blank">Naked Capitalism</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/09/project-s-h-a-m-e-on-megan-mcardle.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Wall Street Rule&#8230;Has Someone Noticed the IRS isn’t Enforcing Tax Laws in the Mortgage-Industrial Complex?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/09/wall-street-rule-has-someone-noticed-the-irs-isnt-enforcing-tax-laws-in-the-mortgage-industrial-complex.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/09/wall-street-rule-has-someone-noticed-the-irs-isnt-enforcing-tax-laws-in-the-mortgage-industrial-complex.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Sep 2012 13:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Wall Street Rule]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Yves Smith]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/09/wall-street-rule-has-someone-noticed-the-irs-isnt-enforcing-tax-laws-in-the-mortgage-industrial-complex.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Yves Smith continues her look at the Wall Street Rule: Reader Deontos highlighted a post on Reuters by two Brooklyn Law School professors, Bradley Borden and David Reiss, on a subject near and dear to our hearts, the abject failure of the IRS to take interest in widespread, probably pervasive, violations of REMIC, the part [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/09/mirable-dictu-has-someone-noticed-the-irs-isnt-enforcing-tax-laws-Tax%20Lin-the-mortgage-industrial-complex.html">Yves Smith</a> continues her look at the Wall Street Rule:<br />
<blockquote>Reader Deontos highlighted <a href="http://newsandinsight.thomsonreuters.com/New_York/Insight/2012/09_-_September/Wall_Street_Rules_Applied_to_REMIC_Classification/">a post on Reuters</a> by two Brooklyn Law School professors, Bradley Borden and David Reiss, on a subject near and dear to our hearts, the abject failure of the IRS to take interest in widespread, probably pervasive, violations of REMIC, the part of the Federal tax code that governs mortgage securitizations.
<p>The reason this matters is that this situation belies on of the Administration’s pet claims, that its hands were tied as far as addressing the foreclosure mess was concerned because it had no leverage over servicers. As we’ll discuss, in fact the Administration has a nuclear weapon in its hands that it is simply refusing to use.<br />The reason the Borden and Reiss piece is noteworthy is it’s the first time I’m aware of that experts have chosen to comment at length on the REMIC issue, suggest that there is likely a BIG problem here, and politely point out that the REMICs may have committed fraud, which would allow the statute of limitations to remain open indefinitely, giving the IRS plenty of time to investigate and litigate.</p>
<p>However, I suspect the professors have heard that the IRS is choosing to do nothing, as their quote of Lee Shepard at the top of their piece suggests:</p>
<p>They take aggressive positions, and they figure that if enough of them take an aggressive position, and there’s billions of dollars at stake, then the IRS is kind of estopped from arguing with them because so much would blow up. And that is called the Wall Street Rule. That is literally the nickname for it.</p>
<p>We suspect they know full well the Wall Street Rule is being applied here.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Read more at  <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/09/mirable-dictu-has-someone-noticed-the-irs-isnt-enforcing-tax-laws-in-the-mortgage-industrial-complex.html#umqqchtpkCfxUg5M.99">Naked Capitalism</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/09/wall-street-rule-has-someone-noticed-the-irs-isnt-enforcing-tax-laws-in-the-mortgage-industrial-complex.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Wall Street’s War Against the Cities:</title>
		<link>./../../2012/09/wall-streets-war-against-the-cities.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/09/wall-streets-war-against-the-cities.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 03 Sep 2012 10:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[municipal bonds]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[municipal finance]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Yves Smith]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/09/wall-streets-war-against-the-cities.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[From Naked Capitalism: Wall Street’s War Against the Cities: Why Bondholders Can’t – and Shouldn’t – be Paid By Michael Hudson, a research professor of Economics at University of Missouri, Kansas City, a research associate at the Levy Economics Institute of Bard College, and author of “The Bubble and Beyond,” which is available on Amazon. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>From Naked Capitalism:</p>
<p><a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/08/wall-streets-war-against-the-cities-why-bondholders-cant-and-shouldnt-be-paid.html">Wall Street’s War Against the Cities: Why Bondholders Can’t – and Shouldn’t – be Paid</a></p>
<p><strong><em>By Michael Hudson, a research professor of Economics at University of Missouri, Kansas City, a research associate at the Levy Economics Institute of Bard College, and author of “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/THE-BUBBLE-BEYOND-Michael-Hudson/dp/3981484207">The Bubble and Beyond</a>,” which is available on Amazon.</em></strong><br /><strong><em><br /></em></strong> The pace of Wall Street’s war against the 99% is quickening in preparation for the kill. Having demonized public employees for being scheduled to receive pensions on their lifetime employment service, bondholders are insisting on getting the money instead. It is the same austerity philosophy that has been forced on Greece and Spain – and the same that is prompting President Obama and Mitt Romney to urge scaling back Social <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/08/#">Security</a> and Medicare.</p>
<p>Unlike the U.S. federal government, most states and cities have constitutions that prevent them from running budget deficits. This means that when they cut property taxes, they either must borrow from the wealthy, or cut back employment and public services. </p>
<p>For many years they borrowed, paying tax-exempt interest to wealthy bondholders. But carrying charges on these have mounted to a point where they now look risky as the economy sinks into debt deflation. Cities are defaulting from California to Alabama. They cannot reverse course and restore taxes on property owners without causing more mortgage defaults and abandonments. Something has to give – so cities are scaling back public spending, downsizing their school systems and police forces, and selling off their assets to pay bondholders. </p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>This has become the main cause of America’s rising unemployment, helping drive down consumer demand in a Keynesian nightmare. Less obvious are the devastating cuts occurring in health care, job training and other services, while tuition rates for public colleges and “participation fees” at high schools are soaring. School systems are crumbling like our roads as teachers are jettisoned on a scale not seen since the Great Depression.</p>
<p>Yet <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/08/#">Wall Street<img src="http://images.intellitxt.com/ast/adTypes/mag-glass_10x10.gif"></a> strategists view this state and local budget squeeze as a godsend. As Rahm Emanuel has put matters, a crisis is too good an opportunity to waste – and the fiscal crisis gives creditors financial leverage to push through anti-labor policies and privatization grabs. The ground is being prepared for a neoliberal “cure”: cutting back pensions and health care, defaulting on pension promises to labor, and selling off the public sector, letting the new proprietors to put up tollbooths on everything from roads to schools. The new term of the moment is “rent extraction.”</p>
<p>So having caused the fiscal crisis, the legacy of decades of property tax cuts financed by going deeper into debt are now to be paid for by leasing or selling off public assets. Chicago has leased its Skyway for 99 years to toll-collectors, and its parking meters for 75 years. Mayor Emanuel has hired J.P.Morgan Asset Management to give “advice” on how to sell privatizers the right to charge user fees for previously free or subsidized public services. It is the modern American equivalent of England’s Enclosure Movements of the 16th to 18th century.</p>
<p>Read more at <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/08/wall-streets-war-against-the-cities-why-bondholders-cant-and-shouldnt-be-paid.html#QQKtocbXrmYiJq27.99">Naked Capitalism</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/09/wall-streets-war-against-the-cities.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
