<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>super pacs &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Super pacs disclosures</title>
		<link>./../../2012/02/super-pacs-disclosures.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/02/super-pacs-disclosures.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2012 15:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Citizens United]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[super pacs]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/02/super-pacs-disclosures.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[OMB Watch notes some figures on Super Pac spending: Outside groups are spending nearly 1,300 percent more on broadcast advertising for the 2012 election than they did in 2008, according to an analysis released on Jan. 30. This is the clearest demonstration yet that Citizens United v. Federal Election Commission has fundamentally rewritten the rules [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.ombwatch.org/node/11972/" target="_blank">OMB Watch</a> notes some figures on Super Pac spending:<br />
<blockquote>Outside groups are spending nearly 1,300 percent more on broadcast advertising for the 2012 election than they did in 2008, according to an <a href="http://mediaproject.wesleyan.edu/2012/01/30/group-involvement-skyrockets/">analysis</a> released on Jan. 30. This is the clearest demonstration yet that <a href="http://www.law.cornell.edu/supct/html/08-205.ZS.html"><i>Citizens United v. Federal Election Commission</i></a> has fundamentally rewritten the rules for political spending.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />The Jan. 31 disclosure reports filed by independent expenditure-only political action committees – typically referred to as “super PACs” – contained few surprises: super PACs have been raising, and spending, dizzying amounts of money in an attempt to influence the 2012 elections. In fact, these more than 300 &#8220;independent&#8221; (that is, &#8220;not coordinated&#8221; with a candidate or political party) groups have accounted for more than 40 percent of all the broadcast ads aired during the Republican presidential primaries, as compared to only three percent of the 2008 ads.</p>
<p>While candidates are vying to attract the support of a broad swath of voters, the super PACs endorsing them are funded almost entirely by very few, very wealthy donors. For example, more than 80 percent of the $17.9 million dollars collected by the super PAC supporting (but not connected to or coordinated with) Mitt Romney&#8217;s campaign came via six-figure contributions. Five other super PACs supporting Newt Gingrich, Ron Paul, Rick Santorum, Rick Perry, and Jon Huntsman <a href="http://tpmmuckraker.talkingpointsmemo.com/2012/02/the_100k_club_presidential_super_pacs_almost_entirely_funded_by_six_figure_contributions.php?ref=fpblg">showed a similar pattern</a>. Winning Our Future, a pro-Gingrich super PAC, received $10 million from just one couple.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/02/super-pacs-disclosures.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Secret Money is Shifting to 501c4s</title>
		<link>./../../2012/02/the-secret-money-is-shifting-to-501c4s.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/02/the-secret-money-is-shifting-to-501c4s.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2012 12:36:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2012 Presidential elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[campaign financing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[super pacs]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/02/the-secret-money-is-shifting-to-501c4s.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Rick Hasen at Election Law Blog instructs us on super pacs and 501c4s: These days, I probably spend more time speaking to reporters (from as far away as Brazil and Italy) about Super PACs than about any other election law subject. There is a lot of misinformation floating out there about what Super PACs are, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://electionlawblog.org/?p=28973" target="_blank">Rick Hasen at Election Law Blog</a> instructs us on super pacs and 501c4s:<br />
<blockquote>These days, I probably spend more time speaking to reporters (from as far away as Brazil and Italy) about Super PACs than about any other election law subject.  There is a lot of misinformation floating out there about what Super PACs are, where they came from, the relationship to Citizens United, and the ability of super PACs to coordinate with candidates without running afoul of the FEC disclosure rules.  For those looking for basic information from what I’ve written, I point reporters to my <a href="http://www.cnn.com/2012/01/09/opinion/hasen-super-pacs/index.html?eref=rss_topstories&#038;utm_source=feedburner&#038;utm_medium=feed&#038;utm_campaign=Feed%3A%20rss%2Fcnn_topstories%20%28RSS%3A%20Top%20Stories%29">recent CNN oped</a>, <a href="http://electionlawblog.org/?p=28207">this blog post</a> on whether <em>Citizens United</em> created Super PACs, and t<a href="http://electionlawblog.org/?p=28617">his blog post</a> which highlights the kinds of coordination which are currently permissible under FEC rules.<br /><strong>&#8230;</strong><br /><strong>. The Secret Money is Shifting to 501c4s, and It Demands a Legislative Response. </strong>Last night ace election lawyer Rob Kelner <a href="https://twitter.com/#">tweeted</a>: “Biggest story today: Crossroads’ c4 raised more than its Super PAC. Confirming that media is missing the boat by focusing on Super PACs.”</p></blockquote>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />
<blockquote> My big concern before yesterday was that we would see a lot of transfers of money from 501c4s to affiliated Super PACs to shield the identity of donors to Super PACs. I’m still trying to get a handle on how much of this took place (apparently less than I thought). But the reason these transfers are not taking place is that it appears the 501c4s are engaging in much more <em>direct </em>election-related activity than they have in the past. That is, we are seeing some 501c4s becoming pure election vehicles. The relation of 501c4s to super pacs is now like the past relation between 527s and pacs—these are now the vehicles of questionable legality to influence elections. While <a href="http://www.mediteerenian.salon.com/2012/01/31/congress_can_fix_the_super_pac_problem/singleton/">Adam Skaggs</a> is rightly focused on fixing the coordination rules for Super PACs, this seems to be fighting yesterday’s war already. The key is to stop 501c4s from becoming shadow super PACs. Yes, campaign finance reform community, it has become this bad: I want <em>more</em> super PACs, because the 501c4 alternative is worse&#8230;</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/02/the-secret-money-is-shifting-to-501c4s.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
