<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>George Will &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Government sponsored enterprises</title>
		<link>./../../2011/07/government-sponsored-enterprises.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/07/government-sponsored-enterprises.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 03 Jul 2011 19:59:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Auto bailout]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Freddie Mac]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[George Will]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/07/government-sponsored-enterprises.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Beverly Mann I Beg to Differ (in Part), Mr. Will A few days ago I posted a post on my blog that responds to George Will’s claim in his weekend Washington Post column that the auto bailout was a privatization of profits but a socialization of losses. The full post, which is at Annarborist, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by <strong>Beverly Mann</strong></p>
<p><strong>I Beg to Differ (in Part), Mr. Will</strong></p>
<p>A few days ago I posted a post on my blog that responds to George Will’s claim in his weekend<a target="_blank" href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/burning-down-the-house/2011/06/30/AGeRSGuH_story.html?hpid=z2"> Washington Post column</a> that the auto bailout was a privatization of profits but a socialization of losses.  The full post, which is at <a target="_blank" href="http://annarborist.blogspot.com/2011/07/i-beg-to-differ-in-part-mr-will.html">Annarborist</a>, and is called <em>I Beg to Differ (in Part) Mr. Will</em>, George Will says:    </p>
<blockquote><p>In 1994, Bill Clinton proposed increasing homeownership through a ‘partnership’ between government and the private sector, principally orchestrated by Fannie Mae, a “government-sponsored enterprise” (GSE). It became a perfect specimen of what such “partnerships” (e.g., General Motors) usually involve: Profits are private, losses are socialized.</p></blockquote>
<p>—“Burning Down the House,” George F. Will, Washington Post, June 30  <br /><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Will’s column discusses a new book by Getchen Morgenson and housing-finance expert Joshua Rosner that Will says “will introduce you to James A. Johnson, an emblem of the administrative state that liberals admire.”  Johnson, for those of you who (like me) don’t instantly recognize the name, headed Fannie Mae during (I guess; Will doesn’t specify the dates) during the 1990s and early 2000s.  He says the book details how Johnson and a few others, acting under the guise of compassion, used the government’s backing of Fannie and Freddie loans and the public policy of encouraging homeownership, to hugely enrich themselves.   </p>
<p>Will writes:  </p>
<blockquote><p>Morgenson and Rosner report that in 1998, when Fannie Mae’s lending hit $1 trillion, its top officials began manipulating the company’s results to generate bonuses for themselves. That year Johnson’s $1.9 million bonus brought his compensation to $21 million. In nine years, Johnson received $100 million.  </p>
<p>Fannie Mae’s political machine dispensed campaign contributions, gave jobs to friends and relatives of legislators, hired armies of lobbyists (even paying lobbyists not to lobby against it), paid academics who wrote papers validating the homeownership mania, and spread “charitable” contributions to housing advocates across the congressional map.</p></blockquote>
<p>But he also suggests, if I understand correctly, that it was Johnson and the other Fannie and Freddie folks, rather than the Wall Street crowd, who instituted the concept of securitized mortgages and credit default swaps—and (inferentially) then caused European banks to spur, say, the Irish housing bubble, which, last I heard, was not funded in any part by Fannie and Freddie.  And he wrote the quote that opens this post, in which he claims that the government’s bailout—loans, most of which have been repaid—to GM and Chrysler have resulted in merely private profits.  Unlike, y’know, the very substantial tax breaks given to oil companies.  </p>
<p>The estimates about the number of jobs saved by those bailouts ranges from about 500,000 to (ultimately; i.e., indirectly) 1.5 million.  Will is saying, in other words, that the federal government has no legitimate business involving itself so directly in the preservation of, or for that matter, the creation of jobs, because, after all, job preservation and job creation are private, not public, financial gains.  The proposition is preposterous and relies upon the sleight of hand that only <i>company and shareholder profits</i> count as “profits”—a conceit that is likely to be seen for what it is, in places like Michigan, Indiana and Ohio.  Assuming, of course, that Will is read in such places, or that some other wingnut picks up the argument and runs (literally, may) be with it there.  <br />(Please, please, Paul Krugman.  Respond to Will’s bizarre claim.  You’re the only one who could do this and who has a wide enough readership for it to matter.  We both know that no response to this type of canard will be forthcoming from the White House.  Ever.  Okay, well, at least until 2017.)  </p>
<p>Two or three weeks ago, <em>Newsweek</em> ran a lengthy article by Bill Clinton listing 14 proposals for job creation.  (Oh, for the days when the Democrat in the White House had some actual ideas, some energy, and the willingness—the eagerness, in fact!—to discuss his policy proposals, in detail and concertedly, with the public.)  One of them concerned one of the Obama administrations (very) few policy ideas: Substantial tax credits and outright loans to green-tech startups, which resulted in an increase in America’s share of worldwide production of batteries for battery-powered cars from 2% to 20% before until our dear leader quietly—why raise this issue publicly during negotiations when it’s just so much easier to simply give the Republicans what they want—caved, er, negotiated away this law during last December’s budget white-flag waving, er, compromise.  Clinton, of course, suggests that this program should be brought back, immediately, and expanded to other types of industries.  </p>
<p>Won’t happen, of course.  Well, maybe in 2017.  </p>
<p>As for Johnson and his ilk, hopefully there’s still time, statute-of-limitations-wise, to prosecute these folks.  And hopefully, the Morgenson and Rosner book will cause enough pressure for that to happen.  And I agree with Will completely that one of the most despicable aspects of what happened with Fannie and Freddie was the fraudulent claim of compassion.  Wonder, though, whether Will would agree with ME that the Repubs’ genuine compassion for, say, oil company execs and shareholders is just as unseemly, in its own way.  Nah.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/07/government-sponsored-enterprises.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
