<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>state and local taxes &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Every State&#8217;s State/Local Tax System Taxes the Poor More than the Wealthy&#8211;And All Exceed Federal Taxes</title>
		<link>./../../2012/09/every-states-statelocal-tax-system-taxes-the-poor-more-than-the-wealthy-and-all-exceed-federal-taxes.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/09/every-states-statelocal-tax-system-taxes-the-poor-more-than-the-wealthy-and-all-exceed-federal-taxes.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 24 Sep 2012 12:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[federal income taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kenneth Thomas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[state and local taxes]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/09/every-states-statelocal-tax-system-taxes-the-poor-more-than-the-wealthy-and-all-exceed-federal-taxes.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Kenneth Thomas Every State&#8217;s State/Local Tax System Taxes the Poor More than the Wealthy&#8211;And All Exceed Federal Taxes A new report from the Institute on Taxation and Economic Policy (ITEP) shows that in every state in the country, the bottom 20% of households pay more of their income in state and local taxes than [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Kenneth Thomas</p>
<p>Every State&#8217;s State/Local Tax System Taxes the Poor More than the Wealthy&#8211;And All Exceed Federal Taxes</p>
<p> A <a href="http://www.itep.org/pdf/poverty2012report.pdf">new report</a> from the Institute on Taxation and Economic Policy (ITEP) shows that in every state in the country, the bottom 20% of households pay more of their income in state and local taxes than does the top 1%. Washington state was the worst, where the bottom 20% pay a whopping 17.3% of their income in state and local taxes. This was followed by Florida at 13.5% and Illinois at 13.0%. Though the report hints at an exception, a reading of their appendix shows that the only one is the District of Columbia.<br />    <br />As the report points out, such high taxation increases the burden of poverty on the people who, by definition, can least afford it. Moreover, this runs counter to the federal tax system, which in its overall effect (see table below) is progressive. On average, the top 1% pay federal taxes equal to 30% of their income, compared to 1.1% for the lowest 20%.<br />    <br /><img alt="undefined" border="0" height="467" hspace="0" src="http://www.taxpolicycenter.org/briefing-book/background/distribution/images/progressive.gif" width="513"><br />Source: <a href="http://www.taxpolicycenter.org/briefing-book/background/distribution/progressive-taxes.cfm">Tax Policy Center</a>    </p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Between these two reports, we can see that the bottom 20% of taxpayers pays a much higher portion of their income in state and local taxes than they do in federal taxes. ITEP therefore recommends four major policies to make state and local taxation less regressive.    </p>
<p>1) Enact a refundable earned income tax credit for state income tax;    <br />2) Enact property tax circuit-breaker caps for all low-income taxpayers, including renters;    <br />3) Enact other refundable income tax credits for childless households below the poverty level;    <br />4) Enact or increase child tax credits, and make them refundable.    </p>
<p>Of course, it should go without needing to be said, but to make federal tax more progressive (think of Mitt Romney and his tax rate below the average 15.1% paid by those in the third income quintile), we should tax capital gains and carried interest the same as ordinary income.</p>
<p>cross posted with <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2012/09/every-states-statelocal-tax-system.html">Middle Class Political Economist</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/09/every-states-statelocal-tax-system-taxes-the-poor-more-than-the-wealthy-and-all-exceed-federal-taxes.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
