<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>health care law &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Health Care Thoughts: Obamacare Updates</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/health-care-thoughts-obamacare-updates.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/health-care-thoughts-obamacare-updates.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 19 Feb 2013 19:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[health care law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health care thoughts]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/health-care-thoughts-obamacare-updates.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt Health Care Thoughts:  Obamacare Updates The slow march toward full implementation continues. Exchanges – As of today 17 states will create their own exchange, seven states will partner with the government, and 26 states have defaulted to the federal program (if anyone asked me I would suggest defaulting in order [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>
<div>by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt</div>
<div></div>
<div>Health Care Thoughts:  Obamacare  Updates</div>
<div></div>
<div>The slow march toward full implementation continues.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Exchanges –  As of today 17 states will create their own exchange, seven states will partner with the government, and 26 states have defaulted to the federal program (if anyone asked me I would suggest defaulting in order to let the feds do the early heavy lifting).</div>
<div></div>
<div>Perhaps the most important questions now are:</div>
<div></div>
<div>Will any of the exchanges be ready on time?</div>
<div></div>
<div>Will the products be affordable?</div>
<div></div>
<div>How will employers respond?</div>
<div></div>
<div>Employer Response – there is a great deal of discussion but very few decisions have been announced (although some are likely in place but not announced). </div>
<div></div>
<div>Will a generally weak economy and slack labor market play into the decisions? Time will tell.</div>
<div></div>
<div>A strategy of self-insuring may gain favor, and I will do a separate post on that topic.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Providers – the word I hear most often is “chaos.”  Providers are trying to prepare for a system as yet poorly defined. Some trends are emerging (integration, the early ACOs) but it is too early to tell how anything will work.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Issues in primary care and rural health care are likely to be especially acute.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Consultants and health care focused lawyers are raking it in – so somebody wins.</div>
<p>Electronic Medical Records and Electronic Health Systems &#8211; this has the potential to turn into a nightmare</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/health-care-thoughts-obamacare-updates.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Health Care Thoughts: Health Exchange Delay</title>
		<link>./../../2012/11/health-care-thoughts-health-exchange-delay.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/11/health-care-thoughts-health-exchange-delay.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 17 Nov 2012 16:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[health care law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health care thoughts]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/11/health-care-thoughts-health-exchange-delay.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by  Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt Health Care Thoughts: Health Exchange Delay The Obama administration has delayed the decision point on state health exchanges until December 14th. Much of the discussion on this issue has centered on politics. My focus is on more practical issues. The Obama administration has a track record of being unable to [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>by  Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt</div>
<div></div>
<div>Health Care Thoughts: Health Exchange Delay</div>
<div></div>
<div>The Obama administration has delayed the decision point on state health exchanges until December 14th.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Much of the discussion on this issue has centered on politics. My focus is on more practical issues.</div>
<div></div>
<div>The Obama administration has a track record of being unable to develop administrative regulations on time and for writing complicated and incoherent regulations. We still do not know for certain what &#8220;essential benefits&#8221; might be and how the administration will balance intense lobbying on this issue versus affordability.</div>
<div></div>
<div>From a management and financial viewpoint it may make perfect sense to have the feds install their &#8220;plug-and-play&#8221; model exchange and to let the feds do the heavy lifting, politics aside. Maybe the Democrat governors are wrong on this one?</div>
<div> </div>
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/11/health-care-thoughts-health-exchange-delay.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Health spending growth in the US</title>
		<link>./../../2012/11/health-spending-growth-in-the-us.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/11/health-spending-growth-in-the-us.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2012 14:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Health care costs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health care law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health care reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health insurance costs]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/11/health-spending-growth-in-the-us.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Yves Smith at Naked Capitalism brings us news of an important study addressing the issues of determining the costs of medical care, delivery, and insurance: A remarkably important and persuasive paper that calls into question the need for “reforming” Medicare has not gotten the attention it warrants. “An Examination of Health-Spending Growth In The United [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/11/fed-budgetary-experts-demolish-cbo-health-cost-model-the-lynchpin-of-budget-hysteria.html">Yves Smith</a> at <i>Naked Capitalism</i> brings us news of an important study addressing the issues of determining the costs of medical care, delivery, and insurance:</p>
<blockquote><p>A remarkably important and persuasive paper that calls into question the need for “reforming” Medicare has not gotten the attention it warrants. “<a href="http://www.bancaditalia.it/studiricerche/convegni/atti/fiscal_sustainability/session_3/Follette%20Sheiner.pdf">An Examination of Health-Spending Growth In The United States: Past Trends And Future Prospects</a>” (hat tip nathan) by Glenn Follette and Louise Sheiner looks at the model used by the Congressional Budgetary Office to estimate long term health care cost increases. Bear in mind that this model is THE driver of virtually all forecasts of future budget deficits.<br />This paper, although written in typically anodyne economese, is devastating in the range and nature of its criticisms.</p></blockquote>
<p>The election for Senator in MA is close and takes a lot of time, so discussion of this topic has received short shrift till later, but reponses are in the works.  I have taken the liberty of lifting comments from that thread at <i>Naked Capitalism</i> from run75441, Yves, and reader river.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>run75441 says:<br />Yves:<br />I have mentioned this before and caught a lot of flak, Elmendorf was one of several who helped kill Hillarycare.<br /> <cite>Yves Smith</cite> says:
<ul>
<li>     <a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/11/fed-budgetary-experts-demolish-cbo-health-cost-model-the-lynchpin-of-budget-hysteria.html#comment-889881">November 4, 2012 at 1:24 pm</a><br />Yes, Dean Baker (along with others) have been criticizing these models for some time, but the fact that it is the folks in the Fed’s fiscal impacts section who have also gone after it (i.e., are not card carrying lefties and therefore don’t have an axe to grind) puts this in a different light.<br />What is distressing is that Krugman in particular (someone who is seen as knowledgeable about health care and a pinko) has been taking the conventional line.</li>
</ul>
<p>And further question and answers here:</p>
<p><cite>river</cite> says:<br /><a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/11/fed-budgetary-experts-demolish-cbo-health-cost-model-the-lynchpin-of-budget-hysteria.html#comment-890411">November 4, 2012 at 6:57 pm</a><br />Long time reader, but haven’t written on here too much, as I am a financial illiterate and find that this blog is above me a great deal of the time.<br />That said, the overall point of this blog post seems to be that the CBO is simply basing their long range predictions of health care spending based on the overall increase in spending seen over the last thirty years, but what will actually happen is that the cost increases will taper off naturally because they almost have to . . . you can’t have ever rising exponential growth in a world of limited resources.<br />The question then becomes what will happen to stop the cost increases from continuing their upward march, and what will be the consequences of that occuring. After all of us experiencing this exact same thing play itself out in the housing market, I can only imagine how it would play itself out in healthcare. For the last few years, most of my raises have gone to healthcare cost increases, and I would expect that to continue, but after a while, we would switch to a catestrophic insurance program and just not use the services that they are providing. As the costs keep going up, more and more people would stop getting any insurance. Bankrupcies, and cost pressures on medical facilities will start to hit the practitioners (if all of the antelopes are starving, the lions will soon starve themselves).<br /><a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/11/fed-budgetary-experts-demolish-cbo-health-cost-model-the-lynchpin-of-budget-hysteria.html?replytocom=890411#respond">Reply</a>
<ul>
<li><cite>run75441</cite> says:<br /><a href="http://www.nakedcapitalism.com/2012/11/fed-budgetary-experts-demolish-cbo-health-cost-model-the-lynchpin-of-budget-hysteria.html#comment-890554">November 4, 2012 at 9:00 pm</a><br />river:<br />I have not looked lately; but, commercial healthcare insurance has been increasing in cost at ~8% as opposed to ~2.4% for Medicare (S&#038;P Healthcare Indices). The goal is to get both down to 1% through a series of cost initiatives led by Medicare. Obama has pledged to allow Medicare to begin negotiating healthcare industry services.<br />The MLR was put in place to control the amount of premiums spent on insurance administration. Within the MLR are risk factors based upon the youngest and healthiest insuree, 150% for smokers (too low), and up to 300% for the elderly. There is also a maximum you will pay as a percentage of income.<br />I had a discussion today with Maggie Mahar on the growing costs and the attached article. I am sure she would not mind my posting some of her thoughts:<br />“It seems to me that any attempt to forecast that far out is nuts. Wall Street analysts don’t try to predict a corporation’s finance out more than 3 years– maybe 5– and that’s just one corporations.<br />They’re talking about healthcare spending– a huge chunk of the economy.They also assume that the aging of America means higher spending.<br />A number of countries in Europe that have populations that are significantly older than ours have shown that just isn’t true. (I’m thinking of Germany &#038; Sweden in particular).<br />We’ve always been somewhat hysterical about “What will happen when the Baby Boomers Grow Old!!” We’ll handle it because we have to.<br />We already know that 1/3 of Medicare dollars are wasted. Cut even 2/3 of that waste, and problem solved. Getting away from fee for service, more efficient systems, refusing to pay for preventable errors, reducing what medicare pays for services we know are not terribly effective; greater use of nurse practitioners, less screening, . . . etc.”</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/11/health-spending-growth-in-the-us.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Congressman Ryan’s Health Care Booby Trap</title>
		<link>./../../2012/04/congressman-ryans-health-care-booby-trap.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/04/congressman-ryans-health-care-booby-trap.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 02 Apr 2012 16:18:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[health care law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health insurance reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Michael Halasy]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/04/congressman-ryans-health-care-booby-trap.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Michael Halasy Congressman Ryan’s Health Care Booby Trap Much has been said about “repeal and replace” it has become almost as much a part of GOP lexicon as “drill baby, drill”. The GOP despite having been supportive of the framework for the ACA previously, wants badly to discredit the administration and claim a victory [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Michael Halasy</p>
<p>Congressman Ryan’s Health Care Booby Trap</p>
<p>  Much has been said about “repeal and replace” it has become almost as much a part of GOP lexicon as “drill baby, drill”.  The GOP despite having been supportive of the framework for the ACA previously, wants badly to discredit the administration and claim a victory in the name of “freedom”. Too bad history shows that the Heritage Foundation and VP Stuart Butler supported a plan almost virtually identical to the ACA.</p>
<p>  Now, along comes Congressman Ryan, despite being rebuffed last year for the “Roadmap”, he has come along with a v 2.0. Unfortunately, he is making headway. I won’t comment on the other aspects of the new and improved Roadmap, but it seems to be just as much of a disaster as the previous one. The House has already passed it of course, and Romney, aka etch a sketch, has enthusiastically received the Congressman’s endorsement and has endorsed Ryan’s plan as well.</p>
<p>So we know that the GOP, primarily the Tea Partier’s, despise the individual mandate as a violation of their freedom. Ezra Klein had a great article last week about the hidden mandate in the Ryan bill , but does not discuss the fact that it will <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/ezra-klein/post/there-was-a-reason-conservatives-once-supported-the-individual-mandate/2012/03/30/gIQAiddnlS_blog.html" target="_blank">essentially eliminate employer based insurance</a>. Now, Ryan’s plan assumes that the state based exchanges (sound familiar?) will produce a lot of savings, and he assumes that market forces will do even more. To that end, he offers a couple of tax credits. But, oh by the way, you LOSE employer based coverage under Ryan. It severs it completely. So an individual gets a 2,300 dollar tax credit (family is 5,700) to buy insurance. I can tell you now, that the average per the Kaiser Family Foundation for a single individual is much higher than 2,300. <br /><a name="more"></a><br />Family plan premiums are $15,073 on average, while coverage for single employees is about $5,429.  </p>
<p>Workers contributed an average of $921 toward the premium of single coverage and $4,129 for family plans.   </p>
<p>What this means, is, that under the Ryan plan, your single insurance premium will cost you 2,208 MORE per year out of your own pocket at current cost. Family plans will cost you 5,244 MORE per year out of your own pocket.  </p>
<p>That&#8217;s the repeal and replace plan folks&#8230;..That&#8217;s what the House voted on and passed&#8230;..That&#8217;s what Romney endorsed&#8230;.THAT&#8217;s the GOP plan&#8230;  </p>
<p>It&#8217;ll save businesses money, and it&#8217;s great for corporate America. However, it is not so great for the average small family living on 40-45k per year combined income.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/04/congressman-ryans-health-care-booby-trap.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Supreme Court and the health care law</title>
		<link>./../../2011/11/the-supreme-court-and-the-health-care-law.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/11/the-supreme-court-and-the-health-care-law.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2011 17:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[health care law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Supreme court]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/11/the-supreme-court-and-the-health-care-law.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In the New York Times today: The Supreme Court on Monday agreed to hear a challenge to the 2010 health care overhaul law, President Obama’s signature legislative achievement. The development set the stage for oral arguments by March and a decision in late June, in the midst of the 2012 presidential campaign… … Appeals from [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the  <a target="_blank" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/11/15/us/supreme-court-to-hear-case-challenging-health-law.html?_r=1&#038;hp">New York Times</a> today:<br />
<blockquote>
<p>The <a target="_blank" href="http://topics.nytimes.com/top/reference/timestopics/organizations/s/supreme_court/index.html?inline=nyt-org">Supreme Court</a> on Monday agreed to hear a challenge to the 2010 <a href="http://topics.nytimes.com/top/news/health/diseasesconditionsandhealthtopics/health_insurance_and_managed_care/health_care_reform/index.html?inline=nyt-classifier">health care overhaul</a> law, President Obama’s signature legislative achievement. The development set the stage for oral arguments by March and a decision in late June, in the midst of the 2012 presidential campaign…</p>
<p>…</p>
<p><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2011/11/13/us/politics/challenges-to-the-health-law.html">Appeals from three courts had been vying for the justices’ attention</a>, presenting an array of issues beyond the central one of whether Congress has the constitutional power to require people to purchase health insurance or face a penalty through the so-called individual mandate. </p>
<p>The Supreme Court agreed to hear appeals from just one decision, from the United States Court of Appeals for the 11th Circuit, in Atlanta, <a name="more"></a>  the only one so far striking down the mandate. <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/08/13/us/13health.html">The decision</a>, from a divided three-judge panel, said the mandate overstepped Congressional authority and could not be justified by the constitutional power “to regulate commerce” or “to lay and collect taxes.” </p>
<p>The appeals court went no further, though, severing the mandate from the rest of the law. </p>
<p>On Monday, the justices agreed to decide not only whether the mandate is constitutional but also whether, if it is not, how much of the balance of the law, the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act, must fall along with it. </p>
<p>…</p>
<p>On Monday, the justices agreed to consider that question. The justices also said they would consider an intriguing threshold issue.</p>
<p>In September, a divided three-judge panel of the United States Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit, in Richmond, Va., <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/09/09/health/policy/09virginia.html">ruled that it was premature to decide the case</a> in light of the Anti-Injunction Act, a federal law that bars suits “for the purpose of restraining the assessment or collection of any tax.” The Supreme Court had interpreted the term “tax” very broadly for purposes of the law. </p>
<p>If the Fourth Circuit ruling is correct, individuals may not challenge the individual mandate until the first penalty is due in April 2015. On Tuesday, a dissenting judge on the United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/11/09/health/policy/appeals-court-upholds-health-care-law.html">also endorsed that position</a>. </p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/11/the-supreme-court-and-the-health-care-law.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
