<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>terrorism &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Shockwave Rider: it&#8217;s Now, Don&#8217;t Tell the Terrorists</title>
		<link>./../../2010/05/shockwave-rider-its-now-dont-tell-the-terrorists.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/05/shockwave-rider-its-now-dont-tell-the-terrorists.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 29 May 2010 08:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[telephony]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[terrorism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/05/shockwave-rider-its-now-dont-tell-the-terrorists.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Bruce Webb I no longer try to follow Science-Fiction, but from 1964 to 1977 which is to say from the time I was seven until I turned twenty and joined the Navy I read pretty much everything and had built up a pretty massive library. Among them was a book called The_Shockwave_Rider by John [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Bruce Webb</p>
<p>I no longer try to follow Science-Fiction, but from 1964 to 1977 which is to say from the time I was seven until I turned twenty and joined the Navy I read pretty much everything and had built up a pretty massive library. Among them was a book called <a target href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/">The_Shockwave_Rider</a> by John Brunner. The wiki article explains the basic premise as follows<br />
<blockquote>The title derives from the futurological work by Alvin Toffler. Future Shock. The hero is a survivor in a hypothetical world of quickly changing identities, fashions and lifestyles, where individuals are still controlled and oppressed by a powerful and secretive state apparatus. His highly developed computer skills enable him to use any public telephone to punch in a new identity, thus reinventing himself, within hours. As a fugitive, he must do this regularly in order to escape capture. The title is also a metaphor for survival in an uncertain world.</p></blockquote>
<p>The novel, originally published in 1975, at a time when the Internet was still mostly a DARPA research project and the home computer was just a dream, was way  ahead of its time both in terms of the technology represented and the genre, one that is now I guess known as cyber-punk (I told you I was out of touch). Well a couple of things combined today to make me realize that not only have we reached the world of Shockwave Rider, we have made it as banal as a trip to 7/11 and Safeway. Because in a world where the government is tracking just about everything, it has never been more easy to go off the info grid while paradoxically staying fully wired at all times. Good news for people who value privacy, which unfortunately include Mafia Dons, Mexican Drug Cartels, and international Terrorists. Some discussion below the fold.<br /><a name="more"></a><br />First thing to realize is that none of this is secret to the bad guys, even public information tells us that these groups are pretty technologically sophisticated. Why is why the event that prompted the post is so misguided. Apparently Senator Schumer has introduced a bill that would require anyone buying a disposible pre-paid cell phone to show ID, This news, brought to me by John Cole at Baloon Juice spurred a long comment which the Intertubes just swallowed a few seconds ago (kind of ironic in context). Well this proposal tied into some things I have been thinking about in relation to my own life situation to add up to the question &#8220;Can anyone ride the Shockwave and remain undetected while still moving through ordinary society and all without engaging in criminal acts?&#8221; Well to a surprising degree you can.</p>
<p>Let&#8217;s start. Let&#8217;s assume you have enough existing ID to obtain a certified copy of your own birth certificate, as it happens I actually have the original of that as well as my original SS card, and some time back used them to secure a valid Passport which added to a valid Washington State Driver&#8217;s license. All perfectly legitimate, and all you need to do is to keep on the right side of the DMV and the IRS,</p>
<p>Now beyond your passport and driver&#8217;s license what are the essentials for living in American society legitimately but invisibly. Well first and foremost you need a mailing address, and ideally one that will accept packages for you. Well even small towns have some equivalent of Mailbox Express, and the IRS and your bank will accept that as a legitimate address. My mailbox place   also offers secured storage, and with legitimate ID will link that to their own premises for invoicing. Having a mailing address and legit ID allows you to open a banking account which now universally come with a Debit Card which doubles as a Credit Card. But of course you can&#8217;t use that card in truly anonymous fashion. So what is next?</p>
<p>Well you establish an online presence, which in turn requires computer access. Now there are ways to do this anonymously via Internet cafes and the like but for true invisibility you have an option, buy a WiFi capable device, for me that is an iPad, paying cash, then find a truly anonymous public WiFi spot. Which these days is likely to be a MacDonalds or a public building. Now you are in business because you don&#8217;t have to supply proof of anything to set up multiple free accounts under Google, Yahoo, and the upgrade MS HotMail, each of which give you legitimate e-mail addresses and access to a variety of services including free online storage and with Google a free incoming phone number with auto voice mail. This in turn allows you to register for free content from across the web, none of which can be readily traced to you, after all if you paid cash or equivalent for you WiFI device and don&#8217;t register it with the manufacturer, all anyone can do is gather your device number (if that) and your current location.</p>
<p>Okay but not everything on the web is free and there will be times you want to engage in e-commerce. Well this is where riding the Shockwave has been reduced to the truly banal, all you need to do is go to the Gift Card section of your local Safeway where you will find a nice assortment of pre-paid and reloadable Gift Cards from each of the major credit card companies, none of which (at least to date) require you to show any ID and while online registration (in case of loss or theft) is possible it is not mandatory. Now this is a huge development whose implications have not I think been grasped. A few years ago I would have said it is near impossible to function at a reasonable level without credit, in particular travel was almost impossible, without a credit card equivalent with a reasonable line you couldn&#8217;t rent a car or often get hotel reservations, or in some cases even hotel check-in. Well these days you can buy your own credit in pretty much whatever amounts you need, and all without giving the credit card companies any room to screw you over by  changing terms and rates or arbitrarily cutting your line. If you work it right and pay attention to grace periods you can have a wallet full of credit and store cards none of which tie back to your credit score or indeed even to your identity.</p>
<p>Put all the pieces together and you can live a life that is perfectly legitimate but for all practical purposes invisible, with online banking you can even cut your physical connection to the mailbox that remains your legal anchor point for your passport, drivers license, and for the tax authorities, and for those you  can have a third party pick up official communications or simply have them forwarded.</p>
<p>This is not theoretical for me, sometime in the next six months I will be relocating, perhaps even taking a job that will have me in constant travel for the next few years, and one consideration was how I could be on the move all the time while still maintaining near 24/7 availability on the web while simultaneously free of the tyranny of the credit card companies and rating agencies. Five years ago I would have told you this was difficult and trending towards impossible, for example insurance companies were increasingly using credit scores to set your car insurance rates or even to deny you coverage at all, and there were indications that health insurers were moving in the same direction, while between your credit card company and your internet provider your entire life could be reconstructed via a combination of your purchases off and on line combined with your web surfing. Well not so now, a combination of a store bought pre-paid credit card, a Google account plus perhaps two or three other online e-mail accounts, and a WiFi browsing device and you too can be a Shockwave Rider, and all without the &#8220;highly developed computer skills&#8221; of the book&#8217;s hero.</p>
<p>This is not to say that there are not some tradeoff&#8217;s. Without current credit history and a good score you won&#8217;t be able to finance a house, then again for millions of people burned by the housing bubble and all too many having their equity and their credit disappear during foreclosure, this may be more a feature than a bug of riding the Shockwave. Similarly you might have serious problems financing a new car or getting it insured, which might get you thinking whether your really need a car to start with. Equally not having a good credit history is likely to block you from employment in the financial sector and perhaps from working for other Fortune 500 companies, not something that concerns me much either, and I suspect it would give a little heartburn to the FBI doing a background check for a security clearance, equally not high on my priority list. All in all I think I&#8217;ll give the Ride at least an approximation of a try, after all I&#8217;ll always be reachable on-line, just like I never left.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/05/shockwave-rider-its-now-dont-tell-the-terrorists.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Trade-Offs and Revealed Preferences, Republican Leadership edition</title>
		<link>./../../2010/02/trade-offs-and-revealed-preferences-republican-leadership-edition.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/02/trade-offs-and-revealed-preferences-republican-leadership-edition.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 20 Feb 2010 21:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[bad economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[employment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Republican brand]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[signalling]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[terrorism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[unions]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/02/trade-offs-and-revealed-preferences-republican-leadership-edition.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Even more than Digby on CalPERS, the one piece everyone should read today is Charlie Stross on International Travel. Since this is an economics blog, let&#8217;s pull a key section: Here&#8217;s the rub: security is a state of mind, not a procedure. Procedures can&#8217;t cope with attackers, because they&#8217;re inflexible. If you search passengers for [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Even more than Digby on CalPERS, the one piece everyone should read today is <a href="http://www.antipope.org/charlie/blog-static/2010/02/international-travel-redux.html">Charlie Stross on International Travel</a>.  Since this is an economics blog, let&#8217;s pull a key section:<br />
<blockquote>Here&#8217;s the rub: security is a state of mind, not a procedure. Procedures can&#8217;t cope with attackers, because they&#8217;re inflexible. If you search passengers for guns, someone will carry a knife. If you search for knives, someone will sew themselves a set of underwear full of PETN. And so on. To deal with a threat — say, someone who wants to attack your air travel infrastructure — you must look for the attacker, not their tools, because they can change their tools at will to exploit weaknesses in your procedure for identifying tools.</p>
<p>JFK is wide open to terrorists intent on causing mass casualties&#8230;.</p>
<p>Schiphol — Amsterdam airport — gets the security screening right, or at least less wrong than JFK and most other airports. Rather than having a hideous bottleneck between check-in and the departure area, security screening is carried out at each depature gate, with a separate metal detector and X-ray belt; no huge crowds form in unsecured areas. On US-bound flights, someone who clearly isn&#8217;t a minimum-wage drone checks ID documents and asks a couple of questions that seem to me to the aimed at flushing out anyone who is disturbed or tense — a crude form of profiling.[italics his; boldfacing mine]</p></blockquote>
<p>South Carolina Senator Jim DeMint preferred to <a href="http://whitehouse.blogs.foxnews.com/2010/01/20/fmr-tsa-nominee-disputes-senators-claim-over-unionization/">let the TSA remain leaderless for the past year</a> in fear of unionization of the workers.  As he explained to CNN:<br />

</p>
<p>Or, as quoted by Mark &#8220;neither Ernest nor earnest&#8221; Hemingway the Washington Examiner, in a piece oh-so-sensibly entitled <a href="http://www.washingtonexaminer.com/opinion/blogs/beltway-confidential/Napolitano-wants-to-unionize-TSA-employees-despite-safety-concerns-80206432.html">Napolitano wants to unionize TSA employees despite safety concerns</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>The administration is intent in on unionizing and submitting our airport security to union bosses [and] collective bargaining, and this is at a time, as Senator Lieberman says, we&#8217;ve got to use our imagination we&#8217;ve got to be constantly flexible. We have to out think the terrorists. When we formed the airport security system we realize we could not use collective bargaining and unionization because of that need to be flexible. Yet that appears to be the top priority of the administration.</p></blockquote>
<p>But DeMint was much clearer on the Senate floor, and <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DBs1OEEakNU&#038;feature=channel">speaking to Fox</a>:<br />
<blockquote>It makes absolutely no sense to submit the security of our airports and the passengers here in this country to collective bargaining with unions.</p></blockquote>
<p>Which, of course, is why police and fire departments are all non-union as well.</p>
<p>The people you attract to any job—by your deliberate practices, not &#8220;unintended consequence&#8221;—are those who cannot get a job that they know to be more stable, pays better, has better benefits, or provide a more friendly work atmosphere.  By your policies and procedures, you reveal the type of worker you prefer.  This is as true of the TSA as it is of Goldman Sachs.</p>
<p>In the case of the TSA, though, the combination produces the natural hire as the people who couldn&#8217;t get a job at Applebee&#8217;s, The Olive Garden, or Ruby Tuesday&#8217;s.</p>
<p>As Paul Kedrosky recently noted, it&#8217;s more &#8220;<a href="http://paul.kedrosky.com/archives/2010/02/adventures_in_a_1.html">security theater</a>&#8221; than security.  So when DeMint compares the TSA to the FBI, he&#8217;s neglecting that <a href="http://www.fbi.gov/pressrel/pressrel02/hire012302.htm">the average staring salary at the FBI <em>eight years ago</em> was over $43,000—with an increase of at least $10,000 upon completion of training</a>.  This is $20,000-$30,000 a year more than the $12/hour my neighbor made when he started with the TSA. (He quit quickly, finding restaurant work more profitable.)</p>
<p>If you want security, you pay for people who know how to do security.  If you want theater, you depend on Jim DeMint to ensure that the TSA remains leaderless, and then have no right to be surprised when a British novelist points out that your security isn&#8217;t secure.  Even when he says:<br />
<blockquote>Suppose I wanted to attack the US air travel infrastructure&#8230;.I can kill lots of passengers! All I need to do is to buy a maximum-size carry on bag (US dimensions: 7&#8243; x 13&#8243; x 20&#8243;) and build the biggest, heaviest bomb into it that I can wheel behind me&#8230;.</p>
<p>All I would have to do then is buy a ticket&#8230;and go queue. Then, when I get to the middle of the crowd, detonate the device. (For added horrors: have an accomplice with a similar device hang back, to detonate their bomb amidst the fleeing survivors.)</p>
<p>[S]ecurity checkpoints are a target, too, because they slow down travellers and cause crowds to form, and another term for &#8220;crowd&#8221; is &#8220;convenient target&#8221;. And because the attacker has not been separated from their weapon at the point when they reach such a target, it&#8217;s the logical weak point for causing maximum damage.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/02/trade-offs-and-revealed-preferences-republican-leadership-edition.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>WMD? YMMV.</title>
		<link>./../../2010/01/wmd-ymmv.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/01/wmd-ymmv.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 09 Jan 2010 02:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[terrorism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WMD]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/01/wmd-ymmv.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In the news over the past couple of days, I have heard the concealed explosives of the Undiebomber described as &#8220;weapons of mass destruction.&#8221; To me, this didn&#8217;t sound quite right &#8212; in fact, it sounded like a naming convention the Bush administration might have used. To check whether this was just me, I first [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the news over the past couple of days, I have heard the concealed explosives of the Undiebomber described as &#8220;weapons of mass destruction.&#8221;</p>
<p>To me, this didn&#8217;t sound quite right &#8212; in fact, it sounded like a naming convention the Bush administration might have used.</p>
<p>To check whether this was just me, I first stopped in at Wikipedia, where I found:<br />
<blockquote>A weapon of mass destruction (WMD) is a weapon that can kill large numbers of humans and/or cause great damage to man-made structures (e.g. buildings), natural structures (e.g. mountains), or the biosphere in general. The scope and application of the term has evolved and been disputed, often signifying more politically than technically. Coined in reference to aerial bombing with chemical explosives, it has come to distinguish large-scale weaponry of other technologies, such as chemical, biological, radiological, or nuclear. This differentiates the term from more technnical ones such as chemical, biological, radiological, and nuclear weapons (CRBN).</p></blockquote>
<p>Now, knocking down an airplane with an explosive is a major act of destruction, but does it qualify as deployment of a WMD?  I wouldn&#8217;t think so.</p>
<p>Taking down four planes, two enormous buildings and part of a third building is a huge act of destruction, but there aren&#8217;t any WMDs involved there either, unless you count the two towers themselves, the dust from which has yielded distinctly WMD-like effects.</p>
<p>So who then made the decision to call the PETN, as destructive as it undoubtedly is, a WMD,  and up the terrorism ante from failed airplane bomber to a wielder of thunderbolts?<a name="more"></a></p>
<p>I found a December 25th CNN article comparing Richard Reid (another plane bomb failure, eight years ago) to Abdulmutallab, and using the term WMD. Checking further using Google News, I found this graph:</p>
<p><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_MSuZ1riS9qU/S0fkASKlGmI/AAAAAAAAAYg/T_sP6sWLsh4/s1600-h/wmd+timeline.jpg"><img src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_MSuZ1riS9qU/S0fkASKlGmI/AAAAAAAAAYg/T_sP6sWLsh4/s400/wmd+timeline.jpg" border="0" alt=""></a></p>
<p>It looks like my intuition  is right and the WMD usage was indeed a Bush hangover, though the term itself originated years previous to the run-up to the Iraq war.</p>
<p>Perhaps the media should be more careful, since WMDs are generally held to be biological, chemical or nuclear weapons, not common items like PETN, used in small caliber ammunition, land mines and shells, and as the explosive core of detonation cord.</p>
<p>A better phrase might be &#8220;weapon.&#8221;  Or, for extreme cases,  &#8220;big weapon.&#8221;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/01/wmd-ymmv.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>36</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The suspected terrorist went to a federal pen?</title>
		<link>./../../2009/12/the-suspected-terrorist-went-to-a-federal-pen.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/12/the-suspected-terrorist-went-to-a-federal-pen.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2009 17:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[terrorism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[War against Terrorism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/12/the-suspected-terrorist-went-to-a-federal-pen.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by: Divorced one like Bush So, we can&#8217;t bring the Gitmo crowd here because they are dangerous and would create an inviting situation for further terrorism, but we can take the suspected Northwest Airline man to a federal pen just outside of Detroit? A suspected terrorist, in a federal pen? What?  Does the government really think [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by: Divorced one like Bush</p>
<p>So, we can&#8217;t bring the Gitmo crowd here because they are dangerous and would create an inviting situation for further terrorism, but we can take the suspected Northwest Airline man to <a href="http://seattletimes.nwsource.com/html/nationworld/2010610468_apusairlinerattackhospital.html">a federal pen just outside of Detroit</a>? A suspected terrorist, in a federal pen?</p>
<p>What?  Does the government really think that we don&#8217;t need the auto industry now so &#8211; so what if Detroit get&#8217;s all blown up? How could they do this to Detroit, risking all our money after helping GM and Chrysler?</p>
<p>Hope everyone remembers this when the super patriots come screaming again about how dangerous it is to close Gitmo and bring them to a federal pen.   At this point in the game, one is suppose to call Bull S#$t.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/12/the-suspected-terrorist-went-to-a-federal-pen.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>49</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>In the eye of the beholder</title>
		<link>./../../2008/05/in-the-eye-of-the-beholder.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/05/in-the-eye-of-the-beholder.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2008 17:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Annie Oakley]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hillory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[terrorism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/05/in-the-eye-of-the-beholder.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Came across a couple of videos. This first one is an issue of perspective on the thought of what is terroism or what is a terroist act. This second one is just plain funny (at least to me). It spoofs on the Annie Oakley comment by Senator Obama. On the economy side of things using [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Came across a couple of videos.  This first one is an issue of perspective on the thought of what is terroism or what is a terroist act.</p>
<p>This second one is just plain funny (at least to me).  It spoofs on the Annie Oakley comment by Senator Obama.</p>
<p>On the economy side of things using my GFP (gross flower production), things were not as good as last year.  What started off as a year with a bang, is now looking to be equal to last years numbers.  We were up 21% end of March.  End of April we were up 4.7%. As of Mother&#8217;s Day, 2.6% on the year.  Interestingly, looking at credit card use for the holiday months Valentines was up 23%, Easter was up 13% and now Mother&#8217;s Day is down 27%.  This is the shift I saw starting last August.  But, cash sales are up for May 33%.  They were up for January and February, but cash sales were down both March and April.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/05/in-the-eye-of-the-beholder.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Anbar and Pakistan</title>
		<link>./../../2007/11/anbar-and-pakistan.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2007/11/anbar-and-pakistan.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2007 03:43:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[terrorism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2007/11/anbar-and-pakistan.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[John Robb offers a viewpoint on progress in Iraq and lessons to be learned. When the Askariya shrine was bombed in February 2006, it fractured Iraqi social systems along religious lines. In the fighting that followed, Sunni guerrilla groups underwent a transformation from small and loosely connected to large and bureaucratic. This change was driven [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://globalguerrillas.typepad.com/globalguerrill/%3C/a">John Robb</a> offers a viewpoint on progress in Iraq and lessons to be learned.</p>
<blockquote><p>When the <a href="http://globalguerrillas.typepad.com/globalguerrillas/2006/02/al_qaedas_black.html">Askariya shrine</a> was bombed in February 2006, it fractured Iraqi social systems along religious lines. In the fighting that followed, Sunni guerrilla groups underwent a transformation from small and loosely connected to large and bureaucratic. This change was driven by three factors:<br />Shiite militias, operating without much government interference, were able to field large military formations in their attacks on Sunni targets.<br />Sunni neighborhoods needed a permanent militia to defend them against attacks.<br />US forces were relatively ineffective against Sunni guerrillas up until that point and offered no meaningful counter. The guerrillas were flush with cash and confident the US posed little threat. The combination of organic group growth and formal cross group affiliation led to the formation of the bureaucratic structures necessary to maintain groups larger than 150 people (read: &#8220;<a href="http://globalguerrillas.typepad.com/globalguerrillas/2004/03/what_is_the_opt.html">The Optimal Size of a Terrorist Network</a>&#8221; for more). Here&#8217;s an example from <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/11/19/AR2007111902022.html?nav=rss_print/asection">Amit Paley&#8217;s</a> WP interview with a recently captured &#8220;al Qaeda&#8221; insurgent in Mosul:<br />The 28-year-old said he was responsible for running the bureaucracy and arranging payments to the 500 or so fighters for the group in the city, who he said try to carry out as many as 30 attacks a day. This expansion in group size led to a radical increase in violence against almost every potential target. It also changed the underlying dynamic of the insurgency. The process of increasing group size and a movement towards local protection forced the following:<br />As groups formally affiliated to form larger organizations, a schism developed between homegrown guerrillas and those operating under &#8220;al Qaeda&#8217;s&#8221; banner.<br />Tighter ties to local communities for protection against Shiite militias led to jihadi control over neighborhoods. This in turn led to jihadi overreach and a local counter-reaction.<br />The increase in group size finally made al Qaeda accessible to US counter-pressure. It now had a center of gravity to attack. This is yet another level of complication that should muddy the &#8220;lesson&#8221; of &#8220;the Anbar tribal revolt.&#8221; The US should military think long and hard before it squanders tens of millions (soon hundreds of millions) of dollars on Pakistan&#8217;s Frontier Corps.</p></blockquote>
<p>This sort of discussion goes on other blogs familiar with the topic. Levels of complication as we talk about success or failure is a useful approach, while political memes of &#8216;less violence&#8217; is not.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2007/11/anbar-and-pakistan.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Gallup world poll and extreme global thought</title>
		<link>./../../2007/09/gallup-world-poll-and-extreme-global-thought.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2007/09/gallup-world-poll-and-extreme-global-thought.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 17 Sep 2007 12:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[terrorism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2007/09/gallup-world-poll-and-extreme-global-thought.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This analysis of Gallup Poll data offers insights for us to seriously think about. It also fits in with John Robb&#8217;s expert theory on terrorisms. Often U.S. policy-makers and other intellectuals draw an analogy between the Cold War and the current &#8220;global war on terror&#8221; and recommend analogous strategies, because, after all, both conflicts battled [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.gallupworldpoll.com/content/?ci=28678">This analysis of Gallup Poll</a> data offers insights for us to seriously think about. It also fits in with <a href="http://globalguerrillas.typepad.com/">John Robb&#8217;s expert theory</a> on terrorisms.</p>
<blockquote><p>Often U.S. policy-makers and other intellectuals draw an analogy between the Cold War and the current &#8220;global war on terror&#8221; and recommend analogous strategies, because, after all, both conflicts battled over people&#8217;s hearts and minds. But results from Gallup&#8217;s surveys in the Muslim world point to important differences between the two conflicts and real risks in confusing them by applying similar strategies.<br />At the heart of the Cold War analogy is the belief that religious fanaticism fuels extremism and therefore replacing Muslims&#8217; worldview with Western liberalism is the path to victory against terrorism. To begin to understand the danger of this diagnosis, we must first understand the factors that do and do not drive sympathy for violence.<br />As a starting point, Muslims do not hold a monopoly on extremist views. While 6% of Americans think attacks in which civilians are targets are &#8220;completely justified,&#8221; in both Lebanon and Iran, this figure is 2%, and in Saudi Arabia, it&#8217;s 4%. In Europe, Muslims in Paris and London were no more likely than were their counterparts in the general public to believe attacks on civilians are ever justified and at least as likely to reject violence, even for a &#8220;noble cause.&#8221;<br />After analyzing survey data representing more than 90% of the global Muslim population, Gallup found that despite widespread anti-American sentiment, only a small minority saw the 9/11 attacks as morally justified. Even more significant, there was no correlation between level of religiosity and extremism among respondents. Among the 7% of the population that fits in the politically radicalized category &#8212; those who saw the 9/11 attacks as completely justifiable and have an unfavorable view of the United States &#8212; 94% said religion is an important part of their daily lives, compared with 90% among those in the moderate majority. And no significant difference exists between radicals and moderates in mosque attendance.<br />Gallup probed respondents further and actually asked both those who condoned and condemned extremist acts why they said what they did. The responses fly in the face of conventional wisdom. For example, in Indonesia, the largest Muslim majority country in the world, many of those who condemned terrorism cited humanitarian or religious justifications to support their response. For example, one woman said, &#8220;Killing one life is as sinful as killing the whole world,&#8221; paraphrasing verse 5:32 in the Quran.<br />On the other hand, not a single respondent in Indonesia who condoned the attacks of 9/11 cited the Quran for justification. Instead, this group&#8217;s responses were markedly secular and worldly. For example, one Indonesian respondent said, &#8220;The U.S. government is too controlling toward other countries, seems like colonizing.&#8221;<br />The real difference between those who condone terrorist acts and all others is about politics, not piety. For example, the politically radicalized often cite &#8220;occupation and U.S. domination&#8221; as their greatest fear for their country and only a small minority of them agree the United States would allow people in the region to fashion their own political future or that it is serious about supporting democracy in the region. Also, among this group&#8217;s top responses was the view that to better relations with the Muslim world, the West should respect Islam and stop imposing its beliefs and policies. In contrast, moderates most often mentioned economic problems as their greatest fear for their country, and along with respecting Islam, they see economic support and investments as a way for the West to better relations. Moderates are also more likely than the politically radicalized to say the United States is serious about promoting democracy.<br />While the politically radicalized are as likely as the moderate majority to say better relations with the West is of personal concern to them, they are much less likely to believe the West reciprocates this concern and therefore much less likely to believe improved relations will ever come. In short, perceptions of being under siege characterize those who sympathize with extremism.</p></blockquote>
<p>Several thoughts occur to me. I am also not an expert on these matters so I must rely on readings to try to figure out what is going on and what policy I can reasonably support.</p>
<p>1. I am averse to &#8216;global truths&#8217; because I have never found them adequate to explain human behaviors or produce accurate planning information.<br />2. History often shows the deficiency of such approaches after the fact, which I will not explore on this post. Such perceptions are used to confirm a priori beliefs instead of leading to questions to be solved. Perhaps this is a matter of temperament for some, or calculation for others.<br />3. In a speech, asking questions of nuance is very hum drum and has no punch or ring to it. Advertising needs catchy stimuli to work, so works on our limbic system the most dramatically. As a way to develop policy&#8230;not so good.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2007/09/gallup-world-poll-and-extreme-global-thought.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Reaer Dan on Terrorism, Part 2</title>
		<link>./../../2007/07/reaer-dan-on-terrorism-part-2.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2007/07/reaer-dan-on-terrorism-part-2.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 30 Jul 2007 12:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[terrorism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2007/07/reaer-dan-on-terrorism-part-2.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This post is by Reader Dan&#8230; &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8211; Another try at a serious discussion of terrorism. This post follows up a previous post on terrorismlisting four very general outlooks. This article on electrical grids in Iraq has wider implications than causing havoc in Baghdad. John Robb has an intelligent opinion that covers part of the terrorist [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This post is by Reader Dan&#8230;</p>
<p>&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8211;</p>
<p>Another try at a serious discussion of terrorism.</p>
<p>This post follows up a previous post on terrorism<a href="http://angrybear.blogspot.com/2007/06/reader-dan-mulling-over-definition-of.html">listing four very general outlooks</a>.</p>
<p><a href="http://globalguerrillas.typepad.com/globalguerrillas/2006/12/losing_the_batt.html">This article</a> on electrical grids in Iraq has wider implications than causing havoc in Baghdad. John Robb has an intelligent opinion that covers part of the terrorist movement in Iraq.</p>
<blockquote><p>The <em>aha</em> moment for Iraq&#8217;s global guerrillas when they discovered how to accomplish an <a href="http://globalguerrillas.typepad.com/globalguerrillas/2005/06/effects_based_o.html">effects based operation</a> using broad-based systems disruption:</p>
<blockquote><p>Electricity officials say the decisive moment came July 6, when saboteurs mounted coordinated attacks across the country, gaining a lead in the battle that the government has not been able to reverse. “They targeted all the lines at the same time, and they all came down,” Mr. Abbo said. Mr. Abbo said a typical strategy was to set off explosives at the four support points of a single tower, which would then pull down two or three more towers as it toppled. As repair crews moved in hours or days later, another tower farther up the line might be struck, and then another, in a race the government had little chance of winning.</p></blockquote>
<p>NOTE: this is a great example of how ideas are driving the evolution of warfare and will ultimately decide the winners and losers in this long war. It&#8217;s interesting to note that the DoD doesn&#8217;t have a mechanism for purchasing ideas that would help them win. They can spend trillions on contextually useless weapons systems and personnel but can barely free up a couple of thousand dollars on the ideas necessary to win this war (let alone a couple of million on a research firm dedicated to this).</p></blockquote>
<p>And another outlook comes from <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/26/world/middleeast/26insurgency.html?ei=5088&#038;en=1bd1f805c30e2ae2&#038;ex=1322197200&#038;partner=rssnyt&#038;emc=rss&#038;pagewanted=all">this article</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>While such data may have been omitted to protect the group’s clandestine sources and methods — the document has a bold heading on the front page saying “secret” and a warning that it is not to be shared with foreign governments — several security and intelligence consultants said in telephone interviews that the vagueness of the estimates reflected how little American intelligence agencies knew about the opaque and complex world of Iraq’s militant groups.</p>
<p>“They’re just guessing,” said W. Patrick Lang, a former chief of Middle East intelligence at the Defense Intelligence Agency, who now runs a security and intelligence consultancy. “They really have no idea.” He added, “They’ve been very unsuccessful in penetrating these organizations.” He said he was equally skeptical about the report’s assertion that the insurgent and militant groups may have surpluses to finance terrorism outside Iraq. “That’s another guess,” he said.</p>
<p>“A judgment like that, coming from an N.S.C.-generated document,” he said, is not an analytical assessment as much as it is a political statement to support the administration’s contention that Iraq is a central front in the war on terrorism. “It’s a statement put in there to support a policy judgment,” he said.</p>
<p>Several analysts said that, except for the possibility that Al Qaeda of Mesopotamia might be transferring money to Qaeda factions elsewhere, the assertion that insurgent money might be flowing out of the country was doubtful considering the single-minded regional focus of most of the militants operating here.</p>
<p>Dr. Magnus Ranstorp of the Swedish National Defense College, an author of extensive studies of the Iraqi insurgency, said he doubted Iraqi groups were ready to finance terrorism outside the country. “There’s very little evidence that they’re preparing to export terrorism from Iraq to the West,” he said. “I think it’s much too early for that.”</p>
<p>The document tracing the money flows acknowledges that investigators have had limited success in penetrating or choking off terrorist financing networks. The report says American efforts to follow the financing trails have been hamstrung by several factors. They include a weak Iraqi government and its nascent intelligence agencies; a lack of communication between American agencies, and between the Americans and the Iraqis; and the nature of the insurgent economy itself, primarily sustained by couriers carrying cash rather than more easily traceable means involving banks and the hawala money transfer networks traditional in the Middle East.</p></blockquote>
<p>If we are not nimble enough and are consistently out maneuvered, at least in the public part of the problem, it seems we will be constantly leveraged in effort to contain the threat.</p>
<p>Part III will include AQ in SE Asia, where the sophisticated threat is located.</p>
<p>&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8211;</p>
<p>This post was by Reader Dan.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2007/07/reaer-dan-on-terrorism-part-2.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Reader Sammy on Terrorism</title>
		<link>./../../2007/07/reader-sammy-on-terrorism.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2007/07/reader-sammy-on-terrorism.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 05 Jul 2007 11:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[terrorism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2007/07/reader-sammy-on-terrorism.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In the wake of the recent attempted car bombings on London and Glasgow, reader Sammy sends along a link to this article: [W]e are confronted with the uneasy reality that our cosy assumptions about who becomes a terrorist and why have once again been shattered. For most of us, the profile of the suicide bomber [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the wake of the recent attempted car bombings on London and Glasgow, reader Sammy sends along a link to <a href="http://news.scotsman.com/scotland.cfm?id=1038722007">this article</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>[W]e are confronted with the uneasy reality that our cosy assumptions about who becomes a terrorist and why have once again been shattered.</p>
<p>For most of us, the profile of the suicide bomber is not particularly complex: young, male (mostly), religiously devout, alienated, angry, disenfranchised, living on the edges of normal society, poorly integrated, and as a result, socially and psychologically outcast &#8211; what we assume is the perfect recipe for vulnerability to violent radicalisation.</p>
<p>But once again, and with more cases being uncovered across the country, these simplistic attributes we can only dismiss as naive and misleading. Evidence from research at the University of St Andrews tells us that not only has no terrorist profile been found, but that it is unlikely one ever will be. </p></blockquote>
<p><strong>&#8230;</strong></p>
<blockquote><p>We can easily identify what I have termed predisposing risk factors for involvement in terrorism. These include:</p>
<p>• Personal experiences of victimisation (which can be real or imagined);</p>
<p>• Expectations about involvement (for instance the lures &#8211; such as excitement, mission, sense of purpose &#8211; associated with being involved in any &#8220;insider&#8221; group and its various roles);</p>
<p>• Identification with a cause, frequently associated with some victimised community;</p>
<p>• Socialisation through friends or family, or being raised in a particular environment;</p>
<p>• Opportunity for expression of interest and steps towards involvement;</p>
<p>• Access to the relevant group.</p>
<p>It must be stated that individually none of these will ever help explain why people become terrorists but, taken in combination, they do provide a powerful framework for understanding why one person might become involved in terrorism and the other does not.</p></blockquote>
<p>Sammy goes on to note&#8230;</p>
<p>On the contrary, based on every spectacular terror attack on Western soil, and according to a former CIA operative who collected the life histories of almost 400 members of the <a href="http://www.jihadwatch.org/archives/002391.php">deadly movement</a> :</p>
<blockquote><p>The stereotype that these terrorists are poor, desperate, single young men from Third World countries, vulnerable to brainwashing, is wrong, Dr. Marc Sageman told an international terrorism conference in Washington this week.</p>
<p>Most Arab terrorists he studied were well-educated, married men from middle- or upper-class families, in their mid-20s and psychologically stable, said Sageman, a psychiatrist at the University of Pennsylvania in Philadelphia . Many of them knew several languages and traveled widely.</p>
<p>But when they settled in foreign countries, they became lonely, homesick and embittered, he said. They felt humiliated by the weakness and backwardness of their homelands. They formed tight cliques with fellow Arabs and drifted into mosques more for companionship than for religion. Radical preachers convinced them it was their duty to drive Americans from Muslim holy lands, killing as many as possible. â€œ<br />â€œSageman served as a CIA case officer in Afghanistan from 1987 to 1989, running agents against the Soviet occupation. In a book, &#8220;Understanding Terror Networks,&#8221; published in May, he traced the roots of the movement to a centuries-old Islamic tradition dedicated to purifying Muslim lands of &#8220;infidels&#8221; and restoring the past glories of Islam.</p>
<p>He described al-Qaida and its global allies as &#8220;a violent Islamist social movement held together by an idea: the use of violence against foreign and non-Muslim governments or populations to establish an Islamist state in the core Arab region.&#8221;<br />For its members, terrorism is &#8220;an answer to Islamic decadence &#8211; a feeling that Islam has lost its way,&#8221; he said. </p></blockquote>
<p>This is backed up by a very <a href="http://www.dailymail.co.uk/pages/live/articles/news/news.html?in_article_id=465570&#038;in_page_id=1770">authoritative source</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>I was a fanatic..I know their thinking, says former radical Islamist.</p></blockquote>
<p><strong>&#8230;</strong><br />
<blockquote>I remember when we used to laugh in celebration whenever people on TV proclaimed that the sole cause for Islamic acts of terror like 9/11, the Madrid bombings and 7/7 was Western foreign policy. They also helped to draw away any critical examination from the real engine of our violence: Islamic theology. The foundation of extremist reasoning rest upon a model of the world in which your are either a believer or an infidel</p></blockquote>
<p>George Bush&#8217;s idealistic goal in Iraq is that freedom and democracy were the antidote to this. There is some logic <a href="http://chronicle.com/free/v49/i39/39b01001.htm">here</a>:<br />
<blockquote>[T]he only variable that was consistently associated with the number of terrorist was the Freedom House index of political rights and civil liberties. Countries with more freedom were less likely to be the birthplace of international terrorists. Poverty and literacy were unrelated to the number of terrorists from a country. Think of a country like Saudi Arabia : It is wealthy but has few political and civil freedoms. Perhaps it is no coincidence that so many of the September 11 terrorist and Osama bin Laden himself came from there.</p></blockquote>
<p>However, this seems like a longshot at this point.</p>
<p>If not stopped, the terrorists will get more and more powerful weapons, culminating with nuclear. Countries will be subjugated. How do we fight them?</p>
<p>&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8211;</p>
<p>My answer to this goes into the comments section.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2007/07/reader-sammy-on-terrorism.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Reader Dan &#8211; Mulling Over the Definition of Terrorism</title>
		<link>./../../2007/06/reader-dan-mulling-over-the-definition-of-terrorism.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2007/06/reader-dan-mulling-over-the-definition-of-terrorism.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Jun 2007 12:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[terrorism]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2007/06/reader-dan-mulling-over-the-definition-of-terrorism.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Reader Dan continues mulling over what Bob Hormats wrote&#8230; &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8211; Rather than define terrorism itself, which appears to have many forms, goals and objectives, and methods, I have found several responses to the ‘war on terror’ to be more manageable and in line with our recent experience with Mr. Hormats and current media coverage. Several [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Reader Dan continues mulling over what Bob Hormats wrote&#8230;</p>
<p>&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8211;</p>
<p>Rather than define terrorism itself, which appears to have many forms, goals and objectives, and methods, I have found several responses to the ‘war on terror’ to be more manageable and in line with our recent experience with Mr. Hormats and current media coverage.</p>
<p>Several proposals emerged that subsumed different assumptions about the nature of terrorism.</p>
<p>An increasingly sophisticated enemy and wmd oriented against the US, and possibly state sponsored at least indirectly. Beef up US Special Forces etc.<br />Not an increasing threat but scattered and few relative to massive responses so wait and see.<br />An increasingly decentralized and well-funded groups using ultra modern communications and organized to disrupt centralized states. Changed from more traditional terrorists in occupying territory. One response is to decentralize our infrastructure instead of bigger forces.<br />Creation of counter forces like Blackwater to be nimble enough to counter threats and avoids the limitations of national forces.</p>
<p>Number one is <a href="http://www.rand.org/pubs/research_briefs/RB202/index1.html">the Rand Corporation PAF briefing report</a> which states that the global jihadist movement is the biggest challenge:</p>
<blockquote><p>Although the U.S.-led global war on terrorism has had some notable successes — such as the destruction of al-Qaeda’s sanctuary in Afghanistan, the elimination of many of the group’s leaders, and the growing resolve of many countries to take action against al-Qaeda and its associates — no informed observers believe that al-Qaeda will be eradicated any time soon. Indeed, in some respects, al-Qaeda has metastasized into an even more formidable adversary, dispersed across the world, largely self-sustaining, and constantly adopting new and innovative tactics. The United States itself continues to be threatened by large-scale attacks. Thus, countering al-Qaeda is likely to preoccupy U.S. national security institutions for at least the remainder of this decade, and probably longer.</p></blockquote>
<p>Number two is<br /><a href="http://www.foreignaffairs.org/20060901facomment85501-p10/john-mueller/is-there-still-a-terrorist-threat-the-myth-of-the-omnipresent-enemy.html">this point of view, posited by John Mueller</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>On the first page of its founding manifesto, the massively funded Department of Homeland Security intones, &#8220;Today&#8217;s terrorists can strike at any place, at any time, and with virtually any weapon.</p></blockquote>
<p><strong>&#8230;</strong><br />
<blockquote>Given the monumental imperfection of the government&#8217;s response to Hurricane Katrina, and the debacle of FBI and National Security Agency programs to upgrade their computers to better coordinate intelligence information, that explanation seems far-fetched. Moreover, Israel still experiences terrorism even with a far more extensive security apparatus</p></blockquote>
<p><strong>&#8230;</strong><br />
<blockquote>It was in 2003 that al Qaeda&#8217;s top leaders promised attacks in Australia, Bahrain, Egypt, Italy, Japan, Jordan, Kuwait, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, the United States, and Yemen. Three years later, some bombs had gone off in Saudi Arabia, Egypt, Yemen, and Jordan (as well as in the unlisted Turkey) but not in any other of the explicitly threatened countries. Those attacks were tragic, but their sparseness could be taken as evidence that it is not only American alarmists who are given to extravagant huffing and puffing.</p></blockquote>
<p>Number three&#8230; <a href="http://www.d-n-i.net/fcs/robb_opensource_war.htm">John Robb has a different point of view</a> in his article and subsequent book Brave New War, which suggests terrorism has evolved into sort of open source, loosely networked and de-centralized groups of people who learn from each other and are organized to disrupt centralized economies and governments…</p>
<blockquote><p>that the insurgency isn&#8217;t a fragile hierarchical organization but rather a resilient network made up of small, autonomous groups. This means that the insurgency is virtually immune to attrition and decapitation. It will combine and recombine to form a viable network despite high rates of attrition. Body counts &#8211; and the military should already know this &#8211; aren&#8217;t a good predictor of success. </p></blockquote>
<p>David Brooks remarks on Robb:</p>
<blockquote><p>Superempowered global guerrillas — whether it’s Al Qaeda, Iraqi insurgents, Nigerian oil fighters or the Brazilian gang P.C.C. — specialize in what Robb calls systems disruption. They attack the networks that support modern life. In one case, Iraqi insurgents spent roughly $2,000 to blow up an oil pipeline in Southeast Iraq. It cost the Iraqi government $500 million in lost revenue. For the insurgents, that was a return on investment of 25 million percent. </p></blockquote>
<p>The 9/11 attacks, the Madrid bombings, the Niger Delta oil well attacks and even the Samarra mosque bombing were all attempts to disrupt the economic and social systems of target nations.</p>
<p>Number four, from <a href="http://www.tcsdaily.com/article.aspx?id=121606A">Tech Central Station</a>, positing stateless fighting forces for hire, good and bad guys:</p>
<blockquote><p>Stateless warfighting organizations are all the rage these days. From Al Qaeda to Blackwater, they come in all shapes and sizes and pursue all varieties of ends. Consider: Al Qaeda is an organization funded by a Saudi tycoon&#8217;s heir, and exists to pursue strategies that are wholly outside the realm of policies of any given state. Indeed, it seeks to topple the governments of many states in the Middle East, from which it draws many of its recruits and funding.</p>
<p>(Other names in describing terrorism Zakaria, Huntington, Fukuyama, Barnet are useful for older forms of terrorism that we are used to thinking about)</p></blockquote>
<p>I also note that this description has no punch and would not be useful for marketing or framing the ‘war on terror’.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2007/06/reader-dan-mulling-over-the-definition-of-terrorism.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
