<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>shock doctrine &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Michael Hudson on Greece</title>
		<link>./../../2012/02/michael-hudson-on-greece.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/02/michael-hudson-on-greece.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2012 16:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[austerity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Banking Crisis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Greece]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[shock doctrine]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/02/michael-hudson-on-greece.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Greece and what is happening to it is not getting enough attention.  What is happening there, in my opinion is an example of the human race at it&#8217;s worse.  I do not see the implementation of austerity as an experiment.  I see it as just one more step by those in the world controlling banking [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Greece and what is happening to it is not getting enough attention.  What is happening there, in my opinion is an example of the human race at it&#8217;s worse.  I do not see the implementation of austerity as an experiment.  I see it as just one more step by those in the world controlling banking to mold the world into its self image.</p>
<p>This <a href="http://www.commondreams.org/video/2012/02/15">is a link to</a> an 11 minute interview of <a href="http://michael-hudson.com/about/">Michael Hudson</a>:  Michael Hudson is President of The Institute for the Study of Long-Term  Economic Trends (ISLET), a Wall Street Financial Analyst, Distinguished  Research Professor of Economics at the University of Missouri, Kansas  City&#8230;  </p>
<p>In this interview, Prof. Hudson suggests that Greece is the test to see how far the world&#8217;s money people can push in preparations for further advancement within the EU.  Interestingly he notes, that in the US, because we privatized our utilities years ago, we are not seeing the same drive of austerity as we are seeing in Europe, including England.  Though we should not be complaisant.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/02/michael-hudson-on-greece.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>It&#8217;s not the tax and spending cuts, it&#8217;s the destroyed trust that has doomed our economy</title>
		<link>./../../2011/08/its-not-the-tax-and-spending-cuts-its-the-destroyed-trust-that-has-doomed-our-economy.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/08/its-not-the-tax-and-spending-cuts-its-the-destroyed-trust-that-has-doomed-our-economy.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2011 17:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[crisis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economic growth]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GDP]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obama economic policy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[shock doctrine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wealth creation]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/08/its-not-the-tax-and-spending-cuts-its-the-destroyed-trust-that-has-doomed-our-economy.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[By Daniel Becker In the comments to my post &#8220;A reminder from Obama&#8217;s February 2009 speech&#8221;, there is the following: &#8220;I guess it relates to the fake Obama they had made up in their heads,&#8230;&#8221;  This sums up the early comments to the post suggesting that those who trusted Obama have only themselves to blame. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>By Daniel Becker</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>In the comments to my post <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2011/08/reminder-from-obamas-february-2009.html">&#8220;A reminder from Obama&#8217;s February 2009 speech&#8221;</a>, there is the following:</div>
<div></div>
<blockquote><div>&#8220;I guess it relates to the fake Obama they had made up in their heads,&#8230;&#8221; </div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div>This sums up the early comments to the post suggesting that those who trusted Obama have only themselves to blame.</div>
<div></div>
<div>I addressed that concept in <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2008/11/obama-is-he-or-isnt-he-real.html">Obama, is he or isn&#8217;t he real&#8230;?</a>  In that post I presented transcripts of Obama&#8217;s speeches and responses to questions and then argued:   </div>
<div></div>
<blockquote><div>&#8220;Are those talking like Glen Greenwald correct in that people should not be surprised with Obama&#8217;s appointments? Maybe, but then based on the above Obama words, that would mean we (you and I) just plain have to approach our relationship with governing as suspect until proven otherwise. Unfortunately, that means we will always be a day late and a dollar short having never known at the time of the decision if we made the correct one because you can not go by what is said.&#8221;</div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>I recommend people go and not only read the posting, but the comments.  (History is always fun to review.)</div>
<div></div>
<div>I concluded that posting with:</div>
<div></div>
<blockquote><div> &#8220;Do you know what happens to a person when they can never get a straight, no hidden agenda answer from one they count on? They go nuts.&#8221;</div>
</blockquote>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />
<hr xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">  
<div>This all speaks to the issue of growing our economy, because to promote distrust in a developed economy where 77% of our capital is intangible (via 2005 World Bank study) is to be destroying the prime driver of our growth. I wrote about the issue of were our true wealth comes from a few times.  For this posting I am drawing on<a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2009/02/attention-republicansblue-dog.html"> Attention Republicans/Blue Dog Democrates: Tax cuts as stimulus work against your goal.</a></div>
<div>February 5, 2009.  </div>
<div></div>
<div>From the World Bank study:  </div>
<div></div>
<blockquote><div>“An economy with a very efficient judicial system, clear and enforceable property rights, and an effective and uncorrupt government will produce higher total wealth.”</div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>I concluded:</div>
<div></div>
<blockquote><div> &#8220;The republicans/blue dogs, and those helping them by lending their &#8220;professionalism&#8221;, think they are only effecting a political strategy. In truth, they are destroying the very basis for the wealth they desire. Their entire campaign for decades to discredit, to instill mistrust in the primary institution we have, the US (We the People) government, has been the primary cause to our economic decline. To increase the level of distrust is to decrease the available “intangible capital” which is 77% of our wealth generating power. &#8220;</div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>Which brings us to what we just experienced with the debt ceiling issue.  It&#8217;s not just the resulting budget changes, it&#8217;s the overall cognitive change being made in the people regarding trust of our ability to access a candidate and make the choice that will produce the desired results.  Clinton, as for the Dems made the first blow to our trust with &#8220;triangulation&#8221;.  I can and have on my own gone back and read speeches and answers to questions by Clinton during his first run and it shows the same as I note regarding Obama in &#8220;is he or isn&#8217;t he real&#8221;.  Obama is (knowingly or not) bringing our trust close to death.   </div>
<div>Even the debt ceiling event is only the latest in a string of recent events that all drive an additional spike into the coffin of &#8220;trust&#8221;.   </div>
<div></div>
<div>Last night on Racheal Maddow&#8217;s show, Chris Hayes, noted that we are now in a phase of governance where &#8220;created&#8221; crisis is the vehicle for results.  Yes, Shock Doctrine governance level II..  It was presented from the perspective that the conservative mind set is the one employing such a tactic.</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>Visit msnbc.com for <a href="http://www.msnbc.msn.com/">breaking news</a>, <a href="http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/3032507">world news</a>, and <a href="http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/3032072">news about the economy</a></div>
<p>
<div></div>
<div>  In my opinion, what he missed, and what makes this a unique form to this nation&#8217;s version of Naomie Klein&#8217;s  Shock Doctrine is that there are enough economically conservative minded people in the opposing party (democratic party in this case) that the ruse can be played out with a more believable presentation than if just one side is playing along.  Yes, both side play it differently, but would that not be expected based on the supposed &#8220;base party&#8221; paradigms?  At no time during any of these &#8220;crisis&#8221; did the primary players on the democratic side resist the crisis by calling it out.  Instead, they used it to get what the conservative faction of the party (a smaller faction since the last election) wants. These &#8220;wants&#8221; being very much inline with the republican non Norquist/Tea Party faction&#8217;s wants.  Commonly referenced as  Wall Street.  In the end, no one to blame&#8230;It was the crisis.  </div>
<div></div>
<div>This pattern has held true through out Obama&#8217;s current term.  In the latest example, the proposed budget from the house progressive caucus, the largest of the democratic party caucuses never was mentioned by the president.  Recall the single payer health insurance issue? </div>
<div></div>
<div>The issue for this posting is not the &#8220;wants&#8221;.  It is not about the resulting policy from the latest ruse played on We the People.  The prime issue, the issue always suggested, implied, bandied about, but never out and out confronted: Public Trust.   </div>
<div></div>
<div>This latest Obama/conservative policy process has brought us closer than ever to the demise of our economy and thus our democracy not primarily by the furthering of the financial disequilibrium, but by the perpetuation and enlarging of the perimeters of social order that will now be distrusted.  I think we have approached, if not completely included the full boundaries of American culture in that which is to be distrusted with the completion of this debt crisis event. </div>
<div></div>
<div>Sadly, I do not think Obama and those referred to as the &#8220;adults in the room&#8221; know what they have done.  Instead. as I stated above, they believe they are just &#8220;effecting a political strategy&#8221;. </div>
<div></div>
<div> </div>
<div>There are 2 versions of distrust.  First is the distrust nurtured by those who have made it a political tool of their strategy for political dominance, power and fortune.  It is the &#8220;&#8230;most dangerous words in the English language: I am from the government and I am here to help you&#8221;.  These people do not know that in essence their distrust is part of the ruse.  The other distrust is those who see the ruse, have acted via those they trusted only to find they can no longer be trusted.  I don&#8217;t believe one is worse than the other, but I do know having both means the solution will be slower in materializing.  In both cases those in power can not be trusted and those who know it, presently have no one in power to represent their solutions.  It serves to make the what is the solution clear, it does not server to make it any easier or quicker in coming. </div>
<div></div>
<div> </div>
<div>I do not believe this mode of operation is forever simply because we are not naturally selfish, self serving for survival sake creatures. We are not naturally so shallow in our collective thinking.  It is only in our isolated, individual thought that we can and will be shallow.  Of course this assumes that the concepts and application of virtual reality throughout our daily lives does not mutate us way from our natural self.   A big assumption considering &#8220;reality&#8221; is in the phrase &#8220;virtual reality&#8221; and the character dynamic is trust.    </div>
<div>  </div>
<div></div>
<div> </div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/08/its-not-the-tax-and-spending-cuts-its-the-destroyed-trust-that-has-doomed-our-economy.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
