<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>WTF &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Wanker of Two Days Ago</title>
		<link>./../../2008/06/wanker-of-two-days-ago.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/06/wanker-of-two-days-ago.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2008 13:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[21st Century economic philosophy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WTF]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/06/wanker-of-two-days-ago.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Dalton Conley. 1. Conley actually wrote this for publication in the New York Times: The truth is that the triumph of conservative ideas may present a political problem for the ailing Republicans, but the party that&#8217;s truly lacking in ideas is my own, the resurgent Democrats. Yeah, that triumph of conservative ideas is why the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/06/22/magazine/22wwln-idealab-t.html?ref=magazine">Dalton Conley</a>.</p>
<p>1. Conley actually wrote this for publication in the New York Times:<br />
<blockquote>The truth is that the triumph of conservative ideas may present a political problem for the ailing Republicans, but the party that&#8217;s truly lacking in ideas is my own, the resurgent Democrats.</p></blockquote>
<p>Yeah, that <a href="http://www.econbrowser.com/archives/2008/06/housing_and_the.html">triumph</a> <a href="http://thepoorman.net/2008/06/18/shrill-3/">of</a> <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2008/apr/06/3trillionmaybetoolow">conservative</a> <a href="http://www.samefacts.com/archives/campaign_2008_/2008/06/it_would_be_a_big_advantage_to_him.php">ideas</a> is why the Republicans are in trouble.</p>
<p>2. In making the case for #1, Conley has trouble distinguishing the (vanishing) postwar corporatist &#8220;social compact&#8221; from the New Deal and Great Society programs, and figuring out that what&#8217;s &#8220;trouble&#8221; for the former is not obviously problematic for the government social insurance programs that are the hallmarks of the latter.</p>
<p>3. Conley mentions possible policy directions like government intervention to form health insurance pools and absorb other economic risks, and the &#8220;soft paternalism&#8221; movement, without noting that such things are hallmarks of Democratic policy, not Republican policy.  For instance, making the government the reinsurer of last resort was the centerpiece of John Kerry&#8217;s health care plan, and arguably the prominent advocate of &#8220;soft paternalism&#8221; is Cass Sunstein — a friend and informal advisor to last-time-I-checked-not-Republican Barack Obama.</p>
<p>4. Conley concludes that Democrats should &#8220;stop talking F.D.R., J.F.K. and L.B.J. and start thinking eBay, Google, and Wiki.&#8221; So the road to prosperity is paved with collaboratively advertising sales of used stuff to each other?!  <em>Great</em> program.</p>
<p>(Cross-posted at <a href="http://scatter.wordpress.com/">Scatterplot</a>.)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/06/wanker-of-two-days-ago.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mysteries of Airline Management</title>
		<link>./../../2008/06/mysteries-of-airline-management.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/06/mysteries-of-airline-management.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2008 13:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[transportation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[WTF]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/06/mysteries-of-airline-management.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[NWA has joined the crowd of domestic airlines announcing (even more) capacity reductions, and their announcement contains this head-scratcher: As a result of the reduced capacity, Northwest is removing a combination of 14 B757s and Airbus narrowbody aircraft from the fleet. In addition, the DC-9 fleet will be reduced from 94 aircraft at the start [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>NWA has <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/06/18/business/18air.html">joined the crowd</a> of domestic airlines announcing (even more) capacity reductions, and their <a href="http://www.nwa.com/corpinfo/newsc/2008/pr061720082015.html">announcement</a> contains this head-scratcher:<br />
<blockquote>As a result of the reduced capacity, Northwest is removing a combination of 14 B757s and Airbus narrowbody aircraft from the fleet.</p>
<p>In addition, the DC-9 fleet will be reduced from 94 aircraft at the start of 2008 to 61 aircraft (20 DC9-30s and 41 DC9-40s/50s) by year-end.  [Emphasis added.]</p></blockquote>
<p>The DC-9s have been overdue for retirement for some time, so that part of the reduction makes sense enough.  Parking the Airbuses, not so much when there are DC-9s still to retire.  While they are a bit big compared to the DC-9-50 (to the tune of around 25 seats; the A319 is the direct substitute in terms of seating capacity), the <a href="http://www.transtats.bts.gov/Fields.asp?Table_ID=297">cost statistics</a> via NWA&#8217;s latest filings with the DOT indicate that the A320 is cheaper to fly than any DC-9 in flying operations expenses.  Significantly, fuel issuance is considerably less for the bigger and heavier A320 even versus the 105-seat DC-9-30 (937 gallons/hour vs. 1039-1215 [*]).  Plus, you know, there are more seats to sell (or offer someone an empty middle seat, remember those?).</p>
<p>Maybe there&#8217;s something about the particular planes they want to park (that isn&#8217;t also something about the ancient DC-9s)?  Otherwise, it looks like someone has their head up a fleet planning model.</p>
<p>[*] Note the decarbonization potential from replacing the relatively aged domestic airline fleet.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/06/mysteries-of-airline-management.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
