<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>leisure inequality &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Consumption inequality and income inequality</title>
		<link>./../../2012/04/consumption-inequality-and-income-inequality.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/04/consumption-inequality-and-income-inequality.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 29 Apr 2012 13:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[income inequality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[leisure inequality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Taxprof blog]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/04/consumption-inequality-and-income-inequality.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[From the same post at Taxprofblog, a different study presents data and definitions on a related issue, but focused on income, which is a somewhat separate and overlapping conversation: Orazio Attanasio (University College London, Department of Economics), Erik Hurst (University of Chicago, Booth School of Business) &#038; Luigi Pistaferri (Stanford University, Department of Economics), The Evolution of [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>From the same post at <a href="http://taxprof.typepad.com/taxprof_blog/2012/04/do-the-1-work-harder-than-the-99.html" target="_blank">Taxprofblog</a>, a different study presents data and definitions on a related issue, but focused on income, which is a somewhat separate and overlapping conversation:<br />
<blockquote><a href="http://www.homepages.ucl.ac.uk/~uctpjrt/">Orazio Attanasio</a> (University College London, Department of Economics), <a href="http://www.chicagobooth.edu/faculty/bio.aspx?person_id=12825092096">Erik Hurst</a> (University of Chicago, Booth School of Business) &#038; <a href="http://www.stanford.edu/~pista/">Luigi Pistaferri</a> (Stanford University, Department of Economics), <a href="http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2035781">The Evolution of Income, Consumption, and Leisure Inequality in the US, 1980-2010</a> (<a href="http://www.nber.org/papers/w17982">NBER</a>):</p>
<p><em>Recent research has documented that income inequality in the United States has increased dramatically over the prior three decades. There has been less of a consensus, however, on whether the increase in income inequality was matched by an equally large increase in consumption inequality. Most researchers have studied this question using data from the Consumer Expenditure Survey (CE)</em></p>
<p><em>&#8230;</em><br /><em> </em></p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p><em>All of our different methods yield similar results. We find that consumption inequality within the U.S. between 1980 and 2010 has increased by nearly the same amount as income inequality</em></p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/04/consumption-inequality-and-income-inequality.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Do the 1% Work Harder Than the 99%?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/04/do-the-1-work-harder-than-the-99.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/04/do-the-1-work-harder-than-the-99.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 29 Apr 2012 11:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[income inequality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[leisure inequality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Taxprof blog]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/04/do-the-1-work-harder-than-the-99.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Taxprofblog offers two studies on income and leisure that should spark some discussion.  I have split the two studies out to two posts at Angry Bear as they are somewhat different conversations: Income Inequality and Leisure Inequality: Do the 1% Work Harder Than the 99%? Wall Street Journal Wealth Report, Do the Wealthy Work Harder Than [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://taxprof.typepad.com/taxprof_blog/2012/04/do-the-1-work-harder-than-the-99.html">Taxprofblog</a> offers two studies on income and leisure that should spark some discussion.  I have split the two studies out to two posts at <strong>Angry Bear</strong> as they are somewhat different conversations:<br />
<blockquote><em>Income Inequality and Leisure Inequality: Do the 1% Work Harder Than the 99%?</em></p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>Wall Street Journal Wealth Report, <a href="http://blogs.wsj.com/wealth/2012/04/27/do-the-wealthy-work-harder-than-the-rest/?mod=WSJBlog">Do the Wealthy Work Harder Than the Rest?</a>, by Robert Frank:</p></blockquote>
<p>
<blockquote><em>A new study [below] offers evidence that higher-educated (and therefore higher-earning)  Americans do indeed spend more time working and less time on leisure than poorer income groups. In fact, while income inequality may be growing, “leisure inequality” – time spent on enjoyment – is growing as a mirror image, with the low earners gaining leisure and the high earners losing.</em></p></blockquote>
<p><em><br /></em><br />
<blockquote><em>The more surprising discovery, however, is a corresponding leisure gap has opened up between the highly-educated and less-educated. Low-educated men saw their leisure hours grow to 39.1 hours in 2003-2007, from 36.6 hours in 1985. Highly-educated men saw their leisure hours shrink to 33.2 hours from 34.4 hours. &#8230; A similar pattern emerged for women. Low-educated women saw their leisure time grow to 35.2 hours a week from 35 hours. High-educated women saw their leisure time decrease to 30.3 hours from 32.2 hours. &#8230; (The study defines leisure as time spend watching TV, socializing, playing games, talking on the phone, reading personal email, enjoying entertainment and hobbies and other activities.) &#8230;</em></p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/04/do-the-1-work-harder-than-the-99.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
