<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Tax Relief Coalition &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Dealing with the Sunset of the Bush Tax Cuts (Part IV in a series)&#8211;the Tax Relief Coalition</title>
		<link>./../../2010/08/dealing-with-the-sunset-of-the-bush-tax-cuts-part-iv-in-a-series-the-tax-relief-coalition.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/08/dealing-with-the-sunset-of-the-bush-tax-cuts-part-iv-in-a-series-the-tax-relief-coalition.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 26 Aug 2010 12:46:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[economic conditions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Job creation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lobbying]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[small business]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tax Legislation. Bush tax cuts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tax Relief Coalition]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/08/dealing-with-the-sunset-of-the-bush-tax-cuts-part-iv-in-a-series-the-tax-relief-coalition.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Bealecrossposted with Ataxingmatter Dealing with the Sunset of the Bush Tax Cuts (Part IV in a series)&#8211;the Tax Relief Coalition The Tax Relief Coalition&#8211;another of the myriad anti-tax groups comprised of Grover Norquist&#8217;s group and those of similar ideology&#8211;is at it again with a letter to Congress (available on BNA) urging the passage [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by <strong>Linda Beale</strong><br />crossposted with <a target="_blank" href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/">Ataxingmatter</a></p>
<p><a target="_blank" href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2010/08/dealing-with-the-sunset-of-the-bush-tax-cuts-part-iv-in-a-seriesthe-tax-relief-coalition.html"><strong>Dealing with the Sunset of the Bush Tax Cuts (Part IV in a series)&#8211;the Tax Relief Coalition</strong></a></p>
<p>The Tax Relief Coalition&#8211;another of the myriad anti-tax groups  comprised of Grover Norquist&#8217;s group and those of similar ideology&#8211;is at it again with a <a target="_blank" href="http://op.bna.com/dt.nsf/id/egrr-88lsgd/%24File/tax.relief.coalition.letter.pdf">letter to Congress</a> (available on BNA) urging the passage of new legislation to pass tax cuts to extend the temporary cuts enacted under the Bush administration.  The group is spending millions lobby for its interests with the dubious claim that discontinuing tax cuts for the wealthiest Americans will hit small businesses the hardest.  See, e.g., Jensen &#038; Salant, <a target="_blank" href="http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2010-08-20/leader-on-bush-tax-cuts-lines-up-backers-to-keep-provisions-from-expiring.html">Leader on Bush Tax Cuts Wins Allies to Keep Provisions in Place</a>, Bloomberg.com (Aug. 20, 2010) (noting that the coalition groups have spent $3.8 million since Jan. 1, 2009 on candidates and advertising, and that the Chamber of Commerce plans to spend $75 million influencing elections in its favor).</p>
<p>Note that the coalition&#8211;formed of &#8220;trade associations, advocacy groups, and corporations&#8221;&#8211;calls itself favoring &#8220;pro-growth tax policies&#8221;.  But what it means is favoring tax cuts.  It is arguable that tax cuts support economic growth&#8211;at best they are a second-rate stimulus compared to direct government spending on public and human infrastructure that provides long-term support for economic stability&#8211; such as public transportation, public communication networks, development of alternative energy sources, education (K1-university), and basic research.</p>
<p>These claims that the tax cuts help small businesses are at best dubious.  (See, e.g.,  yesterday&#8217;s post outlining various reasons why the capital gains preference has very little to do with stimulating entreprenuership or helping small businesses.)  The coalition tries to cast the Bush tax cuts in terms of job creation.  But the fact is, the Bush regime had a lousy record for job creation, and the tax cuts that were especially favorable to corporations probably did almost nothing to contribute to job creation.  The &#8220;American Job Creation Act of 2004&#8221; for example, mainly acted as a tax cut for multinational corporations that used the very low taxation of repatriated money to pay big dividends to shareholders even while they were laying off thousands of workers.  Similarly, expensing provisions and other tax cut provisions (especially for oil and gas industry and other targeted industrial provisions) mainly gave more money to managers and owners, not workers.  Real wages of workers have fallen, while corporations sit on big kitties of cash&#8211;keeping the productivity gains for managers and owners and not sharing them with workers and certainly not creating new jobs for new workers.<br /><a name="more"></a><br />What about the small company owners that the National Federal of Independent Business brings in to calim that any tax increase is a job killer?  See Bloomberg article, above.  That&#8217;s a superficially self-serving claim that is probably in truth a case of blind greed keeping business owners from admitting that federal dollars spent for unemployment, infrastructure, education and other important programs will actually create a more sustainable economy that will be better for their businesses.  A little bit more in taxes now will have positive impact, not negative, on the economy.  And those arguments also leave out a few of the details&#8211;like the fact that the proposed tax increase on joint returns with $250,000 or more impacts very, very few small businesses.  </p>
<p>The hypocrisy is also evident, as coalition members refuse to limit extension of the tax breaks to the lower income group, even while they complain about deficits.  The deficit argument is essentially brought out to create fear in  average voters and to provide a salient objection to any additional spending that does not directly go to the benefit of business managers and owners, but it isn&#8217;t a real concern since it doesn&#8217;t enter into the discussion of whether or not to extend tax breaks to the wealthy who don&#8217;t need them.</p>
<p>Regretably, the Democrats don&#8217;t have much backbone on this issue.  Senators Conrad and Bayh, for example, have accepted the idea that it is problematic to raise taxes on anybody during an economic slowdown.   That their position doesn&#8217;t make sense&#8211;a little bit more in taxes on the wealthiest Americans won&#8217;t really affect either consumption or investment in new businesses&#8211;doesn&#8217;t seem to matter.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/08/dealing-with-the-sunset-of-the-bush-tax-cuts-part-iv-in-a-series-the-tax-relief-coalition.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
