<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>arms sales &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Arms races and sales and Sunday reading&#8230;</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/arms-races-and-sales-and-sunday-reading.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/arms-races-and-sales-and-sunday-reading.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 Jan 2013 07:07:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[arms sales]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[calculator]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sunday reading]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/arms-races-and-sales-and-sunday-reading.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[From Reuters comes this piece on arms spending: Demand for big-ticket U.S. weapons is expected to stay strong for at least the next few years, the trade group said in a 2012 year-end review and forecast released in December.Fears resulting from China&#8217;s growing military spending (bolding mine&#8230;the US has about 4.8% spending to GDP ratio) [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>From <a href="http://www.reuters.com/article/2013/01/01/us-usa-asia-arms-sales-idUSBRE90005D20130101?article" target="_blank">Reuters</a> comes this piece on arms spending:</p>
<blockquote><p>Demand for big-ticket U.S. weapons is expected to stay strong for at least the next few years, the trade group said in a 2012 year-end review and forecast released in December.<br />Fears resulting from China&#8217;s growing military spending (bolding mine&#8230;the US has about <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/08/27/us-arms-sales-2011_n_1833602.html#slide=504167US...4.8%25">4.8% spending to GDP ratio</a>) should lead to enough U.S. sales in South and East Asia to more than offset a slowdown in European arms-buying, according to the forecast.</p></blockquote>
<p>(Dan here:) The graph offers a year to year estimate of China&#8217;s spending to GDP ratio.  What am I  missing?</p>
<div><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-JxKgFLlY6GU/UO7atuiz5RI/AAAAAAAABW0/MD74AmaOmTo/s1600/chinaarms.PNG" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="320" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-JxKgFLlY6GU/UO7atuiz5RI/AAAAAAAABW0/MD74AmaOmTo/s640/chinaarms.PNG" width="640"></a></div>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />The article continues&#8230;<br />
<blockquote>The trade group, whose members include Pentagon suppliers Lockheed Martin Corp, Boeing Co and Northrop Grumman Corp, did not put numbers to its 2013 forecast. Nor did the Pentagon&#8217;s Defense Security Cooperation Agency, which has overseen a boom in worldwide deals under President Barack Obama.</p>
<p>The security agency, in response to a Reuters request, said sales agreements with countries in the U.S. Pacific Command&#8217;s area of activity rose to $13.7 billion in fiscal 2012, up 5.4 percent from a year before. Such pacts represent orders for future delivery.</p>
<p>In 2012 there were about 65 notifications to Congress of proposed government-brokered foreign military sales with a combined potential value of more than $63 billion. In addition, the State Department office that regulates direct commercial sales was on track to receive more than 85,000 license requests in 2012, a new record.</p>
<p>Overall, the United States reached arms transfer agreements in 2011 totaling $66.3 billion, or nearly 78 percent of all such worldwide pacts, according to the nonpartisan Congressional Research Service. The 2011 total was swollen by a record $33.4 billion deal with Saudi Arabia. India ranked second with $6.9 billion in such agreements.</p>
<p><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-AGiYRSvHvX0/UO7auBYwieI/AAAAAAAABXA/Gfm7qQcG8yI/s1600/chinaarms2.PNG" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="232" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-AGiYRSvHvX0/UO7auBYwieI/AAAAAAAABXA/Gfm7qQcG8yI/s320/chinaarms2.PNG" width="320"></a>Rupert Hammond-Chambers, who consults for U.S. arms makers through BowerGroupAsia, an advisory with 10 offices in the region, predicted Southeast Asian defense budgets would expand steadily as a hedge against Chinese assertiveness in disputes in the South China and East China seas.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/arms-races-and-sales-and-sunday-reading.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>What is Bahrain?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/09/what-is-bahrain.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/09/what-is-bahrain.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Sep 2012 14:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[arms sales]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bahrain]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[foriegn policy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[military spending]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/09/what-is-bahrain.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Nick Turse at Tom Dispatch reminds us amid the election flurry&#8230; Secretary of State Hillary Clinton was unequivocal in her condemnation. “We have confronted the Russians about stopping their continued arms shipments to Syria,” she said in remarks earlier this year. “They have, from time to time, said that we shouldn’t worry; everything they’re shipping [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Nick Turse at <a href="http://www.tomdispatch.com/post/175594/tomgram%3A_jen_marlowe%2C_the_%22secret%22_revolution_that_could_set_the_middle_east_aflame/?utm_source=TomDispatch&#038;utm_campaign=b0620ac92a-T">Tom Dispatch</a> reminds us amid the election flurry&#8230;<br />
<blockquote>Secretary of State Hillary Clinton was unequivocal in her condemnation. “We have confronted the Russians about stopping their continued arms shipments to Syria,” she said in <a href="http://www.state.gov/secretary/rm/2012/06/192200.htm">remarks</a> earlier this year. “They have, from time to time, said that we shouldn’t worry; everything they’re shipping is unrelated to their actions internally. That’s patently untrue.”</p>
<p>…</p>
<p>&#8230;year earlier, the ruling Sunni minority of the tiny Persian Gulf kingdom had unleashed its security forces on pro-democracy protesters, leaving many wounded or dead, while others were arrested and tortured. The <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766">U.S. government</a>, which bases the Navy’s Fifth Fleet in Bahrain, stayed largely silent about the abuses and then, a few months later, the Department of Defense notified Congress that it had brokered a new arms deal with the country. The Pentagon had arranged for the sale of $53 million worth of weapons and equipment &#8212; 44 armored Humvees and hundreds of TOW missiles &#8212; to Bahrain’s oil-rich monarchy.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Despite some Congressional opposition, the Obama administration used a legal loophole to move forward with the sale, without any formal public notification, according to a January report by <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766">Foreign Policy</a>. (The Defense Security Cooperation Agency, the branch of the Pentagon<strong> </strong>that coordinates sales and transfers of military equipment to allies, did not respond to TomDispatch’s request for information on the current status of the arms deal.)</p>
<p>Even if had there been public notice of the sale in the U.S., the response would, at best, have been muted. While American media outlets followed the revolutions in Tunisia and Egypt closely, covered Libya’s revolution with zeal, and have remained focused on the brutal civil war in Syria, the story of Bahrain’s popular, largely nonviolent uprising has largely been limited to scattered coverage and wire service roundups. Thankfully, TomDispatch’s <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766">Jen Marlowe</a> traveled to Bahrain this summer to witness the continuing uprising and the brutal government response firsthand, before being detained and then <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766">thrown out</a> of the country. She offers a ground-level view of the “secret” revolution that few Americans have been able to follow and the reasons why they need to.</p>
<p>Earlier this year, armored vehicles <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766">patrolled</a> the streets after Bahrain’s security forces battled protesters on the first anniversary of the 2011 uprising. Next year, thanks to the Obama administration, they may have brand new American Humvees on hand for the crackdown.      <em>Nick Turse</em></p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/09/what-is-bahrain.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
