<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>David Brooks &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>David Brooks Bemoans the Low Standards of Living in Australia, Canada, Germany, Holland, Sweden, Norway, Denmark and Finland</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/david-brooks-bemoans-the-low-standards-of-living-in-australia-canada-germany-holland-sweden-norway-denmark-and-finland.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/david-brooks-bemoans-the-low-standards-of-living-in-australia-canada-germany-holland-sweden-norway-denmark-and-finland.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2013 17:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[David Brooks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Joseph E. Stiglitz]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The New York Times]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/david-brooks-bemoans-the-low-standards-of-living-in-australia-canada-germany-holland-sweden-norway-denmark-and-finland.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In his NYT column today, David Brooks employs his standard column-writing formula of plucking two or more unrelated facts from their context and specifics, putting them into a sequence, and&#8211;voila!&#8211;suggesting a causal relationship, or at least a relationship of some sort, and therefore some conclusory fact.   This time around, he does it in the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">In his NYT <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/03/19/opinion/brooks-the-progressive-shift.html">column today</a>, David Brooks  employs his standard column-writing formula of plucking two or more unrelated facts from their context and specifics, putting them into a sequence, and&#8211;voila!&#8211;suggesting a causal relationship, or at least a relationship of some sort, and therefore some conclusory fact.  </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">This time around, he does it in the service of suggesting that the House Congressional Progressive Caucus’s proposed fiscal plan, written &#8220;by people hermetically sealed in the house of government&#8221;.  Unlike, say, the Ryan plan, written by Paul Ryan, who has spent most of his career in manufacturing.  </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">The CPC plan calls for raising the top income tax rate to 49%, taxing investment income at the same rate as other income, closing a variety of tax loopholes such as the carried-interest gig, taxing estates at their pre-2001 levels, and eliminating the corporate money-laundering-through-foreign-shell-subsidiaries option. It also proposes additional expenditures on such things as infrastructure and education.  Brooks says all this means that the CPC members &#8220;believe that government is the [economic] horse, the source of growth, job creation and prosperity.&#8221;  Not a source, but the source. Because this is a zero-sum game.  </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">He first claims that these high tax rates for the top bracket, when coupled with other taxes&#8211;state and local taxes, sales taxes, gas taxes&#8211;would amount to about 60% of their income. But Brooks being Brooks, he then says, without explanation, that the rates would be “80 percent or 90 percent of somebody’s top marginal earnings.” Somebody’s, maybe, but it’s certainly not clear who’s.  Anyway, this would “begin to change behavior and [we would] wind up with a very different country.”  Which I don’t doubt. </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">“Higher taxes,” he says, “will produce long-term changes in social norms, behavior and growth.”  Not necessarily bad changes, though, since no one is actually talking about taxing 80% or 90% of anyone’s income.  No one serious in this country, anyway.  But what would a David Brooks column be without a sleight of hand or two?</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Brooks offers an illustration to buttress his argument:</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Edward Prescott, a winner of the Nobel Memorial Prize in economics, found that, in the 1950s when their taxes were low, Europeans worked more hours per capita than Americans. Then their taxes went up, reducing the incentives to work and increasing the incentives to relax. Over the next decades, Europe saw a nearly 30 percent decline in work hours.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Yup.  Those 40-hour-a-week labor laws here and in Europe sure lowered standards of living. Bring back sweat shops! Foxconn, not Siemens, is what we want our companies to be modeled after.  </div>
<div dir="ltr"></div>
<div dir="ltr"></div>
<div dir="ltr">&#8220;A study last year by the economists Michael Keane and Richard Rogerson,” Brooks continues, “found that tax rates can have a surprisingly large influence on how much people invest in education, how likely they are to create businesses and which professions they go into.” No doubt. Get rid of the carried-interest break and start taxing hedge fund managers’ income at the same rate as salaries from working as an engineer, and some people who had planned to go into finance might instead go into engineering. Which would be awful for our society.  And raising taxes to the rates they were when state universities received about 70% of their funding from the government rather than most of it from tuition, as they do now, might allow students to borrow&#8211;er, invest&#8211;far less to go to college.  </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">I myself don&#8217;t favor a top tax rate as high as the 49% proposed by the CPC.  Nor do I claim that the top tax rates in each of the countries I list in the title of this post has top tax rates that high. But what&#8217;s so striking and revealing about Brooks’s column is its utter untethering of actual standards of living from his litany of loose declarations of fact and silly conclusions.  There is no apparent recognition in that column that the purpose of fiscal policy isn’t abstractions but personal and societal well-being.  </div>
<div dir="ltr"></div>
<div dir="ltr"></div>
<div dir="ltr">There is, though, on the New York Times’s website today, in the Opinion section, a lengthy, detailed <a href="http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/03/18/singapores-lessons-for-an-unequal-america/">column that actually does exactly that</a>, This one is not by a political pundit but instead by an actual working economist, albeit not one who Brooks would even read, much less cite: Joseph Stiglitz.* And, lo and behold, it demonstrates using relevant, rather than disembodied, facts and statistics, that the government-horse thing isn’t a zero-sum game after all. Unless it’s being ridden backwards by the Tea Party or saddled by a pundit who doesn’t work too hard even though he doesn’t live in Europe.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Raise David Brooks’s taxes a bit and he’ll cut his workweek from 20 hours to 15.  Praise the lord.</p>
<p>*<i>Stiglitz also is a Nobel laureate, by the way.</i></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/david-brooks-bemoans-the-low-standards-of-living-in-australia-canada-germany-holland-sweden-norway-denmark-and-finland.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>From Today’s New York Times Front Page, and From Tomorrow’s New York Times Op-Ed Page</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/from-todays-new-york-times-front-page-and-from-tomorrows-new-york-times-op-ed-page.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/from-todays-new-york-times-front-page-and-from-tomorrows-new-york-times-op-ed-page.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2013 18:17:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[corporate profits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[David Brooks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nelson D. Schwartz]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The New York Times]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/from-todays-new-york-times-front-page-and-from-tomorrows-new-york-times-op-ed-page.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Today, in the New York Times: With the Dow Jones industrial average flirting with a record high, the split between American workers and the companies that employ them is widening and could worsen in the next few months as federal budget cuts take hold. … “So far in this recovery, corporations have captured an unusually [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Today, in the New York Times:
<div dir="ltr">With the Dow Jones industrial average flirting with a record high, the split between American workers and the companies that employ them is widening and could worsen in the next few months as <a href="http://topics.nytimes.com/top/reference/timestopics/subjects/f/federal_budget_us/index.html?inline=nyt-classifier">federal budget</a> cuts take hold. …</p>
</div>
<div dir="ltr">“So far in this recovery, corporations have captured an unusually high share of the income gains,” said Ethan Harris, co-head of global economics at Bank of America Merrill Lynch. “The U.S. corporate sector is in a lot better health than the overall economy. And until we get a full recovery in the labor market, this will persist.”</div>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/03/04/business/economy/corporate-profits-soar-as-worker-income-limps.html?partner=rss&#038;emc=rss&#038;src=igw&#038;pagewanted=all">Recovery in U.S. Is Lifting Profits, but Not Adding Jobs</a>, Nelson D. Schwartz</div>
<p>Tomorrow, in the New York Times:</p>
<div dir="ltr">If President Obama really wants to show leadership, he will seize this moment and propose a reduction in corporate tax rates, so that corporations will have money to invest and hire and raise salaries and wages.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/02/carpe-david-brooks-before-he-drives-me_12.html">Carpe Clueless</a>, David Brooks, op-ed</div>
<p>Bet on it. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/from-todays-new-york-times-front-page-and-from-tomorrows-new-york-times-op-ed-page.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Oh, Dear. The David Brooksification of the Washington Post Editorial Board. And Brooks Doesn’t Even Write For The Washington Post. (But he does still write for the New York Times.) &#8211; UPDATED</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/oh-dear-the-david-brooksification-of-the-washington-post-editorial-board-and-brooks-doesnt-even-write-for-the-washington-post-but-he-does-still-write-for-the-new-york-times-updated.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/oh-dear-the-david-brooksification-of-the-washington-post-editorial-board-and-brooks-doesnt-even-write-for-the-washington-post-but-he-does-still-write-for-the-new-york-times-updated.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 26 Feb 2013 22:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Ben Bernanke]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[David Brooks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[David Ignatius]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Greg Sargent]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mainstream-journalism gimmickry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ron Fournier]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The National Journal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The New York Times]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the sequester]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Washington Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/oh-dear-the-david-brooksification-of-the-washington-post-editorial-board-and-brooks-doesnt-even-write-for-the-washington-post-but-he-does-still-write-for-the-new-york-times-updated.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[As Greg Sargent pointed out this morning, the new “it” gimmick of the pox-on-both-houses punditry is to borrow National Journal editorial something-or-other Ron Fournier’s tac of pretending that Obama can order the military to invade the House of Representatives and hold its members at assault-weapon-point until they agree to a grand bargain.  Or at least [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As Greg Sargent <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/plum-line/wp/2013/02/26/the-morning-plum-the-false-equivalence-pundits-are-part-of-the-problem/">pointed out</a> this morning, the new “it” gimmick of the pox-on-both-houses punditry is to borrow National Journal editorial something-or-other <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/02/why-you-dont-want-ron-fournier-to-be_24.html">Ron Fournier’s tac</a> of pretending that <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/02/national-journal-editor-ron-fournier.html">Obama can order the military to invade the House of Representatives</a> and hold its members at assault-weapon-point until they agree to a grand bargain.  Or at least to a less-grand one that includes additional tax revenue mainly through the closing of loopholes for the wealthy.  </p>
<p>Sargent doesn’t give credit where it’s due, though; he fails to identify Fournier as the etymoligcal source for this.  But, best as I can tell, he is; he just forgot to copyright it.</p>
<p>The key to this particular gimmick is a slight variation on the Orwellian redefinition of the word “lead” offered, repeatedly now, by John Boehner. In that original form, lead actually means follow.  Or, capitulate.  As in: The president needs to show leadership by delegating policymaking to the Republicans.  But in the slightly morphed from being employed by the punditry, it means&#8211;seriously&#8211;using actual force to compel the House to agree to a compromise that includes raising more tax revenue from the wealthy.</p>
<p>And surely this will resonate with the public.  After all, doesn’t everyone want a president who leads?  And isn’t all that matters simply the use of the word lead&#8211;regardless of how closely that use corresponds to the actual common English-language meaning of the word? </p>
<p>Well, obviously, the answer to that question is yes, because today the Washington Post features an editorial called “<a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/sequester-offers-president-obama-a-time-to-lead/2013/02/25/8a9b0e04-7f64-11e2-b99e-6baf4ebe42df_story.html?hpid=z2">Sequester offers President Obama a time to lead</a>,” which suggests that Obama offer a grand bargain that includes … additional tax revenues from the wealthy. </p>
<p>Call up the Army, Mr. President. And a Marine unit or two.  </p>
<p>Actually, apparently the purpose of the editorial&#8211;its purported purpose, anyway&#8211;is to try to goad Obama into proposing a grand bargain that would cut Social Security and Medicare benefit and that would include additional tax revenue.  So editorial writer casually segues from “leader” as someone who forces an actual agreement to “leader” who proposes a bold, sweeping, grand solution that the other side will reject out-of-hand and that therefore doesn’t resolve the sequester issue that the writer insists Obama is obligated to force a resolution of.  </p>
<p>But the actual purpose of the editorial&#8211;at least one actual purpose&#8211;is to support and subtly reiterate <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/02/bob-woodwards-seriously-stupid.html">Bob Woodward’s false and baldly silly claim</a> in that paper last weekend that in Aug. 2011 Obama agreed to a deal that forbade him and the Senate Democrats from bargaining to replace the sequester with any agreement except one that was even more abhorrent to the Dems’ position than the sequester.  According to Woodward, Obama agreed as part of the sequester itself that the Repubs were free to try to replace the sequester with a deal that removed Defense Department cuts and replaced those cuts with draconian cuts to social safety net programs and to other agencies and programs that the Dems support.  (The EPA!  The SEC! The Consumer Product Safety Commission!)  But, Obama agreed, the Dems would not be entitled to try to replace some of the cuts with additional tax revenue. </p>
<p>Uh-uh.  No, sir.  This train runs in only one direction: Republican. </p>
<p>Sounds to me like a deal that Obama could have just cut to the chase and taken right then and there, in Aug. 2011 rather than waiting 18 months.  But it doesn’t sound that way to Woodward. Or to the editorial’s author, who writes:
<div dir="ltr">The Republicans are right when they say that the sequester was <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/bob-woodward-obamas-sequester-deal-changer/2013/02/22/c0b65b5e-7ce1-11e2-9a75-dab0201670da_story.html">Mr. Obama’s idea</a>, in the summer of 2011, and that he agreed to a deal that was all spending cuts, no tax hikes.</div>
<p>Yup. I guess that if you’re a Washington Post editorial writer, you can try to get away with saying that Obama “agreed to a deal that was all spending cuts, no tax hikes,” and not identify which deal you’re talking about&#8211;the sequester deal, which indeed was all spending cuts, or instead a deal to replace the sequester, which has yet to be made and therefore includes no deal that is all spending cuts.  At least if you don’t give a damn about your paper’s credibility.  </p>
<p>And if you don’t care that you’re playing with fire.  Words have actual meanings, and these semantics sleights of hand are matches.</p>
<p>But the editorial is dangerous in a substantive, rather than only a semantics, respect as well, because it bases its grand-bargain argument upon a claim that we must agree now to cut Social Security and Medicare in the future in order to pay for things like increases in education funding and guaranteed quality preschool now.  At least I think that’s what it’s saying.  </p>
<p>Ben Bernake, by the way, made clear today under questioning before the Senate Banking Committee, that he begs to differ with the assessment that this is a grand idea.  The Washington Post&#8217;s economics and finance reporter who covered the hearing will report accurately on what transpired.  The Washington Post&#8217;s editorial board won&#8217;t even understand it.  Or won&#8217;t admit that they do.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, never to be outdone in recommending policies to Obama so that Obama can lead, without offering an iota of explanation or support for them, David Brooks <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/26/opinion/brooks-our-second-adolescence.html?_r=0">weighed in</a> this morning with another leadership-as-a-double-entendre column.  This time, fresh from his mea culpa about his last column, and in fact reiterating the walk-back, Brooks acknowledges that inequality has spiraled out of control since the Clinton era, and agrees that Obama should propose policies to address this.  Like a consumption tax to offset an elimination of income taxes on incomes up to $100,000 and a reduction of corporate tax rates to 15%.  </p>
<p>Brooks doesn’t explain the policy reasons for the two offsets he suggests.  But he doesn’t have to.  Everyone knows that the less progressive the tax code, the less inequality in wealth we will have, and that record corporate profits and record corporate hoarding of those profits leads to more equality of income.  After all, they’ve read past Brooks columns. </p>
<p>As for the Washington Post editorial board, when they consider important people who should lead, but aren’t, they might want to look in the mirror.  They emphasize that the Republicans are right that the sequester was <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/bob-woodward-obamas-sequester-deal-changer/2013/02/22/c0b65b5e-7ce1-11e2-9a75-dab0201670da_story.html">Mr. Obama’s idea</a>, in the summer of 2011.  But they don’t mention that the alternative was the default by the United States on all of its already-incurred financial obligations, including its Treasury bonds. Nor that <i>that</i>, by absolutely all accounts, would have destabilized the entire world economy. </p>
<p>This is important stuff. And as the editorial board of one this country’s emanant general-news publications, they’re important people. They should take that responsibility seriously. They should lead. </p>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />&#8212;&#8211;</p>
<p>UPDATE:  Washington Post columnist David Ignatius writes, in <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/david-ignatius-sequester-stop-the-car/2013/02/26/7a8fc170-804b-11e2-b99e-6baf4ebe42df_story.html">a column</a> posted this afternoon:</p>
<div dir="ltr">Much as I would criticize Obama, it’s wrong to say that both sides are equally to blame for what’s about to hit us. This isn’t a one-off case of Republicans using Obama’s sequestration legislation to force reckless budget cuts. It’s a pattern of behavior: First the Republicans were prepared to shut down the government and damage the national credit rating with their showdown over the debt ceiling; then they were careening toward the “<a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/business/economy/understanding-the-sequester/2013/02/25/71a0186e-7fc2-11e2-a350-49866afab584_graphic.html">fiscal cliff</a>.” This isn’t a legislative tactic anymore; it’s an addiction.</div>
<p>Excuse me, Mr. Ignatius, but given that you acknowledge that the Republicans were prepared to shut down the government and damage the national credit rating with their showdown over the debt ceiling, isn’t it a bit&#8211;oh, I don’t know&#8211;odd for you to imply that that was unconnected to, y’know, Obama’s sequester? Since, <i>without</i>* Obama’s sequester, the government would in fact have shut down, and the damage the national credit rating would have been, um, significant&#8211;so, this is what Obama’s sequester avoided? </p>
<p>Or was Obama’s sequest really just proposed in a vacuum, as you suggest?  I forget.  Or you do. </p>
<p>Or maybe you just pretend to.<br />&#8212;<br />*<i>Typo-corrected.  Originally, it said &#8220;with&#8221; rather than &#8220;without.&#8221;  Oops.</i></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/oh-dear-the-david-brooksification-of-the-washington-post-editorial-board-and-brooks-doesnt-even-write-for-the-washington-post-but-he-does-still-write-for-the-new-york-times-updated.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Carpe David Brooks. Before He Drives Me Crazy. [Freudian typo now corrected. 3:25 p.m.]</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/carpe-david-brooks-before-he-drives-me-crazy-freudian-typo-now-corrected-325-p-m.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/carpe-david-brooks-before-he-drives-me-crazy-freudian-typo-now-corrected-325-p-m.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2013 18:54:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[David Brooks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Innovation Economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medicare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Robert D. Atkinson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Stephen J. Ezell]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The New York Times]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/carpe-david-brooks-before-he-drives-me-crazy-freudian-typo-now-corrected-325-p-m.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[An exchange between reader nitu mishra and me in the Comments thread this morning to this AB post of mine from yesterday. nitu mishra: Here’s a good article on 2012 Q4 earnings outlook. http://tinyurl.com/investing002 Me: Ah. If only I could actually understand graphs, without having to stare at them for ten minutes or so first, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>An exchange between reader nitu mishra and me in the Comments thread this morning to <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/02/the-national-review-invites-obama-to.html">this AB post of mine </a>from yesterday.
<div dir="ltr">nitu mishra: </p>
</div>
<div dir="ltr">Here’s a good article on 2012 Q4 earnings outlook.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">http://tinyurl.com/investing002</p>
</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Me: </p>
</div>
<div dir="ltr">Ah. If only I could actually understand graphs, without having to stare at them for ten minutes or so first, Nitu. But I don’t have to understand the graph posted at that url to know that corporate earnings are TANKING.  I know that because I already read David Brooks’s column today, and he says that Obama should propose a cut in corporate tax rates, because corporations need to have money to use for INVESTMENTS.  And of course Brooks wouldn’t say that unless corporate profits* ARE tanking and corporations, well, just can’t afford to invest.  They need further tax breaks in order to have the money to do that!</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Like Apple. </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">(And, pleeeeease: No one post that aggregate U.S. corporate profits are at all-time highs and that corporations are HOARDING their profits rather than using them to invest.  I know that. My comment is facetious.) </div>
<p>I’m back on <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/01/oh-no-david-brooks-thinks-social_29.html">my David-Brooks-formulaic-conflations watch</a> today, because, well, he has another column in today’s Times.  And (surprise!) it’s another classic I’ve-found-the-secret-formula-for-phoning-in-NYT-columns column.  So I can’t resist.</p>
<p>The formula, of course, as anyone who reads his columns even occasionally knows, is to summarize a new book he’s read about economic or social trends (or both!) and then use the last two or three paragraphs of the column to string together conclusions that are either non sequiturs to the information or ideas he’s just summarized from the book, or to state unexplained conclusions that are contrary to that information or those ideas and pretend that the information or ideas support those conclusions.</p>
<p>It’s easy.  And it’s a very nice gig. </p>
<p><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/12/opinion/brooks-carpe-diem-nation.html?_r=0">Today’s offering</a> is based on a book called “Innovation Economics.”  I’ve selected two excerpts from the column, that, I trust, together illustrate my point.  The first, from early in the column, is:</p>
<div dir="ltr">As Robert D. Atkinson and Stephen J. Ezell note in their book “Innovation Economics,” American firms are also lagging in their commitment to research and development. Between 1999 and 2006, for example, German firms increased research-and-development spending by 11 percent, Finnish firms by 28 percent and South Korean firms by 58 percent. During that same period, U.S. spending increased by a paltry 3 percent.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Increasingly, companies have to spend their money on retirees, not future growth. Last week, for example, Ford announced that it was spending $5 billion to shore up its pension program. That’s an amount nearly equal to Ford’s investments in factories, equipment and innovation.</div>
<p>And then the denouement:</p>
<div dir="ltr">The political debate, though, is largely oblivious to this mental shift. Republicans and Democrats are so busy arguing about the merits of government versus business that they are blind to the problem that afflicts them both.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">In his State of the Union address Tuesday night, President Obama is apparently planning to give us yet another salvo in that left-right war, as he did in his second Inaugural Address. One of his aides, in a fit of hubris, told Politico that the president will be offering Republicans a golden bridge to ease their retreat.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">But it would be great if Obama gave an imaginative speech that reframed things as present versus future.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">If the president were to propose an agenda for the future, he’d double spending on the National Institutes of Health. He’d approve the Keystone XL pipeline. He’d cut corporate tax rates while adding a progressive consumption tax. He’d take money from Social Security and build Harlem Children’s Zone-type projects across the nation. He’d means test Medicare and use the money to revive state universities and pay down debt.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Would Americans buy that agenda? Maybe. Americans are neglecting the future, but I bet they’re still in love with it.</div>
<p>The title of the column is “Carpe Diem Nation.”  The first excerpt is noteworthy both for its statistics and for the fact that Brooks has built a career on trashing European economic policy and culture as anti-entrepreneurial.  The second excerpt would be notable for its vertigo inducement, were vertigo inducement not a regular part of the formula, column after column.  But it is, so it’s not notable.  </p>
<p>In between those two excerpts, Brooks apprises readers who aren’t regulars, and who therefore don’t know, that his real purpose is to argue for the dismembering of the social safety network for the elderly, because, well, we couldn’t possibly raise taxes to cover that social safety network, as they do in, say, Germany and Finland.**  Raising FICA taxes very slightly would take care of Social Security needs, but rather than do that, or to raise taxes on upper-income folks and on corporations to Clinton-era levels, it’s better to remove basic sustenance income from millions of elderly if we want to build Harlem Children’s Zone-type projects across the nation.  <a name="more"></a></p>
<p>This is true especially regarding corporate taxes, since record corporate profits and outright hoarding of those profits by corporations doesn’t mean that increasing their taxes by raising tax rates or by closing loopholes would be a better investment for the country than reducing corporate taxes even further. I mean, you never know when Apple might conclude that it finally has enough after-tax profits to start investing them in research and development. </p>
<p>Of course, seniors who rely entirely or mainly on Social Security benefits and Medicare aren’t known for their dedication to Apple MacBooks, iPhones and iPads, so there’s no real need to worry that a reduction in those seniors’ meager income would hurt the economy by depriving Apple of enough money to enable the company to invest. </p>
<p>So carpe diem to cut taxes on corporations while ending Medicare and Social Security.  Just like Germany and Finland. If it’s the future that you’re interested in. 
<div></div>
<div>&#8212;-</div>
<div>*<i>The post originally said &#8220;corporate taxes ARE tanking&#8230;.&#8221;  That was a typo.  Or maybe a Freudian slip.</i><br /><i><br /></i><i>**Sentence was corrected to correct two typos&#8211;and to make sense. 11:21 p.m.</i></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/carpe-david-brooks-before-he-drives-me-crazy-freudian-typo-now-corrected-325-p-m.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Oh, No. David Brooks Thinks Social Security and Medicare Are State- and Local-Government Programs. Or Thinks We Do. Seriously. &#8212; APPENDED (twice)</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/oh-no-david-brooks-thinks-social-security-and-medicare-are-state-and-local-government-programs-or-thinks-we-do-seriously-appended-twice.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/oh-no-david-brooks-thinks-social-security-and-medicare-are-state-and-local-government-programs-or-thinks-we-do-seriously-appended-twice.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 29 Jan 2013 23:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[David Brooks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Enrico Moretti]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jonathan Chait]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New York Magazine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The National Review]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The New York Times]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the Second GOP]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/oh-no-david-brooks-thinks-social-security-and-medicare-are-state-and-local-government-programs-or-thinks-we-do-seriously-appended-twice.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The final problem is that, in an effort to reduce the economic concentration of power, the administration is concentrating political power in Washington. If the problem is that talent is fleeing blighted localities, it’s hard to see how you make that better if decision-making and resources are concentrated faraway in the nation’s capital. This is [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">The final problem is that, in an effort to reduce the economic concentration of power, the administration is concentrating political power in Washington. If the problem is that talent is fleeing blighted localities, it’s hard to see how you make that better if decision-making and resources are concentrated faraway in the nation’s capital.</div>
<div dir="ltr">This is not to make a partisan point. The Republicans do not have a better approach. It’s simply to say that the liberal agenda is not very good at addressing the inequality problem it seeks to solve. The meritocracy is overwhelming the liberal project.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/01/25/opinion/brooks-the-great-migration.html">The Great Migration</a>, David Brooks, New York Times, Jan. 25</p>
</div>
<p>Brooks is right; that is not to make a partisan point.  It is to make a nonsensensical point. A point that Brooks makes again in <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/01/29/opinion/brooks-a-second-g-o-p.html?_r=0">his column in today&#8217;s Times</a>, if in different words. </p>
<p>It is, in any event, an inaccurate point.  </p>
<p>Okay, I admit it: I’ve become obsessed with David Brooks.  Or, more specifically, with the fact that a New York Times columnist who is regularly referenced by other big-name political columnists and bloggers, operates under a formula in which everything even remotely connected to politics/ideology&#8211;and I do mean everything, best as I can tell&#8211;falls within one or another breathtakingly broad factual category.  The placement into one or another of these categories depends not on whether the category placement is even remotely accurate as a matter of logic or even (sometimes) actual fact, but instead on which category whatever he’s talking about must fit in order to advance his preference for the decentralization of … well … everything, I guess, other than corporate power.  But especially of government functions. </p>
<p>This is so even when he’s arguing in favor of stronger centralization of government functions and of more government functions, but doesn’t realize it.  As, for example, his invocation of the public’s overwhelming support for Social Security and Medicare as … yup! … evidence that “Americans are still skeptical of Washington,” and so “[i]f you shove a big government program down their throats they will recoil.”  An accurate statement if the Americans you’re talking about are the ones who want the government to stay out of their Medicare!  Otherwise, though, there isn’t much evidence that there’s been an 80-year-long recoiling from Social Security and a 45-year recoiling from Medicare, and a populist push to privatize those programs or, to borrow a phrase from Mitt Romney (specifically when talking about emergency disaster aid and Medicaid, but, clearly, he had other programs in mind, too&#8211;like almost all federal programs that don’t directly aide, say, the oil and gas production companies&#8211;send them back to the states.  From which they didn’t come, in the first place.</p>
<p>The two indented paragraphs above come at the end of a column summarizing a new book called The New Geography of Jobs, by Enrico Moretti, with whom Brooks expressly agrees, point after point, paragraph after paragraph.  Until he adds a point of his own, the one he identifies as the final problem.  The one that Brooks thinks cannot be solved by federal money and decisionmaking, because that money would be concentrated in&#8211;by which he means, originates from&#8211;Washington, and because decisionmaking about how to turn this dynamic around, so that localities other than the big tech and finance centers prosper too, would, if the liberals have their way, be concentrated in Washington.  </p>
<p><a name="more"></a>Brooks sums up the problem. Sort of:</p>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">The highly educated cluster around a few small nodes. Decade after decade, smart and educated people flock away from Merced, Calif., Yuma, Ariz., Flint, Mich., and Vineland, N.J. In those places, less than 15 percent of the residents have college degrees. They flock to Washington, Boston, San Jose, Raleigh-Durham and San Francisco. In those places, nearly 50 percent of the residents have college degrees.</div>
<div dir="ltr">As Enrico Moretti writes in “The New Geography of Jobs,” the magnet places have positive ecologies that multiply innovation, creativity and wealth. The abandoned places have negative ecologies and fall further behind.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">This sorting is self-reinforcing, and it seems to grow more unforgiving every year. One small study caught my eye. Robert Oprisko of Butler University found that half of the jobs in university political science programs went to graduates of the top 11 schools. That is to say, if you have a Ph.D. from Harvard, Stanford, Princeton and so on, your odds of getting a job are very good. If you earned your degree from one of the other 100 degree-granting universities, your odds are not. These other 100 schools don’t even want to hire the sort of graduates they themselves produce. They want the elite credential.</p>
</div>
<p>Brooks is good at using other people’s fact-based arguments.  He just isn’t good at figuring out what they mean.  Or at least what they don’t mean.  Butler University is in Indianapolis, Ind. Presumably, Oprisko and all his colleagues live nearby.  The University of Michigan has a large branch in Flint.  The members of its political science faculty probably live within a relatively small radius of Flint.  So this wasn’t a good example of Moretti’s point, an all-too-valid one that highlights a huge national truth.  A truth that surely cannot be solved by removing whatever funds and help the federal government might offer.  </p>
<p>The federal government is not keeping Flint and the other, similar localities around the country, from doing things that might change the economics dynamic so that their young people will be better educated and will want to return there after receiving their degrees.  The federal government is being concertedly demonized as a beast, and starved&#8211;the result of the Republican dominance of Washington policymaking for so long.  And, for the same reason, the federal government’s entire fiscal policymaking apparatus has been prevented from attempting to deal with the problems Moretti discusses (and Brooks purports to discuss) by the capture of the public policymaking dialogue by people who want to end or prevent the federal-government’s role in, among many other things, the very sort of problem-solving that Brooks says is needed, except by … who?  Or by what?  Corporations?  Local governments?  Rush Limbaugh? </p>
<p>Brooks, as is typical of him, doesn’t say.  He just says, as always, that “centralized”&#8211;by which he means, federal government&#8211;power is bad.  He doesn’t like it.  Too much like Europe, you know.  Very bad. </p>
<p>Brooks didn’t write a Sunday column this week.  I figured he just <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/01/does-david-brooks-really-think-student.html">didn’t want me to mock</a> another of his mindless rants about liberal/Obama government/centralized-headquarters-controlled operations that would undermine creativity and initiative&#8211;such as student-loan programs and public universities&#8211;so he took the day off.  But instead it turns out that he didn’t write a Sunday column because he was too busy attending various luncheons, dinners, and other meetings at this decade’s <a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/politics/2013/01/national_review_post_election_summit_conservatives_descend_on_the_magazine.html">National Review review</a> this past weekend about what the hell went WRONG last November, and what the hell can BE DONE to avoid such unfortunate turns of fortune from recurring repeatedly in the coming, say, century. </p>
<p>Brooks recounts pieces of arguments of speakers at the conference, and he concludes, surely accurately, that the Republican Party can’t win unless it develops what he calls a “Second GOP,” lead by new politicians who are not anti-government. These folks would develop federal programs that would address the country’s and individuals’ actual problems.  The quest for actual solutions, in other words, would trump anti-government ideology.  It’s just that, as standard bearers for the GOP, albeit the Second one,  they would have to pretend that federal programs, like Social Security and Medicare, aren’t big government programs.  Or even small government programs.  They would pretend, I guess, that federal government programs aren’t federal government programs.  State programs, maybe?  Local-government programs? Chamber of Commerce programs?</p>
<p>This would work, remember, because most Americans “recoil” from big (i.e.., federal) government programs. Which is why they “cherish” Social Security and Medicare.  Just so you don&#8217;t think I&#8217;ve removed a sentence or clause from its context, here’s the full paragraph:</p>
<div dir="ltr">Americans are still skeptical of Washington. If you shove a big government program down their throats they will recoil. But many of their immediate problems flow from globalization, the turmoil of technological change and social decay, and they’re looking for a bit of help. Moreover, given all the antigovernment rhetoric, they will never trust these Republicans to reform cherished programs like Social Security and Medicare. You can’t be for entitlement reform and today’s G.O.P., because politically the two will never go together. </div>
<p>The Second GOP, Brooks says, “would be filled with people who recoiled at President Obama’s second Inaugural Address because of its excessive faith in centralized power, but who don’t share the absolute antigovernment story of the current G.O.P.”  People who, for example, live in Merced, Calif., Yuma, Ariz., Flint, Mich., and Vineland, N.J., and would be outraged if the Obama administration offered programs and federal financing to try to assist their cities in upgrading their education and infrastructure systems enough that they again become attractive to companies and startups and young professionals. Some of whom, recall, cherish Social Security and Medicare because of their lack of centralized power.</p>
<p>What exactly does Brooks think is an example of Obama’s excessive faith in centralized power?  The operative word here is, example. Even just one or two specific ones, please.  He doesn’t say; after all, generalization and sweeping categorization is his stock in trade. But if he can, and does, eventually provide an example, he might, while he’s on a role, consider identifying a couple of decentralized-power success stories, and explaining why Merced, Calif., Yuma, Ariz., Flint, Mich., and Vineland, N.J., don’t seem to have had similar options.  </p>
<p>Or maybe he can persuade the Second GOP to explain it. Without making too many of us recoil.  </p>
<p>&#8212;<br />UPDATE: Reader Jack and I exchanged the following comments in the Comments thread below:</p>
<div dir="ltr">Jack: </div>
<div dir="ltr">Beverly</div>
<div dir="ltr">Believe me when I say that I share your feelings about Brooks. He is one of the worst of the sycophants of the upper crust, and he is little more than the crumbs that make up that crust. However, the nearly total lack of response to your long post in the past several hours is the best response of all. He is not worthy of criticism. Posting anything he writes is like disposing of feces with your bare hands. Don&#8217;t dirty yourself by acknowledging that you&#8217;ve actually read some of his deceitful meanderings. When you see his column in print take that page and clean some crap off the sidewalk so that at least that page will serve a useful purpose.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">If you must write about him then do so in a brief letter to the managing Editor of the Times and note that the Times should find a more fact based apologist for the takers in our society. Don&#8217;t multiply his words through the process of criticism. It serves no useful purpose because criticism is meant to correct or improve a point of view. He has no capacity for either.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Me:</div>
<div dir="ltr">My instinct is to just say, “But, Jack, you don’t understand.  This is an obsession!”  But I think it’s not a trivial matter that a very high-profile, self-styled “center-right” (as opposed to just plain rightwing), political columnist&#8211;someone whom politicians and other political journalists read and take seriously&#8211;keeps pushing a flatly nonsensical supposedly-factual, but generic “narrative”&#8211;over and over and over again&#8211;while never actually identifying specifics to support his claim of fact: that Obama and the congressional Dems are pushing for federal programs that would undermine creativity and initiative because they would be federal programs rather than state or local programs&#8211;or something&#8211;and that ongoing government programs such as student loan programs and state university systems do the same because they are government rather than private programs&#8211;or something.  </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">These are representations of fact, not statements of opinion.  They either are unpinned by empirical evidence or they are not.  And of course they are not.  So why does the New York Times allow him to keep asserting these things, in column after column, without finally asking him to identify specifics that support his generic claims of fact?  Yes, he’s an opinion columnist.  But these things aren’t opinion; they’re either fact-based or they aren’t, and if they aren’t, why is he allowed to use the Times as his forum to keep saying that they are, without ever actually identifying any empirical evidence to support them, or even specifying rather than merely implying) what programs he’s talking about.  </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Two weeks ago, New York Magazine writer Jonathan Chait wrote <a href="http://nymag.com/daily/intelligencer/2013/01/david-brooks-now-totally-pathological.html">a delicious article</a> there titled “David Brooks Now Totally Pathological,” hilariously deconstructing Brooks’s then-most-recent column in which he angrily blamed Obama for the Republicans’ fiscal-cliff and debt-ceiling embarrassments because Obama didn’t cave to them.  But that column of Brooks’s was, clearly, just opinion.  Hilariously and flagrantly ridiculous opinion.  It wasn’t a misrepresentation of fact. Quite the opposite; it acknowledged that the Republicans lost the substantive and political endgame on both.  It just said it was Obama’s fault.  Which is true. </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Chait’s article is … a don’t-miss. </div>
<div>&#8212;-<br />FOLLOW-UP: In response to Jack’s reply to me in the Comments thread in which he criticized the New York Times as basically a shill for the wealthy, I wrote:</p>
<div dir="ltr">I like the New York Times, generally. That&#8217;s where Paul Krugman&#8217;s column and blog are published, after all. And I&#8217;m not suggesting that the editors should censor their columnists&#8217; opinions. But when a political columnist repeatedly makes sweeping conclusory statements of fact without ever actually specifying the supposed factual basis for the claims, and when it&#8217;s patently clear that no factual basis for the claims exists, it does seem to me that that crosses a line. …</div>
<p>I want to be sure that my criticism of the Times on this is not misunderstood. </div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/oh-no-david-brooks-thinks-social-security-and-medicare-are-state-and-local-government-programs-or-thinks-we-do-seriously-appended-twice.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Does David Brooks Really Think Student Loans, Public Universities, Public Infrastructure, and Small Business Loans Are Attempts at Socialist Central Planning That Undermines Creativity and Private Enterprise? I Mean … REALLY?* [Appended 1/23]</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/does-david-brooks-really-think-student-loans-public-universities-public-infrastructure-and-small-business-loans-are-attempts-at-socialist-central-planning-that-undermines-creativity-and-private-ent.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/does-david-brooks-really-think-student-loans-public-universities-public-infrastructure-and-small-business-loans-are-attempts-at-socialist-central-planning-that-undermines-creativity-and-private-ent.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Jan 2013 17:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dana Milbank]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[David Brooks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[socialism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The New York Times]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Washington Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/does-david-brooks-really-think-student-loans-public-universities-public-infrastructure-and-small-business-loans-are-attempts-at-socialist-central-planning-that-undermines-creativity-and-private-ent.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I’m a political junkie, born and bred.  And so the number of political opinion pieces I’ve read in my life, dating back to my teenage years (me being a child of my parents, they of the ardent liberal Democrat variety&#8211; “Oh, no, Bevy!  You have to return that purse.  That company is anti-union!”  “Okayyy, Mom.”)&#8211;run [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’m a political junkie, born and bred.  And so the number of political opinion pieces I’ve read in my life, dating back to my teenage years (me being a child of my parents, they of the ardent liberal Democrat variety&#8211; “Oh, no, Bevy!  You have to return that purse.  That company is anti-union!”  “Okayyy, Mom.”)&#8211;run probably into the thousands.  (Yikes.)  </p>
<p>And I’ve certainly read, ah-hem, a few pieces by established, mainstream columnists in respected newspapers and magazines that have made my eyes roll or made me shake my head in dismay because of some obvious flaw in logic or some clearly false representation of fact upon which the writer’s premise lies.  </p>
<p>But I don’t think I’ve ever before read such a mystifyingly wacky, whiplash-inducing, incomprehensibly-false-fact-based commentary as <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/01/22/opinion/brooks-the-collective-turn.html?_r=0">the one I just read</a>, by David Brooks, in today&#8217;s New York Times.  The premise: That Obama’s argument for returning the federal government’s domestic-policy emphasis to trying to increase economic and social mobility, improving public infrastructure, encouraging individual creativity, inventiveness and risk-taking, and trying to help limit climate change, Obama was arguing for … you guessed it! (at least if you read Brooks’s columns even occasionally, as I do) … European-style central-government control (commands from “headquarters”; seriously) over the private sector and the private sector’s creativeness and innovativeness.  </p>
<p>No, sir!  Wouldn’t want any of that socialist German-style engineering expertise to make its way across the Atlantic. Especially since all those engineers at, say, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siemens">Siemens</a> got their engineering degrees at &#8212; and this is really dangerous&#8211;places like the University of Heidelberg!  Which is, OMG, a public university!  Supported by German taxes.  And financially accessible by some students whose families are not upscale!</p>
<p>Yup.  And that engineering and computer science school at the University of Illinois, regularly rated among the top such programs in the country, can’t possibly have produced someone who, say, while attending the school, developed the World Wide Web by developing the first Internet browser, called Mosaic, which became Netscape.  Uh-uh.  <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marc_Andreessen">Marc Andreessen</a> only thinks his college memories of life in Champaign, Ill. But they’re really of life in Palo Alto.  Or maybe Cambridge, Mass.  And how did that Wisconsin native even manage to invent anything at all, given the “hammock” (Paul Ryan’s term, not Brooks’s) he found himself in when he (probably) took out a low-interest, no-repayments-required-until-five-years-after-graduation loan to pay that out-of-state tuition back in the late 1980s, and early 1990s, under a federal Great Society program? </p>
<p>The whiplash-inducing stuff in Brooks’s column appears at two points. The first one comes about midway through the column, when Brooks switches from praising the Obama speech as a strong argument for collective government policies to, say, assist in economic and social mobility.  The second one comes late in the column, after paragraphs in which he says such things as that we have a much more dynamic and innovative private sector than does Europe because colleges and universities in the Unites States are private rather than public and Europe’s are public rather than private (I’m not joking or exaggerating; he says this), and that the programs Obama supports, such as student loan programs and financial support for schools and medical and scientific research and the like, are attempts by political progressives to undermine private enterprise and control the private sector from Washington.  He then concedes, apparently unwittingly&#8211;he seems unaware, at least, of the irony&#8211;that public programs and financial regulations can (and do!) assist creativity and innovation.</p>
<p>You really have to read the whole column to get the full flavor.  Just put on a neck brace first.</p>
<p>And while you’re reading it, remind yourself that <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thomas_Edison">Thomas Edison</a>, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_Graham_Bell">Alexander Graham Bel</a>l, and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_">Henry Ford</a> did not attend a private college.  Nor did <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enrico_Fermi">Enrico Fermi </a>or some of the other great physicists who emigrated to this country in the late 1930s after receiving their education at public universities&#8211;in Europe!  </p>
<p>And that David Brooks did attend a private university: the University of Chicago.  And that <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Brooks_(journalist)">his Philadelphia Main Line parents </a>probably paid his tuition and room and board, free and clear.</p>
<p>Enough said. I think.  Unless of course he’s invented something that I don’t know of.  And that’s useful. </p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />*PS: Indulge me in my obsession with idiocy from big-name, mainstream political pundits, writing in (or on) prestigious, widely read political-commentary forums.  Neither David Brooks <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/01/what-dana-milbanks-stunningly-awful.html">nor Dana Milba</a><a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/01/what-dana-milbanks-stunningly-awful.html">nk</a> is, after all, all that important, I recognize.  But Brooks, <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/01/he-asked-not-what-his-country-can-do.html">if not Milbank</a>, flatly crossed the line into misrepresentation of fact in a way that is really beyond the pale. And no one but me probably even noticed.  </p>
<p>Frustrating. </p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />ANOTHER PS: As I said in response to a comment in the Comments thread, Brooks’s longtime shtick is anti-European&#8211;as in, Europe’s standard of living is lower than ours and that’s because their socialist policies deter creativity and innovation and therefore “dynamism.” He’s apparently run out of plausible-sounding arguments to support his belief, so he just blathers the claim incoherently, as needed.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/does-david-brooks-really-think-student-loans-public-universities-public-infrastructure-and-small-business-loans-are-attempts-at-socialist-central-planning-that-undermines-creativity-and-private-ent.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
