<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>unemployment &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Explaining Class Warfare</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/explaining-class-warfare.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/explaining-class-warfare.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2012 17:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[capitalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Class war]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Class Warfare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income inequality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Income redistribution]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Job creation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[job creators]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[unemployment]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/explaining-class-warfare.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Last month one hundred and fourteen thousand unemployed moochers&#8230;suddenly yank the government teat out of their mouths, get off the couch for forty hours a week? Why? I say follow the money; cause I found out, that right around the time those people got those jobs&#8230;they started getting paid! And just where does that money [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><div>Last month one hundred and fourteen thousand unemployed moochers&#8230;suddenly yank the government teat out of their mouths, get off the couch for forty hours a week?  Why?</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>I say follow the money;  cause I found out, that right around the time those people got those jobs&#8230;they started getting paid!   </div>
<div></div>
<div>And just where does that money come from?  Right out of the pockets of the job creators.  How&#8217;s that for your socialist redistribution of wealth?  Folks, it&#8217;s called class warfare.   </div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div><a href="http://videocafe.crooksandliars.com/heather/colbert-pity-poor-billionaires" target="_blank">Mr Colbert</a> has created a new party that will issue a certificate to sooth the hurt of the job creators.  The Certificate of Richness issued by:  </div>
<div>Protecting Industry Titans and Yachtsman party.  The P.I.T.Y. party.</div>
<div></div>
<div>And right <a href="http://finance.yahoo.com/news/ceo-workers-youll-likely-fired-131640914.html;_ylt=AlaAuLdYqs7HHtbpDI5C47KiuYdG;_ylu=X3oDMTN1MnFnZ25nBG1pdANGaW5hbmNlIEZQIE1lZ2F0cm9uIDIEcGtnA2RmNDIxODQ2LTgzOGYtMzQzMC05YjNjLWY4NzE2M2Q4OTY0NgRwb3MDMQRzZWMDbWVnYXRyb24EdmVyAzc3NjY3MmY4LTEyZjAtMTFlMi05ZmZmLTU5YWVjNDdhNGIyMg--;_ylg=X3oDMTFpNzk0NjhtBGludGwDdXMEbGFuZwNlbi11cwRwc3RhaWQDBHBzdGNhdANob21lBHB0A3NlY3Rpb25z;_ylv=3" target="_blank">on cue</a>:</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<blockquote><div>If President Obama is re-elected and raises taxes, Westgate Resort&#8217;s David  Siegel says he will have to lay off workers and downsize his company &#8212; or even  shut it down.</div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/explaining-class-warfare.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Unemployment Rates Across the Euro Area – Tough Times in Key Markets</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/unemployment-rates-across-the-euro-area-tough-times-in-key-markets.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/unemployment-rates-across-the-euro-area-tough-times-in-key-markets.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2012 17:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[euro area]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rebecca Wilder]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[unemployment]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/unemployment-rates-across-the-euro-area-tough-times-in-key-markets.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Rebecca Wilder Unemployment Rates Across the Euro Area – Tough Times in Key Markets Today Eurostat released its unemployment rate figures for the month of August. The Euro area unemployment rate held firm at 11.4% for the third consecutive month. Spain still has the highest unemployment rate in the euro area, 25.1%, and Greece [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by <a href="http://www.economonitor.com/blog/author/rwilder3">Rebecca Wilder</a></p>
<p>Unemployment Rates Across the Euro Area – Tough Times in Key Markets</p>
<p>Today Eurostat released its unemployment rate figures for the month of August. The Euro area unemployment rate held firm at 11.4% for the third consecutive month. Spain still has the highest unemployment rate in the euro area, 25.1%, and Greece is catching up quickly, 24.4% (in June, which is the latest data point).<br />The chart below illustrates the level of the unemployment rate and its month-month change for the euro area 12 countries.<br /><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/10/urate_chart.jpg"><img alt="" height="402" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/10/urate_chart.jpg" width="604"></a></p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>The periphery are under performing the average, with Spain, Greece, Portugal, and Ireland leading the way. Internal devaluation, or driving up the unemployment rate to reduce relative prices with demand, is really taking its toll. Respectively, the unemployment rates in Spain, Greece, Portugal, and Ireland are 178.9 ppt, 234.2 ppt, 93.9 ppt, and 212.5 ppt above their pre-crisis minimums (loosely defined since January 2008) – a simple average of 179.9 ppt above the joint minimum for these four countries. The average euro area 17 unemployment rate is just 56.2 ppt above its 7.3% pre-crisis minimum. Hard days in the periphery, to be sure. Against this backdrop, weekend <a href="http://www.eurointelligence.com/eurointelligence-news/home/singleview-restricted/article/peer-steinbrueck-to-challenge-angela-merkel.html">protests in Paris, Madrid, Lisbon, and Rome</a> are not a surprise.<br />I further point out the troubling trend in the French labor market, as the new government presents its fresh austerity budget for 2013.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/10/fr-ea_urate.jpg"><img alt="" height="390" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/10/fr-ea_urate.jpg" width="605"></a></p>
<p>This budget is highly dependent on tax revenue and positive growth momentum, which is likely to disappoint amid such deterioration in domestic demand. See <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/finance/comment/ambroseevans_pritchard/9577674/Another-domino-falls-as-Hollande-pushes-France-into-depression.html">Ambrose Evans-Pritchard </a>on the expected budget impact.</p>
<p>cross posted with <a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/2012/10/01/unemployment-rate-in-the-euro-area-tough-times-in-key-markets/">The Wilder View&#8230;Economonitors</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/unemployment-rates-across-the-euro-area-tough-times-in-key-markets.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>US wages trail 10 OECD countries, but with higher unemployment than 9 of them</title>
		<link>./../../2012/09/us-wages-trail-10-oecd-countries-but-with-higher-unemployment-than-9-of-them.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/09/us-wages-trail-10-oecd-countries-but-with-higher-unemployment-than-9-of-them.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2012 21:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[industrial countries]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kenneth Thomas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[market wages]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[PPP]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[unemployment]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/09/us-wages-trail-10-oecd-countries-but-with-higher-unemployment-than-9-of-them.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Kenneth Thomas US wages trail 10 OECD countries, but with higher unemployment than 9 of them Contra Eric Cantor, Labor Day celebrates the importance of labor and the labor movement in American history. But the bluster of Cantor, where he celebrates the so-called job creators, does illustrate that organized labor has been in decline [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Kenneth Thomas </p>
<p> US wages trail 10 OECD countries, but with higher unemployment than 9 of them</p>
<p> Contra <a href="http://talkingpointsmemo.com/archives/2012/09/new_labor.php">Eric Cantor</a>, Labor Day celebrates the importance of labor and the labor movement in American history. But the bluster of Cantor, where he celebrates the so-called job creators, does illustrate that organized labor has been in decline in this country for quite some time.    </p>
<p>One result of having a <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2011/09/labor-day-us-has-fifth-lowest-union.html">weak labor movement</a> is that average wages in the United States have fallen behind those of 10 other industrialized democracies that are members of the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD). What is most confounding, for Republicans at least, is that nine of these countries also have lower unemployment, which contradicts their view that high wages (and <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2011/09/labor-day-of-nine-oecd-members-with.html">high minimum wages</a>) harm employment.     </p>
<p>The table below below is constructed from data at OECD StatExtracts, showing the average earnings of all wage and salary workers in each country, as well as its most recent unemployment rate (usually July 2012).<br />Source: <a href="http://stats.oecd.org/Index.aspx#">OECD StatExtracts</a>.</p>
<div><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-XhyZbf6-yNM/UE0JS8DIYxI/AAAAAAAABA4/qEavNdpq94A/s1600/kenneth1.PNG" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="298" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-XhyZbf6-yNM/UE0JS8DIYxI/AAAAAAAABA4/qEavNdpq94A/s320/kenneth1.PNG" width="320"></a></div>
<p>
<div><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-XMMyhcqX2AQ/UE0JXQcTxWI/AAAAAAAABBA/Ne5E0R3Tn5s/s1600/kenneth2.PNG" imageanchor="1"><img a="a" border="0" height="202" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-XMMyhcqX2AQ/UE0JXQcTxWI/AAAAAAAABBA/Ne5E0R3Tn5s/s320/kenneth2.PNG" width="320"><br /></a></div>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>For average wages, select data by theme, then labour, then earnings, then average annual wages, and use &#8220;2011 USD exchange rates and 2011 constant prices&#8221; for each country. For unemployment, select data by theme, then labour, then labour force statistics, then short-term statistics, then short-term labour market statistics, then harmonized unemployment rates.<br />    <br />This table does not make use of purchasing power parity (PPP) conversions to wages (and the U.S. in fact has the highest wages when adjusted for PPP), for a very important reason. Essentially, the PPP calculation adjusts actual exchange rates for differences in the cost of living between countries. In practice, this means downward adjustments for expensive countries like Norway (where I had a personal pan pizza for $25 on my honeymoon six years ago; the <i>New York Times</i> recently published <a href="http://frugaltraveler.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/08/24/scandinavia-on-125-a-day/?ref=travel">more examples</a>) and upward adjustments for developing countries and even Eastern European countries. As I note in <a href="http://us.macmillan.com/investmentincentivesandtheglobalcompetitionforcapital/KennethPThomas"><i>Investment Incentives and the Global Competition for Capital</i></a>, gross national income per capita for the Czech Republic in 2006 was $12,680 at actual exchange rates, but $21,470 at PPP (page 99).<br />    <br />The reason we should ignore PPP when dealing with wages and jobs is that a company deciding to invest in one place rather than another has to pay the wages using the actual exchange rate and is not affected by PPP. Thus, if there is an effect of wages on employment, that will be a response to what an employer actually has to pay to hire someone, not a hypothetical measure of how well off the worker is in terms of PPP-adjusted dollars. The data here does not show any negative effect of wages on unemployment.<br />    <br />Moreover, I would argue that living in a high-wage, high-cost location has distinct advantages over living in a low-wage, low cost location, even if after adjusting for cost of living (via PPP or within a single country) the lower wage location has &#8220;higher&#8221; pay. One important reason is that having extra cash gives you extra options. You will have a higher retirement benefit and will keep it if you move to a lower-cost area, whereas the reverse is not possible. You will have better quality services on average, particularly health care. It is far easier for you to vacation in a low-cost location than it will be for someone in a low-cost location to vacation to a high-cost location ($25 personal pan pizzas!).</p>
<p>Your high salary will be the benchmark if you take a job in a lower-cost location. If you economize from the standard basket of goods used to measure cost of living, your benefit will be higher in the high-cost area. Of course, a full treatment of this issue requires another post, but the big point is that high wages do not necessarily create unemployment and reducing wages is not the route to middle class prosperity.</p>
<p>cross posted with  <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2012/09/labor-day-us-wages-trail-10-oecd.html">Middle Class Political Economist</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/09/us-wages-trail-10-oecd-countries-but-with-higher-unemployment-than-9-of-them.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Does the US Corporate Saving Rate Portend a Lower Unemployment Rate?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/03/does-the-us-corporate-saving-rate-portend-a-lower-unemployment-rate.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/03/does-the-us-corporate-saving-rate-portend-a-lower-unemployment-rate.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Mar 2012 13:34:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Rebecca Wilder]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[savings rate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[unemployment]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/03/does-the-us-corporate-saving-rate-portend-a-lower-unemployment-rate.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Rebecca Wilder Does the US Corporate Saving Rate Portend a Lower Unemployment Rate? An interesting thing happened in Q4 2011: the corporate saving rate declined following two quarters of gains. Nominal net saving by the domestic business sector fell 3%, while nominal gross fixed investment and inventories surged 6% – the two pushed the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by <a href="http://www.economonitor.com/blog/author/rwilder3">Rebecca Wilder</a> </p>
<p>Does the US Corporate Saving Rate Portend a Lower Unemployment Rate? An interesting thing happened in Q4 2011: the corporate saving rate declined following two quarters of gains. Nominal net saving by the domestic business sector fell 3%, while nominal gross fixed investment and inventories surged 6% – the two pushed the saving rate down nearly 40 bps to 2.94% of GDP. The corporate saving rate (gross saving less gross investment) has been on a downward trend since the end of 2009, a welcomed trend by the labor market.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/03/corporate_saving_rate_chart.jpg"><img alt="" height="382" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/03/corporate_saving_rate_chart.jpg" width="582"></a></p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>There’s a very strong correlation between the corporate saving rate and the unemployment rate, 80% according to a simple bivariate OLS regression. I’ve <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2011/03/its-not-structural-unemployment-its.html">argued in the past</a> that there is some causation to this relationship – but that’s not the point of this post. The point here is that the trend in corporate saving has fallen sufficiently to portend some material declines in the unemployment rate in coming quarters….ALL ELSE EQUAL. For example, a simple bivariate regression would forecast a 7.5% unemployment rate if the corporate saving rate falls another 30 bps to 2.6%.</p>
<p>The all else equal is important. The primary driver of this quarter’s decline in the corporate saving rate was the 6% increase in nominal investment spending, the largest quarterly gain since 2010 Q2. Amid relatively weak manufacturing orders and the expiration of the depreciation allowance, I expect that this momentum is unlikely to be matched in coming quarters. Will firms start drawing down nominal saving to finance new hires?</p>
<p>Better put: will the unemployment rate drop to meet the saving rate? Or will the saving rate rise to meet the unemployment rate?</p>
<p><em><strong>Rebecca Wilder</strong></em><br /><em><strong><br /></strong></em><br />originally published at <a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/2012/03/14/does-the-us-corporate-saving-rate-portend-a-lower-unemployment-rate/" target="_blank">The Wilder View..Economonitors</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/03/does-the-us-corporate-saving-rate-portend-a-lower-unemployment-rate.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Which Economy Is Pursuing Procyclical Fiscal Policy?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/02/which-economy-is-pursuing-procyclical-fiscal-policy.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/02/which-economy-is-pursuing-procyclical-fiscal-policy.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2012 20:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[procyclical policies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rebecca Wilder]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[unemployment]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/02/which-economy-is-pursuing-procyclical-fiscal-policy.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by  Rebecca Wilder Which Economy Is Pursuing Procyclical Fiscal Policy? Today the BLS reported that the US unemployment rate dropped to 8.3% in January 2012. This is the lowest measured rate since February 2009 – a local trough. Also this week, Eurostat reported that the Euro area (EA) unemployment rate stabilized in December at 10.4%. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by  <a href="http://www.economonitor.com/blog/author/rwilder3">Rebecca Wilder</a> </p>
<p><strong>Which Economy Is Pursuing Procyclical Fiscal Policy?</strong></p>
<p>Today the <a href="http://bls.gov/news.release/empsit.nr0.htm">BLS reported </a>that the US unemployment rate dropped to 8.3% in January 2012. This is the lowest measured rate since February 2009 – a local trough. Also this week, <a href="http://epp.eurostat.ec.europa.eu/cache/ITY_PUBLIC/3-31012012-AP/EN/3-31012012-AP-EN.PDF">Eurostat reported </a>that the Euro area (EA) unemployment rate stabilized in December at 10.4%. This is the highest level since inception of the euro – a global peak (so far).</p>
<p>It’s pretty easy to see through relative labor performance which economy is pursuing procyclical fiscal policy, namely deficits rise when the economy is booming and fall when the economy is contracting: the EA.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/02/urate_chart1.jpg"><img alt="" height="400" src="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/files/2012/02/urate_chart1.jpg" width="600"></a></p>
<p>originally published at <a href="http://www.economonitor.com/rebeccawilder/">The Wilder View&#8230;Economonitors</a></p>
<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/02/which-economy-is-pursuing-procyclical-fiscal-policy.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Jobs, jobs, jobs</title>
		<link>./../../2011/11/jobs-jobs-jobs.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/11/jobs-jobs-jobs.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2011 13:09:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Hale Stewart]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[unemployment]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/11/jobs-jobs-jobs.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Hale Stewart of BondDad blog discusses jobs&#8230;and jobs&#8230; 1. V shaped real retail sales and industrial production recoveries vs. jobs: &#8230;Comparing those with private jobs (red) and total payrolls (green), we can see that the percentage losses in sales and production were steeper, and have made up nearly or more than all of their ground [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a target="_blank" href="http://seekingalpha.com/article/309329-getting-deep-into-the-weeds-about-jobs-jobs-jobs?">Hale Stewart</a> of <a href="http://bonddad.blogspot.com/">BondDad blog</a> discusses jobs&#8230;and jobs&#8230;</p>
<blockquote><p>1. V shaped real retail sales and industrial production recoveries vs. jobs:</p>
<p>&#8230;Comparing those with private jobs (red) and total payrolls (green), we can see that the percentage losses in sales and production were steeper, and have made up nearly or more than all of their ground compared with jobs. Meanwhile, private jobs have regained only slightly over 30% of their losses. When government employment is added for the total jobs picture, fewer than 25% of the losses have been regained.</p>
<p>2. Comparing improvements in aggregate hours and jobs:</p>
<p>&#8230;Another point I have frequently made is that aggregate hours worked are recovering faster than new jobs. Since more hours were lost than jobs during the recession, if past was prologue then we would have to wait for aggregate hours to regain their lost comparative ground before job growth would match the growth in hours&#8230;.<br /><a name="more"></a><br />3. Comparing real retail sales with jobs:</p>
<p>&#8230;This is yet another indication of just how significant government job losses have been to the relatively poor jobs recovery. At the same time, because real retail sales are a leading indicator for jobs, this reinforces that we should expect to continue to see positive job growth in the economy, with private jobs at least being added at something like a 2% YoY rate.</p>
<p>4. Comparing initial jobless claims with jobs added:</p>
<p>&#8230;In 2010 I thoroughly debunked the idea that we needed 400,000 or less in initial jobless claims to be consistent with job growth. It simply makes a lot of difference how deep the recession is, and also the pattern declining into a recession is quite different from the pattern during a recovery. I pointed out half a year ago that if we were to descend into a &#8220;double dip,&#8221; I would expect to see a break in trend in the scatter graph comparing these two series, with a new trend line to the left of the recovery trend line developing.</p>
<p>5. Okun&#8217;s Law</p>
<p>Okun&#8217;s law is actually a rule of thumb that holds that for every 2% YoY increase in GDP, there should be a 1% decline in the unemployment rate. Generally speaking, 2% YoY GDP growth equals no change in unemployment. A 4% GDP increase gives you a 1% decrease in unemployment. Contrarily a 0% YoY change in GDP gives you a 1% increase in unemployment.</p>
<p>I make use of a corollary, which is the YoY% growth in GDP minus 2% approximately equals the YoY% change in job growth 3 to 6 months later. Here is the graph of this relationship going back 65 years, and it has ominous implications:</p>
<p>&#8230;</p>
<p>As I said, this contradicts virtually all of the previous indicators we have discussed. A possible explanation comes via <a target="_blank" href="http://oldprof.typepad.com/a_dash_of_insight/2011/11/weighing-the-week-ahead-waiting-for-the-ecb.html">Jeff Miller of A Dash of Insight</a>, who informed us yesterday that the BLS&#8217;s Dynamic Business Report of actual job data collected from the states showed that in the first quarter of this year only 250,000 jobs were created, rather than the 500,000 previously reported.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/11/jobs-jobs-jobs.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The social safety net encourages&#8230;?</title>
		<link>./../../2011/11/the-social-safety-net-encourages.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/11/the-social-safety-net-encourages.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2011 15:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Mark Thoma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social safety net]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[unemployment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[unemployment benefits]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/11/the-social-safety-net-encourages.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Mark Thoma responds to the meme that the social safety net encourages bad behavior overall: The idea that the unemployment problem is due to lack of effort on behalf of the unemployed rather than a lack of demand is convenient for the moralists, but inconsistent with the facts. The problem is lack of demand, not [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://economistsview.typepad.com/economistsview/2011/11/social-insurance-and-unemployment-do-people-deserve-poverty.html">Mark Thoma</a> responds to the meme that the social safety net encourages bad behavior overall:<br />
<blockquote>
<p>The idea that the unemployment problem is due to lack of effort on behalf of the unemployed rather than a lack of demand is convenient for the moralists, but inconsistent with the facts. The problem is lack of demand, not the means through which we smooth the negative consequences of recessions.</p>
<p>But what really irks me is the implicit moralizing, the idea that people deserve to be thrown into poverty. Someone who gets up every day and goes to a job day after day, often a job they don&#8217;t like very much, to support their families can suddenly become unemployed in a recession through no fault of their own. They did nothing wrong &#8212; it&#8217;s not their fault the economy went into a recession and they certainly couldn&#8217;t be expected to foresee a recession that experts such as Casey Mulligan missed entirely. <a name="more"></a> They had no reason to believe they had chosen the wrong place to go to work, but unemployment hit them anyway. And since one of the biggest causes of foreclosure is an event like unemployment, it&#8217;s entirely possible that this household would lose its home, be forced to declare bankruptcy, etc., and end up in severe poverty if there were no social services to rely upon.</p>
<p>What moral lesson is being taught here? <!-- more --&gt  Why does this household deserve to be punished for their bad decisions? It did nothing wrong. I understand that people should suffer the consequences of their own bad choices, but that's not what happens in recessions. People who have done nothing to deserve it are nevertheless hit by severe negative shocks. That's what social insurance is for, to smooth the path for such unfortunate households, to avoid sending people into poverty who have done nothing to deserve it (see "<a href="http://economistsview.typepad.com/economistsview/2005/04/_the_need_for_s.html">The Need for Social Insurance</a>"). It is not an attempt to reward bad behavior and most programs do their best to avoid giving benefits to people who have made bad choices (for example, the system is far from perfect but in most states unemployment insurance can only be obtained if you lose your job through no fault of your, e.g. if you quit or get yourself fired it is not available). The extent to which we should distinguish between deserving and undeserving households for social insurance programs is debatable and depends upon the type of program, but the idea that all households are undeserving is, in my view, simply wrong. I would apply the social safety net widely myself -- I think the benefit of the doubt should go to compassion, not harshness and moralizing -- but in any case I'd dispute the idea that "safety-net generosity" is too high. If anything, we are not generous enough.</p>

  
<p><strong>Update</strong>: Karl Smith <a href="http://modeledbehavior.com/2011/11/28/if-the-safety-net-is-so-good-why-is-the-economy-so-bad/">comments</a> on this topic.</p>

  </blockquote>


</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/11/the-social-safety-net-encourages.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>If You Believe the Market Reacts to Information</title>
		<link>./../../2011/08/if-you-believe-the-market-reacts-to-information.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/08/if-you-believe-the-market-reacts-to-information.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2011 19:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[debt]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[markets]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[total information awareness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[unemployment]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/08/if-you-believe-the-market-reacts-to-information.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The bad news of the day is that about $5B ($5,000,000,000) more than previously believed went to buy goods made in China, Japan, non-major South and Central American countries, and other places outside the U.S. Per the Vampire Squid (tm Matt Taibbi), this should cause a revision to Q2 US GDP from 1.3% to 0.9%. [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://www.bea.gov/newsreleases/international/trade/2011/trad0611.htm">bad news of the day</a> is that about $5B ($5,000,000,000) more than previously believed went to buy goods made in China, Japan, non-major South and Central American countries, and other places outside the U.S. Per the Vampire Squid (tm Matt Taibbi), this should cause <a href="http://investmentwatchblog.com/q2-gdp-to-be-second-consecutive-sub-1-print-following-surge-in-trade-deficit/">a revision to Q2 US GDP from 1.3% to 0.9%</a>.</p>
<p>The good news of the day is that weekly unemployment claims were <a href="http://www.dol.gov/opa/media/press/eta/ui/eta20111190.htm">&#8220;only&#8221; 395,000</a>. (Let&#8217;s ignore the detail that last week was originally reported as 398K—<a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2011/07/16-weeks-old-enough-to-drive-not.html">breaking the streak</a>—but is now 402K.)</p>
<p>The net result, at least as of 2:00pm is that the major equity indices are <a href="http://www.google.com/finance?q=INDEXDJX:.DJI#">up by at least 3.80%</a> (DJIA). The early articles claim that was <a href="http://www.thestatecolumn.com/articles/us-stock-market-djia-rebound-after-labor-department-report/">because of the &#8220;good&#8221; news</a>.<br />

<p>
<br /><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-trc09n9EeXQ/TkQlYSECLbI/AAAAAAAAAfs/aS-moQ5EYL0/s1600/newclaims.PNG"><img src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-trc09n9EeXQ/TkQlYSECLbI/AAAAAAAAAfs/aS-moQ5EYL0/s320/newclaims.PNG" border="0" alt=""></a><br />
</p>
<p>
<br />And the scary thing is, they&#8217;re correct. In the 193 weeks since the recession started,* there have only been 39 where initial claims were below 395,000, and two (including the current, possibly-to-be-revised week) that were at that level.</p>
<p>But, especially as <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/plum-line/post/congressional-super-committee-should-focus-on-jobs/2011/03/03/gIQAuWbn8I_blog.html">none of Harry Reid&#8217;s appointees to The Grand Ripoff appear to believe that Jobs would do more good for balancing the budget than the Super Commission</a>, it appears that three-quarters of that August body will be working solely on the numerator, not the denominator, of the Debt/GDP ratio.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/08/if-you-believe-the-market-reacts-to-information.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The current labor market expansion: third poorest performer 24 months after the recession&#8217;s end since 1948</title>
		<link>./../../2011/07/the-current-labor-market-expansion-third-poorest-performer-24-months-after-the-recessions-end-since-1948.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/07/the-current-labor-market-expansion-third-poorest-performer-24-months-after-the-recessions-end-since-1948.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2011 18:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[labor markets]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rebecca Wilder]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[unemployment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[US data]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/07/the-current-labor-market-expansion-third-poorest-performer-24-months-after-the-recessions-end-since-1948.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[It&#8217;s now two years after the end of the Great Recession, and the unemployment rate has ticked downward just 9 pps (percentage points) since its 10.1% peak. Pundits call this an expansion since GDP has fully retraced its recession losses; but the unemployment rate tells a very different story. (click to enlarge) The chart illustrates [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It&#8217;s now two years after the end of the Great Recession, and the unemployment rate has ticked downward just 9 pps (percentage points) since its 10.1% peak. Pundits call this an expansion since GDP has fully retraced its recession losses; but the unemployment rate tells a very different story.</p>
<p>(click to enlarge)</p>
<p><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-mat-CwC8Rug/TiMHwB5uILI/AAAAAAAADxw/nErTS0O9ZsE/s1600/urate_expansion.jpg"><img src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-mat-CwC8Rug/TiMHwB5uILI/AAAAAAAADxw/nErTS0O9ZsE/s400/urate_expansion.jpg" border="0" alt=""></a><br />The chart illustrates the unemployment rate after 24 months since each recession&#8217;s end spanning 1948 to June 2011. The business cycle dates are set by the <a href="http://www.nber.org/cycles.html">National Bureau of Economic Research</a>. The rates are indexed to the first month of each cyclical recovery for comparison, and the raw data are referenced in the table at the end of this post.</p>
<p>MORE AFTER THE JUMP!<br /><a name="more"></a><br />Spanning the business cycles since 1948, the average decline in the unemployment rate is 20 pps from its peak to 24 months after the recession&#8217;s end. In the &#8217;07-&#8217;09 &#8216;expansion&#8217;, the unemployment rate has fallen by less than half the average, -9 pps since the first month of recovery, July 2009.</p>
<p>In terms of relative labor market performance 24 months into the recovery/expansion, this cycle is the fourth worst &#8211; really the third worst since 24 months into the 1980 recovery is the 1981-1982 recession.</p>
<p>Technically, we&#8217;re not seeing a jobless recovery, since the unemployment rate peaked early on in the recovery (month 4); but it might as well be. Sticking with the <a href="http://www.bls.gov/cps/">household survey</a>, employment (as opposed to the <a href="http://www.bls.gov/ces/">nonfarm payroll</a>) is down by near 7 million since the economic peak and down 644 thousand since the recession&#8217;s trough. Yes, employment is net down since the recession ended. These numbers are affected by the annual population controls, but the trend (or lack thereof) is loud and clear. </p>
<p>The labor market is festering &#8211; we need a real policy response now.</p>
<p>Rebecca Wilder</p>
<p>Chart data (before index construction)</p>
<p><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-gZI_9NL_uwE/TiMkVb53IuI/AAAAAAAADyI/WAXCq8IG5BQ/s1600/urate_table.jpg"><img src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-gZI_9NL_uwE/TiMkVb53IuI/AAAAAAAADyI/WAXCq8IG5BQ/s400/urate_table.jpg" border="0" alt=""></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/07/the-current-labor-market-expansion-third-poorest-performer-24-months-after-the-recessions-end-since-1948.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Once more: I WANT MORE SPENDING!</title>
		<link>./../../2011/07/once-more-i-want-more-spending.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/07/once-more-i-want-more-spending.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2011 18:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[income inequality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[monetary policy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obama economic policy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[recession]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[unemployment]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/07/once-more-i-want-more-spending.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by: Daniel Becker Ok some more information to bolster my position that my flower shop being down this year another 4.5% compared to last year (at least the decline is leveling off) is not the results of government debt or too much taxation or banks not lending or unions&#8230; nope, my shop is off because [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>by: Daniel Becker</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>Ok some more information to bolster my position that my flower shop being down this year another 4.5% compared to last year (at least the decline is leveling off) is not the results of government debt or too much taxation or banks not lending or unions&#8230; nope, my shop is off because of one thing: Lack of income in the hands of the many and nothing to date has been done to change that.</div>
<div></div>
<div>As noted <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2011/05/monetary-policy-im-sorry-its-just-not.html">here</a> and<a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2011/06/monetary-policy-im-not-only-not-feeling.html"> here</a>, monetary policy is not going to cut it.  (Please pray for the Greeks.)   </div>
<div>Or I should say, not cutting it for anyone who earns a penny because someone else had an extra penny to spend beyond their non-discretionary expenditures.  That is, they are at the point of autonomous consumption, but not at the point of offsetting income earned from their cognitive or physical labor with that earned from money.  That means we&#8217;re talking about the bottom 90% of the income earning population.  (The top 10% own 82% of the stock.)</div>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />
<hr xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<div>Two<a href="http://libertystreeteconomics.newyorkfed.org/2011/07/discretionary-services-expenditures-in-this-business-cycle.html"> nice charts</a> from the NY Fed bank  </div>
<div><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-TcXXAmEbboY/Ths475J620I/AAAAAAAAARQ/HQ4r-UDgGbU/s1600/Decline+Discretionary+Spending+2011.JPG" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="197" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-TcXXAmEbboY/Ths475J620I/AAAAAAAAARQ/HQ4r-UDgGbU/s320/Decline+Discretionary+Spending+2011.JPG" width="320"></a></div>
<div><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-ByqvlxFgP6Q/Ths4JUFQeYI/AAAAAAAAARM/IJFBHiEvvS8/s1600/Discretionary+spending+in+Recoveries+2011.JPG" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="197" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-ByqvlxFgP6Q/Ths4JUFQeYI/AAAAAAAAARM/IJFBHiEvvS8/s320/Discretionary+spending+in+Recoveries+2011.JPG" width="320"></a></div>
<p>
<div>The first shows just how much of a dive spending has taken.  Considering we&#8217;re a &#8220;consumption economy&#8221;, I don&#8217;t think this bodes well for us.  The second shows how lacking in recovery such spending is compared to prior recession.   </div>
<div></div>
<div>I don&#8217;t know about you, but I don&#8217;t care how much money we pump into the economy at the top, if it doesn&#8217;t get in the hands the bottom 90% of the income earners, there will be no recovery.  It does not matter if the Fed&#8217;s are pumping it in or the Government is doing it via tax reductions because both methods are not putting the majority of the money in the hands of the many.  The Fed article notes that this discretionary spending is &#8220;services&#8221;.  It is 30% of all personal consumption expenditures (PCE).  Non-discretionary is 34% of PCE, that leaves 36% somewhere in the middle?  They state PCE is 70% of all output.  So, 30% of 70% is 21% of all output?  Using $14.7trillion means about 3.09 trillion has taken a 7% hit of $216 billion! ( I readily accept any math corrections in comments)</div>
<div></div>
<div>The author states:  </div>
<blockquote><div>Because consumption accounts for about 70 percent of output, this in turn raises some concern about the future strength of the recovery.</div>
</blockquote>
<blockquote><div>That&#8217;s an understatement!  He hedges some more: Also, households may remain wary about their employment and income prospects, suggesting that they may have lowered their future income expectations.</div>
</blockquote>
<div>Really?  &#8220;May&#8221; is the word one wants to use here? </div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>A <a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/the-collapse-in-us-discretionary-spending-2011-7">Mr. Roche</a> is more direct:</div>
<div></div>
<div>The real weakness in this recovery is rooted in the fact that consumer balance sheets are so mangled that they’re spending primarily on non-discretionary items and saving the rest of their incomes to pay down debts.  This is important to understand because policy must be geared in such a way that it does not further hinder the household balance sheet.  And therein lies the problem with a policy such as QE2.  Anything that can potentially cause cost push inflation will only further weaken the household sector and detract from any possible recovery.  In the case of QE2 I think we saw the increased speculation contribute directly to rising commodity prices which ultimately squeezed consumers further and led to the current soft spot in the economy.</div>
<div>BINGO!</div>
<div></div>
<div>Let&#8217;s not stop there.  From Mr. Weisenthal Under &#8220;<a href="http://real-economics.blogspot.com/2011/07/bankruptcy-of-economics.html">Scariest Job&#8217;s Chart Ever</a>&#8221; we get this one on the duration of unemployment.</div>
<p>
<div></div>
<div><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-OL9753yhsRQ/Ths4_aJ7N5I/AAAAAAAAARU/UOVsmmvGfPo/s1600/Average+Mean+duration+Unemployment+2011.JPG" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="197" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-OL9753yhsRQ/Ths4_aJ7N5I/AAAAAAAAARU/UOVsmmvGfPo/s320/Average+Mean+duration+Unemployment+2011.JPG" width="320"></a></div>
<div>  </div>
<div>Which brings me to my posting from 4/2008:<a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2008/04/longest-recession-ever.html"> The longest Recession Ever</a></div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>I noted in this post that it took 20 months from the Bush 2 recession for the peak of what I call Person Weeks Unemployed (a multiple of the number of people out and the number of weeks out).  I also noted that Reagan with back to back recessions did not see the peak until 30 months past the first recession.  Almost 3 full years!  He also double the quotient.  </div>
<div></div>
<div>I ended with: </div>
<blockquote><div>Thus, the peak of a recession is in the eye of the beholder. If you&#8217;re a person earning money from labor, a recession these days can last a very long time. This data would suggest that what we are seeing in the Spencer post is not a decreased risk but a lull before the storm. One other thing. It appears the Republicans fail again. As a group they have the longest turn-around to seeing a reduction in lost labor.</div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div>There you have it.  You want to fix the economy?  Don&#8217;t follow the conservative ideology.   The Republicans win in delaying recoveries.  Yet, here we are with a &#8220;Democratic&#8221; president using the very language, words, framing of the group that is proven to not know how to create jobs and thus get money in the hands of the many in the shortest amount of time.  Some say the Republicans are doing it this time with intention.  I doubt that, though it is a meme that would make them seem to be the ultimate chess players.  </div>
<div></div>
<div>Yes, I WANT MORE SPENDING!</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/07/once-more-i-want-more-spending.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
