<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>ACA &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Conservative roots of Obamacare</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/conservative-roots-of-obamacare.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/conservative-roots-of-obamacare.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2012 10:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[ACA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kenneth Thomas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obamacare]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/conservative-roots-of-obamacare.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Kenneth Thomas  Conservative roots of Obamacare The pile-on continues. As I discussed in February, Stuart Butler of the Heritage Foundation wrote a breath-taking op-ed in USA Today (via Don Taylor) denying that he fathered the individual mandate. In fact, his revised 140-page research paper was published January 2, 1989, before President George HW Bush [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Kenneth Thomas<br />  <br />Conservative roots of Obamacare</p>
<p> The pile-on continues. As <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2012/02/heritage-doubles-down-on-individual.html">I discussed in February</a>, Stuart Butler of the Heritage Foundation <a href="http://usatoday30.usatoday.com/news/opinion/forum/story/2012-02-03/health-individual-mandate-reform-heritage/52951140/1">wrote a breath-taking op-ed</a> in <i>USA Today</i> (via <a href="http://theincidentaleconomist.com/wordpress/stuart-butlers-change-of-mind/">Don Taylor</a>) denying that he fathered the individual mandate. In fact, his <i>revised</i> 140-page <a href="http://www.heritage.org/research/reports/1989/a-national-health-system-for-america">research paper</a> was <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2012/02/conservatives-refute-butlerheritage.html">published January 2, 1989</a>, before President George HW Bush came into office, let alone President Clinton, whose proposals Butler says his research was directed against. Two conservatives, <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/aroy/2012/02/07/the-tortuous-conservative-history-of-the-individual-mandate/">Avik Roy</a> of <i>Forbes</i> and <a href="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052970204369404577211161144786448.html">James Taranto</a> of the <i>Wall Street Journal</i>, played strong roles in locking down the point that Butler was the first to propose the mandate.<br />    <br />Today, J.D. Kleinke of the American Enterprise Institute goes straight to that 1989 report in a <i>New York Times</i> <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/09/30/opinion/sunday/why-obamacare-is-a-conservatives-dream.html?pagewanted=1&#038;partner=rss&#038;emc=rss">opinion piece</a> to once again lay the mandate at the feet of Heritage. And why not? According to him, the Affordable Care Act is a conservative&#8217;s dream.<br />
<blockquote>The rationalization and extension of the current market is financed by the other linchpin of the law: the mandate that we all carry health insurance, an <a href="http://www.heritage.org/research/reports/1989/a-national-health-system-for-america">idea</a> forged not by liberal social engineers at the Brookings Institution but by conservative economists at the Heritage Foundation. The individual mandate recognizes that millions of Americans who could buy health insurance choose not to, because it requires trading away today’s wants for tomorrow’s needs. The mandate is about personal responsibility — a hallmark of conservative thought. </p></blockquote>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Kleinke argues that Romney&#8217;s incoherence on health care stems precisely from rejecting his accomplishment in Massachusetts. Romney can&#8217;t offer anything better than the ACA because it is the <i>only</i> conservative way to overcome the problems of the health care market while remaining based on the market and individual responsibility. With no single payer and no public option, it is not surprising that, as he puts it, &#8220;the health insurance industry has been quietly supporting the plan all along.&#8221;<br />    <br />Aside from his odd notion that single payer represents a &#8220;government takeover of health care&#8221; (Canada&#8217;s Medicare is not the United Kingdom&#8217;s National Health Service), Kleinke&#8217;s column is on the money: historically, the mandate <i>was</i> developed by Heritage economists, the ACA more broadly relies on conservative rather than liberal principles, and many liberals have been unenthusiastic for just that reason.</p>
<p>Heck, I&#8217;m unenthusiastic (single payer!). But it&#8217;s a big improvement over the status quo that is already providing benefits to millions of people, whether for <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2011/09/aca-works-for-young-adults-as-planned.html">young adults</a>, the millions of consumers getting <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/07/guest-post-health-insurance-rebates.html">rebates</a> due to the medical loss ratio rule, or for seniors getting rid of the donut hole and gaining free preventive care.</p>
<p>crossposted with <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2012/10/conservative-refutation-of.html">Middle Class Political Economist </a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/conservative-roots-of-obamacare.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Hospital Consolidation and ACO&#8217;s</title>
		<link>./../../2012/09/hospital-consolidation-and-acos.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/09/hospital-consolidation-and-acos.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2012 02:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[ACA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ACO]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medical expenses]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Michael Halasy (healthcare)]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/09/hospital-consolidation-and-acos.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Jason Shafrin over at the Healthcare Economist points to this recent paper over at the RWJF. Interestingly the authors find that hospital consolidation increases prices and could decrease quality. Something that many of us have considered in the past. In concentrated markets, the effects were even more pronounced with price increases over 20% noted. Competition was noted to [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Jason Shafrin over at the Healthcare Economist <a href="http://healthcare-economist.com/2012/09/20/hospital-consolidation-prices-and-quality/" target="_blank">point</a>s to this recent <a href="http://www.rwjf.org/content/rwjf/en/research-publications/find-rwjf-research/2012/06/the-impact-of-hospital-consolidation.html" target="_blank">paper</a> over at the RWJF. Interestingly the authors find that hospital consolidation increases prices and could decrease quality. Something that many of us have considered in the past.</p>
<p>In concentrated markets, the effects were even more pronounced with price increases over 20% noted.</p>
<p>Competition was noted to increase quality under an &#8220;administered&#8221; pricing system, ala the NHS in the UK. The evidence for competition increasing quality in a market system was much more mixed.</p>
<p>I have thought this for some time, and have even wrote about the concepts of leverage in the past. For example, I have cited a BNET article before. When one examines the the health markets in Milwaukee and Chicago, which are both midwestern cities, and geographically close to each other, one finds higher prices in Milwaukee, with providers not accepting less than 200% of Medicare. Which does not seem intuitive, as there is far more market competition in the health insurance industry there. In Chicago, one insurer, BC-BS, is rather dominant and prices are lower, with providers accepting 112% of Medicare on average. It would seem to make sense that increasing the leverage of the hospitals and providers through the mechanism of consolidation will increase prices. The same thing happens in Milwaukee, which has no dominant insurer, and therefore is unable to exert leverage over the hospital systems in Milwaukee.</p>
<p>The ACO models as proscribed by the ACA will increase consolidation. By developing an accountable model of care delivery, providers will attempt to consolidate to increase quality and minimize risk exposure in the sense of decreasing reimbursements.</p>
<p>The problem with the RWJF paper, as it rightly notes, is that the study does not really examine integrated health care systems. When you look at consolidation with true vertical and horizontal integration, it is my belief that quality improves even in the absence of competition. True integration in the case of Mayo Clinic and Kaiser also lowers prices.</p>
<p>In essence, I don&#8217;t think the problem is consolidation&#8230;..I think the problem is consolidation in the absence of integration.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/09/hospital-consolidation-and-acos.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Medicare Cuts: What is the Fight About?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/08/medicare-cuts-what-is-the-fight-about.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/08/medicare-cuts-what-is-the-fight-about.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2012 01:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[ACA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cbo projections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[run 75441]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/08/medicare-cuts-what-is-the-fight-about.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Run75411 &#8220;Water For Elephants&#8221; &#8220;carrying water for elephants&#8221; is a phrase that means carrying a heavy load, much like carrying a secret that you can&#8217;t tell even someone you love wholeheartedly, just as in the end Jacob does for his wife.An elephant drinks 25-75 gallons of water a day far more than any man [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Run75411</p>
<p> &#8220;Water For Elephants&#8221;</p>
<p> &#8220;<i>carrying water for elephants&#8221; is a phrase that means carrying a heavy load, much like carrying a secret that you can&#8217;t tell even someone you love wholeheartedly, just as in the end Jacob does for his wife</i><br /><i>.</i><br /><i>An elephant drinks 25-75 gallons of water a day far more than any man would be able to carry at any given time. </i><a href="http://angela-michelle.hubpages.com/hub/Water-For-Elephants"><i>http://angela-michelle.hubpages.com/hub/Water-For-Elephants</i></a><i> &#8220;Water for Elephants&#8221; </i><i>Sometimes when you get older . . . things you think on and wish on start to seem real. And then you believe them, and before you know it they&#8217;re part of your history.&#8221;</i><br /><i><br /></i> Most recently former NY Lt. Governor Betsy McGaughey in the WSJ (August 8th) commented on the ACA in “<i>ObamaCares’s Phoney Deficit Reduction</i>” choosing to carry water for the Republican candidates Romney and Ryan with the hope she can convince voters that President Obama&#8217;s ACA will not reduce the cost of Medicare and instead will rob the Medicare TF. By her words alone, Ms. McGaughey cannot change the numeric of Medicare expected and occurring reduced growth and costs resulting from the passage of ACA. In her, Romney and Ryan&#8217;s mines the logic of how the robbery of benefits and the Medicare is all too real even when the proof of the opposite is self-evident. The three will have to do double time if they are to provide enough water to conflate the ACA to the public if in fact they are to make them believe the illusion.</p>
<p>Ms. McGaughey critiques CBO Director Elmendorf&#8217;s and the JCT&#8217;s analysis (letter to House Leader John Boehner) on the impact of repealing the ACA, what it means to the country in increased costs, and then conflates the cuts to the Advantage Program and other parts of Medicare as actual cuts in benefits to Medicare recipients. The ACA states Medicare benefits cannot be reduced for Medicare recipients. </p>
<p>As operated by commercial insurance companies, the Advantage Program intent was to provide competition to Medicare and separate from Medicare. As Betsy believes and everyone else imagines, private commercial insurance can provide similar benefits at a lower cost and more efficiently. Except the Advantage Program did not do so and has out spent Medicare by an average of $1000 or 7% to 18% (dependent on who you read) more and in total for similar Medicare benefits. </p>
<div><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-wlg41Jc0W4M/UDY_EFHZbHI/AAAAAAAAA-o/5q2gKenImug/s1600/haskell1.png" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="231" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-wlg41Jc0W4M/UDY_EFHZbHI/AAAAAAAAA-o/5q2gKenImug/s320/haskell1.png" width="320"></a></div>
<p>
<div></div>
<div>                                        Ezra Klein , “Romney’s right: Obamacare cuts Medicare by $716 billion. Here’s how.”  <br />                                  Note: HMO is health maintenance organization; PPO is preferred provider organization.<br />   <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/ezra-klein/wp/2012/08/14/romneys-right-obamacare-cuts-medicare-by-716-billion-heres-how/">http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/ezra-klein/wp/2012/08/14/romneys-right-obamacare-cuts-medicare-by-716-billion-heres-how/</a> </div>
<p>                   </p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>The very same CBO Director who wrote about the impact of repealing the ACA to House Leader John Boehner and the resulting increased costs was also a part of the CBO team which pounded the final nail into the &#8220;Hillarycare&#8221; coffin resulting in its demise in Congress. Healthcare then was 20% of the cost of what it is today. I doubt Director Elmendorf has lost any of his boldness since Clinton. So, who is right?</p>
<p>The best way to counter supposition and conjecture by Romney, Ryan, and Ms. McGaughey is to present detail about the cuts and to what they are related , the same as the actual cost of the Advantage program in relation to Medicare. The planned reduction in Medicare costs come from three areas, which also include the government sponsored Advantage program. </p>
<p>
<div><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-AZI2vM2YAQM/UDY-9CwM83I/AAAAAAAAA-g/YXJDPLHnllg/s1600/haskell.jpg" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="245" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-AZI2vM2YAQM/UDY-9CwM83I/AAAAAAAAA-g/YXJDPLHnllg/s320/haskell.jpg" width="320"></a></div>
<div>                                SOURCE: Medicare Payment Advisory Commission Report to Congress, March 2008.</div>
<div>                               &#8220;Medicare Advantage&#8221;; Kaiser Foundation http://www.kff.org/medicare </div>
<p>30.2% of the planned reduction in Medicare costs will come from the elimination of Advantage subsidies as I stated above. The ACA also applies the same rules to the Advantage insurance programs it applies to hospitals by tying reimbursement (or fees) to quality of outcomes instead of a fee for the number of services provided.</p>
<p>34.8% of the reduction in cost comes from revised calculations in the reimbursement of hospitals for provided services. Hospitals not only give up the pay-for-services cost model to embrace better quality outcomes for services cost model; but, they move to electronic record keeping (which proved to be cost effective with the VA, Longman &#8220;<i>Best Care Anywhere</i>&#8220;), and the bundling of payments eliminating multiple billings and forcing a split of the total compensation. Knowing the increase in patients coming from the addition of the uninsured, there is also the influx of an aging baby-boomer population, which also influenced hospitals to accept the changes.</p>
<p>35% of the reduction result from a combination of smaller cuts in extra funds ( ~5%) given to hospitals to cover the uninsured (not needed as more people will be covered), reductions in homecare providers (~8%), fraud reduction, etc..</p>
<p>The $716 billion is far larger than the initial $449 billion first reported. In 2010, the CBO arrived at an estimate of savings of ~$449 billion starting from 2012 onwards and covered 6- 7 years from when the bill takes full effect in 2014 to 2019. The second estimate of savings was the result of John Boehner&#8217;s request for a review of the costs and gains realized from the repeal the ACA in its entirety. The second review covered the period from 2014 to 2022 and resulted in the $716 billion. http://www.brookings.edu/blogs/up-front/posts/2012/08/15-medicare-cuts-galston &#8220;<i>Medicare Cuts: What is the Fight About?&#8221;</i><br /><i><br /></i> <i></i><br />And what of other things implied?</p>
<p>&#8211; Healthcare spending was 17.9% of GDP in 2010 and will rise to 19.6% in 2021. Neglected and a part of the article from which this snippet of CMS information was pulled is this: <i>&#8220;</i><i> Current projections also do not include potential drops in spending through health care delivery reforms, such as the accountable care organizations and medical homes being promoted by the health law.&#8221; </i>In other words, the author projections of $ and % are being made as if the ACA did not exist. The author of this particular article is an MBA and not an economist or a doctor. Quelle Surprise?</p>
<p>&#8211; &#8220;<i>Repeal also would reduce government spending, lower taxes, and undo the evisceration of Medicare; all good results.</i>&#8221; I guess it is still unclear how Medicare is to be eviscerated under the ACA when Obama will plow the results back into Medicare, and the CMS has lengthen the TF out to 2024-2029. Comparing this to Romney wishing to end Medicare and Ryan wanting to keep the very same reductions as the ACA and take the savings for tax breaks, who is eviscerating what?</p>
<p>Healthcare Costs have been decreasing for years? Maybe not so long and since 2009/2010 at the earliest?</p>
<div><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-ujMS2GY8Bjc/UDY_JmpJJ4I/AAAAAAAAA-w/fLBevXKyZk0/s1600/haskell2.jpg" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="189" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-ujMS2GY8Bjc/UDY_JmpJJ4I/AAAAAAAAA-w/fLBevXKyZk0/s320/haskell2.jpg" width="320"></a></div>
<p>Secretary of Heath Kathy Sebelius made the comment in an article that a family of 4 paid ~$6,000 for private insurance in 2000 and ~$12,000 for similar insurance in 2009. http://www.voxxi.com/kathleen-sebelius-affordable-care-act/ &#8220;<i>Public Needs To Get Their Facts Straight</i>&#8221; Part of this is due to increased administrative costs and much more is a reflection of increased healthcare care costs which insurance and Medicare reflects.</p>
<p>Medicare has had slower growth because it has taken the necessary actions to control much of the costs associated with healthcare through pilot programs, negotiations, etc. The results of its actions are clear in the S&#038;P Indices. The increase in enrollment of healthier patients over the last two recessions has contributed to the slow down; however, it is the ACA which started hospitals and doctors to begin to plan for full implementation and take the steps necessary to meet ACA goals for commercial insurance.</p>
<p>&#8220;<i>spending per enrollee slowed to 4.2% annually, as compared with 4.5% among private payers. After large increases in enrollment due to two recessions and the increasing numbers of Americans with disabilities are accounted for, growth of Medicaid spending per enrollee was relatively slow (less than 3% per… http://www.nationaljournal.com/healthcare/both-obama-and-romney-medicare-plans-fail-to-solve-the-cost-problem-20120816</i> &#8220;<i>Medicare and Medicaid Spending Trends and the Deficit Debate&#8221;</i><br /><i><br /></i> &#8211; And the Pink Cadillac Tax? The ACA does impose a tax on plans exceeding $27,000 and typically carried by executives in the rarefied levels of management. They can always shuck it off and go to one of the insurance exchanges for a cheaper plan with no tax. There is also an excise tax on plans with premiums exceeding $10,200 for individuals or $27,500 for a family tax Other taxes include Increase Medicare tax rate by .9% and impose added tax of 3.8% on unearned income for high-income taxpayers.</p>
<p>So what is the Fight About? It is about whether Romney/Ryan can eliminate Medicare and repeal the ACA, and keep the same proposals President Obama put in play for Medicare but using the savings from it elsewhere (tax breaks &#8211; think SS surplus) rather than within Medicare, as both are opposed to Obama plowing the savings back into Medicare. http://www.brookings.edu/blogs/up-front/posts/2012/08/15-medicare-cuts-galston &#8220;<i>Medicare Cuts: What is the Fight About?&#8221;</i><br /><i><br /></i> References:<i> </i></p>
<p><i></i><br /><i>Maggie Mahar Health Beat Blog</i><br /><i></i><br /><a href="http://www.cbpp.org/cms/index.cfm?fa=view&#038;id=3161">http://www.cbpp.org/cms/index.cfm?fa=view&#038;id=3161</a> Federal Government Will Pick Up Nearly All Costs of Health Reform’s Medicaid Expansion<br /><i></i><br />http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/ezra-klein/wp/2012/08/14/romneys-right-obamacare-cuts-medicare-by-716-billion-heres-how/ &#8221; Romney’s right: Obamacare cuts Medicare by $716 billion. Here’s how<br />http://www.drugchannels.net/2011/08/cms-bright-future-for-drug-spending-in.html CMS Bright Future for Spending . . .<br />http://www.cms.gov/apps/docs/ACA-Update-Implementing-Medicare-Costs-Savings.pdf<br />Affordable Care Act Update: Implementing Medicare Cost Savings<br />http://www.ajhp.org/content/69/5/405.abstract Projecting future drug expenditures—2012<br />http://www.brookings.edu/blogs/up-front/posts/2012/08/15-medicare-cuts-galston Medicare Cuts: What Is the Fight About?<br />http://www.kff.org/medicare/upload/2052-11.pdf Medicare Advantage<br />http://factcheck.org/2012/06/romney-obama-uphold-health-care-falsehoods/ Romney, Obama Uphold Health Care Falsehoods<br />http://www.voxxi.com/kathleen-sebelius-affordable-care-act/ Public Needs . . . <br />http://www.reuters.com/article/2012/06/12/us-usa-healthcare-spending-idUSBRE85B1DI20120612 Government forecasts modest health spending growth<br />http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052702303768104577462731719000346.html?mod=WSJ_hps_LEFTTopStories &#8221; Steep Rise in Health Costs Projected&#8221;<br />http://www.nejm.org/doi/pdf/10.1056/NEJMp1204899 &#8220;<i>Medicare and Medicaid Spending Trends and the Deficit Debate&#8221;</i><br />http://www.urban.org/UploadedPDF/412419-Containing-the-Growth-of-Spending-in-the-US-Health-System.pdf &#8220;<i>Containing the Growth of Spending in the U.S. Health System&#8221;</i></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/08/medicare-cuts-what-is-the-fight-about.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>About Ann Romney’s—And Other MS Victims’—Darkest Hour (those who have healthcare insurance, those who have very high deductibles, and those who may lose their jobs and be unable to get new healthcare insurance. Or a dressage horse.)</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/about-ann-romneys-and-other-ms-victims-darkest-hour-those-who-have-healthcare-insurance-those-who-have-very-high-deductibles-and-those-who-may-lose-their-jobs-and.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/about-ann-romneys-and-other-ms-victims-darkest-hour-those-who-have-healthcare-insurance-those-who-have-very-high-deductibles-and-those-who-may-lose-their-jobs-and.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 19 Jul 2012 18:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[ABC News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ACA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ann Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[DNC ad]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[dressage]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mandy Clive]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Multiple Sclerosis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obamacare]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/about-ann-romneys-and-other-ms-victims-darkest-hour-those-who-have-healthcare-insurance-those-who-have-very-high-deductibles-and-those-who-may-lose-their-jobs-and.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The DNC has apologized for using Ann Romney&#8217;s London Olympics-bound horse in an attack targetting her husband. The Hill explains that Democrats had used the dressage horse to illustrate its claim that the presumptive GOP nominee was &#8220;dancing around the issue&#8221; of his decision not to release his tax returns. (Dressage is a dance-like sport, but on [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>The DNC has apologized for using Ann Romney&#8217;s London Olympics-bound horse in an attack targetting her husband.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The <em><a href="http://thehill.com/blogs/blog-briefing-room/news/238879-dnc-backs-off-dressage-romney-attack-ads" target="_blank">Hill</a></em> explains that Democrats had used the dressage horse to illustrate its claim that the presumptive GOP nominee was &#8220;dancing around the issue&#8221; of his decision not to release his tax returns. (Dressage is a dance-like sport, but on a horse. Get it?)
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The problem? The horse is used by Ann Romney for therapy related to her multiple sclerosis.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>DNC spokesperson Brad Woodhouse told ABC News that the decision to use footage of the horse &#8220;was not meant to offend Mrs. Romney in any way, and we regret it if it did.&#8221; Woodhouse added that the group won&#8217;t &#8220;invoke the horse any further to avoid misinterpretation.” 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>For what it&#8217;s worth, the dressage horse, named Rafalca, apparently gets the Romneys a rather hefty tax credit. (Literally, fwiw: <a href="http://jezebel.com/5919987/mitt-romneys-fancy-horse-is-worth-more-than-your-entire-family" target="_blank">$77,000</a> a year.)
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212; <i><a href="http://slatest.slate.com/posts/2012/07/19/ann_romney_s_horse_dnc_says_they_won_t_use_it_anymore_in_campaign_ads_.html#comments">DNC Sorry for Using AnnRomney&#8217;s Horse in Attack Ad: TheDemocrats say they won&#8217;t use the Olympic-bound animal in future campaign spots</a></i>, Abby Ohlheiser, Slate, today
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>A headline today on ABC News’ website, about an interview there today with Ann Romney, is “<a href="http://abcnewsradioonline.com/politics-news/ann-romney-opens-up-about-illness-calls-ms-diagnosis-my-dark.html">Mitt Romney&#8217;s Wife, Ann, Calls MS Diagnosis &#8216;MyDarkest Hour&#8217;</a>.”  Unquestionably, that was a dark hour for her, and one that anyone can empathize with.  And, yes, it’s great that dressage helps her regain some of the ability to balance she lost due to her MS. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>But here’s my question to Ann Romney and her husband: How much darker an hour does she think it is for someone who’s given that diagnosis and either has no healthcare insurance or has a very high deductible, or who now dearly fears the loss of his or her job, either because of the health problem or for other reasons, and who, for resulting financial reasons or preexisting-condition reasons—or both—may never again have health insurance if the ACA is repealed? Or be able to get a dressage horse.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I don’t think Obama or the DNC should shy away from asking this question.  Or from doing an ad in which someone in exactly that position asks it. 
</p>
</div>
<p>&#8212;-</p>
<p>UPDATE: Because of the emotional impact of this particular issue, I want post as part of the main post a Comments Section exchange between reader Mandy Clive and me.  Here it is:</p>
<p>
<div>Mandy Clive: I&#8217;m confused. Does owning horses or houses somehow make you a bad presidential candidate? And therapeutic horse riding is used for all sorts of medical conditions, so this is not unusual. Regardless of who I think should win the election, Ann Romney is drawing alot of attention to multiple sclerosis, which is a largely unknowable disease at this point. I have it. Its ruining my life. We need more awareness and research so we can actually understand what causes this disease and how to treat it with something better than a 33% success rate. I&#8217;m all for candidates hashing out their issues, but I agree with those who are calling for a cease fire when it comes to involving Ann and her illness. MS needs positive attention and deserves respect.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Me: Does owning horses or houses somehow make you a bad presidential candidate? That depends on how you got the money to buy the several dressage horses, each worth several hundred thousand dollars, and to buy the several houses, each worth several million dollars.  And on such things as whether or not you paid the full amount of taxes you owed, or instead hid or misrepresented the value of the assets in offshore accounts, including offshore IRA accounts, in order to evade taxes or even to avoid taxes using legal means available only to the very wealthy.  And whether your proposed tax policies, such as reducing yet again taxes on the wealthy, would benefit you (the candidate) extensively, to the detriment of a large percentage of the public. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And, of course, on what you (the voter, rather than the candidate) thinks is a bad presidential candidate. My view is different than yours, obviously.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>As for Ann Romney’s MS and dressage therapy, it was Romney herself, not the DNC, that raised the issue, by going on television this morning and responding to the DNC ad by telling everyone that she uses the Olympic horse for therapy.  (She has several substitute horses when that horse is training or in, say, London for a competition.  She didn’t mention that, though, I guess.)  She also said that the MS diagnosis was her darkest hour. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Her husband is running for president partly on a platform of repealing the ACA, including the provision that requires insurance companies to accept everyone regardless of preexisting medical conditions, and, of course, the provisions that provide for expansion of Medicaid and for subsidies for premiums for some others.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>You say that we need more awareness and research so we can actually understand what causes this disease and how to treat it with something better than a 33% success rate.  So true.  It’s true for so many other very series diseases, as well, that effect young people and middle-aged people.  ([Muscular dystrophy] comes quickly to my mind; someone dear to me died of it two years ago after having lived most of his life in a motorized wheelchair.)  But in this country, unlike in every other advanced industrialized democracy in the world, medical advances can be made use of here only by those who have access to employee-benefit medical insurance.  You’re obviously among them.  But not everyone else with MS or another debilitating chronic illness is.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>
<div>Although I didn&#8217;t put this in my Comment response, I&#8217;d also like to note that under Romney&#8217;s proposed tax and budget cuts, which are extreme, there would be virtually no federal funds for medical research, either to the universities or to the NIH. So if you&#8217;re someone who places a high value on medical research—and I suspect that most people do—this is no small matter to consider when deciding whether Romney is a bad candidate or not.</div>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/about-ann-romneys-and-other-ms-victims-darkest-hour-those-who-have-healthcare-insurance-those-who-have-very-high-deductibles-and-those-who-may-lose-their-jobs-and.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Let’s try to stick to the real world when we talk about Medicaid,</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/lets-try-to-stick-to-the-real-world-when-we-talk-about-medicaid.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/lets-try-to-stick-to-the-real-world-when-we-talk-about-medicaid.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 18 Jul 2012 11:23:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[ACA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Incidental Economist]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medicaid]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/lets-try-to-stick-to-the-real-world-when-we-talk-about-medicaid.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The Incidental Economist addresses election snippets that keep on going, just like in the movies.  Read the whole thing: Let’s try to stick to the real world when we talk about Medicaid, by Aaron Carroll: (Note: Paul Krugman cites here. Tyler Cowen responds here. I respond to Cowen’s response here.) Tyler Cowen had a piece [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>The Incidental Economist addresses election snippets that keep on going, just like in the movies.  Read the whole thing:</div>
<blockquote><p><a href="http://theincidentaleconomist.com/wordpress/lets-try-to-stick-to-the-real-world-when-we-talk-about-medicaid/">Let’s try to stick to the real world when we talk about Medicaid, by Aaron Carroll</a>:</p>
<p><em>(Note: Paul Krugman cites <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/07/16/medicaid-zombies/">here</a>. Tyler Cowen responds <a href="http://marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2012/07/aaron-carroll-on-medicaid-wars.html">here</a>. I respond to Cowen’s response <a href="http://theincidentaleconomist.com/wordpress/tyler-cowen-on-me-on-medicaid-wars/">here</a>.)</em></p>
<p>Tyler Cowen <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/07/15/business/medicaids-new-tug-of-war-economic-view.html">had a piece in the NYT</a> this weekend on Medicaid. He doesn’t seem too thrilled with its use in the ACA’s coverage expansion. </p>
<p>&#8230; I have to admit that his article set me off a bit. It could be that he didn’t have space in the NYT for more nuance. Perhaps he’ll provide it on his blog. In particular, I’d love him to address some of the points below…</p>
<p>I get a bit annoyed by blanket claims that doctors won’t accept Medicaid&#8230;.<br />I get a bit annoyed when people just claim government programs are “unpopular”&#8230;<br />I get a bit annoyed at the blanket acceptance of the awesomeness of the free market in health care, when there is no phenomenal evidence of its success&#8230;</p>
<p>&#8230;</p>
<p>Look, I get that people may not like the political implications of those systems. They may not like the governments that produce them. They may not like the <a href="http://theincidentaleconomist.com/wordpress/reduced-spending-is-the-wrong-argument/">lack of choice</a>  inherent in such systems. They may not like the potential  limitations within them for making money, and therefore for innovation. But we need to stop making stuff up about them.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/lets-try-to-stick-to-the-real-world-when-we-talk-about-medicaid.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Health Care Thoughts: Crazy like Foxes</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/health-care-thoughts-crazy-like-foxes.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/health-care-thoughts-crazy-like-foxes.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 12 Jul 2012 10:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[ACA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health care thoughts]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/health-care-thoughts-crazy-like-foxes.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt Health Care Thoughts: Crazy like Foxes? Several governors are announcing they will not begin building the state health exchanges required by PPACA (Obamacare). Some of this is pure partisan, and some a stall until November. Failure to comply will result in the feds installing exchanges in those states. The states [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Tom aka Rusty Rustbelt</p>
<p>Health Care Thoughts: Crazy like Foxes?</p>
<p>Several governors are announcing  they will not begin building the state health exchanges required by PPACA  (Obamacare). Some of this is pure partisan, and some a stall until  November.</p>
<p>Failure to comply will result in the feds installing exchanges  in those states.</p>
<p>The states can apparently opt in to the exchange at a  later date.</p>
<p>Could this be a means of allowing the feds to do all of the  heavy lifting, and then jumping in at a convenient time later? Is there more  than partisan thinking here? Interesting?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/health-care-thoughts-crazy-like-foxes.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tax Foundation Misses the Ball (again) in its analysis of Supreme Court Health Care Ruling</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/tax-foundation-misses-the-ball-again-in-its-analysis-of-supreme-court-health-care-ruling.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/tax-foundation-misses-the-ball-again-in-its-analysis-of-supreme-court-health-care-ruling.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 11 Jul 2012 11:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[ACA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linda Beale (Tax law)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Supreme court]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/tax-foundation-misses-the-ball-again-in-its-analysis-of-supreme-court-health-care-ruling.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Beale Tax Foundation Misses the Ball (again) in its analysis of Supreme Court Health Care Ruling The Tax Foundation pretends to be non-partisan.  Of course we all know that is pretense.  Look at the way it has pushed its concept of the so-called &#8220;tax freedom day&#8221;, which misleads everyday Americans into thinking that [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Linda Beale</p>
<p>Tax Foundation Misses the Ball (again) in its analysis of Supreme Court Health Care Ruling</p>
<p>The <a href="http://www.taxfoundation.org/">Tax Foundation</a> pretends to be non-partisan.  Of course we all know that is pretense.  Look at the way it has pushed its concept of the so-called &#8220;tax freedom day&#8221;, which misleads everyday Americans into thinking that they are working for months and months to pay taxes, based on the use of &#8220;average&#8221; tax burdens across every American from Bill Gates to Joe Unemployed and a good deal of uncertainty about just who pays what taxes (like the corporate taxes).</p>
<p>They&#8217;ve done it again in their analysis of the health care decision.  See Richard Morrison and Joseph Henchman, Tax Foundation, <a href="http://www.heraldnews.com/newsnow/x1660542461/GUEST-OPINION-The-tax-flaw-in-health-care-ruling">Guest Opinion, The Tax Flaw in Health Care Ruling</a>, The Hearld News (July 3, 2012).</p>
<p>1.  The Tax Foundation builds its conclusion into its description of the givens.<br />They start out with their conclusion&#8211;a definition of taxes as items whose intent is &#8220;raising revenue for government spending&#8221; and of a &#8220;penalty&#8221; as &#8220;imposed for the purpose of punishing an individual for an unlawful act.&#8221;  Based on that conclusory definition, they conclude unsurprisingly that the ACA&#8217;s <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Individual_mandate">individual mandate</a> is not a tax, because it is a penalty.  That kind of argument has the cart leading the horse.<br />Taxes do increase revenues, but that doesn&#8217;t mean that they cannot also be used to modify behavior, which is what penalties do.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>The obvious type of taxes that act as penalties are excise taxes. There is considerable discussion about &#8220;sin taxes&#8221;&#8211;taxes on cigarettes, alcohol, and other commodities or behaviors that are disliked.  If the person engages in the &#8216;bad&#8217; behavior, the person pays the tax penalty and at least the government gets some revenue from the misbehavior.  If the person is discouraged from engaging in the bad behavior because of the tax penalty, the penalty has done its job and there is more of the desired good behavior.  Tax penalties also exist in our current income tax laws&#8211;the &#8220;singles penalty&#8221;, as mentioned in a prior post, causes a single person to pay more tax than that person would if married, thus penalizing the person for failure to marry.  (Conversely, in situations where there is a <a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2012/07/paul-morenos-short-history-of-the-taxing-power.html">marriage penalty</a>, the tax causes a married person to pay more tax than that person would if single, thus penalizing the person for failure to divorce.)  And there are many credits and other items that can be seen as simply notational variations on a penalty.  For example, the greater tax that childless couples pay than couples of the same income with children pay can easily be viewed as a tax penalty for not having children.</p>
<p>2.  The Tax Foundation tries to raise fears of a bad impact for states<br />The Tax Foundation&#8217;s next argument is the old &#8220;slippery slope&#8221; problem (and depends on the success of their first, unsuccessful, argument).  Since it claims the tax versus penalty distinction is &#8220;vital&#8221;, and there are local and state government revenue sources that are not generally thought of as taxes, the Foundation also claims that the Supreme Court&#8217;s purported broadening of the concept of tax could mean those state and local items must also be treated as taxes for state law purposes, and this could mean that they will be subject to different procedural rules for taxes rather than the procedural rules under which they were passed.<br />This appears beyond silly.   What it does mean for states is that a state like Massachusetts, that had already passed a state health care law with a mandate similar to the ACA&#8217;s mandate, can rest assured that it is not an unconstitutional form of tax.</p>
<p>3.  The Tax Foundation misunderstands the relationship between the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Commerce_Clause">Commerce Clause</a> and the Taxing Power<br />The Foundation didn&#8217;t want the mandate upheld, and the right-wing is fighting hard for a much narrower view of the Commerce Clause with the idea of preventing progressives from undertaking needed national policies.  The Court found the Commerce Clause didn&#8217;t extend to the mandate, a conclusion which seems extraordinarily weak to me and which I predict will be overturned by another Court within thirty years.<br />But the Commerce Clause doesn&#8217;t decide the case, because the taxing power is even broader than the Commerce Clause power.  And Roberts rightly recognized that.  This was not a &#8220;twisting [of] the traditional and historic meaning of a tax&#8221; but rather the expected and predictable analysis based on the traditional and historic understanding of the taxing power.</p>
<p>4. The Tax Foundation raises the &#8220;direct&#8221; tax issue<br />Tax academics have devoted a lot of discussion to consider what would be a direct tax that had to be apportioned among the states.  Calvin Johnson, Professor at the University of Texas,  wrote an interesting book looking into the history of the Constitutional Convention as motivated in large part by a desire to get around the weak taxing power of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Articles_of_Confederation">Articles of Confederation</a>, which required requisitions from the states to allow a strong taxing power in the federal government.  the passage of the income tax amendment&#8211;contravening any need for apportionment&#8211;pretty much left the direct/apportioned taxes as an archaic category.</p>
<p>The article cclaims that the mandate can&#8217;t fall within the income tax since it is a flat tax.  But of course everyone knows that the Tax Foundation and every other right-wing organization thinks that a flat tax on income is constitutional. </p>
<p>The Tax Foundation is quite simply wrong in suggesting that this is a &#8220;new&#8221; definition of tax.<br />(By the way, the Tax Foundation also attributes the entire opinion (and the purported &#8220;new definition&#8221;) to Chief Justice Roberts.  He was the author of the opinion for the Court, but the opinion represents the views of a majority of the Supreme Court Justices.  It is not just Roberts&#8217; opinion. )</p>
<p>crossposted with <a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/tax/2012/07/tax-foundation-misses-the-ball-again-in-its-analysis-of-supreme-court-health-care-ruling-.html">ataxingmatter</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/tax-foundation-misses-the-ball-again-in-its-analysis-of-supreme-court-health-care-ruling.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Same as MA Healthcare Premiums, the ACA Premiums are too Costly . . .</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/the-same-as-ma-healthcare-premiums-the-aca-premiums-are-too-costly.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/the-same-as-ma-healthcare-premiums-the-aca-premiums-are-too-costly.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 11 Jul 2012 11:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[ACA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Incidental Economist]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[run 75441]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/the-same-as-ma-healthcare-premiums-the-aca-premiums-are-too-costly.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Run75441 The Same as MA Healthcare Premiums, the ACA Premiums are too Costly . . . Chicken Little, Courtesy of &#8220;EW.Com Entertainment Weekly&#8221;I have listened to many  stating the MA subsidies do not go far enough in alleviating the costs of healthcare for a family not covered by an Employer Subsidized Healthcare plan. Even [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Run75441</p>
<p>The Same as MA Healthcare Premiums, the ACA Premiums are too Costly . . .</p>
<p><a href="http://lh5.ggpht.com/-CPDv_9UZutA/T_rZb5ObVOI/AAAAAAAAA5w/eMCNEukUbzc/s1600-h/clip_image001%25255B3%25255D.jpg"><img alt="clip_image001" border="0" height="184" src="http://lh4.ggpht.com/-sqzLsgCq5SA/T_rZcYaQJSI/AAAAAAAAA54/P4NMJi6rzwo/clip_image001_thumb.jpg?imgmax=800" title="clip_image001" width="244"></a><br /><a href="http://img2.timeinc.net/ew/dynamic/imgs/061212/16047__little_l.jpg">Chicken Little</a>, Courtesy of<i> &#8220;EW.Com Entertainment Weekly&#8221;</i><br /><i><br /></i><br />I have listened to many  stating the MA subsidies do not go far enough in alleviating the costs of healthcare for a family not covered by an Employer Subsidized Healthcare plan. Even with my pointing out the subsidies in the ACA exceed that of the MA plan, there still has been quite a bit of doubt.</p>
<p>Maggie Mahar at the resurrected Health Beat Blog http://www.healthbeatblog.com/2012/07/what-will-the-supreme-courts-decision-mean-for-the-november-election-part-1/ <i></i>pointed to a new Kaiser Family Foundation subsidy calculator in her article as well as other informative points; &#8220;<i>What Will the Supreme Court Decision Mean In November?&#8221; </i>The ACA Premium Calculator is found here: <a href="http://healthreform.kff.org/Home/KHS/SubsidyCalculator.aspx?source=FS" target="_blank"><i>Healthcare Reform Subsidy Calculator.</i></a><br /><i></i><br /><a name="more"></a><i><br /></i><br />Using the KFF Calculator, a person can calculate what they will pay in premiums under the ACA in 2014. Further on down this post, there is a short discussion of the Mandate and a link to another KFF site to determine what the mandated penalty might be per year for an individual and a family. The last chart by &#8220;The Incidental Economist&#8221; touches upon the relative size of the Mandate in comparison to taxes historically. As a mandated penalty, Obamacare is a middle of the pack tax. </p>
<p>With the KFF calculator, assuming we are discussing Median Household Income, and making an addition assumption Household Median Income increases from the ~$51,000 in 2011 to ~$55,000 in 2013, this is what a family of 4 might pay in 2014:</p>
<p>&#8211; Income (family of 4) $55,000 (235% of Poverty)<br />&#8211; Policyholder Age: 45<br />&#8211; ESI: None Available<br />&#8211; Regional Cost Factor: Median<br />&#8211; Unsubsidized Healthcare Premium: $14,425<br />&#8211; Government Tax Credit: $10,110<br />&#8211; Out of Pocket Premium: $4,125<br />&#8211; 2014 Maximum Out of Pocket Expenses: $6,250</p>
<p>Mandate/Tax Penalty is huge? And what if an individual does not buy insurance from the state insurance exchanges; the individual would pay a Mandate Penalty in 2014 of $95/adult and $47.50 per child (or 1% of income, whichever is greater). In 2016, the mandate would be $695/adult and 50% for children (or 2.5% of income, whichever is greater). http://healthreform.kff.org/the-basics/Requirement-to-buy-coverage-flowchart.aspx <i>&#8220;The Requirement to Buy Healthcare Coverage&#8221; </i>For those who wish to argue Mandate versus Tax, please remember all laws are open to interpretation which does not change the initial intent of the Act passed by Congress.</p>
<p>ACA is the Biggest Tax Ever? It does not even come close to the tax Truman passed to cover WWII costs or even the Reagan Tax Increases of 1982. http://theincidentaleconomist.com/wordpress/obamacare-is-the-biggest-tax-increase-in-history-if-you-ignore-history/ Incidental Economist <i>&#8220;Obamacare is the Biggest Tax Ever, If You Ignore History&#8221;</i><br /><i><br /></i><br /><a href="http://lh6.ggpht.com/-cT38JaKQ4mI/T_rZcorpFxI/AAAAAAAAA6A/99MqShSW6HA/s1600-h/clip_image003%25255B3%25255D.jpg"><img alt="clip_image003" border="0" height="169" src="http://lh6.ggpht.com/-EEpuzxeEJBA/T_rZc21wnpI/AAAAAAAAA6I/pl6HsN8qyCg/clip_image003_thumb.jpg?imgmax=800" title="clip_image003" width="244"></a></p>
<p>Austin Frakt, The Incidental Economist,<a href="http://theincidentaleconomist.com/wordpress/obamacare-is-the-biggest-tax-increase-in-history-if-you-ignore-history/"><i>Obamacare is the biggest tax increase in history … if you ignore history</i></a></p>
<p>Maybe the sky is not falling with SCOTUS declaring the ACA is constitutional?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/the-same-as-ma-healthcare-premiums-the-aca-premiums-are-too-costly.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Opponents Into Frenzy</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/opponents-into-frenzy.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/opponents-into-frenzy.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 09 Jul 2012 12:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[ACA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SCOTUS]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/opponents-into-frenzy.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Barkley Rosserre-posted from Econospeak with permission from the author Lack Of Market Reaction To SCOTUS Ruling On Obamacare Sends Opponents Into Frenzy The day before yesterday, former Obama advisor Austan Goolsbee published a column in the Wall Street Journal entitled &#8220;The Supreme Court Rules, The Market Yawns,&#8221; noting only a small drop in the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by <a href="http://econospeak.blogspot.com/2012/07/lack-of-market-reaction-to-scotus.html">Barkley Rosser</a><br />re-posted from <i>Econospeak</i> with permission from the author</p>
<p>Lack Of Market Reaction To SCOTUS Ruling On Obamacare Sends Opponents Into Frenzy</p>
<p>The day before yesterday, former Obama advisor Austan Goolsbee published a column in the Wall Street Journal entitled &#8220;The Supreme Court Rules, The Market Yawns,&#8221; noting only a small drop in the stock market (about 26 points on the DJIA) on June 28, 2012, the day the SCOTUS ruled most of the ACA to be constitutional.  A nice link can be found on Economists View for &#8220;Links for 07-05-2012&#8221; at <a href="http://economistsview.typepad.com/">http://economistsview.typepad.com/</a> .  Commentary on Mark Thoma&#8217;s link was limited and restrained, mostly discussing fine points of mandates versus taxes and how long the new system might last (which I have many criticisms of, for the record, not my first choice for a reform).<br />    <br />OTOH, when Tyler Cowen made the same link  almost no commentary at <a href="http://marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2012/07/from-austan-goolsbee.html">http://marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2012/07/from-austan-goolsbee.html</a> , many of his commenters simply went bananas.  Besides the name-calling and usual ranting, the substantive point argued was that the market did fall in the immediate aftermath of the announcement (which overturned the strong forecast on intrade, much revered by readers of MR), only to rally later in the day after positive news about European bonds (and to be followed by major gains the following day, supposedly on the bond news as well).  Certainly there were hysterians who think Obamneycare is the end of the world who sold immediately, but it did not take much for others to leap in and start buying and move right on past the decision.  One individual denouncing Goolsbee provided a link, but this one rather sensibly noted that stocks in the healthcare sector went in different directions, with hospital ones generally going up and health insurance ones generally going down.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a>   <br />While Goolsbee perhaps should have noted the initial market drop after the announcement, he was basically right.  There really is no sound basis for thinking that Obamneycare is going to tank the economy.  Many critics say it increases uncertainty, but in fact a negative decision would have increased uncertainty as many would be losing new gains from the law (children under 26 on their health insurance to name one) without knowing what might come next.  That the GOP continues to oppose the law means that there remains uncertainty, although those ranting about uncertainty somehow never notice that their opposition to the law is aggravating this uncertainty &#8220;problem.&#8221;<br />    <br />As it is, the best evidence we have on how the law might work is to look at its predecessor in Massachusetts, RomneyCare implemented in 2006.  According to a January article in Forbes (not  a left wing publication at all), <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/kerapoza/2012/01/romney-care-massachusetts-healthcare-reform">http://www.forbes.com/sites/kerapoza/2012/01/romney-care-massachusetts-healthcare-reform</a> , not only is 99% of the population now with health insurance, but the law is so popular that no Massachusetts Republicans are remotely talking about repealing it.  Small business people were quoted as supporting it, the group supposedly most likely to suffer under Obamacare (aside from those who expect to get free medical care from emergency rooms even if they have never paid a cent for any kind of health insurance or care).  The current issue in MA is that there are efforts to reduce the costs of the program, but no movement at all to repeal it.  It is a clear success, even if its prime author now opposes its nationwide application.<br />    <br />I cannot resist posing a point that has bothered me for some time.  Much has been made of the fact that the individual mandate was originally proposed by a Republican think tank in 1989, the Heritage Foundation.  It was supported by numerous GOP pols since then, with the implementation by a Republican in MA, Romney, simply the obvious highwater mark of this.  This support only came to an end the minute Obama came out for it (rather than single payer) in an open attempt to have a bipartisan bill.  Of course, in the end, not a single Republican in Congress voted for it, not one, without a single one professing the slightest embarrassment about jumping from supporting it to denouncing it as &#8220;unconstitutional socialism&#8221; not to mention even greater idiocies such as opponents shrieking in town hall meetings about &#8220;death panels&#8221; that went on for some time (where are those anyway?).<br />    <br />So, it is my observation that this is the biggest mass shift of the views of a political party on a major issue since the US Communist Party did so regarding Hitler in 1939 and back again the other way in 1941.  I have asked numerous people to name any other shift by any US party on any issue since then that beats or even matches this one by the GOP.  Nobody has come up with one.<br />  <br />My final observation on this is that at least back in 1939 there were enough members of the CPUSA who had principles and honor to resign from the party when it made its pro-Hitler shift in the wake of the Mototov-von Ribbentrop Pact.   I have seen not a single member of the recent US Republican Party about whom the same could be said, and the public repudiations of their own views by Stuart Butler of Heritage and Mitt Romney are astoundingly pathetic by comparison.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/opponents-into-frenzy.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Guest post: Health Insurance Rebates Show How Bad Insurers and State Regulators Can Be</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/guest-post-health-insurance-rebates-show-how-bad-insurers-and-state-regulators-can-be.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/guest-post-health-insurance-rebates-show-how-bad-insurers-and-state-regulators-can-be.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 02 Jul 2012 12:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[ACA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kenneth Thomas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MLR]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/guest-post-health-insurance-rebates-show-how-bad-insurers-and-state-regulators-can-be.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[There is and will be a lot of conversation about the efficacy of the ACA (Affordable Care Act), whether it is a step to deal with the health care cost juggernaut or mostly a boon to private insurers.  What is true is that &#8216;medical inflation&#8217; has resumed to previous levels of year to year increase [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There is and will be a lot of conversation about the efficacy of the ACA (Affordable Care Act), whether it is a step to deal with the health care cost juggernaut or mostly a boon to private insurers.  What is true is that &#8216;medical inflation&#8217; has resumed to previous levels of year to year increase after a lull during the last two years, except for Medicare, which comes in at about 3% and not the 9% for the commercial market. (post to come).  </p>
<p><a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766#editor/target=post;postID=9042039414814543149" target="_blank">Bruce Webb pointed to the medical loss ratio</a> as a way to help control some costs several years ago.  Kenneth has his own take on these issues.</p>
<p>Update 2:   Links repaired</p>
<p>by Kenneth Thomas</p>
<p>Guest post: Health Insurance Rebates Show How Bad Insurers and State Regulators Can Be </p>
<p><a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2012/06/health-insurance-rebates-show-how-bad.html">Health Insurance Rebates Show How Bad Insurers and State Regulators Can Be</a></p>
<p>Thursday&#8217;s health care ruling was a surprising victory for the middle class. I went to bed Wednesday dreading waking up, only to be awakened by a phone call that the law had been upheld. Most of the story is well-known, and summarized in <a href="http://www.whitehouse.gov/the-press-office/2012/06/28/remarks-president-supreme-court-ruling-affordable-care-act">the President&#8217;s speech</a>: six million young adults under 26 who have gained insurance, children now (and adults starting in 2014) can no longer be denied insurance due to pre-existing conditions, an end to terminating people&#8217;s insurance when they get ill, closing the Medicare donut hole, etc. I want to focus on one provision the President mentioned in passing, the $1.1 billion in insurance rebates that 12.8 million Americans will be receiving August 1.    </p>
<p>The rebates are due to the medical loss ratio or &#8220;80/20&#8221; rule that insurance companies cannot spend more than 20% of premium dollars on &#8220;administration, CEO pay, and profits,&#8221; as <a href="http://healthcareforamericanow.org/2012/06/21/1-1-billion-mlr-rebates-to-consumers/">Health Care for America Now</a> (HCAN) summarizes it. The requirement is 85% spent on actual medical care for firms in the large group market, according to <a href="http://www.healthcare.gov/law/resources/reports/mlr-rebates06212012a.html">healthcare.gov</a>.(via HCAN). Of the $1.1 billion in rebates, $393.9 million will be in the individual market, $386.4 million in the large group market, and $321.1 million in the small group market.    <br />Although $1.1 billion in rebates is not a lot of money in the multi-trillion U.S. health care system, it <i>is</i> enough to provide noticeable rebates to millions of consumer before the November election. <a href="http://yourhealthsecurity.org/health-insurance-refund-list-2011">Consumers Union</a> has a state-by-state breakdown of which insurance companies owe rebates in each state, and how much. Three patterns emerge from these data: First, some companies routinely failed to meet the 80/20 rule in state after state after state. Second, Blue Cross/Blue Shield companies, which were once largely non-profit but were converted to for-profit corporations mostly in the 1990s, are now frequent violators of the medical loss ratio rule. Third, some states, most notably Texas, have such lax insurance company regulations that violations of the rule are rampant. The data below come from the Consumers Union link above.    </p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>1) Multiple violations by individual companies: The poster child for gouging consumers and spending premium dollars on things other than health care is Golden Rule Insurance Company (since 2003 a subsidiary of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golden_Rule_Insurance_Company">UnitedHealthcare</a>), which operates solely in the individual market, and not in either the small group or large group health care markets. According to the Consumers Union data, Golden Rule owes rebates in 23 states where it operates. Comparing the CU data with <a href="http://www.goldenrule.com/plans-by-state/">Golden Rule&#8217;s website</a> on where it operates, we find that in only nine states where it operates does it not owe rebates. We also learn that two Golden Rule subsidiaries also owe rebates, American Medical Security Life Insurance Company in Utah in the individual market, and Oxford Health Plans of New Jersey Inc. in the large employer market, bringing Golden Rule&#8217;s total to fully 25 states where it owes rebates under the medical loss ratio rule. In a number of states (Alabama, Florida, Indiana, Kentucky, Maryland, Michigan, Mississippi, and West Virginia) , Golden Rule owes more money than any other insurer in the individual market.    </p>
<p>Furthermore, UnitedHealthcare subsidiaries carrying the UHC name owe rebates in 28 states in the small business market, large business market, or both.    </p>
<p>I don&#8217;t mean to single out UnitedHealthcare for overcharging: depending on the state and the market, Aetna, Connecticut General, and Time Insurance Company, among others, owe substantial rebates to their customers as well. But Golden Rule and UnitedHealthcare failed to meet their 80/20 tests in so many states that they really stand out.    </p>
<p>2) In many states in which Golden Rule does not owe the highest rebates in the individual market, Blue Cross/Blue Shield does. This includes states like Arizona, Missouri, Oklahoma, South Carolina, Tennessee, and most notably, Texas. This represents a complete repudiation of the historical BC/BS ethos, which included non-profit incorporation and community rating (i.e., not penalizing people for getting sick). But that&#8217;s what happens when you turn non-profits into for-profits in health care.    </p>
<p>3) This brings us to lax insurance regulation, as in Texas. Blue Cross/Blue Shield of Texas owes $89.9 million in refunds, all of it in the individual market, which by itself exceeds all the refunds in the much bigger California economy, where total refunds only <a href="http://www.healthcare.gov/law/resources/reports/mlr-rebates06212012a.html">amount to $73.9 million</a>. Total rebates in Texas will total $167.0 million. The only other state with rebates exceeding $100 million this year is Florida, at $123.6 million. However, a number of states have higher average rebates, led by Vermont at $807. I believe both the total and average rebates should be examined for evidence of weak insurance regulation.    </p>
<p>To summarize, the Supreme Court&#8217;s decision was a great one for the middle class. On top of all the provisions that expand coverage and economic security, 12.8 million consumers will see refunds from their insurers to pay back for their price gouging.    </p>
<p>This is not to say that we don&#8217;t have a long way to go to complete health reform. As <a href="http://www.cnn.com/2012/06/28/opinion/carroll-health-supreme-court/index.html">Aaron Carroll</a> points out, there is a great deal more that needs to be done to our $2.7 trillion health system, including making coverage universal and getting cost increase under control. But upholding the Affordable Care Act is a step in the right direction. </p>
<p>crossposted with <a background-color:="" href="http://www.blogger.com/%3Ca%3Ehttp://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2012/06/health-insurance-rebates-show-how-bad.html%3C/a%3E%3Cspan%20style=" target="_blank" white>Middle Class Political Economist</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/guest-post-health-insurance-rebates-show-how-bad-insurers-and-state-regulators-can-be.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
