<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Alan Greenspan &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>We Beat the Germans in 1918/And They&#8217;ve Hardly Bothered Us Since Then</title>
		<link>./../../2011/03/we-beat-the-germans-in-1918and-theyve-hardly-bothered-us-since-then.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/03/we-beat-the-germans-in-1918and-theyve-hardly-bothered-us-since-then.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 30 Mar 2011 21:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Alan Greenspan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[blogs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Brad DeLong]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Crooked Timber]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[technology]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/03/we-beat-the-germans-in-1918and-theyve-hardly-bothered-us-since-then.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Brad DeLong culls the comments to this post at Crooked Timber to produce a &#8220;with notably rare exceptions&#8221; Greatest Hits package—his second post riffing on the original—in honor of The Maestro continuing to attempt to improve the reputations of Paul Volcker and Ben Bernanke, if not G. William (&#8220;I ran a company, I didn&#8217;t need [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Brad DeLong culls the comments <a href="http://crookedtimber.org/2011/03/30/with-notably-rare-exceptions/">to this post at Crooked Timber</a> to produce <a href="http://delong.typepad.com/sdj/2011/03/the-best-of-with-notably-rare-exceptions.html">a &#8220;with notably rare exceptions&#8221; Greatest Hits package</a>—his second post riffing on the original—in honor of The Maestro continuing to attempt to improve the reputations of Paul Volcker and Ben Bernanke, if not <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G._William_Miller">G. William (&#8220;I ran a company, I didn&#8217;t need to know about Finance&#8221;) Miller</a>.*</p>
<p>I point you to Dr. DeLong on the off chance that you didn&#8217;t read any of the other three (one by Henry, two by Brad) posts, while we all wait for <a href="http://www.nielsenhayden.com/makinglight/">Patrick or Jim MacDonald</a> to continue the riff with more variations.</p>
<p>Economics question of the day: whose productivity will be greater: someone who reads all (now four, counting this one) posts, someone who starts with Dr. DeLong&#8217;s second, someone who starts with Dr. DeLong&#8217;s first, or someone who only read Henry Farrell&#8217;s original post but kept clicking back to see the newer comments?</p>
<p>Explain your answer in terms of the value-added of aggregators and/or hedonic pricing. Best answers will be forwarded to Bill Dudley, the current leader of the FRB of New York, <a href="http://www.google.com/search?rlz=1C1RNCN_enCA318CA319&#038;aq=0&#038;oq=let+them+eat+iP&#038;sourceid=chrome&#038;ie=UTF-8&#038;q=let+them+eat+ipad">on the off chance he ever agrees to speak in Queens again</a>.<br />

</p>
<p>*I refuse to believe that Alan Greenspan is stupid enough to believe the things he&#8217;s saying now.  Next thing you know, he&#8217;ll be claiming that <a href="http://online.barrons.com/article/SB120917419049046805.html#articleTabs_panel_article%3D1">his Ph.D. thesis</a> was so perfect that <a href="http://online.barrons.com/article/SB120675340444773623.html">no one should ever read it</a>, lest they despair of following in his giant footsteps.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/03/we-beat-the-germans-in-1918and-theyve-hardly-bothered-us-since-then.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Only that which is rational is real</title>
		<link>./../../2010/07/only-that-which-is-rational-is-real.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/07/only-that-which-is-rational-is-real.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2010 21:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Alan Greenspan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[models]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/07/only-that-which-is-rational-is-real.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[CNBC reports Greenspan … added that the financial crisis could not have been foreseen. “It is just not feasible to forecast a financial crisis,” he said. “A financial crisis by definition is a sharp abrupt, unexpected decline in asset prices.” Notice that he says if it is unexpected, then it *can’t* be forecast. That is [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>CNBC <a href="http://www.cnbc.com/id/38034791">reports</a> </p>
<p>Greenspan … added that the financial crisis could not have been foreseen.</p>
<p>“It is just not feasible to forecast a financial crisis,” he said. “A financial crisis by definition is a sharp abrupt, unexpected decline in asset prices.”</p>
<p>Notice that he says if it is unexpected, then it *can’t* be forecast.  That is if the risk bearing capacity weighted average investor doesn’t forecast something then it isn’t forecastable.  Greenspan is asserting that financial markets are efficient by definition.  He displays no willingness to allow data or evidence any role in answering the question.  </p>
<p>Only that which is rational is real.  The key policy relevant question is answered by definition, that is, by authority.  Efficient is whatever markets are, and also what they should be, therefore markets are what they should be – by definition.</p>
<p>This is dogma, this is faith, this is medieval thinking.  Galileo lived in vain.  The enlightenment arrived in the Fed when Bernanke replaced Greenspan.</p>
<p>via <a href="http://www.eschatonblog.com/2010/07/nobody-could-have-predicted.html">Atrios.</a>  More ranting after the jump.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Also &#8220;Former Federal Reserve Chairman Alan Greenspan said that the recent stock market decline is “typical” of a recovery,&#8221;  If a decline is typical then it is forecastable.  If a decline is typical during a recovery, then financial markets are inefficient.  I see no basis for the claim (which, I amdit, was constructed with only one actually quoted word).  </p>
<p>Note  how the efficient markets hypothesis is switched on and off for convenience.  Something which could have been prevented with tighter regulation must have been unpredictable.  Something which might or might not alarm people was predictable and isn&#8217;t news.  I am fairly sure that no one believes that financial markets are efficient.  It is just a debating trick.  It can be assumed at will in order to make absurd arguments.  It is absurd and has high status, for some reason, so it is a license to make clearly false claims which are not dismissed.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/07/only-that-which-is-rational-is-real.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Perfect Negative Indicator Weighs In</title>
		<link>./../../2009/12/the-perfect-negative-indicator-weighs-in.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/12/the-perfect-negative-indicator-weighs-in.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 16 Dec 2009 01:23:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Alan Greenspan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[frictional unemployment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[inflation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the fed]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[unemployment]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/12/the-perfect-negative-indicator-weighs-in.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Alan Greenspan: The U.S. Federal Reserve has done all it can do to reduce unemployment and needs to worry more about the risk of inflation from the stimulus it poured into the economy, former Fed Chairman Alan Greenspan said on Sunday. But didn&#8217;t we just Get All That Money Back? [link added] Greenspan&#8217;s reason unemployment [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Alan Greenspan:<br />
<blockquote>The U.S. Federal Reserve has done all it can do to reduce unemployment and needs to worry more about the risk of inflation from the stimulus it poured into the economy, former Fed Chairman Alan Greenspan said on Sunday.</p></blockquote>
<p>But didn&#8217;t we just <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2009/12/07/business/07tarp.html?_r=1&#038;sq=Calmes&#038;st=cse&#038;scp=2&#038;pagewanted=print">Get All That Money Back</a>? [link added]</p>
<p>Greenspan&#8217;s reason unemployment will go down soon:  <strong>GOVERNMENT JOBS</strong>:<br />
<blockquote>Greenspan said he expected the U.S. unemployment rate, which is currently at 10 percent, to &#8220;be significantly lower a year from now&#8221; but still very high.</p>
<p>The U.S. Census Bureau&#8217;s plan to hire close to 800,000 workers by April will take several tenths of a percent off the unemployment rate, he said.</p></blockquote>
<p>Let&#8217;s ignore that 800,000 temporary hires won&#8217;t balance <a href="http://www.cbpp.org/cms/index.cfm?fa=view&#038;id=2988">the 900,000 jobs to be lost on the state level next year</a> (h/t <a href="http://delong.typepad.com/sdj/2009/12/ten-economics-paragraphs-december-13-2009.html">Brad DeLong</a>) And let&#8217;s ignore that temporary jobs are, by definition, &#8220;frictional&#8221; and not &#8220;structural&#8221; employment.</p>
<p>But let&#8217;s not forget, <a href="http://angrybear.blogspot.com/2009/12/if-bernanke-did-not-know-feds-mission.html">as Ben Bernanke did</a>,* that, as noted by <a href="http://www.prospect.org/csnc/blogs/beat_the_press_archive?month=12&#038;year=2009&#038;base_name=if_bernanke_did_not_know_the_f">Dean Baker</a>, &#8220;the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Humphrey%E2%80%93Hawkins_Full_Employment_Act">dual mandate</a> [of the Fed] is full employment (<strong>defined as 4.0 percent unemployment</strong>) and price stability.&#8221; [emphasis mine].</p>
<p>10.0% is not 4.0%.  Indeed, 9.3% (10.0-0.7) is not 4.0%.  So unless there is a miraculous 5.3% of other employment coming Real Soon Now (and I don&#8217;t even see <a href="http://www.slate.com/id/2238099/">Daniel Gross</a> predicting that, let alone <a href="http://moneywatch.bnet.com/economic-news/blog/maximum-utility/why-it-may-take-almost-seven-years-for-unemployment-to-reach-five-percent/306/">Mark Thoma</a> or <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2009/12/10/the-jobs-deficit/">Paul Krugman</a>), the Fed, as has been standard under Bernanke, is missing its targets.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/12/the-perfect-negative-indicator-weighs-in.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>6</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Gruesome Find of the Day</title>
		<link>./../../2008/12/gruesome-find-of-the-day.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/12/gruesome-find-of-the-day.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2008 02:09:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Alan Greenspan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economic crisis]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/12/gruesome-find-of-the-day.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Greenspan&#8217;s Body Count “You know go to Disney every year, just have two kids, a boy and a girl, and a retarded golden retriever, and we&#8217;re just a regular family,” she said.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://greenspansbodycount.blogspot.com/">Greenspan&#8217;s Body Count</a><br />
<blockquote>“You know go to Disney every year, just have two kids, a boy and a girl, and a retarded golden retriever, and we&#8217;re just a regular family,” she said.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/12/gruesome-find-of-the-day.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Credit Where Due, Brad DeLong edition</title>
		<link>./../../2008/09/credit-where-due-brad-delong-edition.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2008/09/credit-where-due-brad-delong-edition.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2008 21:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Alan Greenspan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Brad DeLong]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[monetary policy]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2008/09/credit-where-due-brad-delong-edition.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The defences of Alan Greenspan at Grapsing Reality&#8230; are legendary. (This response to Tom is my favorite of the lot, and rather representative.) Which makes today&#8217;s conversion announcement all the more noteworthy.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The defences of Alan Greenspan at Grapsing Reality&#8230; are legendary.  (<a href="http://delong.typepad.com/sdj/2005/03/how_good_is_ala.html">This response to Tom</a> is my favorite of the lot, and rather representative.)</p>
<p>Which makes <a href="http://delong.typepad.com/sdj/2008/09/delong-smackdow.html">today&#8217;s conversion announcement</a> all the more noteworthy.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2008/09/credit-where-due-brad-delong-edition.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Greenspan vs Klein on Democracy Now</title>
		<link>./../../2007/09/greenspan-vs-klein-on-democracy-now.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2007/09/greenspan-vs-klein-on-democracy-now.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2007 23:17:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Alan Greenspan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Naomie Klein]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2007/09/greenspan-vs-klein-on-democracy-now.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Just an FYI related to recent postings here. Democracy Now for 9/24 has about a 38 minute discussion with both Naomie Klien and Alan Greenspan. The remaining minutes is with Jeremy Scahill. This particular exchange caught my attention: AMY GOODMAN: Alan Greenspan, you write in the end of your book, “A Federal Reserve System that [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Just an FYI related to recent postings here.   <a href="http://www.democracynow.org/article.pl?sid=07/09/24/1412226">Democracy Now </a> for 9/24 has about a 38 minute discussion with both Naomie Klien and Alan Greenspan.  The remaining minutes is with Jeremy Scahill.</p>
<p>This particular exchange caught my attention:<br />
<blockquote>
<p>AMY GOODMAN: Alan Greenspan, you write in the end of your book, “A Federal Reserve System that will be confronted with the challenge of inflation pressure and populist politics that have been relatively quiescent in recent years” is something that is very significant. You say the year &#8212; the United States in 2030 is likely to be characterized by populist politics that have been relatively quiescent in recent years. How important is populist politics, and what do you envision those to look like?</p>
<p>ALAN GREENSPAN: Well, remember what populist politics is. It’s a very special brand of short-term focus, which invariably creates very difficult long-term problems. A goodly part of the book, as you know, is written about how populism has gripped, say, many Latin American countries to their detriment. And the term “populist politics” is essentially another way of saying short term versus longer term. And people who emphasize short-term benefits for long-term costs end up with very little in the way of economic growth and prosperity.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Personally, I have never viewed populism as short term viewing.  Infact, I read nothing at <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Populism">Wikipedia </a>that suggested such.</p>
<blockquote><p>Populism is a political doctrine or philosophy that purports to defend the interests of the <a title="Common people" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Common_people">common people</a> against an entrenched, self-serving or corrupt <a title="Elite" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elite">elite</a>.</p></blockquote>
<p>I think Mr. Greenspan has a little projection (in pysch terms) happening here. Naomie Klein furthers the question and raises his policies as playing a part in the rise of economic populism. His answer, we have bad education. She follow up on his example of Latin America:</p>
<blockquote><p>But you also mentioned economic populism in Latin America in your book, and you blame it for inflation episodes and the collapse of regimes and the toppling of governments, and one of your examples was Chile in the 1970s. Was Chile &#8212; was Salvador Allende’s regime toppled because of inflation, or didn’t the CIA have something to do with that? </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>ALAN GREENSPAN: Well, look, let’s &#8212; I’m using Latin America as an example. The key question is not Latin America. Let&#8217;s get back to the United States.  Let&#8217;s get back to the world at large and face the issue of populism here.  Remember, the populist issue in Latin America goes back to the roots of Spanish and Portuguese colonization. </p>
</blockquote>
<p>I&#8217;m sorry, but if that answer wasn&#8217;t a classic “troll” response I don&#8217;t know what is.<br />Enjoy.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2007/09/greenspan-vs-klein-on-democracy-now.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
