<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>iran &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Attacking Iran&#8230;repeat of crazy reasoning?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/02/attacking-iran-repeat-of-crazy-reasoning.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/02/attacking-iran-repeat-of-crazy-reasoning.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2012 15:46:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2012 Presidential elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[foreign policy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[iran]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/02/attacking-iran-repeat-of-crazy-reasoning.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Peter Beinart in The Daily Beast points us to the crazy nature of our current attitude regarding attacking Iran in The Crazy Rush to Attack Iran. He lists and quotes an impressive series of experts familiar with the the last decades wars, and finally asks: Can you find former military and intelligence officials who are [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Peter Beinart in <i>The Daily Beast</i> points us to the crazy nature of our current attitude regarding attacking Iran in <a href="http://www.thedailybeast.com/articles/2012/02/21/experts-say-iraq-attack-is-irrational-yet-hawks-are-winning-the-debate.html" target="_blank">The Crazy Rush to Attack Iran</a>.  He lists and quotes an impressive series of experts familiar with the the last decades wars, and finally asks:  </p>
<blockquote><p>Can you find former military and intelligence officials who are more sympathetic to a strike? Sure. But in my lifetime, I&#8217;ve never seen a more lopsided debate among the experts paid to make these judgments. Yet it barely matters. So far, the Iran debate has been a rout, with the Republican presidential candidates loudly declaring their openness to war and President Obama unwilling to even echo the skepticism of his own security chiefs.</p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>And who are the hawks who have so far marginalized the defense and intelligence establishments in both Israel and the U.S.? They&#8217;re a collection of think-tankers and politicians, most absolutely sincere, in my experience. But from Rick Santorum to John McCain to Elliott Abrams to John Bolton, their defining characteristic is that they were equally apocalyptic about the threat from Iraq, and equally nonchalant about the difficulties of successfully attacking it. The story of the Iraq debate was, in large measure, the story of their triumph over the career military and intelligence officials &#8211; folks like Eric Shinseki and Joseph Wilson &#8211; whose successors are now warning against attacking Iran.   </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><p>How can it be, less than a decade after the U.S. invaded Iraq, that the Iran debate is breaking down along largely the same lines, and the people who were manifestly, painfully wrong about that war are driving the debate this time as well? Culturally, it&#8217;s a fascinating question &#8211; and too depressing for words.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/02/attacking-iran-repeat-of-crazy-reasoning.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Attacking Iran</title>
		<link>./../../2012/02/attacking-iran.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/02/attacking-iran.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2012 16:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[iran]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mideast]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/02/attacking-iran.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Glen Greenwald at Salon takes aim at the media coverage concerning our relationship with Iran and the barrage of coverage having little to do with real assessments. Lots of links.  But this Family Guy segment sums it up for me&#8230;  Any links to some real discussiom from readers??]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://politics.salon.com/2012/02/14/us_media_takes_the_lead_on_iran/singleton/" target="_blank">Glen Greenwald at Salon</a> takes aim at the media coverage concerning our relationship with Iran and the barrage of coverage having little to do with real assessments. Lots of links.  But this Family Guy segment sums it up for me&#8230;  Any links to some real discussiom from readers??</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/02/attacking-iran.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Israel&#8217;s Big Bluff on Iran: You Just Have to Ignore Physics and Geography</title>
		<link>./../../2011/01/israels-big-bluff-on-iran-you-just-have-to-ignore-physics-and-geography.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/01/israels-big-bluff-on-iran-you-just-have-to-ignore-physics-and-geography.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 17 Jan 2011 19:22:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[iran]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Israel]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/01/israels-big-bluff-on-iran-you-just-have-to-ignore-physics-and-geography.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Which though not stated so baldly is the clear conclusion of the following: Abdullah Toukan and Anthony Cordesman:Study on a Possible Israeli Strike on Iran’s Nuclear Development. The authors outline three different attack routes the Israelis could use, each having its own set of political and military problems, but the real missing piece is the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Which though not stated so baldly is the clear conclusion of the following: Abdullah Toukan and Anthony Cordesman:<br /><a target="_blank" href="http://csis.org/files/media/csis/pubs/090316_israelistrikeiran.pdf">Study on a Possible Israeli Strike on Iran’s Nuclear Development</a>.</p>
<p>The authors outline three different attack routes the Israelis could use, each having its own set of political and military problems, but the real missing piece is the refueling. Theoretically Israel might barely have the range to get its planes on target but not to recover them. In fact it appears that a successful raid would depend on refueling the planes on the way in and again on the way out. Which would not only require just about 2X Israel&#8217;s actual aerial refueling capacity, but would have those planes staging for hours and hours in either Turkish, U.S. controlled Iraqi, or Saudi Arabian air space. And while Turkey and the U.S. might not relish a one on one attack on the actual Israeli strike force, and perhaps Saudi Arabia wouldn&#8217;t even attempt it, it would be hard to plausibly ignore those Israeli KC-135s doing figure eights in your airspace waiting for those F-15s and F-16s on the way in AND on the way out.</p>
<p>And since someone is bound to bring them up, similar limits apply to an Eitan drone or Dolphin submarine led attack, Israel doesn&#8217;t have the combination of numbers, range, and deliverable payload to get the job done. Not without the active assistance of the U.S. at a minimum as to refueling and emergency air fields, but likely with actual strike assistance as well.</p>
<p>If any of our commenter/military aviators can point me to or supply themselves a convincing refutation of Toukan and Cordesman then I am certainly willing to reconsider, but on my reading it just can&#8217;t be done. Unless Israel bluffs the U.S. into doing it for them.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/01/israels-big-bluff-on-iran-you-just-have-to-ignore-physics-and-geography.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Is Israel on Deadline? or Who will Control Iraqi Airspace in 2012?</title>
		<link>./../../2010/08/is-israel-on-deadline-or-who-will-control-iraqi-airspace-in-2012.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/08/is-israel-on-deadline-or-who-will-control-iraqi-airspace-in-2012.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Aug 2010 15:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[iran]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Israel]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/08/is-israel-on-deadline-or-who-will-control-iraqi-airspace-in-2012.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Bruce Webb A little over a year ago I put up the following map from Cordesman and Toukan&#8217;s Study on a Possible Israeli Strike on Iran’s Nuclear Development Facilities &#8220; A year later and this issue is back in the headlines and specifically in association with the publication by the uber-Likudnik Jeffrey Goldberg&#8217;s article [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Bruce Webb</p>
<p>A little over a year ago I put up the following map from  Cordesman and Toukan&#8217;s <a target="_blank" href="http://csis.org/files/media/csis/pubs/090316_israelistrikeiran.pdf">Study on a Possible Israeli Strike on Iran’s Nuclear Development Facilities</a> </p>
<p>&#8220;<a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fjW71B3WLTQ/SlI4Sv5Au6I/AAAAAAAAAQs/3gHUDZn9X8E/s1600-h/Bomb+Routes.jpg"><img src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fjW71B3WLTQ/SlI4Sv5Au6I/AAAAAAAAAQs/3gHUDZn9X8E/s400/Bomb+Routes.jpg" border="0" alt=""></a></p>
<p>A year later and this issue is back in the headlines and specifically in association with the publication by the uber-Likudnik Jeffrey Goldberg&#8217;s article in the Atlantic tomorrow called <a target="_blank" href="http://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/1969/12/the-point-of-no-return/8186/">The Point of No Return</a> which essentially argues that the U.S. should bomb Iran and start a third mid-East war basically to save Israel the trouble of doing it itself. So maybe it is time to revisit Cordesman-Toukan in light of the current withdrawal schedule from Iraq.</p>
<p>In the article Cordesman and Toukan provide a comprehensive breakdown of both Israeli and Iranian missile capabilities and of the respective capabilities of Israel to launch an air attack and Iran to  defend against one. Which makes it a useful read all on its own. But I want to highlight the above map that shows the three possible attack routes given the limitations of Israeli air ranges. Some things of note. In each case Israel would need in-air refueling both on the way in and on the way out, meaning that they would have to stage their KC-135&#8217;s over the strike routes for some period of time, and all three of the strike routes require transiting Iraqi air space as well as either Saudi, Syrian or Turkish skies. Leaving for comments the question of whether either Turkey (given the recent Gaza embargo sea clash) or Saudi Arabia would look the other way and not even challenge the refueling effort, will the U.S. retain enough air assets in Iraq after mid-2011 to support an air-refueling effort on behalf of Israel or to provide safe havens for returning Israeli fighter bombers that might sustain damage?</p>
<p>The United States has formally controlled at least Northern and Southern Iraqi airspace since the first Gulf War via the No-Fly Zones. I surmise, though don&#8217;t know for sure, that that control will lapse upon U.S. withdrawal of combat troops from Iraq, or that if there is a residual U.S. air presence that it will at least on paper be subject to Iraqi government approval. Which leads to the question in the title of the post, the whole premise of a unilateral Israeli strike on Iran relies on at least tacit assistance by the U.S. and either Saudi Arabia or Turkey and given the refueling constraints outlined by Cordesman and Toukan almost certainly active assistance at least on the way out, because once those bombs start dropping nobody is going to be able to pretend nothing is going on.</p>
<p>So is time running out for Israel? Is that why we are getting the big push by Goldberg and others? Because they know that any such attack without full US control of Iraqi air space falls from the realm of improbable to impossible?</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/08/is-israel-on-deadline-or-who-will-control-iraqi-airspace-in-2012.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Joe Biden? The Map Office is Calling!</title>
		<link>./../../2009/07/joe-biden-the-map-office-is-calling.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/07/joe-biden-the-map-office-is-calling.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2009 17:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[bombing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[iran]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Israel]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/07/joe-biden-the-map-office-is-calling.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Bruce Webb The blogosphere is alive with news that Joe implicitly green-lighted an Israeli attack on Iran. Well I had my say here and there. I just want to share a map from Cordesman and Toukan&#8217;s Study on a Possible Israeli Strike on Iran’s Nuclear Development Facilities in part because it tells its own [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Bruce Webb</p>
<p>The blogosphere is alive with news that Joe implicitly green-lighted an Israeli attack on Iran. Well I had my say here and there. I just want to share a map from Cordesman and Toukan&#8217;s <a target="_blank" href="http://csis.org/files/media/csis/pubs/090316_israelistrikeiran.pdf">Study on a Possible Israeli Strike on Iran’s Nuclear Development Facilities</a> in part because it tells its own story. Plus it&#8217;s pretty damn cool looking.</p>
<p>&#8220;<a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fjW71B3WLTQ/SlI4Sv5Au6I/AAAAAAAAAQs/3gHUDZn9X8E/s1600-h/Bomb+Routes.jpg"><img src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fjW71B3WLTQ/SlI4Sv5Au6I/AAAAAAAAAQs/3gHUDZn9X8E/s400/Bomb+Routes.jpg" border="0" alt=""></a><br />Gosh if a &#8216;sovereign&#8217; Israel just decides to bomb Iran who could possibly blame the U.S.? It is not like we totally control Iraqi air space. </p>
<p>Oh wait.</p>
<p>Israel cannot attack Iran without material assistance from the U.S. which at a minimum means refueling assistance and emergency landing fields. Full stop.</p>
<p>Update 2. Well the map apparently didn&#8217;t tell the whole story. So here is Cordesman and Toukman&#8217;s &#8216;Mission Analysis&#8217;. Note the mismatch between refueling requirements and actual refueling planes in the Israeli fleet. Note too that the analysis assumes zero effectiveness among Iranian Air and Ground Defense. Iranian pilots may be as bad as Buff assumes, but I don&#8217;t think we can say the same thing about Iran&#8217;s large supply of Soviet built surface to air missiles.<br /><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fjW71B3WLTQ/SlNfMjMxAHI/AAAAAAAAAQ0/KbojhaPvYBg/s1600-h/Mission+Analysis.jpg"><img src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fjW71B3WLTQ/SlNfMjMxAHI/AAAAAAAAAQ0/KbojhaPvYBg/s400/Mission+Analysis.jpg" border="0" alt=""></a></p>
<p>(update- JS Kit doesn&#8217;t recognize my phone. So I will respond to comments here</p>
<p>The Sunday Times (UK) released a very short report based on a supposed secret briefing by Mossad to Netanyahu about some clearance by Saudi Arabia. The only source actually named in the story is John Bolton and considering the J Post/Sunday Times/Murdoch/AIPAC nexus I am waiting for some more authoritative sourcing. For example Haaretz is today reporting an official government denial.</p>
<p>As for the Eitan it is an unmanned turbo-prop more designed for surveilance than bombing hardened targets with its negligible payload. It would be shot down the instant it went under 20000 feet. At 40000 ft it is practically untouchable. Then again so was the U-2-we thought.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/07/joe-biden-the-map-office-is-calling.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Trace the Bombing Route from Israel to Iran</title>
		<link>./../../2009/06/trace-the-bombing-route-from-israel-to-iran.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/06/trace-the-bombing-route-from-israel-to-iran.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2009 13:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[bombing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[iran]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Israel]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/06/trace-the-bombing-route-from-israel-to-iran.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Time for our military readers to step up. Various basement bloggers belonging to the 101st Fighting Keyboardists continually tell us the next step is Israel bombing Iran. But can someone explain exactly how this would work in detail? I mean in actual detail including 1) Israeli strike capabilities, 2) Iranian air defense capabilities, 3a) how [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fjW71B3WLTQ/SjZLuO4CbTI/AAAAAAAAAPM/UVV3rh_kn1k/s1600-h/Middle_east.jpg"><img src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fjW71B3WLTQ/SjZLuO4CbTI/AAAAAAAAAPM/UVV3rh_kn1k/s400/Middle_east.jpg" border="0" alt=""></a><br />Time for our military readers to step up.</p>
<p>Various basement bloggers belonging to the 101st Fighting Keyboardists continually tell us the next step is Israel bombing Iran. But can someone explain exactly how this would work in detail? I mean in actual detail including 1) Israeli strike capabilities, 2) Iranian air defense capabilities, 3a) how you get overflight rights or 3b) how you give a big FU to the Turks or Saudis if you don&#8217;t try to get those rights, and 4) the biggie, how do you establish and maintain aerial refueling capacity?</p>
<p>I can see fairly reasonable scenarios under which Israel could pull a fast one and get bombers on target in Iran, but I don&#8217;t see any that allow them to get back to Israel that don&#8217;t require full co-operation from the United States. Which co-operation would be legally the equivalent of a declaration of war.</p>
<p>A few months ago Israel reportedly did a practice run over much the same distances but instead of flying East flew West over the Med. Which didn&#8217;t require them getting overflight rights from anyone, still less having to take air defense capabilities into account. This map tells me a much different story. Someone, anyone lay out a serious case of how Israel physically pulls this off.</p>
<p>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turkish_Air_Force  Note that Turkey is part of NATO and has 210 F-16s and around 200 F-4s. It is not like they could just be brushed aside.</p>
<p>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_Saudi_Air_Force   American equipped and trained with all the money in the world for buying and upgrading equipment. Among other aircraft around 150 F-15s.</p>
<p>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Islamic_Republic_of_Iran_Air_Force  Handicapped somewhat in that their original fleet was American supplied and so have suffered from parts embargoes. But in recent years have had plenty of opportunity to buy Russian planes and missiles.</p>
<p>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Israeli_Air_Force   Nobody doubts the IAF are good, but do they really have the fire power to both bomb Iran AND protect whatever air-refueling capability they would need? Or do their planes really have the range to fly both ways while ignoring surface-to-air defences from territories they are crossing?</p>
<p>This isn&#8217;t a game of Battleship, or Stratego, or Risk. Real Commanders need to have real plans to get real planes on target across real terrain plus a plan to safely extract those planes. I don&#8217;t see any way of doing this without the full compliance of President Obama. Which raises two questions for any would be war monger.</p>
<p>One. How do you get Obama to greenlight this? or Two. What do you do if he says &#8216;No&#8217;? Given the realities revealed by this map. Because from all I see there is a lot more involved than Bibi just saying &#8216;Go&#8217;.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/06/trace-the-bombing-route-from-israel-to-iran.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
