<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>David Zetland. water economics &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 15:57:33 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Nature bats last</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/nature-bats-last.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/nature-bats-last.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 10:46:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[David Zetland. water economics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/nature-bats-last.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[David Zetland writes a well written nine page look at the limits of economics in at least the media and political level, and a look at the limits of what economic models have to offer most people. This will be a series of posts highlighting major points over time. The paper must be downloaded to [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>David Zetland writes a well written nine page look at the limits of economics in at least the media and political level, and a look at the limits of what economic models have to offer most people. This will be a series of posts highlighting major points over time. The paper must be downloaded to read.</p>
<p>by David Zetland Wageningen UR &#8211; Environmental Economics and Natural Resources Group; PERC &#8211; Property and Environment Research Center</p>
<p><a href="http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2230931">Economists Owe Ecology an Apology</a><br />March 9, 2013</p>
<p>Part 2 from the series <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/03/economists-owe-ecology-apology.html">Economists owe ecology an apology</a></p>
<p>Nature bats last </p>
<p>“When we try to pick out anything by itself, we find it hitched to everything else in the Universe.&#8221; —John Muir (1911)</p>
<p>“The economic problem of society is…a problem of the utilization of knowledge which is not given to anyone in its totality.&#8221; —F.A. Hayek (1945)</p>
<p>John Muir and fellow conservationists, environmentalists and ecologists understood the world not as a machine to bend to man’s will but as a life-supporting organism that reckless humans could damage. They worried about the conversion of wetlands to farm lands, of forests to timber, of rivers to ditches of industrial effluent. Their worries were not based on simple calculations of costs and benefits; they were based on endless observations of the delicate, surprising and endless connections among flora and fauna, rocks and rivers, air and light. They worried that we were harming the ecosystems supporting our prosperity under the dual influences of ignorance and hubris. Economists sympathetic to these views worried that complex human interactions could be mismanaged and damaged like ecosystems. F.A. Hayek, Ronald Coase, Elinor Ostrom and other institutional economists argued against oversimplifying complex systems into reduced-form models and suggested simple policies and limited actions when it came to managing society.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Their humility did not appeal to politicians who liked to direct, bureaucrats who liked to push and pull, or industrialists whose machines rested at the center of (calculated) national wealth—all of them active managers when it came to manipulating factors and adjusting accounts in a quest to achieve the optimal mix of visible costs and benefits. Machine managers disliked fuzzy, vast conceptualizations of biomes that evolved in chaotic directions; they preferred the mechanisms and flow diagrams of industrial consultants who bestrode the world delivering a future from logical minds uncluttered by doubt. Sure, they added columns and rows to “internalize the externalities&#8221; in their ledgers, but they could not add what they could not measure. Their optimal exploitation and discharge diagrams seemed complete, but they failed to include the wisdom of ages: don’t shit where you eat.</p>
<p>It was soon clear that the absence of evidence of problems does not equal the absence of problems; unexpected damages pulled expected outcomes off course. Although trouble could be blamed on techno-optimism, national security, consumerism, and other forces, economists deserve blame for promoting accounts, models and theories that promised to quantify life quality, optimize human action, and integrate the environment, but they failed. Not all economists should be blamed for these failures—we’ll hear from them below—but the mainstream majority can be. Their dominance and influence drove the process and created a reputation which only some of us deserve but all of us bear. Let’s review the charges.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/nature-bats-last.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Economists Owe Ecology an Apology</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/economists-owe-ecology-an-apology.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/economists-owe-ecology-an-apology.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2013 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[David Zetland. water economics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/economists-owe-ecology-an-apology.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[David Zetland writes a well written nine page look at the limits of economics in at least the media and political level, and a look at the limits of what economic models have to offer most people. This will be a series of posts highlighting major points over time. The paper must be downloaded to [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>David Zetland writes a well written nine page look at the limits of economics in at least the media and political level, and a look at the limits of what economic models have to offer most people.  This will be a series of posts highlighting major points over time.  The paper must be downloaded to read.</p>
<p>by David Zetland Wageningen UR &#8211; Environmental Economics and Natural Resources Group; PERC &#8211; Property and Environment Research Center</p>
<p><a href="http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2230931"><i>Economists Owe Ecology an Apology</i></a><br />March 9, 2013</p>
<p>
<div>&#8230;two substantial defects in how we understand and affect our economy and the ecology. The larger defect arises from a human tendency to simplify the world into &#8220;sensible&#8221; concepts that may be inaccurate. Although we might laugh at past versions of this mistake (a flat Earth at the center of the Universe, the spread of malaria from &#8220;bad air,&#8221; woman springing from the side of man, and so on), we continue to make it today when we underestimate the complexity of our human and natural worlds. That miscalculation leads to the second defect in which economists promote theories, observations and prescriptions that fail to include this complexity (or a humble acceptance of it), a problem that worried Adam Smith over 250 years ago:</p>
</div>
<div>The man of system…seems to imagine that he can arrange the different members of a great society with as much ease as the hand arranges the different pieces upon a chess-board. He does not consider…that, in the great chess-board of human society, every single piece has a principle of motion of its own, altogether different from that which the legislature might choose to impress upon it…[Failure to acknowledge the motion of pieces means that] society must be at all times in the highest degree of disorder. —Smith (1759, pp. 233-4)</div>
<div>These disorders did not just manifest in human affairs (via Stalin, Mao and others)—they showed up in the natural systems that we neglected and misunderstood. Climate change—and the unprecedented threat to humans that it represents—has forced our eyes open, but we’re not yet wise (Peters et al., 2013; Marcott et al., 2013).</p>
<p>This apology is neither a wholesale rejection of economic thought and perspective nor an admission of error in our understanding of ecological values or human impacts on the environment. Life is complex. It’s an apology for the unintended damage that’s resulted from misapplying economic ideas: GDP fails to include non-market costs and benefits; transaction-based models mischaracterize dynamic relationships; aggregate social efficiency overlooks distribution impacts; technological advances can have substantial, unmeasured environmental impacts.</p>
<p>The rest of this essay will explain how we made these mistakes and how we can learn from them in facing a perilous future. This structure is not intended to provoke sympathy or excuse error. It’s just a way for us to reset a discussion that’s gotten tangled up in irrelevant details.</p></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/economists-owe-ecology-an-apology.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Derivatives, water and financial risk</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/derivatives-water-and-financial-risk.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/derivatives-water-and-financial-risk.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2013 14:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[David Zetland. water economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[regulations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[risk management]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/derivatives-water-and-financial-risk.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[David Zetland comments on future funding of &#8216;water&#8217; risk management.  There are plenty of examples of misguided government interventions, as well as examples of private enterprise run amok.  Now a derivatives market? : The danger of flashing wrong signals Have you heard the stories of people who have driven through fields, into lakes or off [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/" target="_blank">David Zetland</a> comments on future funding of &#8216;water&#8217; risk management.  There are plenty of examples of misguided government interventions, as well as examples of private enterprise run amok.  Now a derivatives market? :</p>
<p><a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2013/02/the-danger-of-flashing-wrong-signals.html">The danger of flashing wrong signals</a></p>
<blockquote><p>Have you heard the stories of people who have driven through fields, into lakes or off cliffs while following their GPS units? Any outsider would have told them to use their common sense before making a right turn over a cliff, but are WE so wise when it comes to our indicators?<br />Although the water sector really needs more and better information (that&#8217;s why I founded the <a href="http://waterdatahub.org/">water data hub</a>*), I worry about people putting the wrong weight on the wrong information &#8212; a worry that puts these recent stories into a different context:
<ul>
<li>The World Resources Institute released the <a href="http://aqueduct.wri.org/">Aqueduct 2.0</a> tool for water risk.</li>
<li>IBM and Waterfund (a global water risk management firm) <a href="http://finance.yahoo.com/blogs/daily-ticker/could-water-next-big-asset-class-144114830.html">created a benchmark with which to assess risk</a> when it comes to investing in the water sector.</li>
<li>Ceres has put out another report on the <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/sustainable-business/blog/us-water-paradox-demand-infrastructure">importance of water risk to companies</a>.</li>
</ul>
<p>Now, I&#8217;m not worried about the discussion of water risk. I think that it&#8217;s a topic of growing importance, as the end of abundance exposes business models, bureaucratic assumptions and personal habits formed in an era of too much, too cheap water to a new reality of scarce water that cannot be taken for granted.</p></blockquote>
<p>From the IBM/Waterfund  link comes this excerpt:</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<blockquote><p>The principals involved sat down with the Daily Ticker to explain.</p>
<p>“At one end of the spectrum you have housing, the most over-financialized sector of our economy,” Scott Rickards, President and CEO of Waterfund. “At the other end, you have water &#8211; there’s not a single financial product. Investors, Wall Street have pretty much ignored water. What we’re doing is using derivatives and insurance products to link to the index and enable risk management to actually take place for the first time in the water industry.”</p>
<p>“There’s plenty of capital that’s beginning to take an interest in investing in water,” notes Peter Williams, IBM Distinguished Engineer and Big Green Innovations CTO. “What we think the index will do is make it easier to invest in water by establishing a risk benchmark against which people can then lend. And the idea then is to encourage capital inflows into the water sector.”</p>
<p>This means for governments, municipalities, and water agencies looking for ways to finance the estimated <a href="http://finance.yahoo.com/blogs/daily-ticker/three-disturbing-economic-trends-2013-153106539.html">$1 trillion</a> in investment needed in water infrastructure in the U.S. alone, they could more easily raise this money and keep the liquidity (i.e. water) flowing to citizens.</p>
<p>On the note of risk, the misadventures of mortgage-backed securities during the housing crisis (not to <a href="http://finance.yahoo.com/news/next-global-crash-why-fear-143000901.html">mention commodity bubbles</a>) may raise eyebrows when it comes to the idea of speculation over an element so essential to life.</p>
<p>Rickards argues, “It’s taken 25 years for housing to go from non-financialized to where we are today after everything that occurred four years ago.” When it comes to water, “if it ever gets there where speculation is a problem, that will not be a bad thing because we will have come a long way in the meantime.”</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/derivatives-water-and-financial-risk.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Water, energy and the economy</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/water-energy-and-the-economy.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/water-energy-and-the-economy.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 12 Jan 2013 13:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[David Zetland. water economics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/water-energy-and-the-economy.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[David Zetland writes more on pricing water in relation to energy concerns at Growing Blue: Water, energy and the economy …let’s set aside the issue of environmental water and concentrate on water as a resource that can be used for economic activities. Most resource water is managed, priced and distributed by local monopolies, whether it’s [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>David Zetland writes more on pricing water in relation to energy concerns <a href="http://growingblue.com/2013/01/08/water-energy-and-the-economy/" title="http://growingblue.com/2013/01/08/water-energy-and-the-economy/">at Growing Blue</a>:</p>
<p>Water, energy and the economy</p>
<p>…let’s set aside the issue of environmental water and concentrate on water as a resource that can be used for economic activities. Most resource water is managed, priced and distributed by local monopolies, whether it’s an irrigation district delivering water to farmers or a utility delivering water to residential and industrial users. These monopolies often sell their water at the cost of delivery — covering the fixed costs of pipes and variable costs of treatment and pumping. It’s extremely rare that water prices reflect water scarcity, which means that it’s also rare for the price of water to rise when demand exceeds supply. This means that some users may consume “too much” water, leaving other users high and dry. (Or they may not – deciding that they’ve taken “their fair share,” but such restraint is rare when it’s possible to use more cheap water to increase profits.) Water managers may not work to prevent these shortages, since they are not penalized for shortages, allowed to raise their prices above cost, or worried about losing business to competitors.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>That’s not the case for energy, steel or trucks, as each of these businesses operate in markets, where prices adjust to equalize supply and demand and where competition makes it easier for new suppliers to meet demand when their competitors run out of inventory.</p>
<p>The impact of water shortages are much greater than implied by lost sales of water. A restaurant may pay one dollar for 100 gallons of tap water that is used to produce food worth thousands of dollars. An industrial facility may pay the same to produce products worth hundreds of times more. All of these users would be willing to pay far more in the event of water shortage, but their money is worthless when there’s no water. They then have to close the restaurant, turn off the turbines and shut down the machines for producing silicon chips or potato chips. Workers lose their wages, customers lose access to products — the effects multiply and spread, all for lack of “cheap” water that does not exist.</p>
<p>The solution to these problems is the same solution that will end our need to discuss the water-energy nexus: <em>price water for scarcity</em>. Such a solution would treat “economic water” as we treat oil, coal, shoes, coffee or any other product: prices will rise when demand exceeds supply and fall when supply exceeds demand.</p>
<p>Prices that reflect scarcity will keep supply and demand in balance, rationing water to those willing to pay more and preventing shortages. (Water managers will make more money than the cost of delivery, of course, but they can refund excess revenues to customers under the supervision of their regulators.) These operations require only a change in perspective: we need to treat water as a valuable input to our economic activities.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/water-energy-and-the-economy.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The political-economy of water…all in auctions</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/the-political-economy-of-waterall-in-auctions.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/the-political-economy-of-waterall-in-auctions.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 21 Dec 2012 17:16:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[aguanomics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[David Zetland. water economics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/the-political-economy-of-waterall-in-auctions.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[From David Zetland comes this re-posting from  Aguanomics on addressing issues in the political economy for  water. The political-economy of water&#8230;all in auctions I&#8217;ve been working on this idea for 5-6 years, and I think it has great potential for reallocating water while respecting the rights of existing users. It just came out in the Journal of Environmental [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>From David Zetland comes this re-posting from  <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/">Aguanomics</a> on addressing issues in the political economy for  water.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2012/12/all-in-auctions-is-published.html" target="_blank">The political-economy of water&#8230;all in auctions</a></p>
<p>I&#8217;ve been working on this idea for 5-6 years, and I think it has great potential for reallocating water while respecting the rights of existing users. It just came out in the <i>Journal of Environmental Management</i>. </p>
<p>Abstract: This paper proposes a novel mechanism for reallocating temporary water flows or permanent water rights. The All-in-Auction (AiA) increases efficiency and social welfare by reallocating water without harming water rights holders. AiAs can be used to allocate variable or diminished flows among traditional or new uses. AiAs are appropriate for use within larger organizations that distribute water among members, e.g., irrigation districts or wholesale water agencies. Members would decide when and how to use AiAs, i.e., when transaction costs are high, environmental constraints are binding, or allocation to outsiders is desired. Experimental sessions show that an AiA reallocates more units with no less efficiency that traditional two-sided auctions.</p>
<p>Those of you with an academic subscription can download it <a href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0301479712005956">here</a>. Those of you without can download my author&#8217;s copy [<a href="http://www.kysq.org/pubs/AiA_Final.pdf">pdf</a>]</p>
<p>Here&#8217;s <a href="http://www.aguanomics.com/2011/10/all-in-auctions-video.html">an earlier post</a> that links to other presentations of the AiA.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/the-political-economy-of-waterall-in-auctions.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
