<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>income equality &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Ok class, let&#8217;s review before the exam (election)</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/ok-class-lets-review-before-the-exam-election.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/ok-class-lets-review-before-the-exam-election.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2012 15:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2012 elections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income equality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[labor economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax cuts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax policy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[top 1%]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[voting]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/ok-class-lets-review-before-the-exam-election.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I&#8217;m sure you are all feeling kind of blah. You have this final exam for this session and I can tell by your performances on the quizzes that you are still confused. The problem solving portions of the quizzes have been very telling. So lets review. You&#8217;re taxes are not too high. It&#8217;s your income [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>I&#8217;m sure you are all feeling kind of blah.  You have this final exam for this session and I can tell by your performances on the quizzes that you are still confused.  The problem solving portions of the quizzes have been very telling.  So lets review.   </div>
<div>  </div>
<div></div>
<div>You&#8217;re taxes are not too high.  It&#8217;s your income that is too low!  Remember this and you will be able to solve enough of the problems to obtain a passing grade and graduate.  And class, no one running today for president gets this.  It is why President Obama looked like such a dufus in the debate.  Romney took a step to his left&#8230; right into Obama&#8217;s policy space.  Where does one go to gain more space when they have walled up the door to the left of them as President Obama has?</div>
<div></div>
<div>Let&#8217;s get something real clear from the beginning.  Unless you are acquiring the majority of your money from money  YOU ARE NOT<a href="https://www.google.com/#hl=en&#038;output=search&#038;sclient=psy-ab&#038;q=define+capitalist&#038;oq=define+&#038;gs_l=hp.1.0.35i39j0l3.735.1657.0.3579.7.6.0.0.0.0.219.938.0j5j1.6.0.les%3B..0.0...1c.1.VPyK4hyLvzM&#038;pbx=1&#038;bav=on.2,or.r_gc.r_pw.r_qf.&#038;fp=f2b10cd80850d317&#038;biw=1024&#038;bih=600" target="_blank"> A CAPITALIST</a> </div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>Second: A MARKET IS NOT AN ECONOMY.</div>
<p><a name="more"></a>
<div></div>
<div>You my fellow students, are citizens living in a particular social structure that can be understood by various groupings of all human interaction that takes place within.  The largest grouping is “society”.    Yes, there is the ultimate grouping known as the human race, but I&#8217;m keeping this discussion and exam limited to the USA society.  (If you pass, you will get to tackle the larger human race grouping in your graduate studies.)  An economy is one such organizational grouping of activity.  A democracy is another.   A “market” is only a labeling of activity.  It is one of many relational activities within an economy and/or a democracy within a society.  An election is another such activity. </div>
<div></div>
<div>Now, this is very important: THERE IS NO HIEARCHY of the various groupings.  There can&#8217;t be.  It&#8217;s impossible as the groupings are not determinate of life and living.   I will tell you that my physiology professor stated that the determinate of life is a membrane.  So, let&#8217;s get off the “market” kick.  Trust me, “market” will not be an answer on the exam.   </div>
<div></div>
<div>If you are not a citizen capitalist, then you are a citizen laborer.  (These are descriptive labels that are not all inclusive of your potential grouping.)   You are acquiring your money mostly via your labor.  Physical labor, cognitive labor  it does not matter because you are using some ratio of both to acquire your money.  You are expending your labor to your personal level of comfort.  Note, I did not say you are expending your labor to the level of market ability or market possibility.  Your labor does not determine your comfort.  Your labor is not interpretative of your comfort.  It is having obtained your level of desired comfort (comfort as defined by you) that will have determined your labor expended.   </div>
<div></div>
<div>Society ultimately determines your value which is based on what society deems of value to it.  Now I know you are thinking I&#8217;ve really put my foot in it here.  I haven&#8217;t.  The market does not determine your value.  The collective of “society” does determine your value and the collective is dynamic though I am not implying any particular velocity of dynamism.  I am not quantifying or qualifying the dynamism.  Elections do the determining.  </div>
<div></div>
<div>Now that we are all on the same page, let me repeat myself: YOUR TAXES ARE NOT TOO HIGH.</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>Your income is too low and no one running for president sees your relationship in this economy in this way.  They don&#8217;t see it because not enough of you see it this way either.  To many are acting as if they are capitalists.  To many are acting as if the market is determinate.  Who the hell is in control here?  YOU or the market?   </div>
<div></div>
<div>So, let me explain your current condition and thus in doing so provide you with what the goal needs to be of any policy (and a focus of your essay) that either of the two presidential candidates propose.  It is working the goal that will allow you to obtain the highest grade on the exam.  Hell, let&#8217;s include the congressional candidates also. They make proposals all the time.  Understand the goal and how you acquire your money and the essay portion (voting) will be a snap.  Original thinking combined with the greatest inclusiveness will get a higher grade.</div>
<div></div>
<div>You are living in the median household.  I know this because, class&#8230; say it with me: I am not a capitalist.   </div>
<div>In 1976 your household had the median income of $12,690.   </div>
<div></div>
<div>Using the magic of the <a href="http://www.measuringworth.com/m/calculators/uscompare/%20" target="_blank">Measuring Worth</a>site  (it is the  only calculator allowed for your final) your household in 2011 has grown to $52,200.00 based on the skilled labor value.   Notice, we are not using the skilled capitalist value (there is none listed).</div>
<div></div>
<div>Unfortunately for you, the census states that your household actually has only $50,054 of income.  The difference of $2146 is the results of your labor not being valued as much as it was in 1976.  Society has decided that what ever it is you are doing it is not of such value as it was in 1976.  In fact, your value is so little that it did not even keep up with inflation.  How ya feeling about that?</div>
<div></div>
<div>Still thinking it&#8217;s that your taxes are too high?   </div>
<div></div>
<div>Well class, here&#8217;s the real pain: $61,629.00.*   This is the number that you would have if society had just kept the dynamics as they were.   For the sensitive students, unfortunately the ever dynamic society just didn&#8217;t keep the same flaming intensity of love for you as it now cherishes for the capitalist.   Sorry class.  Society has changed.  It values the capitalist more.  Thus, society has changed the economy so that the market activities result in more of the income produced going to the capitalist.  Society did this to you.  </div>
<div></div>
<div>Have I made this personal enough for you?  (Remember&#8230;the essay.)   Just in case I haven&#8217;t, recall the earlier part of this review.  You are a part of a collective group called “society”.  </div>
<div></div>
<div>Let&#8217;s recap:  Society.  You are a part of society.  Society is dynamic.  Elections determine.  You are not a capitalist.  &#8220;Economy&#8221; is a grouping.  &#8220;Market&#8221; is not an answer.  Your taxes are not to high.  Your income is to low.    </div>
<div></div>
<div>Here is the major essay question:  <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Fgjfi1DU1mQ" target="_blank">What do you want from life</a>?  I look for original thought and inclusiveness.   Bonus points if you can relate it all to the preamble of the USA societal organizing document.I remove points for facts supported by opinion.</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>*As calculated by using the ratio of the share of income for the non capitalist to capitalist  in 1976 to the time period of around now (like today).</div>
<div></div>
<div>$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$$</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>I have published on this confusion many times.  My <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2007/01/how-money-is-made-post-by-divorced-one.html" target="_blank">very first post</a> was on this subject.  Most specifically <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2009/02/more-kissing-income-inequality.htm" target="_blank">here,</a></div>
<div></div>
<div>and <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2008/09/class-war-appropriateness-of-wealthys.html" target="_blank">here</a> and <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2009/01/lets-kiss-income-inequality.html" target="_blank">here</a>.</div>
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/ok-class-lets-review-before-the-exam-election.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Screw the Clinton tax rates. Lets party like it&#8217;s 1936!</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/screw-the-clinton-tax-rates-lets-party-like-its-1936.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/screw-the-clinton-tax-rates-lets-party-like-its-1936.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 28 Jul 2012 05:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Bush tax cuts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income equality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[marginal rates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax rates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[top 1%]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/screw-the-clinton-tax-rates-lets-party-like-its-1936.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Update: *Additional numbers added Digby wrote a few days ago about the“grown-up” people coming to town to save America from the deficit. She listed a few of those people and their annual income. Also, a few days ago the Senate had a vote on the tax cuts. Letting the Bush cuts go (I&#8217;m all for [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div></div>
<div>Update: *Additional numbers added </p>
<p>Digby wrote a few days ago about<a href="http://digbysblog.blogspot.com/2012/07/the-grown-ups-are-planning-coup.html"> the“grown-up” people</a> coming to town to save America from the deficit.  She listed a few of those people and their annual income.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Also, a  few days ago the Senate had a vote on the tax cuts.  Letting the Bush cuts go (I&#8217;m all for it and we can stop the payroll tax cut too as it is all stupid policy when the problem is declining wages/income going to labor) will return us to the Clinton years rates.  People have noted just how little such a rise means to those at the top.     </div>
<div></div>
<div>Well, in keeping with my define rich series and my series looking at the purpose of taxation, I thought wouldn&#8217;t it be interesting to see just what these 1%&#8217;ers might be paying if we went back to the beginning of the last great period of <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/03/defining-rich-vi-1936-tax-tables.html">mass prosperity:  1936</a>.   </div>
<div></div>
<div>Yes indeedy, I say go for the brass ring.  Let&#8217;s show our maturity and actually implement the lesson learned from our history, that period from around <a href="http://www.taxhistory.org/www/website.nsf/Web/THM1901?OpenDocument">1906 to 1932</a> and then 1936 to 1979.   </div>
<div></div>
<div>While we&#8217;re at it, let us stop pretending that global trade is something new with an unknowable to man exotic force that we just have to accept as part of the expression of our DNA.   There is RNA also (look it up).</div>
<div></div>
<p><a name="more"></a>
<div></div>
<div>The following  numbers are based on the gross incomes Digby listed.  Thus we&#8217;ll have to keep in mind that there have been no adjustments made for deductions in my calculations.  So in truth, the tax paid would be less and the purchasing power of the actual non-adjusted income would be much greater.  After all, the deductions represent benefits received from the income that was deducted including the government handout in the form of reduced taxes for various activities taken with one&#8217;s income.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Here is what it looks like:</div>
<div><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-1cMkNPATmc8/UBN2YVEaQKI/AAAAAAAAASw/WiV0pUMcLRU/s1600/Party+like+it+1936+income+tax+chart.jpg" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="177" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-1cMkNPATmc8/UBN2YVEaQKI/AAAAAAAAASw/WiV0pUMcLRU/s320/Party+like+it+1936+income+tax+chart.jpg" width="320"></a></div>
<div>All these men managed to hit the top marginal rate of 79%.  Not one of them paid that amount.  Notice how flat the percentage paid becomes.  They want a flat tax, the got it.  They just had to really, really perform to get to that level of tax nirvana in 1936.  They couldn&#8217;t just pull a <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0102609/">Lawrence Garfield</a>, or should I say a Romney?  They couldn&#8217;t just negotiate payment in stock, whack labor costs to increase the stock value, take that money and buy it&#8217;s competitors to the point of oligopoly and then move on.  They could not just raid a solid company like New England Wire and Cable turning all the assets into cash at the expense of all the other relationships such a company had and justify it by saying “I make you money”.  Greenmail?  Junk Bonds?</div>
<div></div>
<div>I wrote <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/07/wages-driven-down-now-relative-to.html">about Caterpillar </a>and their approach to negotiating with the commodity of labor.  The average yearly income of the labor was $55,000/year.  The multiples of the above net income range from 24.8 to 147.38.  (* Multiples of the gross incomes range from 104.6 to 688.)</div>
<div></div>
<div>Granted, what&#8217;s left for these gentlemen would not allow the purchase of a new Cessna Citation X, but there was a 1999 listed for $5,950,000 when I search google.  I think Mr. Sherill could afford the monthly payment on this.  Though <a href="http://www.cessna.com/citation/mustang.html">Cessna is offering the 4 passenger</a> (the X is 12 passenger) at 0% interest for the first 12 months and Wiki says they list for only $2.65 million!  You know, if buying used just curls your hair.</div>
<div></div>
<div>The point?  There is nothing with the 1936 marginal tax rates that these men can not have other than more of it.  Nothing.   Real grown-ups who developed the 1936 tax table new this along with a lot of other stuff related income how it is actually earned and it&#8217;s social effect.  All you have to do is<a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/03/defining-rich-vi-1936-tax-tables.html"> lookat the tables and graphs</a> to see that the marginal rates were not pulled out of selfish and self serving asses.  They had a desired results in mind, one of which was to prevent “economic royalists”.  I am confident the other desire was to take back rent collected from other peoples collective efforts in proportion to the lack of labor performed as one rises up the economic pyramid.    </div>
<div></div>
<div>Have you heard the one about job creation?  The one that asks: When was the last time a poor person gave you a job?  When was the last time a CEO 1%&#8217;er&#8217;s activity saved the human race?   Four people at least from 1928 to the patent granted in 1948 were involved in<a href="http://inventors.about.com/od/pstartinventions/a/Penicillin.htm"> bring penicillin to the point ofcommercial viability</a>. </div>
<div>It was one woman&#8217;s work that allowed the next step of developing additional antibiotics.  </div>
<div></div>
<div>When was the last time a CEO 1% er&#8217;s activity resulted in a leap of human progress?   I&#8217;m thinking of my favorite non-CEO/Banker/1% example of flight.  No, Gates and Jobs did not do it like the Wright Brothers did it.  </div>
<div></div>
<div>1936.  We responded in a way that attest to a time when we did learn from history and acted on lessons from history.</div>
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/screw-the-clinton-tax-rates-lets-party-like-its-1936.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Due Process: Holder vs Colbert. Art or Reality. Choose.</title>
		<link>./../../2012/03/due-process-holder-vs-colbert-art-or-reality-choose.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/03/due-process-holder-vs-colbert-art-or-reality-choose.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Mar 2012 17:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[AG investigations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[equality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income equality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[reality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rule of law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wealth creation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[world bank]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/03/due-process-holder-vs-colbert-art-or-reality-choose.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This is the object:  No person shall be held to answer for a capital, or otherwise infamous crime, unless on a presentment or indictment of a Grand Jury,&#8230; nor be deprived of life, liberty, or property, without due process of law; It&#8217;s all one sentence. Any questions? This is Art: The lyrics of Grand Funk [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div></div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>This is the object: </div>
<p>
<blockquote>
<div>No person shall be held to answer for a capital, or otherwise infamous crime, unless on a presentment or indictment of a Grand Jury,&#8230; nor be deprived of life, liberty, or property, without due process of law;</div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div>It&#8217;s all one sentence.  Any questions?</div>
<div></div>
<div>This is Art:</div>
<div>The lyrics of Grand Funk Railroad&#8217;s <a href="http://www.songlyrics.com/grand-funk-railroad/paranoid-lyrics/">Paranoid </a></div>
<p>
<blockquote>
<div>Did you ever have that feeling in your life</div>
<div>That someone was watching you?</div>
<div>You don&#8217;t have no reason that&#8217;s right</div>
<div>But still he&#8217;s there watching you</div>
<div>Someone is waiting just outside the door</div>
<div>To take you away</div>
<div>Everybody knows just what he&#8217;s there for</div>
<div>To take you away</div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div>vs the lyrics of Red Rider&#8217;s <a href="http://www.songlyrics.com/red-rider/lunatic-fringe-lyrics/">Lunatic Fringe</a> </div>
<p>
<blockquote>
<div>Lunatic Fringe &#8211; in the twilight&#8217;s last gleaming</div>
<div>This is open season, but you won&#8217;t get too far</div>
<div>&#8216;Cause you got to blame someone for your own confusion</div>
<div>We&#8217;re all on guard this time against the Final Solution</div>
<div>all on guard this time</div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div>This is the reality. 44% of <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2007/10/human-capital-is-where-its-at.html">our wealth is due to rule of law.</a></div>
<div></div>
<div>World Bank study on wealth in 2005 stated:  </div>
<p>
<blockquote>
<div align="JUSTIFY">Worldwide, the study finds, &#8220;natural capital accounts for 5 percent of total wealth, produced capital for 18 percent, and intangible capital 77 percent.&#8221;  &#8220;Rich countries are largely rich because of the skills of their populations and the quality of the institutions supporting economic activity,&#8221; the study concludes. According to Hamilton&#8217;s figures, the rule of law explains 57 percent of countries&#8217; intangible capital. Education accounts for 36 percent.”  </div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div>Rule of law equates <a href="http://www.equalitytrust.org.uk/why/evidence/trust-and-community-life">to trust</a>.   </div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div><a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-nVZaff-ud1A/T1jYq6Jlz5I/AAAAAAAAASo/J_iYIXgAUWk/s1600/Trust+Graph.gif" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="229" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-nVZaff-ud1A/T1jYq6Jlz5I/AAAAAAAAASo/J_iYIXgAUWk/s320/Trust+Graph.gif" width="320"></a></div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<div>A nation can not generate $14 trillion per year if there is general suspicion throughout society.  </div>
<p>
<blockquote>“Trust” seems to be the real intangible the report is talking about. We as a whole can be educated to the hilt, but if we can&#8217;t trust that our efforts will be put to constructive use, we have problems. Think habeas corpus, FISA, election fraud, threatening of the press, intimidation of speech, extension of free speech to none human entities, the equating of one voice-one vote to spending of one&#8217;s money, K Street project, etc. Think of the use of fear. If only a few are educated to the hilt or have access to the governance, we can not build capital. </p></blockquote>
<blockquote><div><a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2007/10/human-capital-is-where-its-at.html">Daniel Becker 10/8/2007</a></div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>Which is art, which is reality?</div>
<p>
<blockquote>
<div>Due process and judicial process are not one in the same.  The Constitution guarantees due process, it does not guarantee judicial process.  Erik Holder 3/5/12*  </div>
</blockquote>
<p>
<blockquote>
<div>Due process just means there is a process that you do.  Steven Colbert 3/6/12*</div>
<div></div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<p>Which is art, which is reality? </p>
<blockquote><p>In response to the act perpetrated&#8230;Congress has authorized the President to use all necessary and appropriate force against those groups.  Because the United States is in an armed conflict&#8230; Eric Holder 3/5/12* 
<div></div>
</blockquote>
<p>
<blockquote>
<div>We&#8217;re at war with Terror.   Therefore, the President can blow up any American citizen he chooses until we win the war by defeating the idea of being afraid.  Steven Colbert, 3/6/12.*</div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<p>
<div>Is this art or reality?</div>
<p>
<blockquote>
<div><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Due_process">Due process developed</a> from clause 39 of the Magna Carta in England.</div>
<div><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Due_process"><br /></a></div>
<div>In clause 39 of the Magna Carta, John of England promised as follows: &#8220;No free man shall be seized or imprisoned, or stripped of his rights or possessions, or outlawed or exiled, or deprived of his standing in any other way, nor will we proceed with force against him, or send others to do so, except by the lawful judgment of his equals or by the law of the land.&#8221;</div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div>It appears in this War on Terror, England is not the only nation learning from another regarding how to<a href="http://downingstreetmemo.com/memos.html">“fix” the war</a>.  We too have obviously learned from England regarding war management.  We have learned how to manifest the feeling of “it&#8217;s only a piece of paper” (though not true that Bush 2 made such a statement regarding the Constitution which makes Obama et al&#8217;s position all the more surreal).     </div>
<div></div>
<blockquote><div>As the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Due_process">U.S. Supreme Court has explained</a>, a due process requirement in Britain was not &#8220;essential to the idea of due process of law in the prosecution and punishment of crimes, but was only mentioned as an example and illustration of due process of law as it actually existed in cases in which it was customarily used.&#8221;[11]  </div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>I can see how England&#8217;s approach to war fixing is a much better solution if your goal is to <a href="http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/conflate">conflate art and reality</a>.  There is no need to be clandestine.  Did you notice the closeness of the USA and England on the trust graph?</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>Which will you choose? Art or Reality?  Are you sure which one is which?  Be careful, it&#8217;s <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2007/10/human-capital-is-where-its-at.html">your economic future</a> that is at stake.</div>
<div></div>
<div><a href="http://www.colbertnation.com/the-colbert-report-videos/410085/march-06-2012/the-word---due-or-die%20">*Watch Steven&#8217;s</a> take on this.<a href="http://www.colbertnation.com/the-colbert-report-videos/410085/march-06-2012/the-word---due-or-die"></a></div>
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/03/due-process-holder-vs-colbert-art-or-reality-choose.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Guest post: Who Are the 1%?</title>
		<link>./../../2011/12/guest-post-who-are-the-1.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/12/guest-post-who-are-the-1.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2011 04:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[income equality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Inequality of wealth or income]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[occupy wall street]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[occupying together]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Taryn Hart]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[taxes]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/12/guest-post-who-are-the-1.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Update: Mike Konczal also takes a  look at this question in Who are the one percent and what do they do for a living.Update 2: Another source for historical trends on inequality is at The Center for Budget and Policy Priorities by Taryn Hart     Taryn Hart publishes at her blog Plutocracy files and has interviewed [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>Update: <a href="http://www.newdeal20.org/2011/12/23/the-most-popular-post-of-2011-who-are-the-1-and-what-do-they-do-for-a-living-67946/" target="_blank">Mike Konczal</a> also takes a  look at this question in <i>Who are the one percent and what do they do for a living.</i><br /><i><br /></i><br />Update 2: Another source for historical trends on inequality is at <a href="http://www.cbpp.org/cms/index.cfm?fa=view&#038;id=3629" target="_blank">The Center for Budget and Policy Priorities</a><i><br /></i></p>
<p>by Taryn Hart <br />   <i> </i><br /><i>Taryn Hart publishes at her blog </i><i><a href="http://plutocracyfiles.com/" target="_blank">Plutocracy files</a> and has interviewed John Quiggen, Bill Black, Larry Mishal to name three economists</i></p>
<p>Guest post:    Who Are the 1%?</p></div>
<div></div>
<div>A week or so back, Dan from <i>Angry Bear</i> passed along <a href="http://www.bostonglobe.com/business/2011/12/18/two-communities-are-worlds-apart/6RZboLZCxK7VWrm6Y7xURO/story.html">this</a><a href="http://www.bostonglobe.com/business/2011/12/18/two-communities-are-worlds-apart/6RZboLZCxK7VWrm6Y7xURO/story.html"> </a><a href="http://www.bostonglobe.com/business/2011/12/18/two-communities-are-worlds-apart/6RZboLZCxK7VWrm6Y7xURO/story.html"><i>Boston</i></a><a href="http://www.bostonglobe.com/business/2011/12/18/two-communities-are-worlds-apart/6RZboLZCxK7VWrm6Y7xURO/story.html"><i> </i></a><a href="http://www.bostonglobe.com/business/2011/12/18/two-communities-are-worlds-apart/6RZboLZCxK7VWrm6Y7xURO/story.html"><i>Globe</i></a><a href="http://www.bostonglobe.com/business/2011/12/18/two-communities-are-worlds-apart/6RZboLZCxK7VWrm6Y7xURO/story.html"><i> </i></a><a href="http://www.bostonglobe.com/business/2011/12/18/two-communities-are-worlds-apart/6RZboLZCxK7VWrm6Y7xURO/story.html">article</a>. On its face, the article bemoans rising inequality through a comparison of two Massachusetts neighborhoods: Sherborn, the State’s wealthiest neighborhood and Springfield, a former working-class neighborhood that now resembles a <a href="http://youtu.be/LEzXln5kbuw?t=50s">globalized</a><a href="http://youtu.be/LEzXln5kbuw?t=50s"> </a><a href="http://youtu.be/LEzXln5kbuw?t=50s">ghost</a><a href="http://youtu.be/LEzXln5kbuw?t=50s"> </a><a href="http://youtu.be/LEzXln5kbuw?t=50s">town</a>. Although the article quotes a Sherborn resident disavowing his status as a one percenter, the piece clearly implies that the upscale Sherbornites are one percenters.</div>
<div></div>
<div>However, as Dan correctly pointed out, Sherbonites are not the one percent: The median income of Sherborn is $190,000 per year; not peanuts, I know, but the lowest paid one percenters <a href="http://blogs.wsj.com/economics/2011/10/19/what-percent-are-you/">make</a><a href="http://blogs.wsj.com/economics/2011/10/19/what-percent-are-you/"> $500,000</a> per year (even using a significantly <a href="http://www.freakonomics.com/2011/12/20/there-will-be-rich-always/">narrower</a><a href="http://www.freakonomics.com/2011/12/20/there-will-be-rich-always/"> </a><a href="http://www.freakonomics.com/2011/12/20/there-will-be-rich-always/">definition</a><a href="http://www.freakonomics.com/2011/12/20/there-will-be-rich-always/"> </a><a href="http://www.freakonomics.com/2011/12/20/there-will-be-rich-always/">of</a><a href="http://www.freakonomics.com/2011/12/20/there-will-be-rich-always/"> </a><a href="http://www.freakonomics.com/2011/12/20/there-will-be-rich-always/">income</a><a href="http://www.freakonomics.com/2011/12/20/there-will-be-rich-always/">, </a><a href="http://www.freakonomics.com/2011/12/20/there-will-be-rich-always/">one</a><a href="http://www.freakonomics.com/2011/12/20/there-will-be-rich-always/"> </a><a href="http://www.freakonomics.com/2011/12/20/there-will-be-rich-always/">percenters</a><a href="http://www.freakonomics.com/2011/12/20/there-will-be-rich-always/"> </a><a href="http://www.freakonomics.com/2011/12/20/there-will-be-rich-always/">make</a><a href="http://www.freakonomics.com/2011/12/20/there-will-be-rich-always/"> </a><a href="http://www.freakonomics.com/2011/12/20/there-will-be-rich-always/">in</a><a href="http://www.freakonomics.com/2011/12/20/there-will-be-rich-always/"> </a><a href="http://www.freakonomics.com/2011/12/20/there-will-be-rich-always/">excess</a><a href="http://www.freakonomics.com/2011/12/20/there-will-be-rich-always/"> </a><a href="http://www.freakonomics.com/2011/12/20/there-will-be-rich-always/">of</a><a href="http://www.freakonomics.com/2011/12/20/there-will-be-rich-always/"> $330,000</a> per year). Moreover, <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/graduates-versus-oligarchs/">the</a><a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/graduates-versus-oligarchs/"> </a><a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/graduates-versus-oligarchs/">biggest</a><a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/graduates-versus-oligarchs/"> </a><a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/graduates-versus-oligarchs/">gains</a><a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/graduates-versus-oligarchs/"> </a><a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/graduates-versus-oligarchs/">over</a><a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/graduates-versus-oligarchs/"> </a><a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/graduates-versus-oligarchs/">the</a><a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/graduates-versus-oligarchs/"> </a><a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/graduates-versus-oligarchs/">past</a><a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/graduates-versus-oligarchs/"> </a><a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/graduates-versus-oligarchs/">thirty</a><a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/graduates-versus-oligarchs/">&#8211;</a><a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/graduates-versus-oligarchs/">odd</a><a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/graduates-versus-oligarchs/"> </a><a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/graduates-versus-oligarchs/">years</a><a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/graduates-versus-oligarchs/"> </a><a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/graduates-versus-oligarchs/">have</a><a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/graduates-versus-oligarchs/"> </a><a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/graduates-versus-oligarchs/">gone</a><a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/graduates-versus-oligarchs/"> </a><a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/graduates-versus-oligarchs/">to</a><a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/graduates-versus-oligarchs/"> </a><a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/graduates-versus-oligarchs/">the</a><a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/graduates-versus-oligarchs/"> </a><a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/graduates-versus-oligarchs/">top</a><a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/graduates-versus-oligarchs/"> .1%</a>. </div>
<div></div>
<div>When Occupy Wall Street identifies its opposition as the 1%, it’s not talking about people who live in posh neighborhoods with great schools; it’s talking about people who can hire teams of lobbyists who live in posh neighborhoods with great schools. <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BdV95fC09hE&#038;feature=results_main&#038;playnext=1&#038;list=PLE13031ADC50D5FC6">As</a><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BdV95fC09hE&#038;feature=results_main&#038;playnext=1&#038;list=PLE13031ADC50D5FC6"> </a><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BdV95fC09hE&#038;feature=results_main&#038;playnext=1&#038;list=PLE13031ADC50D5FC6">Gordon</a><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BdV95fC09hE&#038;feature=results_main&#038;playnext=1&#038;list=PLE13031ADC50D5FC6"> </a><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BdV95fC09hE&#038;feature=results_main&#038;playnext=1&#038;list=PLE13031ADC50D5FC6">Gekko</a><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BdV95fC09hE&#038;feature=results_main&#038;playnext=1&#038;list=PLE13031ADC50D5FC6"> </a><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BdV95fC09hE&#038;feature=results_main&#038;playnext=1&#038;list=PLE13031ADC50D5FC6">put</a><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BdV95fC09hE&#038;feature=results_main&#038;playnext=1&#038;list=PLE13031ADC50D5FC6"> </a><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BdV95fC09hE&#038;feature=results_main&#038;playnext=1&#038;list=PLE13031ADC50D5FC6">it</a>:</div>
<div></div>
<div>I&#8217;m not talking a $400,000 a year working Wall Street stiff flying first class and being comfortable, I&#8217;m talking about liquid. Rich enough to have your own jet. Rich enough not to waste time. Fifty, a hundred million dollars, buddy. A player, or nothing.</div>
<div></div>
<div>And keep in mind, that’s 1980s dollars. Given the scandalous increases that have gone to the top 1% since then, the amount required to be a player these days is several times that amount. And the problem with that kind of concentration of wealth is that it inevitably undermines the incentive for collective action required for social well being. </div>
<div><a name="more"></a></div>
<div>As <a href="http://www.rollingstone.com/politics/blogs/taibblog/a-christmas-message-from-americas-rich-20111222">Matt</a><a href="http://www.rollingstone.com/politics/blogs/taibblog/a-christmas-message-from-americas-rich-20111222"> </a><a href="http://www.rollingstone.com/politics/blogs/taibblog/a-christmas-message-from-americas-rich-20111222">Taibbi</a><a href="http://www.rollingstone.com/politics/blogs/taibblog/a-christmas-message-from-americas-rich-20111222"> </a><a href="http://www.rollingstone.com/politics/blogs/taibblog/a-christmas-message-from-americas-rich-20111222">has</a><a href="http://www.rollingstone.com/politics/blogs/taibblog/a-christmas-message-from-americas-rich-20111222"> </a><a href="http://www.rollingstone.com/politics/blogs/taibblog/a-christmas-message-from-americas-rich-20111222">pointed</a><a href="http://www.rollingstone.com/politics/blogs/taibblog/a-christmas-message-from-americas-rich-20111222"> </a><a href="http://www.rollingstone.com/politics/blogs/taibblog/a-christmas-message-from-americas-rich-20111222">out</a> in response to the one-percenter meme that those who are so poor they don’t pay federal income tax have “no skin in the game,” concentration of wealth creates perverse incentives that ensure most of the mega rich are terrible citizens: </div>
<div></div>
<div>The very rich on today’s Wall Street are now so rich that they buy their own social infrastructure. They hire private security, they live in gated mansions on islands and other tax havens, and most notably, they buy their own justice and their own government.</div>
<div></div>
<div>            *            *            *</div>
<div></div>
<div>Most of us 99-percenters couldn’t even let our dogs leave a dump on the sidewalk without feeling ashamed before our neighbors&#8230;.</div>
<div></div>
<div>But our Too-Big-To-Fail banks unhesitatingly take billions in bailout money and then turn right around and finance the export of jobs to new locations in China and India. They defraud the pension funds of state workers into buying billions of their crap mortgage assets. They take zero-interest loans from the state and then lend that same money back to us at interest. Or, like Chase, they bribe the politicians serving countries and states and cities and even school boards to take on crippling debt deals.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Nobody with real skin in the game, who had any kind of stake in our collective future, would do any of those things. </div>
<div></div>
<div>Nobel Prize-winning economist Joseph Stiglitz made the same point in May of 2011 (well before Occupy Wall Street), in a must-read <i>Vanity Fair</i> piece entitled, <a href="http://www.vanityfair.com/society/features/2011/05/top-one-percent-201105">“</a><a href="http://www.vanityfair.com/society/features/2011/05/top-one-percent-201105">Of</a><a href="http://www.vanityfair.com/society/features/2011/05/top-one-percent-201105"> </a><a href="http://www.vanityfair.com/society/features/2011/05/top-one-percent-201105">the</a><a href="http://www.vanityfair.com/society/features/2011/05/top-one-percent-201105"> 1%, </a><a href="http://www.vanityfair.com/society/features/2011/05/top-one-percent-201105">by</a><a href="http://www.vanityfair.com/society/features/2011/05/top-one-percent-201105"> </a><a href="http://www.vanityfair.com/society/features/2011/05/top-one-percent-201105">the</a><a href="http://www.vanityfair.com/society/features/2011/05/top-one-percent-201105"> 1%, </a><a href="http://www.vanityfair.com/society/features/2011/05/top-one-percent-201105">for</a><a href="http://www.vanityfair.com/society/features/2011/05/top-one-percent-201105"> </a><a href="http://www.vanityfair.com/society/features/2011/05/top-one-percent-201105">the</a><a href="http://www.vanityfair.com/society/features/2011/05/top-one-percent-201105"> 1%”</a>:</div>
<div></div>
<div>[A] modern economy requires “collective action”—it needs government to invest in infrastructure, education, and technology&#8230;. America has long suffered from an under-investment in infrastructure (look at the condition of our highways and bridges, our railroads and airports), in basic research, and in education at all levels. Further cutbacks in these areas lie ahead.</div>
<div></div>
<div>None of this should come as a surprise—it is simply what happens when a society’s wealth distribution becomes lopsided. The more divided a society becomes in terms of wealth, the more reluctant the wealthy become to spend money on common needs. The rich don’t need to rely on government for parks or education or medical care or personal security—they can buy all these things for themselves. In the process, they become more distant from ordinary people, losing whatever empathy they may once have had. </div>
<div></div>
<div>Be clear: This is who Occupy Wall Street is talking about &#8211; the small class of people who have amassed so much wealth that they have no need for the social infrastructure that is the life blood of the 99% (even the 99 percenters who live in swank neighborhoods like Sherborn, Massachusets). </div>
<div></div>
<div>And suggesting that Sherborn is the 1% and Springfield is the 99% &#8211; when they’re both the 99% &#8211; seems designed to falsely frame the problem of inequality as the poor (Springfield) versus the well-to-do (Sherborn). Of course, in the realm of those set on denying or deflecting inequality concerns, improperly defining the opponents of the 99% is fairly mild. (See discussions of income-inequality deniers <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2007/01/income-and-wealth-alan-reynolds-is-not.html">here</a> and <a href="http://economistsview.typepad.com/economistsview/2008/06/the-income-ineq.html">here</a>). However, this particular sleight of hand has made more than one appearance of late and therefore, is worth reviewing a bit more closely. </div>
<div></div>
<div><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/opinion/brooks-the-wrong-inequality.html?_r=2&#038;hp">David</a><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/opinion/brooks-the-wrong-inequality.html?_r=2&#038;hp"> </a><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/11/01/opinion/brooks-the-wrong-inequality.html?_r=2&#038;hp">Brooks</a> recently distinguished what he termed “Blue Inequality” of the mega rich from “Red Inequality,” which Brooks claims results from an education gap and is “much more important.” According to Brooks: “The zooming wealth of the top 1 percent is a problem, but it’s not nearly as big a problem as the tens of millions of Americans who have dropped out of high school or college&#8230;.” <u></u></div>
<div></div>
<div>As <a href="http://www.cepr.net/index.php/blogs/beat-the-press/david-brooks-complains-that-he-cant-get-access-to-inequality-data">Dean</a><a href="http://www.cepr.net/index.php/blogs/beat-the-press/david-brooks-complains-that-he-cant-get-access-to-inequality-data"> </a><a href="http://www.cepr.net/index.php/blogs/beat-the-press/david-brooks-complains-that-he-cant-get-access-to-inequality-data">B</a><a href="http://www.cepr.net/index.php/blogs/beat-the-press/david-brooks-complains-that-he-cant-get-access-to-inequality-data">aker</a><a href="http://www.cepr.net/index.php/blogs/beat-the-press/david-brooks-complains-that-he-cant-get-access-to-inequality-data"> </a><a href="http://www.cepr.net/index.php/blogs/beat-the-press/david-brooks-complains-that-he-cant-get-access-to-inequality-data">immediately</a><a href="http://www.cepr.net/index.php/blogs/beat-the-press/david-brooks-complains-that-he-cant-get-access-to-inequality-data"> </a><a href="http://www.cepr.net/index.php/blogs/beat-the-press/david-brooks-complains-that-he-cant-get-access-to-inequality-data">pointed</a><a href="http://www.cepr.net/index.php/blogs/beat-the-press/david-brooks-complains-that-he-cant-get-access-to-inequality-data"> </a><a href="http://www.cepr.net/index.php/blogs/beat-the-press/david-brooks-complains-that-he-cant-get-access-to-inequality-data">out</a>, Brooks’s Blue Inequality/Red Inequality thesis is absolutely unsupported by the data:</div>
<h3>           David Brooks Complains That He Can&#8217;t Get Access to Inequality Data</h3>
<div>Actually he didn&#8217;t complain about his lack of access to data, but he probably should have given the column he wrote today.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Let me just pause for a moment to say: Snap! Good on Dean Baker for pointing out that Brooks’s argument flat-out ignores well-known inequality data. Alright, back to Baker: </div>
<div></div>
<div>Brooks purports to lecture the Occupy Wall Street crew about how they are focused on the wrong inequality.</div>
<div></div>
<div>He tells them that that there are two inequalities in the U.S. On the one hand we have the CEOs, the Goldman Sachs crew, the lobbyists and the other members of the one percent who have done incredibly well in the last three decades. Brooks calls this the &#8220;blue inequality&#8221;&#8230;.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Brooks tells us that this is less of a big deal than the red inequality, which he defines as the gap between college educated workers and those without a college degree&#8230;.</div>
<div></div>
<div>This is where Brooks lack of access to data is so important&#8230;. </div>
<div></div>
<div>[S]ince the 90s, the wages of workers with high school degrees have not departed much from the wages of workers with just college degrees, the <a href="http://www.epi.org/publication/bp331-occupy-wall-street/">vast</a><a href="http://www.epi.org/publication/bp331-occupy-wall-street/"> </a><a href="http://www.epi.org/publication/bp331-occupy-wall-street/">majority</a><a href="http://www.epi.org/publication/bp331-occupy-wall-street/"> </a><a href="http://www.epi.org/publication/bp331-occupy-wall-street/">of</a><a href="http://www.epi.org/publication/bp331-occupy-wall-street/"> </a><a href="http://www.epi.org/publication/bp331-occupy-wall-street/">the</a><a href="http://www.epi.org/publication/bp331-occupy-wall-street/"> </a><a href="http://www.epi.org/publication/bp331-occupy-wall-street/">economy</a><a href="http://www.epi.org/publication/bp331-occupy-wall-street/">&#8216;</a><a href="http://www.epi.org/publication/bp331-occupy-wall-street/">s</a><a href="http://www.epi.org/publication/bp331-occupy-wall-street/"> </a><a href="http://www.epi.org/publication/bp331-occupy-wall-street/">gains</a> have gone to the top 1 percent. </div>
<div></div>
<div>Despite the blatant lack of empirical support and Dean Baker’s decisive take down, <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/business/archive/2011/11/the-great-work-divide/248931/">Megan</a><a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/business/archive/2011/11/the-great-work-divide/248931/"> </a><a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/business/archive/2011/11/the-great-work-divide/248931/">McArdle</a> dutifully picked up on the trope. And, of course, the <a href="http://www.bostonglobe.com/business/2011/12/18/two-communities-are-worlds-apart/6RZboLZCxK7VWrm6Y7xURO/story.html"><i>Boston</i></a><a href="http://www.bostonglobe.com/business/2011/12/18/two-communities-are-worlds-apart/6RZboLZCxK7VWrm6Y7xURO/story.html"><i> </i></a><a href="http://www.bostonglobe.com/business/2011/12/18/two-communities-are-worlds-apart/6RZboLZCxK7VWrm6Y7xURO/story.html"><i>Globe</i></a> piece highlights the education gap between the residents of Springfield and Sherborn and implies the gap between two communities is the result of the “one percent phenomenon.” However, these arguments &#8211; and, more often, implications &#8211; are clearly undercut by the data. </div>
<div></div>
<div>The mega rich Occupy Wall Street opposes do not live in “neighborhoods,” not even well-to-do neighborhoods like Sherborn. The top 1% &#8211; and probably more accurately the top .1% &#8211; live in gated mansions with private security. As Joseph Stiglitz and Matt Taibbi have pointed out, the mega rich have reached a level of wealth that completely insulates them from society. So, don’t be fooled: Occupy Wall Street is not opposed to the affluent. Residents of Sherborn and similar affluent communities &#8211; like all citizens who still have a stake in our country’s well being &#8211; are part of the 99%. </div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/12/guest-post-who-are-the-1.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Income Mobility</title>
		<link>./../../2011/11/income-mobility.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/11/income-mobility.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2011 13:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[income equality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income growth]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Income redistribution]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/11/income-mobility.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Lifted from comments from Daniel Becker&#8217;s post here, reader PJR provides links to two good sources: Another data-driven study indicates income mobility is down at the same time that inequality is up, saying &#8220;Overall, the evidence indicates that over the 1969-to-2006 time span, family income mobility across the distribution decreased, families’ later-year incomes increasingly depended [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Lifted from comments from Daniel Becker&#8217;s post <a target="_blank" href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2011/11/its-not-how-rich-we-are-its-how-equal.html">here</a>, reader PJR provides links to two good sources:</p>
<blockquote><p>Another <a href="http://www.bostonfed.org/economic/wp/wp2011/wp1110.pdf">data-driven study</a> indicates income mobility is down at the same time that inequality is up, saying &#8220;Overall, the evidence indicates that over the 1969-to-2006 time span, family income mobility across the distribution decreased, families’ later-year incomes increasingly depended on their starting place, and the distribution of families’ lifetime incomes became less equal.&#8221;  Check out the charts/data in the back (I wish data went further back in time, but this is pretty good). Some of the charts, and good commentary, is [also available] at  <a href="http://jaredbernsteinblog.com/income-mobility-a-warning/">Jared Bernstein&#8217;s place</a> [edited for functionality, readability]</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/11/income-mobility.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Define Rich, Part III. What the tax tables of yore say.</title>
		<link>./../../2011/09/define-rich-part-iii-what-the-tax-tables-of-yore-say.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/09/define-rich-part-iii-what-the-tax-tables-of-yore-say.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2011 18:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[define rich]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income equality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income inequality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Income redistribution]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rich]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tax]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax burden]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax code]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax cuts]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/09/define-rich-part-iii-what-the-tax-tables-of-yore-say.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[ By Daniel Becker Randolph Duke: Money isn&#8217;t everything, Mortimer. Mortimer Duke: Oh, grow up. Randolph Duke: Mother always said you were greedy. Mortimer Duke: She meant it as a compliment. Trading Places 1983 A while ago (an understatement) I posted on the question of what is rich. The first dealt with what issues to consider [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p> By Daniel Becker
<div></div>
<div>Randolph Duke: <em>Money isn&#8217;t everything, Mortimer.</em> </div>
<div>Mortimer Duke: <em>Oh, grow up.</em> </div>
<div>Randolph Duke: <em>Mother always said you were greedy.</em> </div>
<div>Mortimer Duke: <em>She meant it as a compliment.</em></div>
<div><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0086465/">Trading Places</a> 1983 </div>
<div></div>
<div>A while ago (an understatement) I posted on the question of what is rich. The <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2009/04/define-rich.html">first dealt</a> with what issues to consider in defining rich. The <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2009/05/define-rich-part-ii-rat-race-and.html">second</a> was looking at the issue of getting rich if that is even what one wants to do. The “rat race”. I don&#8217;t believe most people really want to be rich. I believe most people when thinking about being rich are thinking about what it would take to remove the fears of events that would make one&#8217;s life either very difficult in a world that requires money to remove risk or drastically different from what one&#8217;s life was. I&#8217;m thinking things like losing a job, debilitating injury or illness possibly resulting in physical disability or Louis Winthorpe III. </div>
<div></div>
<div>This all ties into “The American Dream”. The “Dream” is not just an ideology of governance and social philosophy. It is also a life style and thus requires a specific level of income. I have posted on this issue also and noted just how high in income we have driven this “Dream” such that two people with bachelor’s degrees just starting life together may not be able to have it. </div>
<div></div>
<div>Now that we have entered a period where taxes are on everyone&#8217;s minds such that there is serious consensus to raising taxes, maybe we need to see what we had in the past to know what we need now. I am sure most readers are aware of Mike&#8217;s work defining what rates appear to effect economic growth the best. If I recall correctly the number for the top 1% was around 65%. I have also suggested that there is a range as to how large a share of the income the top 1% should have. That number for the top 1% is not to be above 15% and not to much below 10%. </div>
<div></div>
<div>I should also <a href="http://angrybear.blogspot.com/2008/01/opus-1-discussion-on-taxation.html">mention my postings</a> on <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2008/01/opus-1-second-movement-on-taxation.html">taxation’s purpose</a>. Specifically I looked at taxing from the perspective of the legal profession as oppose to the economic profession. The conclusion was that there was one main reason for taxing. It is to fulfill the directive of our constitution: equality of power. It is to assure the concept of one voice one vote. If there was ever a time in our history to raise taxes in order to assure this directive it is now in the age of the Citizens United ruling. President FDR referred to the issue and those with the one voice multiple votes do to their monied power as “economic royalty”. I like that phrase and I wonder why it is not used as are retort to those who use “class warfare” as a guilt trip.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Let&#8217;s get started.</div>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />I have constructed 4 sets of data using the tax rates of 1936/37, 1945/46, 1965/67 and 2010. I chose 1936 because it is a tax rate increase after the economy had turned north based on Mikes posting. I chose 1945/46 because it is another adjustment that happens right after after WWII. I chose 1965/67 because it is the decrease often spoken of fondly. Of course 2010 is because that is where we are at. 
<div></div>
<div>This posting would be hugely long if I post on all 4 periods at once, so I have broken it up. Let me first and I think most importantly note that we people today have no idea just how much we were willing to tax ourselves to have the society that we now refer to as “the good old days”. Not only did we have the tax tables of 1936, that table eventually had a 10% surcharge added to pay for the war. Yes, another reason to consider the generation that fought the 1<sup>st</sup> and 2<sup>nd</sup> world wars the greatest generation. There was a 7% surcharge for the Vietnam war, though that number became less as time passed. Still, we knew that if we wanted to do exceptional things, we had to tax ourselves exceptionally. Also, the early taxation made no distinction for single or married, never mind filing joint or separate. Everyone paid the same rate. Most interestingly, with the current table, the people who comparatively get screwed are those who are married and file separately. All the rates kick in at a lower income than even those who are single. The other thing we don&#8217;t seem to understand is that all the tax rhetoric we have been hearing since Reagan <a href="http://taxhistory.tax.org/www/website.nsf/Web/THM1901?OpenDocument">we&#8217;ve heard before virtually to the word.</a></div>
<div></div>
<div>Andrew Mellon, Treasury Secretary 1921 to 1932 :</div>
<div></div>
<blockquote><div>Generally speaking, Mellon argued that tax burdens were too high. Steep rates, he insisted, served only to stifle incentive and foster tax evasion. “Any man of energy and initiative in this country can get what he wants out of life,” he wrote. <em>“But when initiative is crippled by legislation or by a tax system which denies him the right to receive a reasonable share of his earnings, then he will no longer exert himself and the country will be deprived of the energy on which its continued greatness depends.”</em></div>
<div></div>
<div>Worse yet, Mellon argued, high rates didn’t even raise money. By encouraging both legal tax avoidance and illegal tax evasion, they eroded the tax base and reduced overall revenue. <em>Lower rates, he said, would actually raise money by spurring economic growth and reducing the incentive for tax avoidance. “It seems difficult for some to understand,” he complained, “that high rates of taxation do not necessarily mean large revenue to the government, and that more revenue may actually be obtained by lower rates.”</em> In particular, Mellon insisted that high rates distorted investment decisions, boosting the popularity of tax-free state and local government bonds. Indeed, Mellon made these tax-free bonds a regular target of his reform attempts, but Congress resisted his plans to eliminate them.</div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div>Atlas Shrugged wasn&#8217;t even written then!  What we don&#8217;t hear much of are the original concerns and reasoning for progressive taxation. Teddy Roosevelt:</div>
<div></div>
<blockquote><div>1906&#8230;<strong>We should discriminate in the sharpest way between fortunes well-won and fortunes ill-won; between those gained as an incident to performing great services to the community as a whole, and those gained in evil fashion by keeping just within the limits of mere law-honesty.</strong></div>
<div></div>
<div>1907 regarding an income tax:&#8230;while in addition it is a difficult tax to administer in its practical working, and great care would have to be exercised to see that it was not evaded by the very men whom it was most desirable to have taxed, for if so evaded it would, of course, be worse than no tax at all; <strong>as the least desirable of all taxes is the tax which bears heavily upon the honest as compared with the dishonest man. </strong></div>
<div></div>
<div><strong>No advantage comes either to the country as a whole or to the individuals inheriting the money by permitting the transmission in their entirety of the enormous fortunes which would be affected by such a tax; and as an incident to its function of revenue raising, such a tax would help to preserve a measurable equality of opportunity for the people of the generations growing to manhood.</strong> We have not the slightest sympathy with that socialistic idea which would try to put laziness, thriftlessness and inefficiency on a par with industry, thrift and efficiency; which would strive to break up not merely private property, but what is far more important, the home, the chief prop upon which our whole civilization stands. Such a theory, if ever adopted, would mean the ruin of the entire country&#8211;a ruin  which would bear heaviest upon the weakest, upon those least able to shift for themselves.</div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>At this moment, I want to mention corporate taxes. There are lessons to be learned from it&#8217;s history. I think it is a factor in understand more completely the issue Mike is focusing on: taxation and GDP growth. <a href="http://www.taxpolicycenter.org/taxfacts/displayafact.cfm?Docid=203">Wrap your minds around the fact</a> that from 1936 to 1943 there were 6 years that corporate tax collections were greater than personal income tax collections. 1943 was the best year for this as personal income tax collections were 68.1% of the corporate tax collections. Just one year later it flips to corporate tax collections being 75.3% of personal income tax collections. In 1944 $34,543 million in total for the two taxes was collected vs 1943 $16,062 million in total.  <a href="http://www.taxpolicycenter.org/taxfacts/displayafact.cfm?Docid=204">In fact, personal income taxes</a> remain in the mid to high 40 percent of total revenue collections from 1944 to present. The corporate share of total revenue peaks in 1943 at 39.8% and declines to hover around the 10% level with a few ventures into the single digits. Most notably 1983 the corporate share was 6.2% and 2009 it was 6.6%. </div>
<div>First up is our current tax table. I used the “married filling jointly” as that would be consistent with the other tables. One big rule of this series of postings: DO NOT concern yourself or me about the deductions that exist. They do not matter for this presentation and for all intent and purposes we can consider the income to have already gone through the deduction calculator and is now ready to have the tax table applied. This is because, these tables only apply to adjusted gross income.</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-lX4293efG5Y/Tl_Efh3ab1I/AAAAAAAAARc/W7X0lIr0Ki0/s1600/2010+Tax+table+Define+Rich+3.JPG" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="211" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-lX4293efG5Y/Tl_Efh3ab1I/AAAAAAAAARc/W7X0lIr0Ki0/s320/2010+Tax+table+Define+Rich+3.JPG" width="320" xaa="true"></a></div>
<div></div>
<div>You will notice that the table is calculated out to $,1,000,000 of income. I did this in order to keep all the tables going to the same income level. The 1936 table actually has rates for incomes up to $8 million. That is $8 million in 1936. (Using my <a href="http://www.measuringworth.com/calculators/compare/">favorite money converter</a> that would be $301,000,000 in unskilled labor or $573,000,000 in GDP/capita.) Going to $1,000,000 in income also allows one to see what happens at the top when the rate no longer rises. </div>
<div></div>
<div>A very important concept to understand is that not every dollar is taxed at the single percentage rate as you go up the income ladder. Thus, there are two columns in my charts. The “Marginal Tax” is the additional money paid at the top of the bracket for the corresponding rate. The “Total tax” is the actual money paid up to that level. It is the “effective rate”. In simple terms, if you are at the 35% level, you  </div>
<div>are not paying 35% on all that you earn. Instead you are paying the amount based on your income being divided up into the number of brackets that exist. For 2010, there are 6 brackets, thus you have six different incomes so to speak. </div>
<div></div>
<div>This is what it looks like as a graph.</div>
<div></div>
<div><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-OCqtKMLzE3A/Tl_Ejt_NFtI/AAAAAAAAARg/bwU8IixjaGc/s1600/2010+Tax+rate+graph+Define+Rich+3.JPG" imageanchor="1"><img border="0" height="240" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-OCqtKMLzE3A/Tl_Ejt_NFtI/AAAAAAAAARg/bwU8IixjaGc/s320/2010+Tax+rate+graph+Define+Rich+3.JPG" width="320" xaa="true"></a></div>
<div></div>
<div>When the rate maxed out, I divided the range to $1 million into even parts so that the tax paid for each additional income level is the same. For the 1945/46 and 1965/67 data sets I converted the net income to 2010 dollars. I used the “unskilled labor” and GDP/cap as those are the 2 factors suggested as being the best for knowing what income equivalents are over time. The 1936 data set is converted to 1967 dollar because the numbers just get crazy. For example, a net income of $3840 is $145,000 in unskilled labor and $275,000 in GDP/cap. Though it is only $60,400 via the CPI. Which doesn&#8217;t say much for today&#8217;s median family income. It also gives us a clue as to just how much money is considered “rich”.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Next posting, I will start presenting the historical data sets. I&#8217;m still thinking about the best way to do it as what is important is the comparison among the data sets.  Maybe post just the data charts and later the graphs or maybe one data set and it&#8217;s graphs at a time.  </div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/09/define-rich-part-iii-what-the-tax-tables-of-yore-say.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Monetary policy. I&#8217;m sorry, it&#8217;s just not doing it for me.</title>
		<link>./../../2011/05/monetary-policy-im-sorry-its-just-not-doing-it-for-me.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/05/monetary-policy-im-sorry-its-just-not-doing-it-for-me.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2011 00:09:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[income equality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income inequality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Income redistribution]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[monetary policy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wealth creation]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/05/monetary-policy-im-sorry-its-just-not-doing-it-for-me.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[By Daniel Becker Stock market is up, Profits are up and banks are safe. So what? Unemployment is somewhere between going down and I can&#8217;t get no satisfaction. Housing values are still falling.  A new nationwide survey from real estate Web site Zillow.com says the value of U.S. homes fell 3% from January 1 to [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>By Daniel Becker</div>
<div></div>
<div>Stock market is up, Profits are up and banks are safe. So what? Unemployment is somewhere between going down and I can&#8217;t get no satisfaction. Housing values <a href="http://www.cnn.com/2011/US/05/14/falling.home.prices/">are still falling</a>.  </div>
<div></div>
<blockquote><p>A new nationwide survey from real estate Web site Zillow.com says the value of U.S. homes fell 3% from January 1 to March 30 &#8212; the steepest quarterly decline since 2008.</p></blockquote>
<div> </div>
<div>I know, I&#8217;m suppose to care. Bigger picture and all. But frankly, when I read comments such as that by <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2011/05/euro-area-is-miserable.html#comments">Mark Sadowski&#8217;s</a>: </div>
<div> </div>
<blockquote><p>Since Bernanke&#8217;s Jackson Hole speech the steep rise in stock prices has increased household wealth by some $5 trillion. The rise in inflation expectations has helped to ease the household debt deflation problem. Consumption has been the bright story in the BEA numbers last two quarters,&#8230;</p></blockquote>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>I just get all “A vineyard? Really?” Now I know Rebecca&#8217;s post is about looking for some indication that things are better though tipsy and Mark is responding that with: No, things are rather solid in the “we&#8217;re moving forward” category. </div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>I&#8217;m going to be bold here and state right out that I&#8217;m speaking for the middle-class. (Those of this class can correct me if I&#8217;m wrong.) Five trillion dollar in new stock market wealth is not reaching us. I&#8217;m happy for you all that are now more wealthy, but really, you&#8217;re only a small percentage of the population and thus your success is not representative of how well We the People in total are doing.</div>
<p><a name="more"></a>
<div>Before I go further, let us do a little simple math (for you stat manipulators, the key word: simple. Add more complication as you wish in comments.) I am allowed to do this, keep it simple because I&#8217;m not an economist. Or am I? </div>
<div></div>
<div>Let&#8217;s say <a href="http://www.levyinstitute.org/pubs/wp_589.pdf">that 81.2% of all stock</a> is owned by the top 10% of wealth gatherers. (table 9). Let&#8217;s say there was 100 shares at $1 each for a total value in stock on 8/31/10 of $100. That $100 became $129.80 by 5/2/11.(S&#038;P closing numbers)  But, I&#8217;m going to round off all of this to keep it really simple. 100 shares. 80 shares owned by 10 people. 20 shares owned by 90 people. Fast forward 9 months and now the $100 is $120. Still 100 shares. (We&#8217;re excluding splits, initial offerings and anything else that would increase the number of shares, simple.) </div>
<div></div>
<div>So, 10 people now have a total worth of $96. The 90 people are splitting up $24. Both saw a 20% rise. Hooray! But here&#8217;s the issue, an additional $1.60 will do a lot more than an additional $0.04. The issue is coin in the pocket. For the middle-class, it&#8217;s just not happening.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Let&#8217;s add a some more fun facts to this Yahoo party.  <a href="http://www.levyinstitute.org/pubs/wp_589.pdf"> I used:</a>  <strong>Recent Trends in Household Wealth in the United States: Rising Debt and the Middle-Class Squeeze—an Update to 2007</strong> by Edward N. Wolff, Levy Economics Institute of Bard College, March 2010</div>
<div> 
<div>As of 2007, 38% of all households have stock via pensions and of that group it represents 31.4 % of all stock. (Table 14b, 14c) Unfortunately, the middle 3 quintiles 65.1% of their assets are their house, 12.9% is pension, 3.6% is stock held in some form. Darn few of the middle-class have any stock at all and what they have is tied up. </div>
<div></div>
<div>So again, that 29.8% rise&#8230; ain&#8217;t feeling it. I ain&#8217;t feeling it in customers in my shop. I ain&#8217;t feeling it in volume of sales in my shop. I ain&#8217;t feeling it in dollar&#8217;s per sale in my shop. Guess what I ain&#8217;t gonna do? I ain&#8217;t gonna hire anyone. </div>
<div></div>
<div>Let me leave you with this. Let&#8217;s say we manage to move 5 more people into the group that has 80% of the stock for a total of 15 people. They each have $5.333.  (Finance likes to measure as if they are using micrometers.) The remaining 85 have $0.235. The 85 have 5.9% more wealth to start. 9 months later, the 15 people have $6.40 each. They have $1.067 more. The 85 have $0.282. </div>
<div></div>
<div>Certainly $0.047 more to those in the 85 group is not going to make them go out and buy flowers. However, 5 more people have more than a buck to spend and in my shop that buys one carnation that will last 2 to 3 weeks.  As I noted before, buying that flower for one&#8217;s self has <a href="http://generallythinking.com/positivepsychology/flowers-happiness-the-emotional-impact-of-plants-external/">major positive benefits</a> for one&#8217;s personality. I have a better shot at selling that 1 carnation when there are 15 people that could purchase it than when there are 10. That mean&#8217;s there is a better chance that there will be one more happy person and thus push the consumer confidence index up. <br />That my middle-class friends, is the power of policy designed to promote income and wealth equality vs just wealth increases.  I want me some of that there policy.  </div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>A vineyard. Really?</div>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/05/monetary-policy-im-sorry-its-just-not-doing-it-for-me.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Joseph Stiglitz: Of the 1% by the 1% for the 1%</title>
		<link>./../../2011/04/joseph-stiglitz-of-the-1-by-the-1-for-the-1.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/04/joseph-stiglitz-of-the-1-by-the-1-for-the-1.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2011 13:36:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Budget]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bush tax cuts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economic growth]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[environment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income equality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Joseph Stiglitz]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/04/joseph-stiglitz-of-the-1-by-the-1-for-the-1.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Daniel Becker This is an interview of Joseph Stiglitz on Democracy Now regarding his article in the current Vanity Fair.  He discuss the issue of income inequality, taxes, etc and how it has set us up to be less of a land of oportunity than what old Europe was. A few quotes: The question [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Daniel Becker</p>
<p>This is an interview of Joseph Stiglitz on Democracy Now regarding his article in the current Vanity Fair.  He discuss the issue of income inequality, taxes, etc and how it has set us up to be less of a land of oportunity than what old Europe was.<br /><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>A few quotes: <br />
<blockquote>The question was, if people were getting rewards for contributing to our society, a theory that was in the 19th century called &#8220;marginal-productivity theory,&#8221; then you could say, &#8220;OK, those who contribute more should get more.&#8221; But what we saw in that crisis was that these titans of the financial industry got mega-bonuses while their companies were making mega-losses.</p>
<p>And with this one percent getting so much, there’s only one place really to get that extra revenue. The good news is it’s relatively easy. You have 25 percent—almost 25 percent of the income in the upper one percent, you raise their taxes by a few percentage points, and you get an awful lot of money.</p>
<p>This raises a very important point that I raise in my article, which is that much of the wealth of this one percent comes not from hard work, not from innovation, but from good investments in Washington, investing in political capital.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/04/joseph-stiglitz-of-the-1-by-the-1-for-the-1.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Let the tax cuts go and you actually stick it to the top for real.</title>
		<link>./../../2010/12/let-the-tax-cuts-go-and-you-actually-stick-it-to-the-top-for-real.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/12/let-the-tax-cuts-go-and-you-actually-stick-it-to-the-top-for-real.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2010 05:09:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[income equality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obama economic policy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax cuts]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/12/let-the-tax-cuts-go-and-you-actually-stick-it-to-the-top-for-real.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[By: Daniel Becker (DOLB) On Countdown (12/9/10), Keith had on Thomas Buffenbarger, president of the International Machinist Union. It was a chance for an “I told you so moment”in that Mr. Buffenbarger noted while campaigning for Secretary Clinton that President Obama would not be a fighter. Go watch the episode. I made my position on [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By: Daniel Becker (DOLB)</p>
<p>On Countdown (12/9/10), Keith had on Thomas Buffenbarger, president of the International Machinist Union. It was a chance for an “I told you so moment”in that Mr. Buffenbarger noted while campaigning for Secretary Clinton that President Obama would not be a fighter. Go watch <a href="http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/3036677/ns/msnbc_tv-countdown_with_keith_olbermann/#40596879">the episode</a>.</p>
<p>I made<a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2010/11/all-you-need-to-know-to-understand.html"> my position on of Obama</a> clear after the 60 Minutes interview. Mr. Buffenbarger&#8217;s comments only reinforces my position as to understanding President Obama as does Obama&#8217;s latest “negotiation”. Surprisingly, only 4 comments were made. Too bad, the nation would have been more prepared for this latest act in &#8220;Obama the Negotiator. Not!&#8221;</p>
<p>But, that is not what got me regarding Mr. Buffenbarger&#8217;s interview. No. It was that he confirmed something I have been thinking since Obama stated his compromise policy after this current midterm elections. </p>
<blockquote><p>&#8230;when Bush put the tax cut&#8217;s in place, very few of the members I&#8217;m privileged to represent noticed any difference in their pay check. And so, if the tax cuts were to go away, and we go back to the tax rates of then, our members would see very little change in their tax rates again.</p></blockquote>
<p><a name="more"></a>
<div>Exactly. Has not the argument been that the cuts did little for the middle class? Then what is the problem with letting them go? I know for me it meant very little difference. Though, I realize having “meaning” is different for all so, here is a <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/packages/khtml/2005/06/05/national/20050605_HYPER_GRAPHIC.html?scp=2&#038;sq=%22class+matters%22&#038;st=m">very nice chart</a> I saved from 2005 looking at the tax cuts and what they meant for the various income groups.</div>
<div></div>
<div>First, let me say that when I initially viewed this chart years ago, I thought: How appropriate. Those who most likely think the republican party was watching out for them via tax cuts because they were in that top part of the food chain, were actually getting screwed too. Yeah, the one who you believes loves you is taking you for a ride. Those in the $100K to $300K range of income by 2015 were projected to pay a higher percentage of the share of national income taxes than they had before the cuts. And, even those above the $300k to the $1.5m range were getting much less of a break than their income relatives above them. Poetic justice? Just goes to show, that even those with significant incomes have no real conception of how small theirs is compared to the incomes of the upper echelons of this nation. But hey, you keep believing you&#8217;re just like them. It&#8217;s what they want. </div>
<p>More to the point of this post. Look at the “Average yearly tax savings” line for those from the lowest to the $383K level. I realize everyone&#8217;s situation is unique, but really, the range of the cost of the loss of the tax savings is virtually zero to 2.5% if your at $160K or 1% for those at $383k. As a share of supporting this nation, you/we have been screwed. I ask you all. The bottom 99%. Wouldn&#8217;t you like to really stick it to the economic royalty in this nation? Is 1% to 2.5% to much to give to finally get reality into the income tax?</p>
<p>You there in the 95 to 99% category. Your 2001 share of income was 15%.   Your projected share of the taxes in 2015 is 18.5% A ratio of 0.81. For your senior income family members the ratio in 2015 is 0.74. Still feeling loved? </p>
<p>Look at it this way. Based on this 2005 chart. The bottom 99% paid 75.3% of all income taxes before the tax cuts. Our projected share for 2015, the very tax cuts Obama et al have just negotiated to keep is 77.1%. </p>
<p>Who loves you now, baby?</p>
<p>Mr. Buffenbarger ended noting that his members understand that paying taxes is a privilege and is an act of support of our country. It is paying our way. So what do you say. Let&#8217;s show those at the very top just how unpatriotic they are. Let the tax cuts go and stand proud because honest American justice has prevailed.   You just screwed the biggest screwer of them all&#8230;The American Economic Royalty.</p>
<p>That is what the real Tea Party was about.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/12/let-the-tax-cuts-go-and-you-actually-stick-it-to-the-top-for-real.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Define rich!!!!!!!!</title>
		<link>./../../2009/04/define-rich.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/04/define-rich.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 26 Apr 2009 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[define rich]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income equality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Income tax]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rich]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/04/define-rich.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[(I&#8217;m broadening the discussion now.)by Divorced one like Bush Define rich. Define rich! Define rich? That&#8217;s the come back every time the issue of raising the income tax on the rich come up. What is unsaid is: Go ahead. Define rich. I dare ya! (Triple dog dare at that.) Fine. I&#8217;ll accept the challenge. But, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>(I&#8217;m broadening the discussion now.)<br />by Divorced one like Bush</p>
<p>Define rich.  Define rich!  Define rich? </p>
<p>That&#8217;s the come back every time the issue of raising the income tax on the rich come up.  What is unsaid is: Go ahead. Define rich.  I dare ya!  (Triple dog dare at that.)</p>
<p>Fine.  I&#8217;ll accept the challenge.  But, first understand that I accept the challenge because having a definition of “rich” is needed if we are going to fix the money from money economy.  We have to ask: When is enough, enough?  We have to take the responsibility of having determined what enough is, if we are going to return to the ideal of our democracy.  The ideal of equality of power.  This ideal was discussed in my postings (3 of them) <a href="http://angrybear.blogspot.com/2008/02/opus-finale-discussion-on-taxation.html">on taxation</a>.   </p>
<p>I think this nation used to know when enough was enough.  We used to know what rich was.  It was a life; as in “pick a life, not a job”.  It was an ability made capable by the amount of money managed (not flowing) through one&#8217;s hands.  That it was a life meant we did not fall for the rhetorical trick of: Define rich! I dare ya.  The trick is that the question is asked in reference to defining levels of income at which a specified percentage of taxation will take place.  It is the infamous black and white trap when we all know we live in a life that is the spectrum of color.  Cross this line you pay, don&#8217;t cross it, then you don&#8217;t pay.  As with all dares, there is a threat.  The threat for the rhetorical “define rich” dare is that the moment a number is chosen, the one doing the daring will retort with a life example of the chosen number that under the life circumstances retort might not be considered rich.</p>
<p>Back when we knew what rich was, we had an income tax based on a spectrum of rich.  In fact, something I quoted in my tax series confirms that we knew what &#8220;rich&#8221; was:<br />
<blockquote>There was another agenda at play as well in the early years of the federal income tax: the desire to use progressive taxation as a way to “ stave off more radical calls for industrial democracy.”  This explains why even some high-income Republican groups supported the Sixteenth Amendment. Andrew Mellon, Secretary of the Treasury in the 1920s and one of the wealthiest Americans, “ believed that keeping tax schedules graduated (albeit flatter) would mitigate radical demands for restructuring the capitalist system.” </p></blockquote>
<p>Even the rich knew what rich was.  </p>
<p>Let me say, for me wealth is not the rich I&#8217;m talking about.  Wealth is another issue that should not be brought into the discussion of &#8220;rich&#8221; related to an income tax.  It get&#8217;s thrown in as another rhetorical trick, the trick being that one will think about a dollar amount of wealth and then think how much money it took to get that wealth ala income.  But, wealth is accounted under the asset category, not income.  </p>
<p>Professor Mankiw posted in 2006 about a study that defined a level of rich world wide based on wealth <a href="http://gregmankiw.blogspot.com/2006/12/define-rich.html">which I think has a presentation ripe for rhetorical trap making. He quotes</a>:<br />
<blockquote>
<blockquote>The research finds that assets of $2,200 per adult placed a household in the top half of the world wealth distribution in the year 2000. To be among the richest 10% of adults in the world required $61,000 in assets, and more than $500,000 was needed to belong to the richest 1%, a group which — with 37 million members worldwide — is far from an exclusive club.</p></blockquote>
<p>So, from a global perspective, if you have net worth of more than $61,000, you are rich.</p></blockquote>
<p>Really?  Thirty 37 million members world wide on a planet of 6 billion is not exclusive?  $61,000 of assets should make us all feel rich?  The message (and I am not interpreting that Profressor Mankiw&#8217;s posting suggests any qualification) is that we should all feel equally wealthy and thus rich.  Can you see how such a presentation could be used as a rhetorical trap in determining &#8220;rich&#8221;.  So, let&#8217;s not go there.  “There” is for the discussion of the estate tax.  Besides, once the income has been turned into an asset, it&#8217;s kind of too late to worry about taxing the income. No? </p>
<p>Also, we are talking the United States of America.  Not Zimbabwe.  (See the above issue.)  I know there are children starving in Africa.  We have the same here, it&#8217;s just that the income needed here to not have a child starving  is higher.  Purchasing power parity and all that.  Though, if we would be adult about the issue of “rich” and define when enough is enough, we would be able to do more for such people as there would be more left for them.</p>
<p>We have lost our definition of rich and I believe it was  done intentionally.  If you are rich, then what better camouflage is there than to undefine “rich”?  And, what better way to undefine “rich” than to have an argument accepted that “rich” can not really be defined?  AND, once you can&#8217;t define rich, well then hey, how can you single out anyone number as a line for having to pay a higher percentage of tax on their income? Thus, we should all pay the same percentage and thus obtain our constitutional nirvana of all man is created equal.  Throw in a little pity play as in the “rich are paying most of the taxes”, (funny how those complaining about how much the rich pay in taxes seem to know what “rich” is) present your candidates as the every-man or every-woman, salt of the earth, blab, blab, blab to reinforce the perception that this is all about constitutional equality and  BINGO, you get to convert life from an economy that worked for society to a society that works for an economy.  And <a href="http://angrybear.blogspot.com/2008/02/opus-finale-discussion-on-taxation.html">as presented</a>, once you get beyond “enough”, all you have is to have more:<br />
<blockquote>Wealth confers power beyond its consumption value. This power is economic, social, and political. The economic power of the rich derives primarily from their ability to use their wealth to invest in enterprises that employ thousands of people and can dominate large sectors of the economy. </p></blockquote>
<p>Yes, they are talking wealth.  However, as I noted, this is after the rich bought their stuff to make them happy.  Now they are just accumulating power.</p>
<p>We need to define “rich”.  We need to be adult about this and take the responsibility for understanding the interplay of society and an economy within our form of democratic governance.  Personally, I think we will find that defining rich for our purposes is rather easy once we stop answering the rhetorical dare of: Define rich?</p>
<p>For this discussion “rich” is a life classification.  The classification is consumption determined, the amount of which is a function of energy expended (ie: physical labor/intellectual labor), work performed (ie: blue collar/white collar) along with energy conserved (freedom), work diverted (power).  This aspect of life is not about what the individual finds satisfying.  That is another rhetorical trap.  We all know of those who are fine with just hitch hiking through the galaxy and would consider them self rich for the memories.  The life aspect needed for determining “rich” for the purpose of taxing is the aspect determined by the structure of the society one lives in.  For us, that structure is idealized in the phrase: The American Dream.   That phrase is the socially understood goal and that phrase is underscored by how much money your hands manage.  </p>
<p>Classification as in “class warfare”.  Consumption as in “autonomous consumption”.  American Dream as in more than autonomous consumption.  All three a function of the amount of money managed by one&#8217;s hands.</p>
<p>To be continued. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/04/define-rich.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
