<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Jeff Shesol &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>John Roberts and Elena Kagan: Mirror Images of Each Other</title>
		<link>./../../2012/06/john-roberts-and-elena-kagan-mirror-images-of-each-other.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/06/john-roberts-and-elena-kagan-mirror-images-of-each-other.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2012 14:16:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[ACA litigation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Elena Kagan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jeff Shesol]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Roberts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ken Houghton]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linda Greenhouse]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obamacare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/06/john-roberts-and-elena-kagan-mirror-images-of-each-other.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The second biggest surprise of the day, after the survival of the Affordable Care Act, is that we’ve never really gotten over our collective crush on John Roberts. How else to explain today’s outpouring of praise, not merely for the decision but for the man himself, for his statesmanship and judicial modesty? All these years, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>The second biggest surprise of the day, after the survival of the Affordable Care Act, is that we’ve never really gotten over our collective crush on John Roberts. How else to explain today’s outpouring of praise, not merely for the decision but for the man himself, for his statesmanship and judicial modesty? All these years, it now appears, we’ve held it in our hearts; we’ve written it in our diaries, remembering every one of those sweet nothings he once whispered about “common ground” and “humility.” No, we never really gave up on Roberts. Not during that long judicial bender he took with the boys—Nino, Clarence, Tony, and Sam; not during the <em>Citizens United</em> argument, when he called the government “big brother”; not when he swept away a century’s worth of campaign finance regulations. So complete is our swoon, in the afterglow of the ACA ruling, that <a href="http://www.thedailybeast.com/articles/2012/06/28/obamacare-supreme-court-ruling-john-roberts-changes-his-legacy.html" target="_blank">Bob Shrum has written</a> that if Roberts had been Chief Justice in 2000, <em>Bush v. Gore</em> might have gone the other way.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212; <a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/jurisprudence/2012/06/john_roberts_is_hardly_the_hero_and_judicial_statesman_people_make_him_out_to_be_.html#comments">John Roberts Is No Hero: Why ourcrush on the chief justice is silly—and undeserved</a>, Jeff Shesol, Slate, Jun. 28
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>To which I posted the following comment:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I write on legal and political issue issues for a left-of-center blog and have indicated there that I detest and really fear John Roberts because of his deeply diabolical nature and his checklist of ‘80s-era Federalist Society things-to-do.   Linda Greenhouse has written several columns, two or three of them within the last few months, highlighting those two quintessential John Roberts traits.  But Greenhouse, and I, predicted that Roberts would save the ACA because the case is so high-profile and the grounds for striking down the statute so utterly artificial that it would place more public scrutiny on the types of things he and his cadre normally get away with with virtually no public awareness.  I don’t think he did what he did out of a sense of statesmanship, nor in order to gut the Commerce Clause; I think the Commerce Clause ruling will have almost no practical effect, and he could have done the same thing with it simply by joining the other four conservatives in a 5-4 ruling striking down the ACA. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I think he’s, in a way, the mirror image of Elena Kagan, who in high-profile cases usually votes liberal but who, best as I can tell, almost never goes out on a limb for the “nobody” “cert” petitioner and actually fights to get a “cert grant,” as Sotomayor does, and who I’d bet doesn’t even vote very often to hear such cases.  Her priorities seem to be her own public image and being buddies with the “in” crowd on the Court, whereas Roberts’ priority is making as many dramatic changes to the law as he can, but doing so as much under the public’s radar as possible.  (I also think Kagan is a bit naïve on some issues because of her unfamiliarity with them—see, e.g.: federal habeas review of state-court convictions—and fairly easily snowed.)
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>So I agree with Ken Houghton in his post below that John Roberts is not the friend of progressives.  I disagree with Ken, though, that Roberts has set up some trap through which he will later orchestrate the striking down of the ACA as a violation of equal protection because of the way in which the Medicaid expansion is administered (if I understand Ken correctly) is nil.  Roberts ended his opinion with a statement saying that the proper manner in which to determine the ultimate fate of the ACA is through the political process, not the judicial process—and I think he means it.  There are two parts of Roberts’ opinion—the part concerning Congress’s regulatory powers under the Commerce Clause and the part concerning Congress’s power to enact federal-state partnership legislation <i>a la </i>Medicaid—that raise serious concerns about the impact on <i>other</i>legislation.  I wrote separate posts yesterday about each of these, and I’ll be writing another one on Medicaid issue later today. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>But any lawsuits concerning some aspect of how the law is working in practice, once it gets underway, would result in the possible tweaking of an HHS regulation or in the manner in which a particular state is implementing the Act, but I just don’t foresee a successful attack on the constitutionality of some provision in the Act itself. 
</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/06/john-roberts-and-elena-kagan-mirror-images-of-each-other.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
