<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Inequality &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 12:45:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Real wages decline; literally no one notices</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/real-wages-decline-literally-no-one-notices.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/real-wages-decline-literally-no-one-notices.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 23:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Inequality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wages]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/real-wages-decline-literally-no-one-notices.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Cross-posted from Middle Class Political Economist. Your read it here first: Real wages fell 0.2% in 2012, down from $295.49 (1982-84 dollars) to $294.83 per week, according to the 2013 Economic Report of the President. Thus, a 1.9% increase in nominal wages was  more than wiped out by inflation, marking the 40th consecutive year that [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Cross-posted from <a href="http://www.middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/">Middle Class Political Economist</a>.</p>
<p>Your read it here first: Real wages fell 0.2% in 2012, down from $295.49 (1982-84 dollars) to $294.83 per week, according to the 2013 <a href="http://www.whitehouse.gov/sites/default/files/docs/erp2013/ERP2013_Appendix_B.pdf"><i>Economic Report of the President</i></a>. Thus, a 1.9% increase in nominal wages was  more than wiped out by inflation, marking the <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2012/03/basics-real-wages-remain-below-their.html">40th consecutive year</a> that real wages have remained below their 1972 peak.</p>
<p>Yet no one in the media noticed, or at least none thought it newsworthy. I searched the web and the subscription-only Nexis news database, and there are literally 0 stories on this. So I meant it when I said you read it here first. In fact, there was little press coverage of the report at all, in sharp contrast to last year.g</p>
<p>Below are the gory details. The data source is Appendix Table B-47, &#8220;Hours and Earnings in Private Non-Agricultural Industries, 1966-2012.&#8221; The table has been completely revised since last year&#8217;s edition of the report. The data is for production and non-supervisory workers in the private sector, about 80% of the private workforce, so we are able to focus on what&#8217;s happening to average workers rather than those with high incomes.. I use weekly wages rather than hourly because there has been substantial variation (with a long-term decline) in the number of hours worked per week, from 38.5 in 1966 to 33.7 in 2012. The table below takes selected years to reduce its size.</p>
<p>Year     Weekly Earnings (1982-84 dollars)</p>
<p>1972     $341.73 (peak)<br />
1975     $314.77<br />
1980     $290.80<br />
1985     $284.96<br />
1990     $271.10<br />
1992     $266.46 (lowest point; 22% below peak)<br />
1995     $267.17<br />
2000     $285.00<br />
2005     $285.05<br />
2010     $297.79<br />
2011     $295.49<br />
2012     $294.83 (still 14% below peak)</p>
<p>This decline is especially amazing when we consider that private non-farm productivity has doubled in this period:</p>
<div><a href="http://research.stlouisfed.org/fred2/graph/?s%5B1%5D%5Bid%5D=OPHNFB"> <img src="http://research.stlouisfed.org/fred2/data/OPHNFB_Max_630_378.png" alt="Graph of Nonfarm Business Sector: Output Per Hour of All Persons" width="630" height="378" border="0" /> </a></div>
<div></div>
<div>But, if you&#8217;ve been paying attention, you know the drill: higher productivity plus lower wages = greater inequality. The question is, why aren&#8217;t our media paying attention when real wages fall, yet again?Update: <a href="http://blogs.seattletimes.com/jontalton/2013/03/25/real-wages-fell-in-2012/">Jon Talton</a> at the <i>Seattle Times</i> has now taken note of this.</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/real-wages-decline-literally-no-one-notices.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Inequality Gap</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/the-inequality-gap.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/the-inequality-gap.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2013 00:23:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Inequality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Linda Beale]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/the-inequality-gap.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Linda Beale The Inequality Gap Robert Reich, former labor secretary, has some worthwhile advice for the President&#8217;s State of the Union address:  he notes that the focus should be the &#8220;central issue you want the nation to help you take action on&#8221;.  That&#8217;s &#8220;not immigration, guns or the environment&#8221; (though &#8220;[a]ll are important&#8221;) but [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Linda Beale</p>
<p>The Inequality Gap</p>
<p>Robert Reich, former labor secretary, has some worthwhile advice for the President&#8217;s <a href="http://www.last.fm/music/David%2BFord/State%2Bof%2Bthe%2BUnion">State of the Union address</a>:  he notes that the focus should be the &#8220;central issue you want the nation to help you take action on&#8221;.  That&#8217;s &#8220;not immigration, guns or the environment&#8221; (though &#8220;[a]ll are important&#8221;) but rather &#8220;joblessness, falling real wages, economic insecurity, and widening inequality&#8221; . See Robert Reich, <a href="http://www.salon.com/2013/02/11/memo_to_obama_focus_on_the_inequality_gap_partner/">Memo to Obama: Focus on the inequality gap</a>, Salon.com (Feb. 11, 2013).</p>
<p>He&#8217;s right.</p>
<p>&#8220;<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/It%27s_the_economy%2C_stupid">It&#8217;s the economy, stupid</a>&#8220;, that old slogan from the Clinton campaign days, goes only so far.  It doesn&#8217;t tell us, for example, what parts of the economy are most important&#8211;is it the stock market&#8217;s well-being, and indirectly the fortunes of the very few at the top of the income distribution who own significant amounts of those items being sold on the market?  Or is it the unemployment data, with its distressing litany of continuing failure of our economy to provide decent jobs for ordinary people?  Is it the way that corporate owners and managers can use the powers of government to make unionization difficult and thereby make it much easier for corporate management and shareholders to retain all the productivity gains while workers wages stagnate (everything from Wal-Mart&#8217;s tendency to tear down union fliers in worker areas (based on my personal observation) to the CEO&#8217;s determination to beat unions down any way possible (see the New York Times story in the 2/12 edition, At Cablevision, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norma_Rae">Norma Rae</a>&#8216;s Been Escorted Outside, New York Times (Feb. 12, 2013), at A23, regarding Cablevision&#8217;s firing of two  dozen employees for being off work,</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>after claiming to have an &#8220;open&#8221; management that invited worker conversations yet allowing those same employees to cool their heels for 40 minutes waiting to talk to him and then walking out and firing them for not being on the job)?  Or is it the general optimism of the upper class, who can pass on untaxed estates to heirs who will get those stocks at stepped up basis and renew the cycle of monetization without taxation for their own account?</p>
<p>Stock market statistics mostly tell us about the upper class, along with the upper part of the middle class that has some share of that bounty:  they don&#8217;t tell us about how well the economy is serving others, unless the general well-being of corporate America spills over to the general well-being of average Americans.  It doesn&#8217;t do that in an era of push-down on unions to ensure that workers have no voice, push-back on taxes to ensure that the wealthy managers and owners not only get all the productivity gains but have to pay too little in taxes to support the system that made those gains possible.  Mostly, stock market statistics tell us about how the privileged are maintaining their privilege, as their ownership of most of the financial assets continues to mean their heightened influence over most laws and their garnering of most of the gains that do take place.</p>
<p>This is well noted in a <a href="http://economistsview.typepad.com/economistsview/2013/02/there-is-nothing-inevitable-about-low-rates-of-economic-mobility.html">post on Economist&#8217;s View </a>(Mark Thoma), embedding a post by Miles Corak on Free Exchange about research on inter-generational social mobility.<br />
<blockquote>The real lesson from the historical research is not that there is anything inevitable about a low degree of inter-generational mobility, or that it signals more persistence than other research. The most privileged will do everything they can to perpetrate their status across generations, and in past eras the structure of labor markets and public policies permitted, and in some measure continue to permit, a non-level playing field.</p></blockquote>
<p>I&#8217;ve long argued that the way to evaluate the economy is in terms of how well it is serving ordinary people who make up the middle class (roughly defined as the middle three quitiles of the income and wealth distribution)  and how adequate is the safety net it provides for those who make up the lower class (the bottom quintile of income and wealth).</p>
<p>What matters is economic sustainability, in terms of  adequacy of those many intangibles by which we measure quality of life&#8211;like accessible quality health care, accessible quality education, accessible quality jobs, decent wages for decent work.  That means that government&#8217;s intervention in the economy will need to be on the side of the little guy, ensuring that resource allocation isn&#8217;t so skewed to the already rich that we become an oligarchy where most of us live off crumbs and a few of us live like kings.  If we want a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sustainability">sustainable economy</a> and sustainable democracy, democratic eqalitarianism demands that governments temper market forces with protections for underdogs, providing counter forces to the redistribution upwards tendency of brute force capitalism.</p>
<p>Today, the rise of the US oligarchy and the frightening power of wealth in determining how laws work have put us in a terrible situation:   &#8220;debtor prisons, once a relic of the 18th century, are making a frightening comeback in the U.S. justice system.&#8221;  Alex Kane, <a href="http://www.salon.com/2013/02/11/miss_a_traffic_ticket_go_to_jail/">Miss a traffic ticket, go to jail?</a>, Salon.com (Feb. 11, 2013).</p>
<p>So an appropriate slogan for progressives today should be something along the lines of &#8220;It&#8217;s the inequality, stupid.&#8221;  And that certainly doesn&#8217;t mean more of the same old failed GOP policies that favor the wealthy, mistakenly labeled &#8220;job creators&#8221; by the GOP in its constant effort to undo unions (witness Michigan&#8217;s disastrous anti-union legislation or Cablevision&#8217;s determination to aid anti-union forces and squelch union activists), favor capital over labor (from the problematic preferential rate for capital gains to the ridiculous &#8220;carried interest&#8221; taxation of the compensation payments to so-called profits partners (a category of &#8220;partner&#8221; for tax purposes not provided for in the tax code but essentially an invention of Wall Street) to the squandering waste of an estate tax and charitable contribution deduction that favor meritless accession to and use of untaxed wealth and pushes the burden for government revenues to laborers instead).  And it certainly doesn&#8217;t mean more of the same &#8220;deficit hawks, austerity mavens, trickle-down charlatans, and government haters who have commanded center stage for too long.&#8221;  <a href="http://www.salon.com/2013/02/11/memo_to_obama_focus_on_the_inequality_gap_partner/">Memo to Obama: Focus on the inqueality gap</a>,</p>
<p>As Reich says:<br />
<blockquote>The President should make it clear that any Republican effort to hold the nation hostage to the GOP&#8217;s ideological fixation on the budget deficit and a smaller government will slow the economy, likely pushing us into another recession.  And that those most imperiled are the middle class and the poor.<br />He should emphasize that the real job creators are not the rich but the vast majority of ordinary Americans whose purchases give businesses reason to add jobs.  And that if most Americans still cannot afford to buy, the government must be the spender of last resort.  Id.</p></blockquote>
<p>Reich goes on to make some specific policy suggestions for acting to reduce inequality.  These include
<ul>
<li>reversing the impact of the reinstatement of the higher Social Security tax rate by exempting the first $20,000 of income from the tax and lifing the ceiling on income subject to it; </li>
<li>reviving government-run work corps, like the WPA and CCC, &#8220;to put the long-term unemployed directly to work&#8221; </li>
<li>raising the minimum wage </li>
<li>imposing a 2% tax surcharge on wealth in excess of $7 billion to be dedicated to education </li>
<li>Cutting corporate and military welfare </li>
<li>not cutting public investments or safety nets </li>
<li>giving tax credits for actual job creation </li>
<li>supporting states that rehire teachers, firefighters police and social workers.  Id. (quoting and paraphrasing).</li>
</ul>
<p>Sounds like a pretty good plan.   As Corak noted (in the <a href="http://economistsview.typepad.com/economistsview/2013/02/there-is-nothing-inevitable-about-low-rates-of-economic-mobility.html">Economist&#8217;s View post </a>cited above):<br />[D]ynamic labor markets offering new opportunities to the population as a whole, progressive public policies of relatively more benefit to the relatively disadvantaged, and strong families with growing incomes and human capital will lead to much more mobility than aristocrats of a pervious era could ever have imagined.</p>
<p>And the Reich plan is certainly better than what most of the GOP-led state experiments like Michigan are coming up with, which read like a plan for even more redistributing upwards to the top few, including:
<ul>
<li>eliminating income taxes in favor of regressive sales taxes, </li>
<li>eliminating business taxes in favor of regressive user fees (a GOP-led Michigan &#8220;upward&#8221; redistribution &#8220;innovation&#8221;), </li>
<li>pushing hard against unions  (a GOP-led Michigan &#8220;innovation&#8221;), </li>
<li>reducing safety net support like Medicaid (being considered in Michigan), </li>
<li>taxing vulnerable seniors on pension income (another of Michigan&#8217;s recent &#8220;innovations&#8221;), </li>
<li>cutting support for state universities while reallocating the support that remains to those that serve the upper class rather than underprivileged who will generally need to borrow more and take longer to succeed (another of Michigan&#8217;s redistributionist efforts).</li>
</ul>
<p>cross posted with <a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/2013/02/the-inequality-gap.html">ataxingmatter</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/the-inequality-gap.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The National Health</title>
		<link>./../../2011/02/the-national-health.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/02/the-national-health.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2011 19:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[asymmetrical information]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health care costs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health care reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Inequality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[just life]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[opportunity costs]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/02/the-national-health.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I wasn&#8217;t going to mention Melissa Mia Hall&#8217;s death here—this is economics and politics, not sf—but now it is clear that, as usual, there is an overlap: If she had seen the doctor, most likely he would have suspected more than a pulled muscle and would have ordered a life-saving EKG. As Texas lawyer, writer [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I wasn&#8217;t going to mention Melissa Mia Hall&#8217;s death here—this is economics and politics, not sf—but now it is clear that, as usual, <a href="http://thelipstickchronicles.typepad.com/the_lipstick_chronicles/2011/02/the-least-of-us.html">there is an overlap</a>:<br />
<blockquote>If she had seen the doctor, most likely he would have suspected more than a pulled muscle and would have ordered a life-saving EKG.</p>
<p>As Texas lawyer, writer and Melissa&#8217;s friend, Laurie Moore, wrote to me, &#8220;She would&#8217;ve had a huge doctor bill she couldn&#8217;t pay, and would probably have lost her house over it, but she would be alive instead of taking pain pills and dying in the night. &#8220;</p>
<p>In the end, Melissa didn&#8217;t die from an overdose, not even an accidental one; Melissa died of the very heart attack she feared&#8230;.</p>
<p>Melissa worked hard. She owned a home. She paid her taxes. She was trying to live a dream &#8211; the American Dream &#8211; that supposedly we as citizens are promised &#8211; the right to pursue life, liberty and happiness. For her, that couldn&#8217;t be achieved in a traditional job that came with the perks of health care.</p></blockquote>
<p>This is the quintessential &#8220;hard-working American&#8221; who gets talked about by The Teabaggers as if nothing ever goes wrong and <a href="http://slog.thestranger.com/slog/archives/2011/01/31/and-here-i-thought-the-purpose-of-the-oped-page-was-to-promote-debate-not-crush-it">they never need &#8220;government help</a>.&#8221; (link h/t <a href="http://www.eschatonblog.com/2011/01/rural-counties-are-sucking-us-dry.html">Dr. Black</a>) This is <a href="http://blogs.publishersweekly.com/blogs/genreville/?p=978">the woman of whom Peter Cannon (via Rose Fox)* said</a>:<br />
<blockquote>Melissa contributed hundreds of reviews to PW, in all different genres, as well as dozens of Q&#038;As. In recent years, ever reliable and diligent, she was reviewing three books a week for me&#8230;</p></blockquote>
<p>This isn&#8217;t someone who was getting &#8220;fails to perform&#8221; ratings or &#8220;stealing&#8221; a house. This is someone whose every effort was aimed at making money and paying bills to keep what little she had gained. She used her skills—human capital, painfully developed—and made rational decisions.</p>
<p>And the rational <em>ex ante</em> decision not to use the medicines she needed or to have to pay out of pocket for an exam that may well lead to more expenses that are beyond her liquidity constraints are, well, exactly what we teach as &#8220;correct&#8221; in Ph.D. micro- and macro- Economics courses.</p>
<p>So this isn&#8217;t a science fiction post, because no one who reads and writes science fiction would believe that a hard-working, conscientious person with great skills, a positive personality, and diligent attention to opportunities would die because they couldn&#8217;t afford to live.</p>
<p>It&#8217;s an economics and politics post, one I wish I hadn&#8217;t had to write.</p>
<p>*Full disclosure: I&#8217;ve known Peter Cannon for years; he edited both myself and my wife at PW. (Full, full disclosure: he fired me, after having previously turned down my request to quit for a while. Both were good decisions on his part.) I&#8217;ve met Rose Fox several times and she edited my wife for a while when PW still paid something resembling minimum wage for the effort required.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/02/the-national-health.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>My Kids Have School Today: An Inequality Survey</title>
		<link>./../../2010/10/my-kids-have-school-today-an-inequality-survey.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2010/10/my-kids-have-school-today-an-inequality-survey.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 11 Oct 2010 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[contract law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Inequality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[just life]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[labor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rule of law]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2010/10/my-kids-have-school-today-an-inequality-survey.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The kids in the next town over don’t.  Indeed, the place where my Eldest Daughter’s swim team practices is closed because it’s a holiday, and their schools are.  But not here: the banks are closed, the government offices are closed, the local libraries are closed. (Heck, the New York Public Library is closed.)  But the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The kids in the next town over don’t.  Indeed, the place where my Eldest Daughter’s swim team practices is closed because it’s a holiday, and their schools are.  But not here: the banks are closed, the government offices are closed, the local libraries are closed. (Heck, the New York Public Library is closed.)  But the schools are open.
<p>For more than three years, the teachers worked without a contract.  While the Administration grew—and paid itself <em>very </em>well, taking an ever-increasing share of the budget—the teacher showed good faith.  They continued to negotiate, continued not to strike.  It wasn’t until the third year that they started cutting back on the extra effort they put in—things such as displaying children’s art projects in the hallways&#8211;.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>Finally, two years ago, a contract agreement was reached.  One of the things no one bothered to specify—since the schools are public, and therefore a government institution—was that Federal and State holidays would not be school days.  The teachers might work some of them—teachers, as with most academics, do more work outside of the classroom (in preparation, in training, in research) than in it, so there might be a training day on some of the minor ones—but there would not be classes.  No Administration would be crazy enough to schedule classes on a Federal holiday, when many of the parents would have planned three-day weekends.</p>
<p>Except ours, to punish the teachers for having the temerity to negotiate for a contract, would do exactly that.  And it has for the past few years.</p>
<p>While taking my usual walk from Penn Station to Times Square, I saw more than the usual amount of tourists: a marginal effect of the holiday, as economists would note.  And that marginal effect is marginally reduced by the families whose children had to go to school today, even though their parents have the day off.  By the Law of Large Numbers, economists won’t even notice the difference—though individual stores and businesses might.</p>
<p>Columbus Day may be a minor Federal holiday. An NCIS “Undercover Marathon” on the USA network does not a unique celebration make.  And explaining why it is a holiday may become problematic. (“Well, <a href="http://open.salon.com/blog/keka/2010/10/10/white_men_with_guns" target="_blank">white men with guns</a> came here because like most men they were really lousy at asking for directions. And unlike the previous white men, they stayed, more or less.” is so much less doggerel or open to misinterpretation than “In 1493, Columbus sailed the Deep Blue Sea.”)  But explaining that the kids have to go to school, not the beach, because the superintendent wants to punish the teachers and the kids are collateral damage, well, that’s an economics lesson that will abide.</p>
<p>Especially when you tell them the punch line: Despite more than containing teacher expenses, the school budget has exploded for the past several years as more and more Administrators have been paid more and more money. And the result of this is that the Superintendent who is responsible for that got a five-year contract extension, bloating the budget even more, with even less of it allocated to children’s education (since the Superintendent is a Fixed Cost).</p>
<p>From there, explaining the growth of income inequality is at worst a lay-up.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2010/10/my-kids-have-school-today-an-inequality-survey.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Egalitarian U.S. Health Care System?</title>
		<link>./../../2009/06/the-egalitarian-u-s-health-care-system.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/06/the-egalitarian-u-s-health-care-system.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 06 Jun 2009 17:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Health Care]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Inequality]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/06/the-egalitarian-u-s-health-care-system.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Tom Bozzo Tyler Cowen writes: Since old, high-bank-account white males have lots of social status and power, [believers in egalitarianism] cannot bring themselves to regard those males as holding very poor overall endowments. Cowen claims that the poor old rich white guys&#8217; supposedly &#8220;poor overall endowments&#8221; arise from the impairment of their human capital [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Tom Bozzo</p>
<p>Tyler Cowen <a href="http://www.marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2009/06/why-us-policy-is-especially-egalitarian-.html">writes</a>:<br />
<blockquote>Since old, high-bank-account white males have lots of social status and power, [believers in egalitarianism] cannot bring themselves to regard those males as holding very poor overall endowments.</p></blockquote>
<p>Cowen claims that the poor old rich white guys&#8217; supposedly &#8220;poor overall endowments&#8221; arise from the impairment of their human capital at the more-or-less imminent end of life.  There might be half of an argument here if human capital were the only component of individual wealth.  Instead, we have Shorter [*] Tyler Cowen: The rich actually aren&#8217;t so rich if you don&#8217;t count their money.  Whether and to what extent marrying Neutron Jack increased Mrs. Suzy Welch&#8217;s human capital as distinct from social and financial capital is left as an exercise for the reader.</p>
<p>So it&#8217;s pretty easy to construct an exception to Cowen&#8217;s claim that<br />
<blockquote>The &#8220;poorest&#8221; people are not those with low incomes but rather those with low human capital endowments.&#8221;</p></blockquote>
<p>Take a suitably dimwitted heir to a sufficiently large fortune and I will show you someone not only a lot richer than a comparably bright person who picked his or her parents badly, but in fact just about everyone else.</p>
<p>Now Cowen actually is right to point out that the U.S. health care system provides plenty of care to seniors at the end of life despite what I will agree are often modest endowments of wealth (including, but not necessarily limited to, human capital).  The inference that this makes the U.S. health care system more egalitarian than European systems, however, is highly questionable to say the least.  First of all, health care for the elderly is the most European part of the U.S. system: more-or-less universal, more-or-less socialized medicine.  Second, to the extent European systems spend (relatively) less money on the elderly, they don&#8217;t have obviously worse outcomes (shorter lives, etc.) to show for it.</p>
<p>Subject the elderly to the more-or-less private sector part of the U.S. system and those financial endowments are likelier to drive allocations of health care resources.  And indeed it tends to be individuals with high human capital endowments who get the jobs with benefits that provide decent health care.  Certainly the state of the U.S. health care system isn&#8217;t going to make me, whether egalitarian-minded or acting on pure self-interest, more inclined on the margin to switch places with the middle-aged immigrant behind the McDonald&#8217;s counter next door to the office.  A leveling possibility in the U.S. system is that a bout of unemployment coinciding with an unlucky draw from the distribution of health outcomes can leave a middle-aged economics PhD approximately as screwed as the guy at McDonald&#8217;s, but reasonable people can reject race-to-the-bottom egalitarianism.  I&#8217;ll wager the lower-endowment exceptions with decent health insurance are disproportionately public-sector employees (where a common complaint from conservatives and libertarians is that they have it too good relative to their private-sector counterparts; see e.g. U.S. Postal Service, bargaining-unit employees of) and other unionized workers.</p>
<p>The egalitarian reformer of the U.S. may reasonably conclude that fairness is best served by making the U.S. system more like the Europeans, or by promoting public plans over private ones.</p>
<p>[*] *‘Shorter’ concept created by <a href="http://d-squareddigest.blogspot.com/2003/02/shorter-steven-den-beste-as-part-of-my.html">Daniel Davies</a> and perfected by <a href="http://busybusybusy.com/">Elton Beard</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/06/the-egalitarian-u-s-health-care-system.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
