<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Mike Halasy &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Opposition to the Mandate</title>
		<link>./../../2012/05/opposition-to-the-mandate.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/05/opposition-to-the-mandate.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 05 May 2012 03:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Mike Halasy]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/05/opposition-to-the-mandate.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[So, one thing has continually troubled me throughout the health care debate, and this is the consistent polling showing opposition to the individual mandate. It&#8217;s taken me a while, but I think that I have finally figured this out. THIS article reviewing data from the AFLAC Workforces Report shows that we are doing a terrible [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>So, one thing has continually troubled me throughout the health care debate, and this is the consistent polling showing opposition to the individual mandate. It&#8217;s taken me a while, but I think that I have finally figured this out.</p>
<p><a href="http://finance.yahoo.com/news/americans-denial-likelihood-accidents-serious-090000836.html" target="_blank">THIS</a> article reviewing data from the AFLAC Workforces Report shows that we are doing a terrible job in educating our public on health concerns.</p>
<p><i>six out of ten workers (62 percent) think it&#8217;s not very or not at all  likely they or a family member will be diagnosed with a serious illness  like cancer, and more than half (55 percent) said they were not very or  not at all likely to be diagnosed with a chronic illness, such as heart  disease or diabetes.</i></p>
<p><i> </i>But of course, this is not reality. This fundamental disconnect as the article notes, is more than simply problematic..</p>
<p><i>Americans may be overly optimistic when it comes to thinking they  won&#8217;t ever be diagnosed with a serious illness or experience an  accident. According to the American Cancer Society, </i><i>Cancer Facts &#038; Figures 2012,  one in three women and one in two men will be diagnosed with cancer at  some point in their lives, and the National Safety Council, </i><i>Injury Facts 2011 edition, says that more than 38.9 million medically consulted injuries occur in a year. The American Heart Association, </i><i>Heart Disease &#038; Stroke Statistics 2012, show that one in six deaths in the U.S. was caused by coronary heart disease. &#8220;The fact that American workers aren&#8217;t aware of their medical risks  and the potential financial impact of those risks is a very real concern  that is only compounded when workers don&#8217;t take full advantage of  available benefits options or adjust their savings strategies to be more  prepared,&#8221; said Audrey Boone Tillman, executive vice president of  Corporate Services at Aflac. &#8220;Now, more than ever, people need to  understand that well-being means more than just good health—it&#8217;s being  prepared for the reality of whatever life may bring and taking the  necessary measures to protect themselves and their families.&#8221;</i></p>
<p>I think that this explains this. Certainly some people are fundamentally opposed to government mandates of any sort, but they would hardly constitute a plurality, let alone a majority, but pure ignorance, or a magical suspension of disbelief I think explains it. I cannot think of any other explanation.</p>
<p>Having watched several relatives go through illness that resulted in death, and having a chronic condition myself, I simply cannot help but wonder how people have reached this conclusion. The simple fact that they don&#8217;t understand this is likely more troublesome than a rejection of the mandate itself.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/05/opposition-to-the-mandate.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
