<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>About Angry Bear &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>About Angry Bear</title>
		<link>./../../2012/11/about-angry-bear.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/11/about-angry-bear.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 04 Nov 2012 01:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[About Angry Bear]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/11/about-angry-bear.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Angry Bear 2012: made it to 21st on the list in popularity and influence this time around at Onalytica Indexes Angry Bear 2011:  Mindful Money posted at Minyanville named Angry Bear among some of the top influential independent financial blogs. Angry Bear 2010: In 2010 24/7 Wall St. named Angry Bear among the top twenty [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Angry Bear 2012: made it to 21st on the list in popularity and influence this time around at <a href="http://onalyticaindexes.com/2012/11/26/top-200-most-influential-economics-blogs/" target="_blank">Onalytica Indexes</a></p>
<p> Angry Bear 2011:  <a href="http://www.minyanville.com/dailyfeed/the-20-most-influential-blogs/" target="_blank">Mindful Money</a> posted at Minyanville named Angry Bear among some of the top influential independent financial blogs.</p>
<p>Angry Bear 2010: <a href="http://247wallst.com/2010/03/31/the-247-wall-st-twenty-best-financial-blogs/" target="_blank">In 2010 24/7 Wall St. named <strong>Angry Bear</strong></a> among the top twenty independent financial blogs on the net.<br />
<blockquote>The Angry Bear www.angrybearblog.com. Half a dozen professionals, including a tax law expert, a historian, PhDs in economics, business consultants and financial professionals provide perspectives on the financial world. Despite their expansive coverage of economic issues, their articles are as deep as their coverage is extensive. Topics include world trade, industrial production, U.S. Government programs, and major regulatory issues.</p></blockquote>
<p><a href="http://angrybear.blogspot.com/2010/02/top-five-tax-accounting-blogsour-own.html" target="_blank">2010 FINS from The Wall Street Journal</a> named Linda Beale&#8217;s <a href="http://www.blogger.com/" target="_blank"><strong>ataxingmatter</strong></a> in The Top Five Tax Accounting blogs to read for 2009-2010.</p>
<p>In no particular order our current economists and contributors in macro, micro, and finance are Mike Kimel, Ken Houghton, Spencer England, Robert Waldmann, Linda Beale (tax and law),  Rebecca Wilder (The Wilder View at Economonitor), Steve Roth and Jazzbumpa.  Bruce Webb has added his nationally recognized expertise in particular on Social Security.. Beverly Mann writes on Supreme Court proceedings.  Mike Halasy and Tom Ealy cover the health industry. Dan Becker offers his perspective as a owner of two small businesses.</p>
<p>Mostly in alphabetical order:</p>
<p><strong>Daniel Crawford</strong>:  aka Rdan owns, designs, moderates, and manages Angry Bear since 2007. </p>
<p><strong>Linda Beale: </strong> Linda is a law professor at Wayne State University Law School who teaches various courses in the area of federal income tax, such as introduction to federal income tax, corporate taxation, partnership taxation, international taxation and perhaps in the future a course in statutory interpretation focussed on tax. </p>
<p>Her philosophy is that &#8220;the tax system should reflect the values of ordinary Americans and our long-held belief in principles of liberty, equality and community. I fear that we have instead tended to give too much credence to purportedly &#8220;objective&#8221; ideas about taxation based on the rationales of law and economics and unverified theories about economic growth, and too little credence to human needs for community that require allocating the burdens and benefits of the tax system fairly among the people and entities that make up our system.&#8221; She maintains her own blog <a href="http://ataxingmatter.blogs.com/" target="_blank">ataxingmatter</a> as well.</p>
<p>Dan Becker:</p>
<p><strong>Tom Ealey</strong> (aka Save the Rustbelt):  Rusty Rustbelt aka save_the_rustbelt aka Tom Ealey has had a career as a CPA,  management consultant, health care executive, college lecturer, researcher,  technical writer, seminar leader and litigation analyst (after factory and  construction laborer and union member). He is currently resisting retirement as  a college lecturer, writer, researcher, seminar leader, occasional accountant,  advisory committee member, church finance director and occasional day laborer.  He is married to &#8220;the world&#8217;s greatest nurse,&#8221; is a doting grandfather and is  currently starting a publishing company.</p>
<p><strong>Spencer England:</strong> Before I started my own consulting business I was an economist for the CIA for 10 years and worked for a couple of Boston investment management firms as their in house economist, investment strategist for some 12 years. My original field of study was international economics and international finance. I just celebrated the 25th anniversary of publishing <a href="http://econseer.blogspot.com/" target="_blank">SEER</a> &#8212; my equity strategy product. I model the S&#038;P industries and advise portfolio managers on how to structure their portfolios by recommending industry weights.<strong></strong></p>
<p>Mike Halasy:</p>
<p><strong>Ken Houghton:</strong> A principle in his own company and former economist for several major financial companies.</p>
<p>Jazzbumpa:</p>
<p><strong>Mike Kimel</strong>: An economist for a private corporation and author of <a href="http://www.presimetrics.com/blog/?p=3" target="_blank">Presimetrics blog</a> and the book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1579128351?ie=UTF8&#038;tag=angr0b-20&#038;link_code=as3&#038;camp=211189&#038;creative=373489&#038;creativeASIN=1579128351" target="_blank">Presimetrics: How Democratic and Republican Administrations Measure Up on the Issues We Care About</a> published August,  2010.</p>
<p>Beverly Mann:</p>
<p>Steve Roth:  Steve Roth is a serial entrepreneur whose businesses have ranged from book and magazine publishing to high-tech professional conferences to corporate services. He is self-taught in economics over many years, with great help from the remarkable community of the econoblogosphere, and of course the traditional sources of textbooks and published econ papers. </p>
<p>Steve&#8217;s publications include &#8220;Capital in the American Economy Since 1930: Kuznets Revisited,&#8221; an appendix to James Livingston&#8217;s <i>Against Thrift: Why Consumer Culture is Good for the Economy, the Environment, and Your Soul. </i>That appendix and supporting data are available <a href="http://www.asymptosis.com/capital-in-the-american-economy-since-1930-kuznets-revisited.html">here</a>. Steve has been blogging at <a href="http://www.asymptosis.com/">Asymptosis</a> since 2004. He&#8217;s also a self-described and variously published Shakespeare dweeb; his Shakespeare scholarship is viewable at <a href="http://princehamlet.com/">princehamlet.com</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Robert Waldmann:</strong> &#8230;born the day after Kennedy was elected (November 9 1960). I have a PhD in economics (Harvard 1989) and teach economics at the University of Rome &#8220;Tor Vergata&#8221;. I wasn&#8217;t always like this. I have a bachelor&#8217;s degree in biology. Oddly, I don&#8217;t blog much at my own site <a href="http://rjwaldmann.blogspot.com/">rjwaldmann</a> about economics or Italy. Currently, I am obsessed with Obama, but I&#8217;ll try not to bore people with stuff they already read 10 times today. As an economist (roughly) I am interested in behavioral economics, growth, and the economics of inequality. Actually much of my current research, such as it is, is really in econometric methodology and statistics. I was very unorthodox in the 80s, but the orthodoxy is much less rigid now.</p>
<p><strong>Bruce Webb: </strong>I am by training a historian and mythologist who then has spent my working career in information retrieval and land use regulation. My interest in Social Security arose when I noticed in passing that the dates related to &#8216;crisis&#8217; were moving but that nobody seemed to be noticing that and still less asking the key questions &#8216;why?&#8217; and &#8216;can this go on?&#8217; So I set out to try to answer those questions and then share the results which somehow led to a gig here at AB. Politically I am somewhat left of left of center and could best be described as a &#8216;New Dealer&#8217; and so weigh in on more overtly political questions as the opportunity arises.</p>
<p><strong>Rebecca Wilder: </strong> She writes her own column, <strong>The Wilder View</strong>, at Nouriel Roubini&#8217;s <em>Economonitor</em> as well.  After receiving my Doctorate in Economics, I was an assistant professor for two years. However, I realized that teaching just wasn&#8217;t for me and took a job in private sector. Now, I am an Economist in the financial industry. As an economist in finance, I analyze data, write commentary, and offer economic insight to traders, chiefs of staff, and really anyone who wants my opinion. It is in this job that I developed a fancy for writing, but mostly I love talking about economics to anyone who will listen.</p>
<p><strong>History of Angry Bear:</strong> Written by Cactus</p>
<p>The eponymous Angry Bear blog is the brainchild of&#8230; Angry Bear (&#8220;AB&#8221;), who founded the blog in <a href="http://angrybear.blogspot.com/2003/02/income-and-consumption-so-heres.html">February of 2003</a>. The title of the blog reflects his emotional reaction (anger) to his view of the state (bearish) of the state of the economy when the blog was founded. Sadly, he had cause to maintain that sentiment for quite a while.  Kash Mansori joined the blog in <a href="http://angrybear.blogspot.com/2003/08/recognizing-obvious-i-liked-this.html">August 2003</a>, and PGL arrived <a href="http://angrybear.blogspot.com/2004/06/national-review-v.html">a year later</a>.</p>
<p>AB, Kash, and PGL formed the core of the blog for many years. Each has a Ph.D. in economics, but AB&#8217;s focus is on microeconomic issues, Kash&#8217;s are in macroeconomic issues, and PGL&#8217;s training is in finance. Neither AB nor Kash has posted here in a while, but we hold out hope for their eventual return. We also hold out hope for the return of <a href="http://angrybear.blogspot.com/2005/03/another-budget-another-disaster.html">CR</a>, who posted for several years at both Angry Bear and his own blog, <a href="http://calculatedrisk.blogspot.com/">Calculated Risk</a>. However, we can at least continue to enjoy his insights on real estate, housing, and banking trends, and economic indicators at the Calculated Risk blog.</p>
<p>Since 2006, Angry Bear has added more regulars &#8211; some have remained, some have stayed for a while and then moved on.  Former regulars include  <strong>Stormy,</strong> <strong>Tom Bozzo</strong>, and Noni Mausa.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/11/about-angry-bear.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
