<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>HR676 &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>HR676: Serious policy? or Simple political posturing?</title>
		<link>./../../2009/11/hr676-serious-policy-or-simple-political-posturing.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/11/hr676-serious-policy-or-simple-political-posturing.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 02 Nov 2009 15:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[health care reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[HR676]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/11/hr676-serious-policy-or-simple-political-posturing.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Bruce Webb A lot of progressives insist that there is a simple golden-bullet solution to the health care crisis. All we need to do is substitute the 30 page HR676 Single Payer/Medicare For All bill for the 1990 page HR3962. Which led me to ask &#8220;How can you possibly supply code language to overhaul [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Bruce Webb</p>
<p>A lot of progressives insist that there is a simple golden-bullet solution to the health care crisis. All we need to do is substitute the 30 page HR676 Single Payer/Medicare For All bill for the 1990 page HR3962. Which led me to ask &#8220;How can you possibly supply code language to overhaul the U.S. health care system in 30 pages?&#8221; Well you don&#8217;t, HR676 is in bluntest terms a political joke. I provide a lengthy breakdown in this post at the Bruce Web <a target="_blank" href="http://bruceweb.blogspot.com/2009/11/hr676-political-fools-gold.html">HR676: Political Fools&#8217; Gold</a> and in the interest of space provide a severely abbreviated version here.</p>
<p>Provisions of the bill:<br />Universal coverage for all residents including undocumented workers. (Sec 101)<br />No out of pocket expenses for anyone. (Sec 102 (c) )<br />Benefits include unlimited medical, dental, vision, perscription drugs, substance abuse treatment, long term care all at no direct cost to the end user. (Sec 102 (a) )<br />For profit medicine made illegal. Including dentistry, optometric services, pharmacies, out patient or in patient care. (Sec 103)<br />Investor owned medical facilities to be converted to non-profit status within one year with the government paying for &#8220;&#8221;reasonable financial losses incurred as a result of the conversion from for-profit to non-profit status. &#8221; (Sec 103)<br />Private insurance for any benefit covered in the bill made illegal. (Sec 104)<br />Providers must either be salaried or paid on a set national schedule regardless of geographic variations. (Sec 202)<br />Costs will be covered by unspecified income taxes on the upper 5%, a &#8220;modest&#8221; payroll tax, and some tax on stock and bond transactions. (Sec 211)<br />All costs for construction and renovation of medical facilities to be paid for by the government (Sec 202)<br />Indian Health Service to be eliminated after five years. (Sec 401)<br />VA Hospital system potentially to be eliminated after ten years. (Sec 401)</p>
<p>It is pretty common for commenters on the Left to say that no one is proposing a government takeover of medical care on the model of the British National Health System. And they are right. This proposal goes far beyond that. There is not a single hysteric charge by the Limbaugh/Beck/Bachmann crowd that would not be supported by the text of this bill. With one exception, it doesn&#8217;t actually provide for death panels. But in every other respect this is a proposal for a communist-style health care system.</p>
<p>Think that is too strong? Well check out the bill as it is presented by its biggest supporter Physicians for a National Health Program.  http://www.pnhp.org/publications/united_states_national_health_care_act_hr_676.php</p>
<p>Let me add my urging to theirs: <a target="_blank" href="http://www.pnhp.org/docs/nhi_bill_final1.pdf">Read the Text of H.R.676</a></p>
<p>Don&#8217;t let anyone tell you that this is just a case of opening Medicare to everybody, this is a root and branch transformation of the entire medical delivery system. Under this bill Perle Vision Centers and &#8220;your neighborhood Walgreens&#8221; become illegal operations. As it does any group owned clinic including in all likelihood your dentist. I mean who could afford to finance establishment of a new medical facility out of pocket with no outside investors?</p>
<p>The answer to the question in the title of my post? Blatant posturing for effect. No serious person would put forth a policy that at one and the same time provides unlimited free medical care for illegal immigrants and phases out a dedicated health care system for disabled veterans. Christ the campaign ads write themselves.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/11/hr676-serious-policy-or-simple-political-posturing.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
