<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Slate &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Paul Ryan Is the Joe McCarthy of Our Era. Maybe the Mainstream Media Finally Will Recognize That. Then Again, Maybe It Won’t.</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/paul-ryan-is-the-joe-mccarthy-of-our-era-maybe-the-mainstream-media-finally-will-recognize-that-then-again-maybe-it-wont.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/paul-ryan-is-the-joe-mccarthy-of-our-era-maybe-the-mainstream-media-finally-will-recognize-that-then-again-maybe-it-wont.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2013 16:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Edward R. Murrow]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Joe MCarthy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mainstream news media]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Matthew Yglesias]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Ryan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Walter Cronkite]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/paul-ryan-is-the-joe-mccarthy-of-our-era-maybe-the-mainstream-media-finally-will-recognize-that-then-again-maybe-it-wont.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Paul Ryan is, in effect, the Joe McCarthy of our era.  He consistently spews outlandishly false statements of fact, never offers actual evidence in support of them and never refutes factual challenges using actual and full facts, and tries as a matter of routine to obfuscate his specific and broader objectives and therefore to trick [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Paul Ryan is, in effect, the Joe McCarthy of our era.  He consistently spews <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/moneybox/2013/03/12/paul_ryan_currency_debasement.html">outlandishly false statements of fact</a>, never offers actual evidence in support of them and never refutes factual challenges using actual and full facts, and <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/moneybox/2013/03/12/class_war_budgeting_paul_ryan_and_house_gop_want_more_money_for_the_rich.html">tries <i>as a matter of routine</i> to obfuscate his specific and broader objectives </a>and therefore to trick the public.  </p>
<p>He is a serious nutcase.  And yet he has garnered mainstream media attention as though what he puts out is credible.  We have a mainstream media that treats this nutjob as though he were a legitimate policy wonk. And that acts as though facts are legitimately in the eye of the beholder.  </p>
<p>If only Obama were more like Ike.  And if only there were an Edward R. Murrow around now, although a Walter Cronkite would do, too.  If only.  </p>
<p>Broadcast news, of course, no longer has nearly the power and audience it once had, but we now have the veritable <i>reverse</i> of what this country once had in its highest-profile journalists.  and we have a president who cowers in the face of whatever media juggernaut is currently saying &#8220;boo.&#8221;  </p>
<p>True, Ike was buoyed, not hindered, by the mainstream press when he helped end the McCarthy stranglehold.  And McCarthy and Eisenhower were, technically anyway, members of the same political party, so there was no insistence that Eisenhower humor McCarthy in the name of bipartisanship.  But there&#8217;s also no law that requires the president, this one or any other, to mindlessly do the mainstream media&#8217;s bidding if that bidding is in the name of bipartisanship.  At least not when bipartisanship means delegating fiscal policy to a rightwing faction of a minority party that a majority of voters recently pretty-darned-clearly  rejected.</p>
<p>This is getting really, really scary.  </p>
<p>&#8212;-<br /><i>The links are to two Matthew Yglesias posts in Slate this morning.</i></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/paul-ryan-is-the-joe-mccarthy-of-our-era-maybe-the-mainstream-media-finally-will-recognize-that-then-again-maybe-it-wont.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>THREAT-LEVEL-GATE©: Bob Woodward’s Awful Hope-Y’All-Won’t-Notice-Ryan-Lizza’s-Report Ploy</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/threat-level-gate-bob-woodwards-awful-hope-yall-wont-notice-ryan-lizzas-report-ploy.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/threat-level-gate-bob-woodwards-awful-hope-yall-wont-notice-ryan-lizzas-report-ploy.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2013 21:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Alexandra Petri]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bob Woodward]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gene Sperling]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Matthew Yglesias]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ryan Lizza]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The New Yorker]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the sequester]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Washington Post]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[THREAT-LEVEL-GATE]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/threat-level-gate-bob-woodwards-awful-hope-yall-wont-notice-ryan-lizzas-report-ploy.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Bob Woodward, the legendary Watergate reporter turned reliable chronicler of insider accounts of political events, has made a series of bizarre assertions over the past week. &#8212; Matthew Yglesias, Bob Woodward Trolls the World, Slate, today Yglesias then summarizes last weekend’s exciting Woodward-related events, and then updates us: Things moved into the absurd Wednesday night [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">Bob Woodward, the legendary Watergate reporter turned reliable chronicler of insider accounts of political events, has made a series of bizarre assertions over the past week.</div>
<div dir="ltr">&#8212; Matthew Yglesias,<a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/moneybox/2013/02/28/bob_woodward_vs_gene_sperling_veteran_reporter_trolls_washington.html#article_comment_box"> Bob Woodward Trolls the World</a>, Slate, today</div>
<p>Yglesias then summarizes<a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/02/bob-woodwards-seriously-stupid.html"> last weekend’s exciting Woodward-related events</a>, and then updates us:</p>
<div dir="ltr">Things moved into the absurd Wednesday night when it was revealed that National Economic Council director Gene Sperling had concluded an email disagreement with Woodward with the observation that in Sperling&#8217;s view Woodward would come to regret clinging so tenaciously to an untenable position.</div>
<div dir="ltr"></div>
<div dir="ltr">As if determined to prove Sperling right,<a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/weigel/2013/02/28/the_nature_of_the_threat.html"> Woodward chose to start talking around town about how Sperling had threatened him</a>—a ridiculous interpretation that the ridiculous conservative media has been running with—rather than sticking with the obvious interpretation that Woodward&#8217;s reputation among journalists is going to suffer from flagrant wrongness. It would be interesting to see Woodward try to hash this out with, say, fellow Post-ie Ezra Klein, but instead he&#8217;s going the full wingnut and<a href="http://themoderatevoice.com/177366/woodward-says-white-house-threatened-him-will-appear-on-sean-hannitys-fox-show/"> will be appearing on Sean Hannity&#8217;s show</a> Thursday night to advance the agitprop agenda. In retrospect, this whole affair was foreshadowed by the release of<a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1451651104/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&#038;camp=1789&#038;creative=390957&#038;creativeASIN=1451651104&#038;linkCode=as2&#038;tag=slatmaga-20"> Woodward&#8217;s latest book last fall</a>. It made much less of a splash than many other Woodward books. Most well-informed observers<a href="http://www.newrepublic.com/book/review/bob-woodward-price-of-politics"> agreed with Noam Scheiber that it was marred by anti-Obama bias</a>, but under the circumstances of the time, it didn&#8217;t get the right geared up either. By essentially doubling down on the worst qualities of that book, Woodward has managed to make himself the center of attention again.</div>
<p>Surprisingly, though, Yglesias doesn’t mention that earlier this week, New Yorker writer Ryan Lizza published<a href="http://www.newyorker.com/reporting/2013/03/04/130304fa_fact_lizza#ixzz2MCuygBWh"> a journalistic scoop</a> that undermined the thing about Woodward being a reliable chronicler of insider accounts of political events.  Lizza quoted none other than Eric Cantor, who conceded that Boehner, at Cantor’s urging, reneged on the 2011 grand bargain deal at the last minute, for political reasons.  </p>
<p>Uh-oh.   </p>
<p>So, do you think Woodward might have decided to ratchet up the off-the-rails stuff a-few-fold yesterday because yesterday (or maybe the day before) was the day when Ryan Lizza’s New Yorker story broke?  Yeah?  You think?</p>
<p>Yes, that&#8217;s right.  Bob Woodward, the legendary Watergate reporter had turned a reliable chronicler of insider accounts of political events, and has now been exposed as a reliable and gullible tool of Republican insiders.  But he hopes no one will notice that.</p>
<p>What I find interesting about this is that apparently the Washington Post has pulled the plug on Woodward’s unfettered use of it as a forum in which to spread false statements of fact. Thus he was relegated to seeking out Politico<a href="http://www.politico.com/story/2013/02/exclusive-the-woodward-sperling-emails-revealed-88226.html?hp=t2_3"> as his venue</a> for the “breaking news” this time.</p>
<p>Progress.</p>
<p>I can&#8217;t help wondering, though, whether Sperling was right that Woodward might come to regret his flagrantly false reporting on what the sequester agreement is.  He hasn&#8217;t yet, though. He&#8217;s still cowering with fear from that threat, but determined to press on nonetheless. </p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />By the way, you really, really need to see Alexandra Petri’s <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/compost/wp/2013/02/28/how-to-threaten-bob-woodward/?hpid=z3">threat-level piece </a>on this. Seriously.  (Just be sure you’re not eating anything you might choke on when you do.)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/threat-level-gate-bob-woodwards-awful-hope-yall-wont-notice-ryan-lizzas-report-ploy.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>OK, Maybe Not Uwe Reinhardt for Labor Secretary, But Maybe Alan Krueger?</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/ok-maybe-not-uwe-reinhardt-for-labor-secretary-but-maybe-alan-krueger.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/ok-maybe-not-uwe-reinhardt-for-labor-secretary-but-maybe-alan-krueger.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2013 20:23:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Alan Krueger]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Secretary of Labor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uwe Reinhardt]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/ok-maybe-not-uwe-reinhardt-for-labor-secretary-but-maybe-alan-krueger.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In the Comments thread yesterday to my Uwe-Reinhardt-For-Labor-Secretary post, an old fellow “Frayster” (definition: Someone who posted regularly to Slate’s wonderful, late, great “Fray” comments board), Woolley, wrote: I don&#8217;t know anything about Uwe and after reading your piece, I still don&#8217;t know anything about [him]. Can you tell us why [he] is such a [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the Comments thread yesterday to my <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/02/my-audacious-wish-uwe-reinhardt-for.html">Uwe-Reinhardt-For-Labor-Secretary post</a>, an old fellow “Frayster” (definition: Someone who posted regularly to Slate’s wonderful, late, great “Fray” comments board), Woolley, wrote:</p>
<div dir="ltr">I don&#8217;t know anything about Uwe and after reading your piece, I still don&#8217;t know anything about [him]. Can you tell us why [he] is such a good candidate and what exactly you think the DoL should be doing?</div>
<p>Here’s what I wrote in response: </p>
<div>
<div dir="ltr">Hi again, Woolley. Reinhardt’s Wikipedia page is [<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uwe_Reinhardt">here</a>].  His Princeton page is [<a href="http://wws.princeton.edu/people/display_person.xml?netid=reinhard&#038;display=core">here</a>].</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">This post of mine hasn’t exactly gone off the charts for hits, maybe because most everyone who did read it probably rolled their eyes.  I guess they recognize that the chance that Reinhardt would accept an offer to become Labor secretary is about as likely as that he’d be offered the position.  Which is to say, not … um … great.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Reinhardt, as I said in my post, is prominent these days mainly for his expertise in the economics of healthcare funding and insurance.  But, in looking just now for an example of his writings on labor issues, I found a good example, from two years ago, [<a href="http://economix.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/02/18/how-convincing-is-the-case-for-free-trade/">here</a>].  He is, or at least was, one of the regular contributors to the NYT’s Economix blog.  </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">The blog is subtitled “Explaining the Science of Everyday Life,” and that post of Reinhardt’s is called “How Convincing Is the Case for Free Trade?”  In it, he makes clear the distinction between free trade and offshoring.  He does that partly by discussing a 2007 article in the Washington Post by his Princeton Econ. Dept. colleague Alan Blinder called “<a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/05/04/AR2007050402555.html?nav=rss_print/outlook">Free Trade&#8217;s Great, but Offshoring Rattles Me</a>.”  That issue and, I believe, the issue of whether modern technology&#8211;robots in manufacturing; computers of all sorts&#8211;really is different than earlier huge advances in technology, such as the automobile putting horse-buggy makers out of business, in its effect on employment, worldwide, but especially in advanced economies like ours.  </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Blinder is, best as I can tell, the most prominent liberal Princeton economist other than Paul Krugman.  He would be a wonderful choice as Labor secretary, but my impression is that he would be too risky a pick, politically, just as Krugman would be.  Same, I suppose, for Brad Delong. Which is why I suggested Reinhardt instead.  </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">The point I was trying to make in my post has less to do with Reinhardt himself than with my hope for the appointment as Labor secretary of an economist well-versed in the academics of these issues and also who has the ability to explain these things clearly, and publicly, to lay people.  And to help Obama do that.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Another excellent choice&#8211;one I didn’t think of until this morning&#8211;would be Alan Krueger, another liberal Princeton-associated economist, and one who actually could, theoretically, be nominated.  That’s because since November 2011, he has been the chairman of the White House Counsel of Economic Advisors. He has done extensive research and writing on issues of growing inequality, and the role of government-supported education in the economy.  His Wikipedia page is [<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alan_Krueger">here</a>].</div>
<p>Hope that takes care of it.</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/ok-maybe-not-uwe-reinhardt-for-labor-secretary-but-maybe-alan-krueger.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>What Dana Milbank’s Stunningly Awful Column Today Reveals About the Washington Press Corps &#8211; [UPDATED]</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/what-dana-milbanks-stunningly-awful-column-today-reveals-about-the-washington-press-corps-updated.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/what-dana-milbanks-stunningly-awful-column-today-reveals-about-the-washington-press-corps-updated.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2013 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Angry Bear]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dana Milbank]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dave Weigel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[debt ceiling]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Krugman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Washington Post]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[White House press corp]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/what-dana-milbanks-stunningly-awful-column-today-reveals-about-the-washington-press-corps-updated.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Okay.  There’s no way to do justice to Washington Post centerist columnist Dana Milbank’s column today about Obama’s “presser” yesterday by just summarizing it or quoting a sentence or short paragraph from it.  And justice for that column, titled “President Congeniality talks tough,” is what I want. So here are the first six (blessedly short) [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Okay.  There’s no way to do justice to Washington Post centerist columnist Dana Milbank’s column today about Obama’s “presser” yesterday by just summarizing it or quoting a sentence or short paragraph from it.  And justice for that column, titled “<a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/dana-milbank-president-congeniality-talks-tough/2013/01/14/6f5b50a0-5e9d-11e2-90a0-73c8343c6d61_print.html">President Congeniality talks tough</a>,” is what I want.  So here are the first six (blessedly short) paragraphs of it:
<div dir="ltr">“I’m a pretty friendly guy,” President Obama said near the end of his White House news conference Monday afternoon.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">The claim might have been a touch more plausible if he hadn’t spent the bulk of the previous hour demonstrating just how adversarial he could be. Indeed, there was no precipitating event that led him to schedule the last-minute session in the East Room — lending credibility to the theory that he summoned reporters so he could bait Republicans.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">“If congressional Republicans refuse to pay America’s bills on time, Social Security checks and veterans benefits will be delayed,” the friendly president said, explaining his refusal to negotiate over increasing the debt limit.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Calling the opposition’s stance “absurd,” Obama advised Republicans that they “have two choices here: They can act responsibly and pay America’s bills, or they can act irresponsibly and put America through another economic crisis. But they will not collect a ransom in exchange for not crashing the American economy. . . . And they better choose quickly, because time is running short.”</p>
</div>
<div dir="ltr">And that was just the opening statement. The hectoring continued through the Q&#038;A. Exactly one month after the massacre at an elementary school in Newtown, Conn., Obama said of debt-reduction talks: “What I will not do is to have that negotiation with a gun at the head of the American people.”</p>
</div>
<div dir="ltr">The Republicans’ view, President Congeniality added, “was rejected by the American people when it was debated during the presidential campaign. . . . But if the House Republicans disagree with that and they want to shut down the government to see if they can get their way on it, that’s their prerogative.”</div>
<p>I agree completely.  The president should never summon White House reporters to the White House press room in order to hold a press conference.  Or at least not to bait Republicans.</p>
<p>And, I guess, not even to respond to Republican daily baiting of him by falsely telling the public that a quirk in the law, requiring Congress to authorize the Treasury to pay the government’s already-incurred bills and bond interest, and pay such things as salaries to military personnel, air traffic controllers, Agriculture Department food inspectors, and Homeland Security airport marshals&#8211;not to mention not-yet-but-about-to-be owed Social Security payments, Medicaid payments to nursing homes, and Medicare payments to physicians and hospitals&#8211;is instead a request by the president and the Democrats in Congress to increase spending appropriations.  </p>
<p>No, sir.  Much better to allow the Republicans to prey on the public’s misunderstanding of the phrase “raise the debt ceiling.”   </p>
<p>Pass the ransom note, Republicans. Just do it through the mainstream media, as you have been doing.  They’ll happily repeat your message, <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/01/will-republicans-debt-ceiling-is-about.html">complete with disinformation</a>, without adding their own: a brief explanation of what the debt ceiling actually is.  Apparently, congressional reporters, unlike the White House press corp, don’t mind being summoned as bait.  Nor do the Sunday talk-show folk.  </p>
<p>Worms, all. </p>
<p>Milbank does allow that:</p>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Arguably, Obama’s no-more-Mr.-Nice-Guy approach is good politics. His first-term experience made clear that he gained nothing from Republicans when he took a passive approach. When it comes to getting things done in Washington, there’s no substitute for forceful presidential leadership. Teddy Roosevelt, whose oil-on-canvas likeness gazed at Obama from an East Room wall, probably would have approved.</div>
<p>Actually, not even just arguably, Milbank conflates statements of fact&#8211;in this instance, fact about what the debt ceiling is&#8211;with politics.  Certainly, correcting the opposition’s campaign of disinformation, and educating the public about a critical but technical statute that almost no one other than Washington pols, fiscal-policy wonks, and journalists who cover these people and subjects are familiar with, is damn good politics.  It is, in fact, absolutely necessary politics.  It’s dereliction-of-duty-for-failure-to-do-so politics.  </p>
<p>But statements of fact, and statements of policy based on the statements of fact, are not themselves mere politics.  They’re statements of fact and statements of policy based on those facts. </p>
<p>What’s most disturbing about this column is not that one high-profile political columnist confuses these things, but that he says that the entire White House press corp in attendance at the press conference yesterday does.  </p>
<p>So I suggest that they get out more.  Milbank, for example, might consider stepping out of Washington and into, maybe, Baltimore.  Not a long drive, really.  There, he could stop in at a coffee shop or mall and maybe ask people whether they had heard or read of Obama’s comments yesterday and, if so, whether they understood more now about the what debt ceiling statute is than they did a day before.</p>
<p>Then he can report his findings to the rest of the White House press corp.  And offer a different theory about the reason Obama summoned them to the press room yesterday.</p>
<p>Or he could <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/01/rep-greg-walden-r-or-explains-debt.html">just</a> <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/01/obama-we-are-not-deadbeat-nation-but.html">start</a> <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/01/see-harold-meyersons-washington-post.html">reading</a> <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/01/call-this-spade-spade-deadbeat-threat.html">Angry</a> <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/01/the-continued-necessity-of-explaining.html">Bear</a>.  </p>
<p>Seriously, I hope Paul Krugman and other “names” will expose Milbank’s argument for what it is. Obama has that tendency to cower whenever a media meme takes hold on fiscal-policy issues. Milbank and the White House press corp don’t read Angry Bear, but they might read Krugman’s blog. 
<div>  Nah; probably not.  It’s not like Krugman’s a centerist, or anything.  Still, it’s worth a shot, especially since what matters most is that Obama or someone close to him might.<br /> <i>This</i> Bear is <i>really</i> ANGRY today.</p>
<p>&#8212;-</p>
<p>&#8212;-</p>
<p>UPDATED:  Well, I woke up this morning to a few congratulatory emails, including from some Bears, telling me that Paul Krugman linked to my post yesterday <a href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/">in a blog post of his</a>.  Awesome!  (Thanks, Prof. Krugman.  And thanks to everyone for the congrats.)  </p>
<p>But I also want to republish here as an update an exchange between Bear JazzB. and me in the comments to the post:</p>
<div dir="ltr">JazzBumpa:   I always thought Milbank was more or less OK.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">But this is really stupid.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Me:  Milbank was terrific back when he was the Post’s WH correspondent during the first G.W. Bush term, JazzB. But he rarely writes anything in his column that I think is really insightful or informative, and sometimes he writes a column that’s just baffling. Like yesterday’s.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">What really dismays me is that he and some of the other “name” pundits flat-out missed the purpose of Obama’s Monday press conference. Obama was explaining what the debt ceiling law actually is&#8211;and what it is not. An explanation that was (and is) necessity because it’s a law that sounds like it means something that it does not, and that means something that it does not sound like it means&#8211;a fact that the Repubs have abused nearly every time one of them says anything publicly about it.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Dave Weigel <a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/politics/2013/01/barack_obama_s_last_first_term_press_conference_the_president_spoke_of_republicans.html">wrote</a> a [Politics article]* on Slate on Monday after the press conference that started out sounding like he missed the point&#8211;and then, wham!  He hit the nail on the head, pointing out that back in Sept. Obama said he planned to speak much more, directly, to the public and explain policy issues.  Weigel said that the Repubs mocked that then, but learned on Monday what he meant.  </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">And it does seem that the Repubs did learn a lot on Monday, because since then, several have publicly acknowledged that the debt ceiling game is over.  Yet Milbank and a few other pundits didn’t catch on.</div>
<p>And as long as I’m updating here, I’ll indulge myself and republish another exchange I had in the Comments to the post&#8211;this one with FastCommerce:</p>
<div dir="ltr">FastCommerce:  Worms. You an idiot.</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Me:  Oh, dear. FastCommerce, it looks like you took the BAIT.</div>
<p>So sorry, folks.  But I couldn’t resist.</p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />*In my original comment, I said Weigel wrote a blog post.  Actually, what he wrote was a full-length article, not a comment or short piece on his Slate blog.  (Those of us who are longtime Slate addicts know there’s a difference.)</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/what-dana-milbanks-stunningly-awful-column-today-reveals-about-the-washington-press-corps-updated.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Do ‘Right to Work’ Laws Violate the Constitution&#8217;s Article I Contracts Clause? [Updated]*</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/do-right-to-work-laws-violate-the-constitutions-article-i-contracts-clause-updated.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/do-right-to-work-laws-violate-the-constitutions-article-i-contracts-clause-updated.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2012 04:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[constitution]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Matthew Yglesias]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Right-to-Work laws]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/do-right-to-work-laws-violate-the-constitutions-article-i-contracts-clause-updated.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[No State shall enter into any Treaty, Alliance, or Confederation; grant Letters of Marque and Reprisal; coin Money; emit Bills of Credit; make any Thing but gold and silver Coin a Tender in Payment of Debts; pass any Bill of Attainder, ex post facto Law, or Law impairing the Obligation of Contracts, or grant any [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>No State shall enter into any Treaty, Alliance, or Confederation; grant Letters of Marque and Reprisal; coin Money; emit Bills of Credit; make any Thing but gold and silver Coin a Tender in Payment of Debts; pass any Bill of Attainder, ex post facto Law, or Law impairing the Obligation of Contracts, or grant any Title of Nobility.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212; Article I, Section 10, Constitution of the United States<br /><!--[if !supportLineBreakNewLine]--><br /><!--[endif]-->
</p>
</div>
<div>No, I didn’t post this to highlight the prohibition against states’ granting any title of nobility.  I posted it to highlight the prohibition against states’ enacting a law impairing the obligation of contracts—which the Supreme Court has interpreted as a guarantee of the right to freely enter into contracts.  </div>
<div></div>
<div>That guarantee does have exceptions, of course, none of which includes the type of contract that state so-called ‘right to work’ laws bar.  Including the ones passed today by the Michigan legislature, after springing out of nowhere last week.  (Although maybe the proponents of these laws think these statutes come within this exception created by the current Supreme Court’s majority: any law that helps corporations is constitutional.  It’s a corollary to the majority’s maxim that any federal statute, such as ones concerning compelled contractual arbitration, or labor unions, or federal-court jurisdiction, be distorted beyond plausible recognition of the statute’s actual language, if necessary, to favor corporations.  This is known by them as “originalism” and “textualism.”  And known by others, not all of whom are justices, as cute, pick-and-choose gimmickry.)
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>But as Slate’s Matthew Yglesias <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/moneybox/2012/12/11/right_to_work_laws_stunning_hypocrisy.html">points out</a> today, what these bills do is use the force of law—state law—to interfere with the right of contract between two private parties: labor unions and private employers.  In Michigan, the legislature actually passed two separate laws today: one pertaining to labor contracts between labor unions and private employers, the other pertaining to contracts between labor unions and public employers (i.e., state and local governments).  But as a constitutional matter, this doesn’t matter.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Yglesias points out what does matter, although he argues it only as a matter of hypocrisy, not as a possible violation of constitutional law.  After saying that the concrete economic impact of these statutes is murky—something that Paul Krugman and most Angry Bears would dispute (and have disputed)—he hits the nail on the head about the actual nature of these laws:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>[What is] not murky is the absurd hypocrisy that has to go into making the case for right-to-work legislation.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The way this works is that if there&#8217;s a labor union at a given business establishment that&#8217;s bargaining for some higher pay or benefits or better work-rules or whatever it&#8217;s rapidly going to find that there&#8217;s a free rider problem. Everyone in the relevant class of workers gets the benefits whether or not they join the union. So something the union is often going to want to bargain for is some kind of rule stating that everyone hired in the relevant class has to join the union, or has to pay dues to the union, or something else along those lines.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Now naturally an employer&#8217;s not going to want to agree to that. But he&#8217;s not going to want to agree to higher pay or more vacation days either. That&#8217;s why it&#8217;s a negotiation. A right-to-work law is a law <em>banning</em> employers from making that concession.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The impact, obviously, is to make it hard to form strong unions in a given jurisdiction and thus make it a more business-friendly jurisdiction. But note that this same trick works across the board. You could just ban pay raises in general. Any one firm, after all, faces a dilemma. On the one hand it would be more profitable to pay people less. On the other hand, it&#8217;s also unprofitable to have everyone quit to go work for some other higher-paying company. So a law against pay raises would make everyone more profitable, spurring crazy business investment and job creation. Except nobody does that because it would be (a) insane and (b) obviously unfair. And yet the proponents of right-to-work laws are generally <em>exactly</em> the people most inclined to stand up for freedom of contract under other circumstances.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And yet the proponents of right-to-work laws are generally <em>exactly</em> the people most inclined to stand up for freedom of contract under other circumstances, indeed.  They do this standing up in legislatures, think tanks, and lobbying firms.  And in court, including the Supreme one.  Some of them doing this standing from the black-robes-wearing, comfortable-leather-chair-sitting side of the courtroom bench.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Now that the gauntlet has been thrown, labor should pick it up and take it to court.  There is, I think, little doubt that these laws impair the obligation of <i>current</i> labor contracts and also impinge upon the right to freely enter into contracts.  The proponents of these laws will defend them on the ground that state laws impairing the obligation of this particular type of contract isn’t what the framers had in mind.  And undoubtedly they’re right; it’s a historical fact that the Washington, Madison, and the others considered union organizing <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/the_slatest/2012/10/05/justice_scalia_the_textualist_scotus_justice_explains_stance_on_abortion_gay_rights_.html">right up there with sodomy and murder</a> as unprotected by the Fourteenth Amendment, which they foresaw would be added to the Constitution a few decades later, or by the clause in Article 1, Section 10, prohibiting states from impairing the obligation of contracts. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>But labor unions still should challenge the constitutionality of these laws, even if they have to try to convince the courts, and eventually <i>the </i>Court, that the laws are Letters of Marque and Reprisal. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Which, at least regarding the Reprisal part, sounds about right. 
</p>
<p>&#8212;-</p>
<p>UPDATE: Excellent, thorough article by Rick Ungar in Forbes today, titled “<a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/rickungar/2012/12/11/right-to-work-laws-explained-debunked-demystified/">‘</a><a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/rickungar/2012/12/11/right-to-work-laws-explained-debunked-demystified/">Right-to-Work’ Laws Explained, Debunked &#038; Demystified.</a>&#8221;  Don&#8217;t miss it.</p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />*I just posted a lengthy follow-up post, <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/12/follow-up-to-do-right-to-work-laws.html">here</a>.</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/do-right-to-work-laws-violate-the-constitutions-article-i-contracts-clause-updated.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Victory for the Reality-Based Community! Oh, Know! Er, Oh, No!</title>
		<link>./../../2012/11/a-victory-for-the-reality-based-community-oh-know-er-oh-no.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/11/a-victory-for-the-reality-based-community-oh-know-er-oh-no.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 09 Nov 2012 19:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Phillip Rucker]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Washington Post]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[William Saletan]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/11/a-victory-for-the-reality-based-community-oh-know-er-oh-no.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Every four years, the race for the White House ends in accusations of deceit. Each side says the other spent millions of dollars to lie and skew the outcome. This year’s post-election accounts of backstage calculations and fateful turning points continue that tradition. But if you read these accounts carefully, you’ll find a happy surprise [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>Every four years, the race for the White House ends in accusations of deceit. Each side says the other spent millions of dollars to lie and skew the outcome. This year’s post-election accounts of backstage calculations and fateful turning points continue that tradition. But if you read these accounts carefully, you’ll find a happy surprise beneath the spin and recriminations: Lies failed. Truth prevailed.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212; <i><a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/frame_game/2012/11/_2012_election_facts_in_the_obama_romney_showdown_truth_beat_lies_and_spin.html#comments">The Power of Truth: In the 2012 election,reality overwhelmed pretense, gamesmanship, and self-deception.</a></i>, William Saletan, Slate, today
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Saletan goes on to discuss the several critical points during the campaign that pundits say are what ultimately led to Romney’s defeat, including the impact of Hurricane Sandy and of Romney’s appalling Jeep-jobs-to-China ad in Ohio last week.  You know, the one that said, “<a href="http://www.politifact.com/truth-o-meter/statements/2012/oct/30/mitt-romney/mitt-romney-obama-chrysler-sold-italians-china-ame/" target="_blank">Obama took GM and Chrysler into bankruptcy and sold Chrysler to Italians who are going to build Jeeps in China</a>.”
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Saletan points to a delicious comment by a Romney fundraiser<a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/decision2012/life-after-defeat-for-mitt-romney-public-praise-private-questions/2012/11/07/4db3bc38-2916-11e2-96b6-8e6a7524553f_story.html"> to Washington Post reporterPhillip Rucker</a>—“A lot of people feel like Christie hurt, that we definitely lost four or five points between the storm and Chris Christie giving Obama a chance to be bigger than life,” a Romney fundraiser tells Rucker”—and nicely refutes its premise, voiced also by numerous pundits during the last week.  He points out that Obama wasn’t <i>acting</i>, or <i>looking</i>, presidential.  He was instead <i>being</i> presidential; he was performing his job.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Saletan’s article in mostly terrific.  But it—like most of the other pundit assessments—fails to mention the <i>actual</i> key factor for why Hurricane Sandy made it impossible for Romney to win: That the public learned of Romney’s primary-campaign statement that he wanted to remove disaster relief and all sorts of other federal programs as a federal responsibilities and place the responsibility for them on the states.  The very premise of this surely struck a large percentage of the population as nutty.  This ideology was at the very heart of Romney’s campaign, yet most people didn’t know that until a week before the election. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The Sandy effect, in other words, had less to do with Obama’s “looking presidential” than Obama’s being presidential, as Saletan notes, but that’s because the public learned then pretty much what the difference was between Obama’s idea of what the federal government, rather than the states, should do.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Another important factor was, as this article and many others point out, Romney’s appalling ad last week in Ohio about Chrysler and Jeep, but I think the ad’s importance went even beyond the obvious problem that it intended to perpetuate a clearly erroneous fact.  Everyone in any way connected to the auto industry knows that Chrysler could not have survived at all without its purchase by Fiat.  Everyone who is currently employed because of Chrysler’s continued existence—including employees of Chrysler’s parts suppliers—knows that there would be no Chrysler, and therefore no Jeep jobs to be sent to China, or not—were it not for the sale of Chrysler to Fiat. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>So the ad, in addition to being flatly false in suggesting that the Jeep factory in Toledo was being shuttered, made no sense.  And it made no sense in a way that everyone recognized made no sense.  The ad, although it ran only in Ohio, got lots of publicity nationwide because the auto executives’ stunned and angry refutation, and Obama’s comments in Toledo about the ad, were big political news around the country.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The only conceivable reason that the Romney campaign gambled by putting out an ad that so obviously could backfire exactly as it did is that they already knew they were losing in Ohio and were willing to try, literally, anything.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>These two factors, the hurricane and the Toledo Jeep factory, both of them coming in the closing ten days of the campaign, actually summed up the Romney campaign: mendacity as its prime <i>modus operandi,</i>and Tea Party ideology, <i>both</i> of which depend upon a concerted removal from the fact-based world.  
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I suspect that it will be a long time before another Republican presidential nominee tries either of these.  At least until he or she is inaugurated. 
</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/11/a-victory-for-the-reality-based-community-oh-know-er-oh-no.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Public Learns Disaster Relief Was Etched Out of the Sketch. Uh-Oh.</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/the-public-learns-disaster-relief-was-etched-out-of-the-sketch-uh-oh.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/the-public-learns-disaster-relief-was-etched-out-of-the-sketch-uh-oh.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 29 Oct 2012 20:46:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Bill Keller]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[disaster relief]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Etch-A-Sketch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[FEMA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Matthew Yglesias]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New York Times]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/the-public-learns-disaster-relief-was-etched-out-of-the-sketch-uh-oh.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[MITT ROMNEY: &#8220;Every time you have an occasion to take something from the federal government and send it back to the states, that&#8217;s the right direction. And if you can go even further, and send it back to the private sector, that&#8217;s even better. Instead of thinking, in the federal budget, what we should cut, [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>MITT ROMNEY: &#8220;Every time you have an occasion to take something from the federal government and send it back to the states, that&#8217;s the right direction. And if you can go even further, and send it back to the private sector, that&#8217;s even better. Instead of thinking, in the federal budget, what we should cut, we should ask the opposite question, what should we keep?&#8221;
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>DEBATE MODERATOR JOHN KING: Including disaster relief, though?&#8221;
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>ROMNEY: We cannot &#8212; we cannot afford to do those things without jeopardizing the future for our kids. It is simply immoral, in my view, for us to continue to rack up larger and larger debts and pass them on to our kids, knowing full well that we&#8217;ll all be dead and gone before it&#8217;s paid off. It makes no sense at all.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212; <i>Republican primary campaign debate last year
</p>
<p></i></div>
<div></div>
<div>Slate’s Matthew Yglesias points to that today <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/moneybox/2012/10/29/romney_s_fema_cuts.html">andcomments</a>:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>More prosaically, though the Romney campaign was understandably <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/10/28/mitt-romney-fema_n_2036198.html" target="_blank">circumspect over the weekend about his spending plans</a> the fact is that his overall budget requires sharp cuts in everything. The central issue is that Romney wants to cap government spending at 20 percent of GDP while boosting military spending to 4 percent of GDP and leaving Social Security harmless. That <a href="http://www.cbpp.org/cms/?fa=view&#038;id=3658" target="_blank">means a 34 percent across-the-board cut in other programs</a> according to the Center on Budget and Policy Priorities. Unless, that is, Medicare is also exempted from the cuts in which case you&#8217;d need a 53 percent cut. …
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>If a storm damages basic physical infrastructure (power lines, bridges) and imperils human life it would be the height of penny-wise, pound-foolish thinking to suppose that the afflicted area should wait months or years to repair the damage. Ultimately, anyplace is going to go back to robust wealth creation faster if basic stuff gets fixed up faster. But that requires financing by an entity capable of rapidly financing expensive projects—i.e., the federal government. Left to its own devices a storm-ravaged Delaware or Louisiana is going to be squeezed between balanced budget rules and falling sales tax receipts and be forced into an increasing state of dilapidation.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>How about a storm-ravaged <i>Florida</i>?  According to current polls, slightly more than half of Florida voters want their state to take over disaster relief, at least until arrangements can be made for the private sector to take it over.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And, about that question Romney asked: What should we KEEP?  Well, in addition to the Bush tax cuts for the wealthy and defense spending for private contractors, what DOES Romney think we should keep?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>We cannot – we cannot afford to do things like disaster relief without jeopardizing the future of our kids.  We CAN, though, afford to give massive additional tax cuts to the wealthy, and huge additional contracts to Republican defense contractors, without jeopardizing the future of our kids.  Right?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>What’s truly unconscionable is that it’s taking Hurricane Sandy to educate the public about the plans Romney and Ryan have stated so clearly.  I’ve been utterly unable to understand why the Obama campaign hasn’t been running video clips of Romney’s primary-campaign statements as the foundation of their ads.  I’ve thought all along that this is all Obama would need to do in order to win.  I think Sandy will prove me right.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And, here’s a shout-out to New York Time columnist Bill Keller for <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/10/29/opinion/keller-the-no-agenda-myth.html?_r=0">exposing for the absurd myth that it is</a> the punditry’s “in” refrain that we don’t know what either of the two candidates would use the office to do in the next four years, because, well, neither has specified sufficiently.  As Keller says, actually <i>both</i> have specified sufficiently. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And Romney’s <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/10/did-romney-begin-to-reverse-etch-sketch.html">already begun to reverse-sketch his etchings</a>.  Suffice it to say that he’s not spent the last week promising “BIG CHANGE” because he plans to etch out of his sketch all those primary-campaign promises. 
</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/the-public-learns-disaster-relief-was-etched-out-of-the-sketch-uh-oh.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Quiet Fact That Obama Should SHOUT About</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/the-quiet-fact-that-obama-should-shout-about.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/the-quiet-fact-that-obama-should-shout-about.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Oct 2012 17:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Consumer Financial Protection Bureau]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Edward Wyatt]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Katharine Q. Seelye]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New York Times]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/the-quiet-fact-that-obama-should-shout-about.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Two articles published late yesterday in the New York Times, when juxtaposed with each other, pretty much encapsulate my frustration with this campaign.  One, titled “New Federal Rules for Debt Collectors,” by Edward Wyatt, reports: Debt collection agencies, whose sometimes aggressive tactics have earned them scrutiny from consumer protection groups and state regulators, will come [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>Two articles published late yesterday in the New York Times, when juxtaposed with each other, pretty much encapsulate my frustration with this campaign.  One, titled “<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/10/24/business/new-federal-rules-for-debt-collectors.html?partner=rss&#038;emc=rss&#038;src=ig&#038;pagewanted=print">New Federal Rules for Debt Collectors</a>,” by Edward Wyatt, reports:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Debt collection agencies, whose sometimes aggressive tactics have earned them scrutiny from consumer protection groups and state regulators, will come under federal supervision for the first time beginning Jan. 2, when the <a href="http://topics.nytimes.com/top/reference/timestopics/organizations/c/consumer_financial_protection_bureau/index.html?inline=nyt-org" title="More articles about the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection.">Consumer Financial Protection Bureau</a> begins oversight.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The next several paragraphs of the article say:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>In addition to companies that specialize in collecting money from consumers for personal, family or household debt, the consumer bureau will begin monitoring debt collectors that contract with the Education Department to collect overdue <a href="http://topics.nytimes.com/top/reference/timestopics/subjects/s/student_loans/index.html?inline=nyt-classifier" title="More articles about student loans.">student loans</a>. The department has more than $850 billion in student loans outstanding, officials said.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>“Millions of consumers are affected by debt collection, and we want to make sure they are treated fairly,” Richard Cordray, the director of the consumer bureau, said in a statement issued before the public release of the bureau’s rules on Wednesday. “We want all companies to realize that the better business choice is to follow the law — not break it.”
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The authority to oversee debt collection agencies comes under the portion of the Dodd-Frank regulatory law that deals with so-called nonbank financial companies.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The consumer agency will examine companies to ensure that they properly identify themselves to consumers and properly disclose the amount of debt owed. In addition, collectors must have a process to resolve disputes and communicate “civilly and honestly” with consumers.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Wow, I said to myself when I read the article last night.  Obama will mention this when he campaigns in Ohio, in Virginia, in Nevada.  Especially, please, in Ohio and Nevada. And all of us who are on the “list-serve” of the campaign will receive notice of the article.  Or at least of the fact that the article is about.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>But we didn’t.  Instead, we received a lot of stuff about the Mourdock controvery and about Romney’s refusal to withdraw his support of Mourdock.  Which was fine, but not to the exclusion of the subject of the Wyatt article.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Wyatt is not a political reporter or pundit.  He’s a hard-news reporter, and in that article he reported hard facts.  Katharine Q. Seelye, who wrote the other Times article that got my attention, <i>is</i> a political reporter.  Her article is titled “<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/10/25/us/politics/female-swing-voters-a-coveted-demographic.html?pagewanted=all">Crucial Subset: Female Voters Still Deciding</a>,” and it focuses on what she terms “waitress moms.”  Seelye’s report is from New Hampshire.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Indeed.  What Obama needs most in swing states such as Ohio, Nevada, Virginia and New Hampshire is to have white so-called working-class voters—men and woman—step into the voting booth and quietly, maybe even suddenly, decide to vote for <i>him</i>.  And the way to do that, at least with respect to those whose main concern is their own precarious economic situation, is to highlight concrete facts that actually could matter all-too-concretely in their lives. 
</p>
</div>
<div><a name="more"></a></div>
<div>Like the <a href="http://topics.nytimes.com/top/reference/timestopics/organizations/c/consumer_financial_protection_bureau/index.html?inline=nyt-org" title="More articles about the Bureau of Consumer Financial Protection.">Consumer Financial Protection Bureau</a> and other important legislation and regulations that limits the power of banks and other financial institutions, and that Romney surely will try to reverse.  What about the law that became effective in the summer of 2011 that significantly limits bank fees, for example on checking account inadvertent overdrafts—something that matters even to people who are not waitress moms?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>PrioritiesUSA, the pro-Obama PAC, has <a href="http://youtu.be/TZlu2f_8gk4">a new ad</a> that I love.  But so many of the pro-Obama ads lately have left me really frustrated, because they mostly focus on some particular phrase rather than on making a point of fact.  Slate yesterday had <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/the_slatest/2012/10/24/romney_s_nyt_op_ed_on_detroit_let_detroit_go_bankrupt_tops_nyt_most_read.html">an article </a>about Romney’s infamous Nov. 18, 2008 “Let Detroit Fail” New York Times op-ed, and that a huge number of people accepted Romney’s and Obama’s Monday-night invitation to check out the op-ed itself.  In a comment to the Slate article, I wrote:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>What bothers me even more than that Romney is lying about what his position is is that this is the guy who claims that his business expertise shows that he knows how to create 12 million jobs.  <br /> <br />This guy who thought a federal bailout by the Bush administration to tide the companies over, and who thought that the bailout in early 2009, would virtually guarantee the demise of the Big Three, is so adept at understanding business and how to create jobs that he should become president, on that basis??? <br /> <br />Why on earth the Obama campaign isn&#8217;t putting up ads on this is a real mystery to me.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>To which someone responded that the campaign was doing just that in Michigan and Ohio. To which I replied:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>No, the ads focus only on the &#8220;Let Detroit go bankrupt&#8221; language&#8211;which lets Romney get away with doing an &#8220;It depends on what the meaning of &#8216;bankruptcy&#8217; is&#8221; routine. That&#8217;s soooo not enough to make Obama&#8217;s point.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The polls now are looking like enough people are figuring this out for themselves; the op-ed speaks for itself, quite well, thank you very much.  And Obama’s current focus on trust—pointing out that the words “trust” and “Romney” are mutually exclusive—is terrific.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>But Obama could put this election away within the next few days with a few clearly-stated, specific facts of this sort, in ads and in campaign appearances.  
</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/the-quiet-fact-that-obama-should-shout-about.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Jim Lehrer Wins the Debate?? Heaven Help Us.</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/jim-lehrer-wins-the-debate-heaven-help-us.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/jim-lehrer-wins-the-debate-heaven-help-us.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2012 19:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[David Weigel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[debate moderator's role]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jim Lehrer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/jim-lehrer-wins-the-debate-heaven-help-us.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[And a debate is a perfect place to spit out numbers and plan names without a moderator fact-checking you. &#8212;  Paul Ryan’s Word Salad, David Weigel, Slate, today Indeed. I was absolutely dumbfounded to read yesterday that the MSM is now buying Lehrer’s idea of what a debate should be. Do they not understand that [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>And a debate is a perfect place to spit out numbers and plan names without a moderator fact-checking you.
</p>
</div>
<div>&#8212;  <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/weigel/2012/10/11/paul_ryan_s_word_salad.html"><i>Paul Ryan’s Word Salad</i>, David Weigel</a>, Slate, today</p>
<p>Indeed.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I was absolutely dumbfounded to read yesterday that the MSM is now buying Lehrer’s idea of what a debate should be. Do they not understand that these are not actually debates—that they are instead simply statements by each of the candidates? Yes, both candidates are on the stage. But they don’t get to talk to <i>each other</i>. They don’t get to question—to cross-examine—<i>each other</i>. </div>
<div>How, then, is it a good idea to have a format in which the moderator just says, “Your turn to talk about your plan on taxes, Mr. Romney,” and lets him spout off nonsense, unabated by questions from <i>anyone</i> about specifics and about how what he says could possibly add up? </div>
<div></div>
<div>Do tell, MSM pundits. Also tell, MSM pundits, why you are so stupefyingly gullible.  </div>
<div></div>
<div>I mean … good grace. </div>
<div></div>
<div>In fact, Jim Lehrer did win the debate.  The one last Wednesday.  That doesn&#8217;t seem to me like a recommendation for his method, though.</div>
<div></div>
</p>
<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/jim-lehrer-wins-the-debate-heaven-help-us.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Mad Hatter For President! (Pleeease, Obama campaign, do a Halloween Fun-House ad. Pleeeease.)</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/the-mad-hatter-for-president-pleeease-obama-campaign-do-a-halloween-fun-house-ad-pleeeease.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/the-mad-hatter-for-president-pleeease-obama-campaign-do-a-halloween-fun-house-ad-pleeeease.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2012 18:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Halloween]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Josh Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lewis Carroll. Obama campaign]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mad Hatter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[William Saletan]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/the-mad-hatter-for-president-pleeease-obama-campaign-do-a-halloween-fun-house-ad-pleeeease.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Have you heard the news? Mitt Romney met with editors of the Des Moines Register yesterday and dropped a bombshell. “Romney promises no abortion legislation,” says the Associated Press. “Romney: No abortion legislation,” says Politico. “Romney says no plans to restrict abortion,” says Agence France-Presse. Nope. That isn’t what Romney said. This is a man with a long history [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>Have you heard the news? Mitt Romney met with editors of the <em>Des Moines Register</em> yesterday and dropped a bombshell. “<a href="http://news.yahoo.com/romney-promises-no-abortion-legislation-004508435--election.html" target="_blank">Romney promises no abortion legislation</a>,” says the Associated Press. “<a href="http://www.politico.com/news/stories/1012/82225.html" target="_blank">Romney: No abortion legislation</a>,” says <em>Politico</em>. “<a href="http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5gS9JzyIMR83DWX2o5_NqwCA1YO8Q" target="_blank">Romney says no plans to restrict abortion</a>,” says Agence France-Presse.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Nope. That isn’t what Romney said. This is a man with a <a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/the_conversion/2012/02/mitt_romney_s_abortion_record_flip_flop_or_conversion_.html">long history of using technicalities to disguise his abortion views</a>. You have to read his exact words, with attention to the loopholes. So let’s back up and <a href="http://blogs.desmoinesregister.com/dmr/index.php/2012/10/09/mitt-romney-on-his-tax-cut-plan-the-math-works#fullaudio" target="_blank">listen to the full audio</a> of Romney’s remarks.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212; <i><a href="http://why/">Romney’s Abortion “Agenda”:  Don’t fall for his insinuation that he won’t restrict abortion. It’s full of weasel words</a>, </i>William Saletan, Slate, today</div>
<div></div>
<div>Saletan goes on to summarize what he brilliantly calls Romney’s Massachusetts-pol-days use of escape-clause language on the abortion issue—how he would calculatingly <i>appear</i> to state a position and then, for the sake of political expedience,  renege and point to some hedge he’d included in the contract—er, the campaign promise. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Saletan concludes his article by warning, “That’s why you need to spot the weasel words up front. In the end, with Romney, they’re all that matters.”
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Well, yes. That’s true on <i>every</i> issue, not just on that one.  We’re dealing here with the Mad Hatter.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>One of Romney’s sons, Josh,<a href="http://livewire.talkingpointsmemo.com/entry/josh-romney-dad-learned-how-to-debate-obstinate--1"> said yesterday</a> in an interview that Obama had lied about Romney’s positions.  The son was restating, but even more clearly, the father’s debate claim that Obama keeps stubbornly claiming that Romney has proposed things that Romney hasn’t proposed.  Except that Romney in fact has, repeatedly, proposed those things—like cutting taxes (not just tax rate, replaced with the closing of loopholes, but <i>tax payments</i>) for the wealthy by 20%.</p>
<p>This Orwellian strategy of saying that the person who says you said something you said is an “obstinate child” (Josh’s phrase) who is “lying” (Josh’s word) is downright scary.  It’s a direct attempt to pervert democracy. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The news media really, really, <i>really</i> should point that out.  Cleary.  But the Obama campaign needs to, too.  More effectively than it has in the last week. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And what better than a Halloween fun house—ghosts suddenly jumping out of nowhere; the floor suddenly dropping out from under you; fake smoke and real mirrors that distort your body shape (or his)—to illustrate the point?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Oh, and Romney’s Halloween costume?  The Mad Hatter, of course.  Romney wearing it to go trick-or-treating while spouting lines written by Lewis Carroll.  And by Josh Romney.  Who’s now made himself fair game.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/the-mad-hatter-for-president-pleeease-obama-campaign-do-a-halloween-fun-house-ad-pleeeease.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
