<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Dean Baker &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Worms, Pond Scum and Economists</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/worms-pond-scum-and-economists.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/worms-pond-scum-and-economists.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2013 10:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dean Baker]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security for the young]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/worms-pond-scum-and-economists.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Dean Baker writes Worms, Pond Scum and Economists The effort to blame the awful plight of the young on Social Security and Medicare is picking up steam.In the last week, there were several pieces in The Washington Post and The New York Times that either implicitly or explicitly blamed older workers and retirees for the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://truth-out.org/news/item/15167-worms-pond-scum-and-economists" title="http://truth-out.org/news/item/15167-worms-pond-scum-and-economists">Dean Baker writes</a><br /><strong><br />
<blockquote></blockquote>
<p></strong> <strong>Worms, Pond Scum and Economists</strong></p>
<p>The effort to blame the awful plight of the young on Social Security and Medicare is picking up steam.<br />In the last week, there were several pieces in <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/%20%20blogs/wonkblog/wp/2013/03/15/yes-raising-the-retirement-age-would-be-bad-for-the-poor-no-that-%20%20doesnt-mean-its-unfair/">The Washington Post </a>and <a href="http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/03/14/stop-%20%20stealing-from-our-kids/">The New York Times</a> that either implicitly or explicitly blamed older workers and retirees for the bad economic plight facing young people today. There is now a full-court press to cut Social Security and Medicare benefits, ostensibly out of a desire to help young workers today and in the future.</p>
<p>Just to be clear, there is no doubt that young workers face dismal economic prospects at the moment.</p>
<p>…</p>
<p>This means that young people today can expect many more years of dire labor market conditions, because the remedies that could turn around their job situations have been blocked by nonsense spewing from economists. Incidentally, this situation works out very nicely for those on top, who are enjoying the benefits of record-high profit shares, which have also helped to fuel a soaring stock market.<br />The failure to see the largest asset bubble in the history of the world, coupled with the failure to prescribe an effective remedy to deal with the damage, should be sufficient to earn the economics profession the contempt of right-thinking people everywhere. But there is nothing too low for this group of professionals.</p>
<p>We are now seeing economists joining the crusade to cut Social Security and Medicare by implicitly or explicitly claiming that these programs are somehow responsible for the dismal economic plight of the young. The argument is that we can only free up money for helping our young if we take money from the old, a group with a median income of $20,000 a year.</p>
<p>By contrast, the upward redistribution of income to the richest 1 percent is equal to 10 percentage points of national income, or more than $1.3 trillion a year. To put this in the ten-year-budget-window context that dominates Washington debate, the amount that has been redistributed upward will be more than $16 trillion over the next decade. And that is based on the heroic assumption that the upward redistribution does not continue.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/worms-pond-scum-and-economists.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Housing wealth effect, Baker, Goldfarb and Waldmann</title>
		<link>./../../2012/11/housing-wealth-effect-baker-goldfarb-and-waldmann.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/11/housing-wealth-effect-baker-goldfarb-and-waldmann.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 24 Nov 2012 15:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dean Baker]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Robert Waldmann]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/11/housing-wealth-effect-baker-goldfarb-and-waldmann.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Robert Waldmann Everything is possible and I think that Dean Baker just lost a debate with a Washington Post reporter.  Post reporter Zachary A. Goldfarb  wrote The two economists compared what happened in U.S. counties where people had amassed huge debts with those where people had borrowed little. It had long been thought that [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Robert Waldmann</p>
<p>Everything is possible and I think that Dean Baker just lost a debate with a Washington Post reporter.<br />   <br />Post reporter Zachary A. Goldfarb  <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/business/economy/economists-obama-administration-at-odds-over-role-of-mortgage-debt-in-slow-recovery/2012/11/22/dc83f25e-2e87-11e2-89d4-040c9330702a_story.html">wrote</a></p>
<blockquote><p><a href="http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=1961211">The two economists compared what happened in U.S. counties where people had amassed huge debts with those where people had borrowed little.</a> It had long been thought that when property values declined in value, homeowners would spend less because they would feel less wealthy. <br />But Mian and Sufi’s research showed something more specific and powerful at work: People who owed huge debts when their home values declined cut back dramatically on buying cars, appliances, furniture and groceries. The more they owed, the less they spent. People with little debt hardly slowed spending at all.</p></blockquote>
<p>among other things.  The link is his.  </p>
<p>Dean Baker <a href="http://www.cepr.net/index.php/blogs/beat-the-press/underwater-homeowners-cannot-explain-the-weak-recovery">wrote</a>  <br />
<blockquote>The <a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?hl=en&#038;q=housing+wealth+effect&#038;btnG=&#038;as_sdt=1%2C9&#038;as_sdtp=">housing wealth</a> effect is one of the oldest and most widely accepted concepts in economics. It is generally estimated people spend between 5 and 7 cents each year per dollar of housing wealth. This means that the collapse of the bubble would be expected to cost the economy between $400 billion and $560 billion in annual demand. </p></blockquote>
<p>among other things  Again the link is his.<br />   <br />Baker&#8217;s main point is that low consumption by underwater home owners is not a plausible explanation of the sluggish recovery.  However, he also confidently asserts that the housing wealth effect is linear based on &#8220;google it&#8221;.  I think that he has decided that new empirical research is irrelevant, because he already knew how economies work.<br />    <br />My comment below the fold.</p>
<p>In the comment I define your disagreement with post reporter  Zachary A. Goldfarb as a disagreement about whether reduced but still positive home equity causes a reduction of consumption on the order of between 5 and 7 cents each year per dollar of housing wealth or on the order of zero.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a>    <br />That is, I won&#8217;t address you valid points that the recovery of consumption was roughly normal while the recovery of house construction was not.</p>
<p>Notably Goldfarb cites empirical estimates based on micro data.  He claims there is a significant change in the slope of the home equity effect on consumption at home equity equals zero.  To say he is wrong, you must convince me that the 5 to 7 % estimate is valid for a sample containing only homeowners with positive equity.<br />    <br />An estimate with aggregate data just does not address the claim in the article which you criticize.    <br />Notably, in this case the Washington Post cites specific research by named economists.  You, in contrast, cite what all macroeconomists know.<br />    <br />I am shocked to find that I call this one for The Washington Post.  Your conclusion may be correct, but your reasoning is based on the assumption that all functions are linear.  I don&#8217;t like to be square, but that&#8217;s not true.</p>
<p>cross posted with  <a href="http://rjwaldmann.blogspot.com/2012/11/i-beat-beat-press.html">Robert&#8217;s Stochastic thoughts</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/11/housing-wealth-effect-baker-goldfarb-and-waldmann.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Big government pushed by the right</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/big-government-pushed-by-the-right.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/big-government-pushed-by-the-right.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 02 Jul 2012 11:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dean Baker]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[liberals]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/big-government-pushed-by-the-right.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Dean Baker notes that liberals have let the right wing get away with the small government mythology&#8230; It is astounding how liberals are so happy to work for the right by implying that conservatives somehow just want to leave markets to themselves whereas the liberals want to bring in the pointy-headed bureaucrats to tell people [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a target="_blank" href="http://www.cepr.net/index.php/publications/books/the-end-of-loser-liberalism">Dean Baker</a> notes that liberals have let the right wing get away with the small government mythology&#8230;</p>
<blockquote><blockquote>It is astounding how liberals are so happy to work for the right by implying that conservatives somehow just want to leave markets to themselves whereas the liberals want to bring in the pointy-headed bureaucrats to tell people what they should do. This view is, of course, nonsense. Pick an issue, any issue, and you will almost invariably find the right actively pushing for a big role for government.<br />&#8230;These TBTF banks operate with an implicit subsidy from the government. Lenders expect the government to step in to back up these banks&#8217; debt if they fail, as happened on a massive basis in 2008. As a result, TBTF banks can borrow money at lower interest rates than would be possible in a free market.<br />&#8230;To take another easy example, drug patents raise the price of prescription drugs by close to $270 billion a year above their free-market price. This is roughly five Bush tax cuts to the wealthy&#8230;<br />&#8230;Patents imply very big government since the government will imprison anyone who produces a drug without the patent holder&#8217;s consent. In recent years, big government has been actively working to extend Pfizer&#8217;s and Merck&#8217;s patent monopolies to the rest of the world through NAFTA, CAFTA, and other recent trade deals.<br />&#8230;While the government has been using the banner of &#8220;free trade&#8221; to drive down the wages of manufacturing workers, it has simultaneously been increasing the protection afforded doctors in order to prevent any similar downward pressure on their wages&#8230;</p></blockquote>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/big-government-pushed-by-the-right.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Social Security &#8216;Reform&#8217;: the Undead Return</title>
		<link>./../../2009/01/social-security-reform-the-undead-return.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2009/01/social-security-reform-the-undead-return.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2009 22:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Dean Baker]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul Krugman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[social security]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2009/01/social-security-reform-the-undead-return.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[by Bruce WebbWhat does it take? A stake through the heart? A bullet through the brain? Baker and Krugman do some pushback.Dean Baker in his post The Post&#8217;s Jihad against Social Security points to this article Obama Predicts Years of Deficits over $1 trillion and notes that they don&#8217;t hesitate to single out the usual [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>by Bruce Webb<br />What does it take? A stake through the heart? A bullet through the brain? Baker and Krugman do some pushback.<br />Dean Baker in his post <a target="_blank" href="http://www.prospect.org/csnc/blogs/beat_the_press_archive?month=01&#038;year=2009&#038;base_name=the_posts_jihad_against_social">The Post&#8217;s Jihad against Social Security</a> points to this article <a target="_blank" href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2009/01/06/AR2009010602849.html">Obama Predicts Years of Deficits over $1 trillion</a> and notes that they don&#8217;t hesitate to single out the usual suspect. Is it the cost of the war? The cost of the bailout? The cost of the stimulus package? Nope apparently those are just short term problems. Instead as always the first stop for deficit reform is Social Security.<br />
<blockquote>WaPo: The mounting debt has raised an alarm on Capitol Hill, where some Republicans and moderate Democrats are pressing Obama to tackle the looming challenge of skyrocketing Medicare and Social Security spending, and to adopt tough new budget rules to prevent future deficits from ballooning.</p></blockquote>
<p> Which leads Dean to reply with some exasperation:<br />
<blockquote>The article includes a comment about &#8220;the looming challenge of skyrocketing Medicare and Social Security spending. &#8221; Of course Social Security spending is not projected to skyrocket. It is projected to increase gradually, and its costs are fully covered by its own tax stream until 2048, according to the Congressional Budget Office&#8217;s latest projections.</p></blockquote>
<p>In a related note Paul Krugman poses the question in a Jan 5 post <a target="_blank" href="http://krugman.blogs.nytimes.com/2009/01/05/a-bullet-dodged/">A Bullet Dodged</a><br />
<blockquote>What would have happened if George W. Bush had actually succeeded in his plan to privatize Social Security?</p></blockquote>
<p> and suggests an answer &#8216;Ask the Italians&#8217; <a target="_blank" href="http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=20601109&#038;sid=aty4gEh9wups&#038;refer=home">Bloomberg News: Italian Pensions Sapped by Private Funds Bush Backed</a></p>
<p>In my view it is practically criminal for policy makers to be wasting a second talking about Social Security given the very real possiblity we are headed for a new Great Depression. And so equally criminal for opinion makers to be twisting current events to pursue this old vendetta. It is a shame that people like Baker and Krugman still have to keep a vigilant eye out for the zombies intent on eating the flesh of Social Security. Maybe we can make a deal. If the Right will simply stop taking every possible opportunity to take a bite at Social Security then I promise to shut up. And then maybe we can let Krugman and Baker continue the really important discussion.</p>
<p>&#8220;Social Security &#8216;reformers&#8217;! Report back to your graves!&#8221;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2009/01/social-security-reform-the-undead-return.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
