<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>couch potatoes &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Chris Christie’s Sweet Dream (And Romney’s)</title>
		<link>./../../2012/04/chris-christies-sweet-dream-and-romneys.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/04/chris-christies-sweet-dream-and-romneys.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 11 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[auto-industry bailout]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chris Christie]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[couch potatoes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[student-loan program]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/04/chris-christies-sweet-dream-and-romneys.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[“I’ve never seen a less optimistic time in my lifetime in this country and people wonder why,” the first-term Republican governor said at the Bush Institute Conference on Taxes and Economic Growth in New York City. “I think it’s really simple. It’s because government’s now telling them ‘stop dreaming, stop striving, we’ll take care of [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div>“I’ve never seen a less optimistic time in my lifetime in this country and people wonder why,” the first-term Republican governor said at the Bush Institute Conference on Taxes and Economic Growth in New York City.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>“I think it’s really simple. It’s because government’s now telling them ‘stop dreaming, stop striving, we’ll take care of you.’ We’re turning into a paternalistic entitlement society,” he said.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>“That will not just bankrupt us financially, it will bankrupt us morally because when the American people no longer believe that this a place where only their willingness to work hard … determines their success in life then we’ll have a bunch of people sittin’ on a couch waiting for their next government check,” Christie said.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212; &#8220;<a href="http://www.politico.com/news/stories/0412/74987.html">Christie: Nation of couch potatoes</a>,” Politico
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>That, pretty clearly, is the message that the Republicans, party-wide, have settled on for this election: People are depressed because of the existence of the social safety net and other government programs such as student-loan and job-retraining programs, and because the very wealthy haven’t had their tax rates cut enough, the gap between the very wealthy, and all those couch potatoes who work regular jobs isn’t large enough.  
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I wish them all the best with that message.  And I hope they keep pushing it, all the way to November. </p>
<p>I think it’s simple, too. I&#8217;ll leave it at that.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Can’t wait to hear the <i>next</i> installment of Christie’s VP audition script.  Maybe something about all those auto-industry-worker couch potatoes who’ve stopped dreaming and striving now that Obama has handed GM and Chrysler to the UAW?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>By the way, did Christie ever use the student-loan program, I wonder?  Or did he, like Romney and Romney’s kids, have no need for it?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>Christie was speaking at the Bush Institute Conference on Taxes and Economic Growth. Tomorrow’s audition will be by Paul Ryan. It’s a follow-up audition, actually.</p>
<p>&#8212;-
</p>
</div>
<div>Apparently, <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/04/05/nyregion/christie-gives-new-jersey-firms-tax-breaks-for-short-moves.html?pagewanted=all">not <i>all</i> government programs</a> cause mental depression.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/04/chris-christies-sweet-dream-and-romneys.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
