<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Miley Cyrus &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Saving SPOT! (Thank You, Miley Cyrus.)</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/saving-spot-thank-you-miley-cyrus.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/saving-spot-thank-you-miley-cyrus.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2013 01:59:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[ASPCA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Feld Entertainment Inc.]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Miley Cyrus]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[the legal-fees racket]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/saving-spot-thank-you-miley-cyrus.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I’m not a fan of circuses, or for that matter, of zoos.  I am a fan of the American Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals.  And this breaks my heart.   I don’t want to even think about the animals who won’t be rescued because $9.3 million of donations to the ASPCA will [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’m not a fan of circuses, or for that matter, of zoos.  I am a fan of the American Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals.  And <a href="http://legaltimes.typepad.com/blt/2013/01/animal-rights-group-to-pay-circus-producer-93-million-settlement.html">this</a> breaks my heart.  </p>
<p>I don’t want to even think about <a href="https://donate.aspca.org/donate/Donations/TN/Guardian_TN_V2_PPC.aspx?PlacementID=2869247&#038;mpch=ads">the animals who won’t be rescued</a> because $9.3 million of donations to the ASPCA will be used, not for their intended purpose, but to pay this circus’s legal fees.  </p>
<p>But now that we’re beyond the year-end rush for donating to charities and getting a tax deduction for 2012, there’s a way that animal lovers can assist animals in need without donating money: by rescuing an animal from a high-kill shelter, even if only to foster the pet temporarily, until a permanent home can be found.  </p>
<p>That’s what an organization in Los Angeles, called Saving SPOT!, does; it rescues dogs and cats from high-kill shelters and provides medical care, if needed, and then places the pet in a home.  I have no connection with anything in Los Angeles, but I learned of the organization last week, when I read an article listing the entertainment celebrities who have donated the most to charity.  Miley Cyrus was number two on the list, mainly for her financial support for the organization&#8211;and for her efforts to publicize the lifesaving charity.  </p>
<p>There are, of course, similar nonprofits elsewhere, although, also of course, not enough.  Not nearly enough.  But they’re easy to learn of on google; you just have look.</p>
<p>Anyway … let’s hear it for Miley Cyrus.  And for the ASPCA, and for Saving SPOT!, and for similar organizations.  </p>
<p>And for any group active in trying to change the federal and state laws that make going to court against anyone with access to big-name lawyers, or against the government in any type of case not favored by the Republican right.  </p>
<p>It’s long past time for this issue to become a high-profile one.   </p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />PS: It just occurred to me that the ASPCA&#8217;s liability insurance might pay this settlement.  I dearly hope so.  </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/saving-spot-thank-you-miley-cyrus.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
