<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>wages &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 12:45:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Real wages decline; literally no one notices</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/real-wages-decline-literally-no-one-notices.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/real-wages-decline-literally-no-one-notices.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 23:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Inequality]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wages]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/real-wages-decline-literally-no-one-notices.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Cross-posted from Middle Class Political Economist. Your read it here first: Real wages fell 0.2% in 2012, down from $295.49 (1982-84 dollars) to $294.83 per week, according to the 2013 Economic Report of the President. Thus, a 1.9% increase in nominal wages was  more than wiped out by inflation, marking the 40th consecutive year that [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Cross-posted from <a href="http://www.middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/">Middle Class Political Economist</a>.</p>
<p>Your read it here first: Real wages fell 0.2% in 2012, down from $295.49 (1982-84 dollars) to $294.83 per week, according to the 2013 <a href="http://www.whitehouse.gov/sites/default/files/docs/erp2013/ERP2013_Appendix_B.pdf"><i>Economic Report of the President</i></a>. Thus, a 1.9% increase in nominal wages was  more than wiped out by inflation, marking the <a href="http://middleclasspoliticaleconomist.blogspot.com/2012/03/basics-real-wages-remain-below-their.html">40th consecutive year</a> that real wages have remained below their 1972 peak.</p>
<p>Yet no one in the media noticed, or at least none thought it newsworthy. I searched the web and the subscription-only Nexis news database, and there are literally 0 stories on this. So I meant it when I said you read it here first. In fact, there was little press coverage of the report at all, in sharp contrast to last year.g</p>
<p>Below are the gory details. The data source is Appendix Table B-47, &#8220;Hours and Earnings in Private Non-Agricultural Industries, 1966-2012.&#8221; The table has been completely revised since last year&#8217;s edition of the report. The data is for production and non-supervisory workers in the private sector, about 80% of the private workforce, so we are able to focus on what&#8217;s happening to average workers rather than those with high incomes.. I use weekly wages rather than hourly because there has been substantial variation (with a long-term decline) in the number of hours worked per week, from 38.5 in 1966 to 33.7 in 2012. The table below takes selected years to reduce its size.</p>
<p>Year     Weekly Earnings (1982-84 dollars)</p>
<p>1972     $341.73 (peak)<br />
1975     $314.77<br />
1980     $290.80<br />
1985     $284.96<br />
1990     $271.10<br />
1992     $266.46 (lowest point; 22% below peak)<br />
1995     $267.17<br />
2000     $285.00<br />
2005     $285.05<br />
2010     $297.79<br />
2011     $295.49<br />
2012     $294.83 (still 14% below peak)</p>
<p>This decline is especially amazing when we consider that private non-farm productivity has doubled in this period:</p>
<div><a href="http://research.stlouisfed.org/fred2/graph/?s%5B1%5D%5Bid%5D=OPHNFB"> <img src="http://research.stlouisfed.org/fred2/data/OPHNFB_Max_630_378.png" alt="Graph of Nonfarm Business Sector: Output Per Hour of All Persons" width="630" height="378" border="0" /> </a></div>
<div></div>
<div>But, if you&#8217;ve been paying attention, you know the drill: higher productivity plus lower wages = greater inequality. The question is, why aren&#8217;t our media paying attention when real wages fall, yet again?Update: <a href="http://blogs.seattletimes.com/jontalton/2013/03/25/real-wages-fell-in-2012/">Jon Talton</a> at the <i>Seattle Times</i> has now taken note of this.</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/real-wages-decline-literally-no-one-notices.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>If I were writing that piece</title>
		<link>./../../2013/03/if-i-were-writing-that-piece.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/03/if-i-were-writing-that-piece.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2013 15:43:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[recession]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wages]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/03/if-i-were-writing-that-piece.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Here is an interesting way to deal numbers, with the complete post to be read from the link: Obama taxes us into recession  (Mish&#8217;s musings) Withheld income and employment taxes have been running about 8.3% higher year over year, comparing the same 33 business days between Tuesday, January 8 and Monday, February 25.&#8230;Regardless, there is [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Here is an interesting way to deal numbers, with the complete post to be read from the link:</p>
<p><a href="http://globaleconomicanalysis.blogspot.com/2013/02/did-obama-tax-us-into-recession.html">Obama taxes us into recession</a>  (Mish&#8217;s musings)<br />
<blockquote>Withheld income and employment taxes have been running about 8.3% higher year over year, comparing the same 33 business days between Tuesday, January 8 and Monday, February 25.<br />&#8230;<br />Regardless, there is no doubt that the Obama Administration has taxed us into a recession. Congratulations.</p></blockquote>
<p>Lifted from several e-mails in response to the link being sent:</p>
<p>Ken Houghton:    If I were writing that piece, it would be about how the cuts in taxes last year are the only thing that allowed people to pretend we were in a recovery, which has otherwise been jobless. (Check out YoY for 2009 to 2010 or 2010 to 2011.) Krugman is probably right not to dismiss out of hand the idea that you can sustain economic growth with a plutocracy, but it&#8217;s not at all an even odds bet.<br />&#8230;</p>
<p>Personal income was just released; down 3%.</p>
<p>The game with numbers was to treat the employer side of SocSec tax as if it would otherwise be circulating. It&#8217;s more accurate to think of that as I than C. (I would argue all of SocSec payments are I&#8211;a &#8220;forced savings&#8221; program, as it were&#8211;but that&#8217;s a sidebar.)</p>
<p>And we know that those monies were not being reinvested last year. (See <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/02/does-saving-fund-investment.html">Steve Roth&#8217;s post a couple of days ago</a>.). Will be interesting if we see Excess Reserves start to fall when those tax payments all come due.</p>
<p>And a sad thank you, Mike. You and I may have improved our lot last year, but that was the exception, not the rule, and not without painful transition.</p>
<p>How we call extended joblessness and growth based on consuming savings a &#8220;recovery&#8221; befuddles me.</p>
<p>Dale Coberly:  As I may have tediously tried to point out elsewhere, rescinding the tax holiday is not a tax raise.. it is the end of a government &#8220;stimulus&#8221; funded by borrowing, unnecessarily attached to the payroll tax for devious political purposes.  the SS &#8220;tax&#8221;  is always circulating&#8230; it goes to benefits to the otherwise poor elderly who spend it right away.  unless you are going to fund those benefits by borrowing or taxing the rich,  reducing the payroll tax would reduce &#8220;circulating&#8221;  by the extent to which people &#8220;saved&#8221; that money for their eventual retirement&#8230; assuming they could find a way to &#8220;save&#8221; it, given the fact that no one is &#8220;investing.&#8221;  i guess we could go back to gold coins buried in jars in the backyard.  that should be good for the economy.</p>
<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/03/if-i-were-writing-that-piece.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Wages driven down, now relative to market you&#8217;re over paid!</title>
		<link>./../../2012/07/wages-driven-down-now-relative-to-market-youre-over-paid.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/07/wages-driven-down-now-relative-to-market-youre-over-paid.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 Jul 2012 20:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Class war]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[labor economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[labor markets]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[labor share]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[market wages]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wages]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/07/wages-driven-down-now-relative-to-market-youre-over-paid.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Update: spelling corrected in title. I heard and then went to look see that Caterpillar is working hard to control it&#8217;s costs. &#8220;Despite earning a record $4.9 billion profit last year and projecting even better results for 2012, the company is insisting on a six-year wage freeze and a pension freeze for most of the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Update: spelling corrected in title.</p>
<p>I heard and then <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/07/23/business/profitable-caterpillar-pushes-workers-for-steep-cuts.html?pagewanted=all">went to look see </a>that Caterpillar is working hard to control it&#8217;s costs.</p>
<blockquote><p>&#8220;Despite earning a record $4.9 billion profit last year and projecting even better results for 2012, the company is insisting on a six-year wage freeze and a pension freeze for most of the 780 production workers at its factory here. Caterpillar says it needs to keep its labor costs down to ensure its future competitiveness.&#8221; </p></blockquote>
<p>It has <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caterpillar_Inc.">purchased 17 other business</a> since 2008, 9 were non US companies.  Two companies were purchased in 2011.  Here&#8217;s the thing, a 6 year freeze?  I guess there will be no inflation?  I mean like zero.  Though economist are saying inflation is needed as part of the solution to our slow economy.  Of course, Obama having frozen government wages, I guess Caterpillar is just being patriotic.   Nothing like We the People blazing the trail for how we want the private sector to treat We the People.</p>
<p>
<div>Caterpillar made $4.9 billion profit.  If they raised these people&#8217;s pay $10,000 each, your only talking $7.8 million.  It is 0.159%  (0.00159)of Caterpillar&#8217;s profit. <a href="http://inflationdata.com/inflation/inflation_rate/currentinflation.asp">Inflation has averaged</a> since 2008  about 2.075%.   Giving the worker $10,000 more per year does not equal the inflation rate as a share of the profit.  If the worker were getting their due based on inflation they would get a piece of $101,675,000.  This would be $130,352.56 each for the 780 workers.  Caterpillar would still have $4,798,325,000.00 profit.  Imagine what that $130,352.56 would do for the economy in Joliet!  I&#8217;ll bet Caterpillar equipment sales would rise do to demand for construction.</div>
<div></div>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<div>I just picked $10,000 for the heck of it.  It&#8217;s a lot of money for the worker at Caterpillar.  Unfortunately it is less than the $15,300 per family I calculated and posted about over the years that is now in the hands of the top 1% EACH AND EVERY YEAR!   </div>
<div>The article notes that these workers average $55,000/yr before overtime.  A $10,000 raise is 18.18% of their pay for what is 0.159% of Caterpillar&#8217;s profit FOR ONE YEAR!  Imagine what Joliet&#8217;s economy would be with $7,800,000 more in it&#8217;s community.</div>
<div></div>
<div>Why is labor not allowed to consider inflation?  Using the above wage and inflation, we get a $1141.25 increase in annual income.  This is for the worker to stay even for 2011.  It totals $890,175 for the 780 employees.  This is 0.01817% (0.0001817) of Caterpillar&#8217;s profit.  Do you know how much that is?   Do you have any idea of how insignificant this cost would be to Caterpillar?</div>
<div></div>
<div>The moon is 238,900 miles from the earth.  0.01817% of that distance is 43.4 miles!  People drive that daily round trip to work.  The earth is 24,901 miles in circumference, times 0.0001817 is 4 and 1/2 miles!  It&#8217;s a leisurely 1.5 hour  walk compared to a 41.23 hour flight around the earth in a <a href="http://blog.privatefly.com/how-fast-can-a-private-jet-fly">Cessna Citation X</a> at its cruise speed of 604mph (201 times faster than the walk). </div>
<div></div>
<div>Here is the real twilight zone/catch 22 fun house these and all workers are in.   </div>
<p>
<blockquote>
<div></div>
<div>&#8220;Last winter, Caterpillar locked out about 450 workers at its locomotive plant in London, Ontario, and then closed the factory after the union rejected its demand to cut wages by 55 percent.&#8221; </div>
<div>Robert Bruno, a labor relations professor at the University of Illinois, said Caterpillar was trying to drive compensation down to a new floor.</div>
<div>“Caterpillar sees this as ‘the new normal,’&#8230;</div>
<div>Carlos Revilla, the plant’s operations manager, defended the push for a pay freeze, saying the top-tier workers were paid 34 percent above market level.</div>
<div>   </div>
<div>“A competitive and fair wage package is a must,” he said in a statement. “Paying wages well above market levels makes Joliet uncompetitive.”   </div>
<div>&#8220;The company had profit of $39,000 per employee last year.&#8221;  </div>
</blockquote>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>First, no one asks for a 55% cut without already having plans to close the factory.  Obviously Caterpillar&#8217;s offer was your typical flea market (“swap meet” for you car people, yard sale for the rest) low ball, I don&#8217;t need it but if your willing&#8230;bogus offer.  Oh, what is &#8220;market level&#8221;?  Is this the average of Walmart/retail and food service industry jobs thrown in?  The phrase used to be: industry level.  Cute game they are playing.</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>First, no one asks for a 55% cut without already having plans to close the factory.  Obviously Caterpillar&#8217;s offer was your typical flea market (“swap meet” for you car people, yard sale for the rest) low ball, I don&#8217;t need it but if your willing&#8230;bogus offer.</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>How is it, that one party can drive down the market and then is allowed to use the new market level they created as the reason for why they need to drive down the market and society not see the self serving nature of the argument?  Law calls such power &#8220;contracts of adhesion&#8221;.  If we had an actual functioning Department of Labor, they would not let such monopolistic activities take root.  This is not free market capitalism as we idolize it.  Where is the negotiating power of labor so that the declining wage base driven by the employer is not used as the reason to further decline wages?  You wonder why those charts of declining union numbers correlate with declining average wages? Caterpillar et al.   </div>
<div></div>
<div>Of course, part of the issue is that the workers are being handled as if that one plant is all there is to Caterpillar.  Mr. Revilla&#8217;s position is that the plant shall not be considered part of the whole operation and thus Caterpillar&#8217;s profit is not a serviceable fact during the negotiations.  Only the unique profitability of that one plant is of concern.  So, what happens to the customary answer of &#8220;globalization&#8221; by corporations such as Caterpillar when ask why?   The globalized profits are not to be considered?  Is Caterpillar only selling the product from the Joliet plant in Joliet?  The Joliet situation is a closed market, independent from all else around it with no influence to or from the outside?     </div>
<div></div>
<div>Lets go one step further: taxes.  I&#8217;ll bet Caterpillar gets some kind of a break.  Maybe payment in lieu of taxes?  Does Illinois have any kind of job creation tax incentives?  Inventory tax reductions?  No sales tax paid?   The proverbial catch 22 is your local property taxes.  You can&#8217;t afford them, right?  They keep going up, right?  The state is not sending your town the same amount of money it used to, right?  And companies like Caterpillar keep driving down wages to a new base, while they off load the tax burden to labor&#8217;s wage base  with arguments that they are doing their part by creating jobs. </div>
<div></div>
<div>Citizens of the US&#8230;WAKE UP! </div>
<div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/07/wages-driven-down-now-relative-to-market-youre-over-paid.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Double Double &#8212; The Absolute Simplest Look at Wages and Pensions</title>
		<link>./../../2012/02/double-double-the-absolute-simplest-look-at-wages-and-pensions.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/02/double-double-the-absolute-simplest-look-at-wages-and-pensions.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2012 12:07:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[pensions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wages]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/02/double-double-the-absolute-simplest-look-at-wages-and-pensions.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[By Noni Mausa Double Double &#8212;  The Absolute Simplest Look at Wages and Pensions       One of the best loved Canadian drinks is the famed Double-Double, a big coffee with two creams and two sugars from the Tim Horton’s coffee shop chain.  Millions of double-doubles warm grateful workers hands and wake up their brains on the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By <strong>Noni Mausa</strong></p>
<p><strong>Double Double &#8212;  The Absolute Simplest Look at Wages and Pensions  </strong><br />     <br />One of the best loved Canadian drinks is the famed Double-Double, a   <br />big coffee with two creams and two sugars from the Tim Horton’s coffee    <br />shop chain.  Millions of double-doubles warm grateful workers hands    <br />and wake up their brains on the way to work each morning.  Want to    <br />raise a cheer from a Canadian crowd?  Just toast the double-double.<br />But Canadian workers need more than coffee to see them through.  They   <br />need wages and pensions.  How big do they need to be?  In a time of    <br />drooping wages and wavering pensions, we need to know.  Let’s approach    <br />the wages, retirement and pension discussion by simplifying it as much    <br />as possible.</p>
<p>Let’s assume that the work life extends from age 20 to 60.  The work   <br />that people do before and after those ages is balanced by people who    <br />are not able to work at all, for whatever reason.  We’re talking    <br />averages here, spread across 33 million Canadians.<br />So for half your life you work, and for half (birth to 20, and 60 to   <br />80) you don’t.</p>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />As you can see, on average every person working must earn double what   <br />it costs him to live.  That extra money pays for the child the worker    <br />is before he goes to work, and the senior he is afterwards.  For the    <br />population of Canada to stay level, each Canadian must raise one    <br />child, and he must support himself once he retires.  What it costs to    <br />do that is the “lifetime wage.”</p>
<p>How can we calculate that?</p>
<p>Well, to start we can set a lower limit.  Each individual must earn or   <br />somehow acquire no less than what he needs to stay alive.  A rough    <br />guess for that number is around $800/month.  That’s in the range of    <br />what single welfare recipients receive.  I have no idea how they live    <br />on that, but thousands of them do.</p>
<p>Full time minimum wage is roughly double that, about $1600/month   <br />before taxes, about $1350 after. (Manitoba minimum wage currently    <br />$10/hour.)   This is still not enough to be a lifetime wage.  Also,    <br />most minimum wage jobs are not full time or continuous employment, so    <br />the effective income from minimum wage employment is closer to welfare    <br />rates.</p>
<p>Canadians are being exhorted to live responsibly, only bearing   <br />children if they can afford to raise them, saving for their education    <br />and also for the their own retirement.  The smallest sufficient income    <br />to accomplish this seems to be about double current minimum wages, or    <br />about $20/hour in Manitoba, $35,000 to $45,000 per year averaged over    <br />a working life.</p>
<p>Business won’t pay such wages if they aren’t forced to.  But somebody   <br />must.  Why?  Not for moral reasons, we’re not dealing with morality    <br />here, just practicality.  Whatever way you try to jig the numbers,    <br />half the population depends on the other half just to live.  In a    <br />nation, these life-stages overlap so the burden levels out over time,    <br />but effectively one half is always supporting the other.<br />Paying out to each worker less than double the bare cost of living in   <br />a closed system will result in collapse or shrinkage of the system.<br />But suppose you don’t treat your nation as a closed system?  Maybe you   <br />can outsource some of the cost at the two “nonproductive” ends of the    <br />lifespan.  If you want to cut your costs to the bone so your workers    <br />can be paid only their immediate costs of living, you have to tackle    <br />the problem at the child end and the senior end.</p>
<p>At the child end, you can outsource the production of new workers to   <br />other, poorer countries – i.e. depend on immigration for population    <br />growth.  That’s one thing Canada is doing.</p>
<p>StatsCan tells us “In 2006, international migration accounted for   <br />two-thirds of Canadian population growth… in the mid-1990s, a reversal    <br />occurred: the migratory component became the main engine of Canadian    <br />growth, particularly because of low fertility and the aging of the    <br />population… Around 2030, deaths are expected to start outnumbering    <br />births. From that point forward, immigration would be the only growth    <br />factor for the Canadian population…”</p>
<p>In Canada in 2010, of the 280,000 immigrants, 60% were “economic”   <br />(adults ready to work.)  Another 28% were classed as “family.” The    <br />hard lifting of childbirth and childrearing and child mortality was    <br />done by other countries with no cost to Canada. In fact, immigrants    <br />pay a small but significant landing fee, $500 to $1000 depending on    <br />entry class.   We further maximized the value of the outsourced new    <br />citizens by selecting capable applicants free of serious medical    <br />problems.</p>
<p>At the senior end of the lifespan, you can cut elder supports as much   <br />as possible.  This is harder to do because elders are aware of the    <br />process and often have younger relatives to advocate for them, but    <br />though it’s going slowly, it is a work in progress.<br />A maximally efficient economy in a non-closed system would be one   <br />where you import all your workers, keep them as long as you need them,    <br />and repatriate them afterwards.  But that is not a nation.  Nations    <br />grow their own people, they don’t rent them.</p>
<p>Canada-the-nation may not need to support home-grown population   <br />growth, because we are a nation that encourages many cultures.   The    <br />fact that our immigration policy skims good citizens from poorer    <br />nations doesn’t bother anyone except, I suppose, the poorer nations.    <br />But Canada-the-nation must support seniors.  Business won’t pay enough    <br />in wages for workers to save money for retirement, and for many people    <br />saving or investing isn’t a reliable strategy.  Private business    <br />pensions are becoming quaint luxuries (unless you’re in the government    <br />or you’re a CEO.)</p>
<p>We pride ourselves on being a secure, stable nation.  The chaotic,   <br />competitive and short term business community won’t and probably can’t    <br />supply that stability; only a government has the ability over    <br />generations to ensure stability.</p>
<p>A centralized, national fixed-benefit pension, solid and boring and   <br />guaranteed by the government, is the only practical approach for most    <br />Canadians.  Additional savings are fine, for people who can afford    <br />them, but millions cannot.  Cutting and privatizing senior supports    <br />(Canadian Pension Plan, Old Age Security, and for the very poorest,    <br />the Guaranteed Income Supplement) is the opposite of what    <br />Canada-the-nation needs to be doing.<br />&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;<br />(This was written in the Canadian context, where our right-wing prime   <br />minister is in the fast lane to transform Canada to conform more    <br />closely to US antisocial policy.)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/02/double-double-the-absolute-simplest-look-at-wages-and-pensions.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Warm Wind At the Backs of Some, Generated Off the Backs of Others</title>
		<link>./../../2011/10/a-warm-wind-at-the-backs-of-some-generated-off-the-backs-of-others.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/10/a-warm-wind-at-the-backs-of-some-generated-off-the-backs-of-others.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2011 13:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[dividends]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[income taxes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tax reform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wages]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/10/a-warm-wind-at-the-backs-of-some-generated-off-the-backs-of-others.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This piece offers an understandable comparison between wages and dividend income and neatly summarizes the cost to wage earners. (h/t Mike Kimel) by Peter S. Meyers Myers Urbatsch PC A Warm Wind At the Backs of Some, Generated Off the Backs of Others Yesterday, I learned in this Mother Jones article that workers have increased [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This piece offers an understandable comparison between wages and dividend  income  and neatly summarizes the cost to wage earners.  (h/t Mike Kimel)
<p>by Peter S. Meyers</p>
<p>Myers Urbatsch PC</p>
<p><a target="_blank" href="http://petermyers.typepad.com/my_weblog/2011/07/a-warm-wind-at-the-backs-of-some-generated-off-the-backs-of-others.html">A Warm Wind At the Backs of Some, Generated Off the Backs of Others </a> Yesterday, I learned in <a href="http://motherjones.com/politics/2011/02/income-inequality-in-america-chart-graph">this Mother Jones article</a> that workers have increased their contribution to government revenue disproportionately since 1980.  In other words, payroll tax (paid by workers) is a larger portion of government revenue than it used to be.  That&#8217;s a macroeconomic analysis, which still doesn&#8217;t answer the question of whether rich people are being treated &#8220;unfairly&#8221; by the current tax system.  </p>
<p>So to elaborate a little, let&#8217;s take two people who make exactly the same amount:  $100,000 in taxable income (after the standard deduction &#8211; let&#8217;s not get complicated).  &#8220;Worker Taxpayer&#8221; earns her money by working (getting compensation by way of a W2) and &#8220;Investor Taxpayer&#8221; earns her money from dividends in a $4 million stock portfolio she holds (its about 2.5% in yield &#8211; about right).  Let&#8217;s say they are both unmarried.  Investor taxpayer does not work and has no compensation income.  They are otherwise &#8220;equal,&#8221; right? (except that investor taxpayer fits the description of those who vituperate about lazy welfare recipients who sit on the couch all day and watch TV, right?)  I&#8217;ll keep the rhetoric down, because the facts are outrageous enough to speak for themselves.</p>
<p> <a name="more"></a>
<p>Worker taxpayer will pay $7650 in payroll tax, plus $21,617 in income tax (2011 brackets), for a total tax burden of $29,267. </p>
<p>Let&#8217;s look at investor taxpayer.  You would think they would be taxed at the same rate as worker, right?  Wrong.  Because investor taxpayer receives all of her income from qualified dividends, they get a &#8220;special&#8221; tax treatment.  Bear with me, we&#8217;re almost done.  Generally, the maximum tax rate for qualified<strong></strong> dividends is 15%, BUT HERE it is actually 0% because investor&#8217;s other income (remember she doesn&#8217;t work) is taxed at the 10% or 15% rate. </p>
<p>To refresh:  worker making $100K pays about $30K in tax.  Investor making $100K in qualified dividends pays $0 &#8211; no &#8211; tax.  Huh?  Yup.  </p>
<p>What this means is that rich people &#8211; who are incented by tax policy to remain on their couches (too much earned income would otherwise trip them into the 15% dividend tax bracket) &#8211; are now getting off their couches and going to tea-party rallies to maintain this unfair redistribution of wealth in their favor.  For if they work, they risk having their dividends taxed at 15% (still half of what, say, worker taxpayer paid in taxes, but confiscatory in their view).  Perverse incentive?  Yup.  Does it sound like the rhetoric of the right wingers about unemployed persons and welfare recipients laying on couches and not incented to work?  Hm. . . .</p>
<p>Now let&#8217;s say you didn&#8217;t work, or you worked very little, and instead you made all of your income from qualified dividends.  The &#8220;magic number&#8221; (the income threshold you need to stay under to avoid paying any tax on your dividend income) is $69,000 (married), $34,500 (single or married filing separately) or $46,250 (head of household).  Thus, you can actually work a little, and you have all this extra time &#8211; to attend rallies, political functions, cook your food, clean your house or do other things that people who actually earn their income from working have to: (a) pay someone else to do (which is not deductible), (b) do in the evenings or on weekends, or (c) simply let it slide.</p>
<p>I will now illustrate how it is almost impossible for someone who is already rich to not get richer, in fact much richer.  Both working taxpayer and investor taxpayer have identical lifestyles and thus spend the exact same amount of money (not likely, given that worker has to pay for commuting expenses &#8211; again NOT deductible).  Let&#8217;s assume that&#8217;s $70,000 per year.  We know that worker taxpayer already paid $30K in tax, so let&#8217;s see what they have left to save:  uh, nothing.  Investor taxpayer paid no tax, so what do they have left over to save: $30K.  Exactly the same amount that worker taxpayer paid in taxes.</p>
<p>The rationale for the tax policy you see illustrated above is George W. Bush&#8217;s.  In 2003 he said that &#8220;double taxation is bad for our economy and falls especially hard on retired people.&#8221; He also argued that while &#8220;it&#8217;s fair to tax a company&#8217;s profits, it&#8217;s not fair to double-tax by taxing the shareholder on the same profits.&#8221;</p>
<p>Its odd to me that the above disparate treatment of otherwise similarly-situated earners is defended on the basis of &#8220;fairness.&#8221;  Is this 1984?  And I also wonder whether there is a joke in there somewhere &#8211; i.e., given that a zero-percent tax bracket would apply to someone who made all of their money from dividends and capital gains, why wouldn&#8217;t they retire?  I sure as hell would.  Working too much would bump all of their dividend income into the 15% tax bracket.  Volunteering for the tea-party rally, or perhaps some other Republican cause, would be a far better use of one&#8217;s time.</p>
<p>    reposted with permission of the author  July 23, 2011 post</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/10/a-warm-wind-at-the-backs-of-some-generated-off-the-backs-of-others.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Who Cares About Nominal Rigidities?</title>
		<link>./../../2011/08/who-cares-about-nominal-rigidities.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/08/who-cares-about-nominal-rigidities.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2011 00:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[employment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Macroeconomic Theory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Prices]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wages]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/08/who-cares-about-nominal-rigidities.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Tyler Cowen doesn&#8217;t much. I tend to agree with Cowen. Nominal rigidities were quite the thing just before I arrived, so I think they are over rated. However, there are two points one of which is totally twitty and the other of which is a dead horse still being beaten by Paul Krugman. OK twitty: [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Tyler Cowen <a href="http://marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2011/08/how-are-nominal-wages-sticky-for-the-unemployed.html">doesn&#8217;t much</a>.</p>
<p>I tend to agree with Cowen.  Nominal rigidities were quite the thing just before I arrived, so I think they are over rated.  However, there are two points one of which is totally twitty and the other of which is a dead horse still being beaten by Paul Krugman.</p>
<p>OK twitty:  By definition for there to be unemployment there must be three agents, an employer, an employee and an unemployed person.  The unemployed person must be eager to work as the employee does at the employee&#8217;s wage.  The employer must consider the unemployed person qualified.  This means that unemployment can certainly be eliminated if wages fall.  At some point, either the employee decides to quit and just live off savings till social security kicks in or the unemployed person decides he or she doesn&#8217;t want the job.  By definition, wage rigidity is needed to explain unemployment.  This is true even if lower wages do not at all cause higher employment.  If nothing else super low wages can convince people to leave the labor force eliminating unemployment that way.  In this case wage flexibility doesn&#8217;t help the unemployed &#8212; it makes the alternative of working worse so they consider their horrible predicment the best they can hope for.  I said it was twitty.</p>
<p>Second, things are unusual because we are in a liquidity trap.  The reason nominal rigidities usually matter is that the real money supply could increase if the nominal money stock staid the same and wages and prices fell.  From 1940 through 2008 this meant that wage and price flexibility should have prevented output from fallin.  N ow, however, the money supply doesn&#8217;t matter since we are in a liquidity trap.  In the IS-LM model (M/P) (money divided by the price level) appears.  If P is free to adjust, then there can be no problem with insufficient aggregate demand.  Therefore in all of the macro literature from 1940 through 2008, nominal rigidities were considered important.  The idea here is wages go down so the firms cut prices (to maximize profits they would) so real balances (M/P) goes up so aggregate demand goes up so GDP goes up.  There is no need for real wages to fall.</p>
<p>Right now this doesn&#8217;t matter as M/P doesn&#8217;t matter.  But for decades and decades it mattered a lot, so nominal rigidities mattered.  In practice, wages and prices are sticky so all reality based macroeconmists (&#8220;that&#8217;s not enough I need a majority&#8221; &#8212; Adlai Stevenson) agreed that nominal rigidities mattered.  Now not so much.  M/P doesn&#8217;t matter so P only matters because of debt deflation (lower P makes nominal mortgage debt an ever worse problem) so wage and price flexibility won&#8217;t save us so Keynesians don&#8217;t talk about it. </p>
<p>As always, don&#8217;t confuse &#8220;Keynesians&#8221; with Keynes.  Keynes was not interested in nominal rigidities The General Theory through &#8220;The General Theory Restated&#8221; included nothing on nominal anything.</p>
<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/08/who-cares-about-nominal-rigidities.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>US labor market: wage and salary growth vs. payroll growth</title>
		<link>./../../2011/07/us-labor-market-wage-and-salary-growth-vs-payroll-growth.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/07/us-labor-market-wage-and-salary-growth-vs-payroll-growth.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Jul 2011 14:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[consumption]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Job creation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rebecca Wilder]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[US data]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wages]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/07/us-labor-market-wage-and-salary-growth-vs-payroll-growth.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I&#8217;ll make this quick, since I&#8217;m going to get in trouble for writing on a national holiday. But the pace of annual jobs growth is too slow to generate strong wage and salary income. Much empirical research has been dedicated to the estimation of consumption functions, generally finding that labor income is the primary driver [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;ll make this quick, since I&#8217;m going to get in trouble for writing on a national holiday. But the pace of annual jobs growth is too slow to generate strong wage and salary income. Much empirical research has been dedicated to the estimation of consumption functions, generally finding that labor income is the primary driver of consumption (here&#8217;s a <a href="http://www.federalreserve.gov/pubs/feds/2001/200109/200109pap.pdf">primer at the Federal Reserve Board</a>). However, by extension jobs growth is highly correlated with wage and salary growth, roughly 50% of personal income &#8211; this is the relationship I analyze here.</p>
<p>Roughly half of the <a href="http://bea.gov/newsreleases/national/pi/2011/pdf/pi0511.pdf">BEA&#8217;s measure of personal income</a> comes in the form of wage and salary, so called labor income and simply referred to as &#8216;wages&#8217; from here on out. This is highly correlated with nonfarm payroll growth, both in nominal and real terms (92% and 79%, respectively, since 1996). The chart below illustrates the correlation between real wage growth and nonfarm payroll since 1982 (I use real wage so as to account for the effects of inflation).</p>
<p><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-jCZR1i0ppjU/ThG01ErmhII/AAAAAAAADug/GFcm2gEmIys/s1600/payroll_rwage_chart.jpg"><img src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-jCZR1i0ppjU/ThG01ErmhII/AAAAAAAADug/GFcm2gEmIys/s400/payroll_rwage_chart.jpg" border="0" alt=""></a><br />The annual pace of real wage gains and jobs growth have declined over time (jobs growth is measured using the nonfarm payroll). Simply eyeballing the data, there&#8217;s a structural shift roughly around 1996, as listed in the table below.</p>
<p><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-2ykpmwz2oP4/ThG2HXuFuPI/AAAAAAAADuo/KyS6SJkSS8A/s1600/table_wages_payroll.jpg"><img src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-2ykpmwz2oP4/ThG2HXuFuPI/AAAAAAAADuo/KyS6SJkSS8A/s400/table_wages_payroll.jpg" border="0" alt=""></a>Using these two time periods, 1982-1995 and 1996-05/2011, I estimate a simple model of real wage growth on nonfarm payroll growth. The chart for the 1996-2011 model is illustrated below; and for reference, the regression results across both time periods are copied at the end of this post.</p>
<p>READ MORE AFTER THE JUMP!<br /><a name="more"></a><br />Note: I do not have time for a full blown econometric analysis. I did, however, perform statistical tests for serial correlation in the errors, unit roots in the transformed data (none), and general modeling tests.</p>
<p><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-Xn1ePnaMRyc/ThHRWxhBKuI/AAAAAAAADvY/7c98PnelgRo/s1600/model_1996.jpg"><img src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-Xn1ePnaMRyc/ThHRWxhBKuI/AAAAAAAADvY/7c98PnelgRo/s400/model_1996.jpg" border="0" alt=""></a>I come to two general conclusions regarding the relationship between real wage growth and jobs growth over time:</p>
<p>(1) Real wage growth has become more persistent over time. In the first period, 1982-1995, just one lag was required to expunge the errors of autocorrelation. Spanning the second period, 1996-2011, three lags were required. The sum of the coefficients on the three lags is 0.87 in the later sample, or current wage growth is highly dependent on previous periods &#8211; sticky if you will.</p>
<p>(2) Nonfarm payroll growth has become less significant over time. Spanning the years 1982-1995, the coefficient on annual payroll growth was 0.27 &#8211; for each 1pps increase in the annual payroll growth, the trajectory of annual real wage growth increased by 0.27pps. The coefficient dropped to 0.17 in the sample spanning 1996-2011. This is probably a consequence of service sector jobs growing as a share of the labor market. I&#8217;d like your ideas in comments as well.</p>
<p>Clearly this is a very simple model but it does highlight that wages are likely stuck in the mud for some time. In May, annual real wages fell 0.6% over the year, having decelerated for 5 of the 7 months since November 2010. Real wages can pick up, but it takes time AND jobs growth faster than the 0.67% annual pace in May 2011.</p>
<p>Ultimately, what this analysis tells me is with wealth effects slowing markedly &#8211; the <a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/quote?ticker=SPX:IND">trajectory of the S&#038;P</a> decelerated and house prices <a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2011-06-28/home-prices-in-u-s-cities-decreased-4-in-april-from-year-ago.html">continue to fall</a> &#8211; it&#8217;s going to take a burst of payroll growth to get real wage and salary growth back on track enough to finance US domestic consumption. One caveat to all of this negativity is that <a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/quote?ticker=USCRWTIC:IND">oil prices are coming off</a> &#8211; this will boost real wage and salary growth directly.</p>
<p>Rebecca Wilder<br />P.S. I guess this turned out somewhat less &#8216;quick&#8217; than I had anticipated &#8211; not in trouble yet! Gotta go.</p>
<p>Results:</p>
<p><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-HfoBlg_FTBg/ThHMY8tL7jI/AAAAAAAADvI/1RmQclj-lp0/s1600/eviews_1982-1995.jpg"><img src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-HfoBlg_FTBg/ThHMY8tL7jI/AAAAAAAADvI/1RmQclj-lp0/s400/eviews_1982-1995.jpg" border="0" alt=""></a></p>
<p><a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-v9Mrt1ribX4/ThHSbq70TuI/AAAAAAAADvo/owYASojJUUA/s1600/eviews_1996-2011.jpg"><img src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-v9Mrt1ribX4/ThHSbq70TuI/AAAAAAAADvo/owYASojJUUA/s400/eviews_1996-2011.jpg" border="0" alt=""></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/07/us-labor-market-wage-and-salary-growth-vs-payroll-growth.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Unemployment Rate and Compensation Growth</title>
		<link>./../../2011/03/the-unemployment-rate-and-compensation-growth.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/03/the-unemployment-rate-and-compensation-growth.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2011 10:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[compensation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kash Mansori]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[unemployment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wages]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/03/the-unemployment-rate-and-compensation-growth.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Crossposted at The Street Light. Last week I took a look at the way that higher labor productivity has not translated into higher worker compensation, particularly during the 1980s and 2000s. This is at odds with classical labor market theory, which suggests that as workers become more productive, their increasing value to firms should cause [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Crossposted at <em><a href="http://streetlightblog.blogspot.com/">The Street Light</a></em>.</p>
<p>Last week I took a look at the way that <a href="http://streetlightblog.blogspot.com/2011/03/growing-productivity-stagnating.html">higher labor productivity has not translated into higher worker compensation</a>, particularly during the 1980s and 2000s. This is at odds with classical labor market theory, which suggests that as workers become more productive, their increasing value to firms should cause their wages to be bid higher so that their compensation rises accordingly.</p>
<p>There are a number of possible explanations for the divergence between productivity and compensation, and for how this may play into the broader phenomenon of stagnant wages for average workers. Part of the explanation is that an increasing share of worker compensation takes the form of benefits rather than wages and salaries. As shown in the chart below, fully one-fourth of worker compensation in 2010 took the form of benefits. (Source: <a href="http://www.bea.gov/national/index.htm#personal">BEA personal income data</a>.)</p>
<p><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-iWvWl3nGBx0/TYf72Ss56QI/AAAAAAAAAcM/qITOagMhUMc/s1600/benefits%2Bas%2Bshare%2Bof%2Bcomp1.PNG"><img border="0" alt="" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-iWvWl3nGBx0/TYf72Ss56QI/AAAAAAAAAcM/qITOagMhUMc/s400/benefits%2Bas%2Bshare%2Bof%2Bcomp1.PNG"></a></p>
<p><a name="more"></a><br />This upward trend has been driven almost entirely by the rise of health care costs in the US, and the corresponding rise in health insurance premiums. Note that the one dip in the series in the late 1990s was due to the widespread implementation of HMOs &#8211; but they clearly proved to provide a one-time gain rather than a permanent increase in health insurance efficiency. So part of the reason that workers&#8217; paychecks have not been rising is directly attributable to the rise in health care costs in the US.</p>
<p>But that&#8217;s not the whole story, and doesn&#8217;t address the question of slowly growing total compensation (as opposed to stagnant wages). There are, I think, reasonable arguments to be made about social and political factors, such as the decline in the power of unions. Along similar lines, <a href="http://rortybomb.wordpress.com/2011/03/18/the-federal-reserve-unions-wage-stagnation-and-risk-shifted-jobs/">Mike Konczal</a> recently wondered to what degree this could be due to the Fed&#8217;s consistent and explicit desire to prevent wage increases.</p>
<p>And then there&#8217;s plain old supply and demand as a possible explanation. What did the 1980s and 2000s have in common from a macroeconomic point of view? One answer is this: multi-year long periods of high or rising unemployment rates.</p>
<p>The chart below shows, in blue, the seven-year moving average of the portion of increased labor productivity that were paid to workers in the form of higher compensation. During the 1960s and 70s, for example, workers typically received around 80% of gains in labor productivity over any given seven year period. Then during the 1980s that portion fell to about 40%. Meanwhile, the series in red is the seven-year moving average of the unemployment rate.</p>
<p><a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-oQoHR5A33KI/TYf9OgNvipI/AAAAAAAAAcU/y1g3u96lLAE/s1600/prod%2Band%2Bcomp3.PNG"><img border="0" alt="" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-oQoHR5A33KI/TYf9OgNvipI/AAAAAAAAAcU/y1g3u96lLAE/s400/prod%2Band%2Bcomp3.PNG"></a><br />To make it a little easier to interpret, I&#8217;ve color coded the 60 years shown in the chart by shading the periods when workers were losing their share of productivity growth red, while the periods when workers were increasing their share of productivity gains are shaded in green. This helps to make it quite clear that &#8220;green&#8221; times &#8211; i.e. times when workers seem to be enjoying more of the gains in productivity &#8211; were periods when unemployment was falling. &#8220;Red&#8221; times (I guess it actually looks more pink than red in this chart) are clearly associated with periods when the unemployment rate was stagnant or rising.</p>
<p>One implication of this is clear: the high unemployment rate in the US right now, which is expected to decline only slowly over the next several years, is likely to mean that it will be a long time before worker compensation begins to rise as rapidly as worker productivity. Put another way, the overall level of high unemployment right now not only has the obviously enormous personal implications for those who are unemployed &#8212; it also is likely to seriously affect the compensation of workers who have never lost their jobs, for years and years to come.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/03/the-unemployment-rate-and-compensation-growth.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Growing Productivity, Stagnating Compensation</title>
		<link>./../../2011/03/growing-productivity-stagnating-compensation.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/03/growing-productivity-stagnating-compensation.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2011 23:09:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[compensation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kash Mansori]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[productivity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wages]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/03/growing-productivity-stagnating-compensation.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Crossposted at The Street Light. Yesterday Ezra Klein had a chart (from a paper by Larry Mishel and Heidi Shierholz at EPI) showing that both private sector and public sector wages have been stagnating for the past several years, and have certainly not kept up with productivity growth. I think it’s useful to look at [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Crossposted at <em><a href="http://streetlightblog.blogspot.com/">The Street Light</a></em>.</p>
<p>Yesterday <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/ezra-klein/post/the-economy-has-been-bad-to-both-public-and-private-sector-workers/2011/03/10/ABHoAAY_blog.html">Ezra Klein</a> had a chart (from a paper by Larry Mishel and Heidi Shierholz at <a href="http://www.epi.org/publications/entry/the_sad_but_true_story_of_wages_in_america">EPI</a>) showing that both private sector and public sector wages have been stagnating for the past several years, and have certainly not kept up with productivity growth. I think it’s useful to look at the relationship between productivity and compensation over a longer time horizon.</p>
<p>The following chart shows labor productivity and real hourly compensation since 1950. (Data from the <a href="http://www.bls.gov/">BLS</a>.)  Two things strike me particularly about this graph. The first is how closely the two series track each other between 1950 and 1980. During those 30 years labor productivity in the nonfarm business sector of the US economy rose by 92%; real hourly compensation paid to workers rose by a nearly identical 87%. Classical economic theory says that is exactly what we would expect – as workers become more valuable to firms by producing more output with every hour of labor, firms should compete with each other to employ them, driving up wages by an equal amount.</p>
<p><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-Pr_4xJgdDHE/TYEavWwvbtI/AAAAAAAAAbc/zi7yjclW7ho/s1600/prod%2Band%2Bcomp1.PNG"><img border="0" alt="" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-Pr_4xJgdDHE/TYEavWwvbtI/AAAAAAAAAbc/zi7yjclW7ho/s400/prod%2Band%2Bcomp1.PNG"></a><br />The second striking feature of this picture is, of course, how much the two series have diverged since the early 1980s. Output per hour of work in 2010 was 87% higher than in 1980, while real hourly compensation was only 38% higher.</p>
<p>The table below shows changes in labor productivity and hourly compensation by decade. Again, let me draw your attention to two features. First, this data confirms that the “<a href="http://www.nber.org/digest/jun05/w10950.html">great productivity slowdown</a>” of the 1970s and 80s seems to have been vanquished; over the past 15 to 20 years US businesses have been improving productivity at rates as high as during the 1950s and 60s. Yet more evidence that Tyler Cowen’s “Great Stagnation” is <a href="http://www.economist.com/node/21016577">not a productivity story</a>.</p>
<p><a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-s0DrJjS52UQ/TYEa2gU-IvI/AAAAAAAAAbk/ec4gBHuBHWo/s1600/prod%2Band%2Bcomp2.PNG"><img border="0" alt="" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-s0DrJjS52UQ/TYEa2gU-IvI/AAAAAAAAAbk/ec4gBHuBHWo/s400/prod%2Band%2Bcomp2.PNG"></a><br />The second remarkable feature of this table is that the vast majority of the gap between productivity and hourly compensation comes from the 1980s and 2000s, while during the 1990s workers shared in productivity gains nearly as fully as they did in the 1960s. And that, of course, leads us directly to the $64,000 question: what was it about the 1980s and 2000s that made it so difficult for workers to reap the fruits of their more productive labor?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/03/growing-productivity-stagnating-compensation.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Are Earnings Rising or Stagnant?</title>
		<link>./../../2011/01/are-earnings-rising-or-stagnant.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2011/01/are-earnings-rising-or-stagnant.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 16 Jan 2011 11:43:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[earnings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wages]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2011/01/are-earnings-rising-or-stagnant.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In 2005 Kash Mansori of Angry Bear took a look at Are Earnings Rising or Stagnant? It is an issue worth periodic review: This question is not as easy to answer as it may first appear. In working on various posts last week I came across an apparent contradiction in the official data on compensation: [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In 2005 Kash Mansori of Angry Bear took a look at <a target="_blank" href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2005/06/are-earnings-rising-or-stagnant.html">Are Earnings Rising or Stagnant?</a> It is an issue worth periodic review:<br />
<blockquote>This question is not as easy to answer as it may first appear. In working on various posts last week I came across an apparent contradiction in the official data on compensation: some series show it rising in real terms, while others show it barely able to keep up with inflation. This discrepancy was also noted by a few readers, who deserve credit for their sharp eyes.</p>
<p>So I thought I’d take a bit of time to sort out these conflicting data series for myself. Here’s what I found. (A warning and apology here: what follows is a relatively econ-geeky post about data details that many may find uninteresting&#8230; and I won&#8217;t be offended if you stop reading here.)<br /><a name="more"></a></p>
<p><strong>&#8230;</strong></p>
<p>So what’s my answer to the title question of this post? Personally, if I had to choose just one series to use it would be the P&#038;C series. In addition to being arguably the most complete series, it seems to have done the best job of matching my sense about how the economy has done over the past 20 years. When asked, I think that most people would agree that income growth was indeed much lower during 2002 and 2003 than it had been during the late 1990s; the P&#038;C series bears that out, while the ECI series doesn’t. Meanwhile, the CES series excludes benefits, which I think are a major part of the story today.</p>
<p>But let me reiterate the point that I have made several times now: just because real compensation is rising, that doesn’t mean that people are better off, particularly if nearly all of the gains are just going to paying higher health insurance premiums. This data persuasively illustrates that nearly all of our real compensation gains today (and I do think we&#8217;re seeing them) are being eaten up by the monster that we call a health care system in the US. Until we address the profound inadequacies of our health care system, this trend will only get worse.</p>
<p>Kash</p></blockquote>
<p><strong>Spencer</strong> took another quick look in 2010, lifted from his email this Saturday:</p>
<p>This is not an easy subject and there is no &#8220;right&#8221; answer.  </p>
<p>A few comments.  The average hourly earnings data is for people who earn an hourly wage or punch a time clock as oppose to those earning a salary.  As a general rule this is the lower earning segment of the population as college educated professionals and managers are much more likely to be salaried. It reflects what is happening to about 80% of the labor force.  Surprisingly, this percent has not changed significantly over the years.  But the average hourly earnings data has clearly been changed by the changing composition of employment as more highly paid manufacturing employment has both declined in importance and relative pay.  </p>
<p>I always though of the ECI as a measure of what it cost a firm to keep an employee in the same job.  It is deliberately designed this way to try to avoid the problem of changing composition of the labor force from distorting the data.  There are positive and negatives to this.  </p>
<p>The compensation data is the most comprehensive measure of labor payments.  The one question I have never resolved to my own satisfaction is how it treats the payment to CEOs and other senior management with stock options.  It is a difficult accounting issue at the level of the individual firm, let alone for the aggregate economy.  But remember the chart I did a while back of compensation as a share of business cost.  From WW II to 1980 this was a very stable ratio with minor cyclical fluctuation around 66%.  But since 1980 labors share of the pie has been on a falling trend and is now at around 57% of business cost.  <br />I think this best shows the way the middle class has been squeezed. This measure avoids the issue of how to measure inflation.  </p>
<p>The best data for seeing the middle class squeeze is the data published by the Census on family and household income by age,sex, race,etc.,.  </p>
<p>All the inflation series have their drawbacks and shortcomings.  The PCE deflator does not have the cost of housing and so until the last few years probably significantly understated the true cost of living for the middle class.  We are all familiar with the unresolved issue of how the CPI treats housing cost.  <br />The CPI only measures &#8220;out-of-pocket&#8221; medical expenses and because of this I suspect it significantly  <br />understates and under-weights the impact of rapidly rising medical prices on the middle class.  All the Census data uses the CPI-U-RS that recalculated the CPI from 1978 to 2002 using the new methodology for the CPI that incorporates the rental equivalence housing measure and other methodological changes in the way the CPI is calculated.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2011/01/are-earnings-rising-or-stagnant.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
