<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Farm Bill &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Richard Milhous Romney Gets Specific, Says He’ll Cut Out All Programs That Aren’t Worth Borrowing From China For</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/richard-milhous-romney-gets-specific-says-hell-cut-out-all-programs-that-arent-worth-borrowing-from-china-for.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/richard-milhous-romney-gets-specific-says-hell-cut-out-all-programs-that-arent-worth-borrowing-from-china-for.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 04 Oct 2012 03:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[CBS news]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Debate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Farm Bill]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jan Crawford]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Richard Nixon]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rob Portman]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/richard-milhous-romney-gets-specific-says-hell-cut-out-all-programs-that-arent-worth-borrowing-from-china-for.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Yup. All those farmers in Iowa and Nebraska who’ve been waiting for the Farm Bill to pass are as nervous tonight as Richard Nixo … er … Mitt Romney was this evening during the debate, but their problem is different than his was.  Instead of babbling incoherently while wearing a frozen, glassy-eyed smile, the farmers [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>Yup. All those farmers in Iowa and Nebraska who’ve been waiting for the Farm Bill to pass are as nervous tonight as Richard Nixo … er … Mitt Romney was this evening during the debate, but their problem is different than his was.  Instead of babbling incoherently while wearing a frozen, glassy-eyed smile, the farmers are spending the night tossing and turning while trying to figure out whether the program that they rely on so much is much is worth borrowing from China for. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Maybe tomorrow they can put in a call about that to Ohio senator and Romney “surrogate” Rob Portman, and ask him.  Portman, according to a very serious-faced CBS reporter Jan Crawford (of Clarence-Thomas-is-an-intellectual-leader book fame), told her immediately after the debate ended that Romney we’ll be “repeating” the “specifics” of his economic plan throughout the next five weeks.  Just as he did tonight!  Oh, and be just as confident in his manner as he was tonight!
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>As a Democrat, I surely hope so.  And once those farmers find out, specifically, whether the Farm Bill subsidies are worth our borrowing from China for them, the can call Portman back and verify that massive tax cuts for the wealthy are worth borrowing from China for. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Seriously … do these folks really think that if they call this stuff “specifics,” people will think that Romney’s incoherent gibberish included specifics and they (the viewers) just sorta <i>missed</i> them?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And seriously … at least Richard Nixon was coherent.  I’ve seen the black-and-white clips of parts of that first 1960 debate.  Yes, he was obviously nervous.  But he was coherent.  And specific.  As the dictionary defines that word, not as Sen. Portman defines it. 
</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/richard-milhous-romney-gets-specific-says-hell-cut-out-all-programs-that-arent-worth-borrowing-from-china-for.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Farmers, Medicare Recipients, and Sons of Multimillionaires, Some of Whom Won’t Take Responsibility for Their Own Lives &#8211; [UPDATED]</title>
		<link>./../../2012/09/farmers-medicare-recipients-and-sons-of-multimillionaires-some-of-whom-wont-take-responsibility-for-their-own-lives-updated.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/09/farmers-medicare-recipients-and-sons-of-multimillionaires-some-of-whom-wont-take-responsibility-for-their-own-lives-updated.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Sep 2012 16:23:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Agricultural subsidies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Farm Bill]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medicare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mitt Romney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Solamere Capital]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tagg Romney]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/09/farmers-medicare-recipients-and-sons-of-multimillionaires-some-of-whom-wont-take-responsibility-for-their-own-lives-updated.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This summer’s widespread drought has been extremely hard on Midwestern and plains-states crop farmers, and many of them are chafing at the thought of having to take responsibility for their own lives if the Farm Bill doesn’t make it through Congress before the upcoming recess. They had panicked earlier in the summer when Congress was [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>This summer’s widespread drought has been extremely hard on Midwestern and plains-states crop farmers, and many of them are chafing at the thought of <a href="http://www.politico.com/news/stories/0912/81333.html?hp=f2">having to take responsibility for their own lives</a> if <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agricultural_subsidy">the Farm Bill </a>doesn’t make it through Congress before the upcoming recess.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>They had panicked earlier in the summer when Congress was dallying in passing an emergency relief bill, but were rescued from having to take responsibility for their own lives when the Republican-controlled House agreed at the last minute before Congress’s August recess to allow the farmers—including some who won’t be paying income tax for this year unless those federal subsidies increase their incomes enough—to mooch off the likes of Mitt Romney and his son Tagg, <a href="http://www.solameregroup.com/">whom Romney convinced to take responsibility for himself</a>. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Which Tagg did, by borrowing a reported (if I recall correctly) $10 million from his parents to start a (very) private equity firm whose investors apparently all, or almost all, were people who’d made their fortunes through investments with Bain Capital. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Tagg is a role model for young people just starting out today who want to take responsibility for themselves.  His father suggested last winter that other young people should emulate the son: “Start a business.  Borrow money from your parents, if you have to,” Romney told a group of them.  Or something like that.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>In that same speech, he advised young people to “get that education.”  Presumably, by having their parents pay their tuition and expenses.  Like Mitt Romney himself did.  And like all his kids did.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>No silver spoon for the Romneys, though.  No sir. Just personal responsibility. Unlike all those farmers in Kansas, Nebraska and Indiana who are part of Obama’s base.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Then, of course, there the Medicare recipients who refuse to take responsibility for their lives by paying their healthcare costs, or at least the part of their healthcare costs that exceed the amounts they’d paid into the fund over the years. People who think they’re entitled to healthcare.  And, probably, to you-name-it.
</p>
<p>
<div>&#8212;&#8211;
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>UPDATE: A commenter on another blog pointed out that Israelis, whose healthcare system Romney praised during his July overseas rollout, are similar to Obama supporters in that they think they’re entitled to healthcare. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>For that matter, so are Poles, who’s free-enterprise culture Romney praised during that same overseas trip.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>And, now that I think about it, so do the Australians, Austrians, Germans, Japanese, Dutch, Taiwanese, and the citizens of quite a few other countries that are known for their people’s feelings of victimhood and socialist freeloading. 
</p>
<p>
<div>SECOND UPDATE:I’m copying here the three comments posted to this post:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div><a href="http://www.blogger.com/profile/03101422996950773526">Elliot MacLeod-Michael</a> Sep 18, 2012 1:44:00 PM
</p>
</div>
<div>I sure hope people like Boeing don&#8217;t catch wind of this, or any other massive company type people who do not pay taxes.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div><a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/" name="comment-4110644717119929236"></a>little john Sep 18, 2012 2:12:00 PM
</p>
</div>
<div>This blog told me earlier that the Farm Bill was welfare for Agribusiness. Now it&#8217;s just for &#8220;regular&#8221; farmers in Kansas, Nebraska and Indiana? Hmmm.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div><a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/" name="comment-3646167961398017715"></a><a href="http://www.blogger.com/profile/16242719751320079485">Beverly Mann</a> Sep 18, 2012 3:23:00 PM <a href="http://www.blogger.com/delete-comment.g?blogID=5048766&#038;postID=3646167961398017715" title="Delete Comment"> </a>
</p>
</div>
<div>No, john, my post doesn&#8217;t say that the Farm Bill is just for regular farmers. It&#8217;s also for agribusinesses, who, as Elliot points out, are people too. And some of them may not pay taxes, and the rest pay taxes at, I guess, about the rate that Romney did for 2010.</p>
<p>Presumably, the ones who pay no taxes will vote for Obama in the hope of avoiding taking personal (they&#8217;re people, after all) responsibility for themselves.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>So sorry; I couldn’t resist.
</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/09/farmers-medicare-recipients-and-sons-of-multimillionaires-some-of-whom-wont-take-responsibility-for-their-own-lives-updated.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
