<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Supreme court &#8211; Angry Bear</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../index.html</link>
	<description>Slightly left of center economic commentary  on news, politics and the economy.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 16:09:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Individual caps on political contributions</title>
		<link>./../../2013/02/individual-caps-on-political-contributions.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/02/individual-caps-on-political-contributions.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 21 Feb 2013 01:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Supreme court]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/02/individual-caps-on-political-contributions.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[From the NYT …the Supreme Court on Tuesday agreed to hear a new campaign finance lawsuit that challenges long-established federal caps on the total amount an individual can contribute to federal campaigns in a two-year cycle. In a ruling last year, a special court in Washington correctly upheld those limits, which in some form have been [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>From the <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/20/opinion/campaign-donations-and-political-corruption.html?emc=tnt&#038;tntemail1=y&#038;_r=0">NYT</a> </p>
<blockquote><p>…the Supreme Court on Tuesday <a href="http://www.supremecourt.gov/orders/courtorders/021913zor_19m1.pdf">agreed to hear</a> a new campaign finance lawsuit that challenges long-established federal caps on the total amount an individual can contribute to federal campaigns in a two-year cycle. In a ruling last year, a special court in Washington correctly <a href="http://www.fec.gov/law/litigation/mccutcheon_dc_memo_opinion.pdf">upheld</a> those limits, which in some form have been included in federal law since 1974.</p>
<p>If the justices were to overturn that decision, it would be the first time that the court has struck down a contribution limit as unconstitutional. That would eliminate an essential tool in combating the corrupting effects of money in politics. </p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/02/individual-caps-on-political-contributions.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Even The Tragicomical Newly-Released Supreme Court ‘Cert. Grant’ Statistics Don’t Reveal The Worst Of It</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/even-the-tragicomical-newly-released-supreme-court-cert-grant-statistics-dont-reveal-the-worst-of-it.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/even-the-tragicomical-newly-released-supreme-court-cert-grant-statistics-dont-reveal-the-worst-of-it.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2013 17:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[cert. petitions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Daily Writ]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Supreme court]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/even-the-tragicomical-newly-released-supreme-court-cert-grant-statistics-dont-reveal-the-worst-of-it.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[From a website called Daily Writ today, in a post called “Likelihood of a Petition Being Granted”: There are a lot of numbers thrown out about the likelihood of a cert. petition being granted. The number I’ve always heard is 1%, but I sometimes hear numbers as high as 5%. According to statistics from the [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div dir="ltr">From a website called Daily Writ today, in a post called “<a href="http://dailywrit.com/2013/01/likelihood-of-a-petition-being-granted/">Likelihood of a Petition Being Granted</a>”:</div>
<div dir="ltr">There are a lot of numbers thrown out about the likelihood of a cert. petition being granted. The number I’ve always heard is 1%, but I sometimes hear numbers as high as 5%.</div>
<div dir="ltr"></div>
<div dir="ltr">According to <a href="http://www.supremecourt.gov/orders/journal/jnl11.pdf">statistics</a> from the Supreme Court, between June 30, 2011 and July 2, 2012, the Court disposed of 7,654 appeals and granted 63 for oral argument (.862%). That doesn’t count GVRs, but with those, it is safe to say the rate of grant is about 1% for all cert. petitions.</div>
<div dir="ltr"></div>
<div dir="ltr">If you want to break up petitions into paid and IFP petitions — the most obvious division among all appeals filed at the Court — the following table provides a breakdown of the cases disposed of and granted during a twelve-month period between June 2011 and July 2012:</div>
<div dir="ltr"></div>
<div dir="ltr">
<table>
<colgroup></colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>
<div dir="ltr">Paid</div>
</td>
<td>
<div dir="ltr">IFP</div>
</td>
<td>
<div dir="ltr">Total</div>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<div dir="ltr">Disposed</div>
</td>
<td>
<div dir="ltr">1564</div>
</td>
<td>
<div dir="ltr">6090</div>
</td>
<td>
<div dir="ltr">7654</div>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<div dir="ltr">Granted</div>
</td>
<td>
<div dir="ltr">59</div>
</td>
<td>
<div dir="ltr">7</div>
</td>
<td>
<div dir="ltr">66</div>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<div dir="ltr">Percentage</div>
</td>
<td>
<div dir="ltr">3.77%</div>
</td>
<td>
<div dir="ltr">.114%</div>
</td>
<td>
<div dir="ltr">.862%</div>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Of course, last year was a slight aberration because the Court decided fewer cases after oral argument than it had in at least the past twenty years. But data from the previous year confirms that the past year was only a slight deviation from the norm. During the previous twelve-month period, the Court granted 76 of 1580 paid petitions (4.8%), 14 of 6245 IFP petitions (.224%), and 90 of 7825 all petitions filed (1.15%). Here are averages of the past 10 years:</div>
<div dir="ltr"></div>
<div dir="ltr">
<table>
<colgroup></colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>
<div dir="ltr">Paid</div>
</td>
<td>
<div dir="ltr">IFP</div>
</td>
<td>
<div dir="ltr">Total</div>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<div dir="ltr">Disposed</div>
</td>
<td>
<div dir="ltr">1674.3</div>
</td>
<td>
<div dir="ltr">6384.6</div>
</td>
<td>
<div dir="ltr">8058.9</div>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<div dir="ltr">Granted</div>
</td>
<td>
<div dir="ltr">71.8</div>
</td>
<td>
<div dir="ltr">11</div>
</td>
<td>
<div dir="ltr">82.8</div>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<div dir="ltr">Percentage</div>
</td>
<td>
<div dir="ltr">4.29%</div>
</td>
<td>
<div dir="ltr">.172%</div>
</td>
<td>
<div dir="ltr">1.03%</div>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
<div dir="ltr">If you need to tell someone how likely it is that a petition will be granted, here is a cheat sheet:</div>
<p>
<ul>
<li dir="ltr">
<div dir="ltr">Overall: 1%</div>
</li>
<li dir="ltr">
<div dir="ltr">Paid petition: 4%</div>
</li>
<li dir="ltr">
<div dir="ltr">IFP petition: .1%</div>
</li>
</ul>
<p>But even those bald statistics don’t accurately indicate what’s happening.  “IMP” stands for “in forma pauperis.”  In order to be permitted to file a Supreme Court “cert. petition” (a petition asking the Court to hear your case in  order to consider reversing the lower appellate court’s ruling against you, on some issue of federal law) without paying the filing fee&#8211;or, for that matter, in order to be permitted to file any lawsuit or appeal at any level of the state or federal court system, without paying the filing fee to do so&#8211;you have to demonstrate that you do not have the filing fee.  
<div>The filing fee for a cert. petition is $300, which actually is $155 less than the fee to file an appeal in a lower federal appellate court (called a “circuit” court).  And since almost all federal lawsuits filed by ordinary individuals are systematically dismissed by the trial-court-level judge (knows as the “district judge”) shortly after they’re filed, and you have only 21 days in which to file a notice of appeal and pay the filing fee, you have to pay lay out about $800 within a very short period of time in order to have some chance to actually litigate your lawsuit.  </p>
<p>The cost of filing a cert. petition&#8211;the term “cert. is shorthand for “certiorari,” and is used only to refer to U.S. Supreme Court petitions&#8211;actually is roughly $5,000 to $7,000.  That’s because the Supreme Court’s Rules require the submission of an “original” and 39 (39!) copies of the cert. petition, which, the Rules require, must be submitted in “booklet” form.  “Booklet” form being a term of art: a prescribed size paper, which, suffice it to say, you can’t buy at Staples, card-stock covers of that same prescribed size (not available at Staples either), and a specific type of (expensive, actual-book-style) binding.  Only (I believe) three printing companies in the country specialize in this.  The petition itself is limited to 30 pages, but the Appendix&#8211;relevant court documents and exhibits in the case&#8211;must be included in the “booklet” or printed in its own separate “booklet.”  Only IFP petitioners can avoid this; they can file just an original and nine copies, on standard-size photocopy paper.  </p>
<p>So unless you literally don’t have  $300 (many prisoners don’t, of course), and you don’t have $5,000 to $7,000 at your disposal to spend on a lottery ticket, you can’t file a cert. petition at all, unless you’re able to get some nonprofit organization; there are a number of rightwing ones that will litigate for you and pay the expenses, but only the ACLU, to my knowledge, on the left.  Good luck, unless you have a real estate “takings” case, a gun-ownership-rights case, a freedom-of-religion/government-discrimination-against-religion case, or a reverse-race-discrimination case. </p>
<p>But I digress.  The subject of this post is the number of <i>filed</i> cert. petitions the Court grants.  And whose filed cert. petitions the Court grants.  And the statistics reflected in the Court’s new report give only part of that story, because a large percentage of the petitions the Court grants each year are those filed by governments&#8211;sometimes the federal government, but more often state governments (usually formally in the name of a state government employee or official such as a prison warden, thanks to a peculiarity in constitutional law), or local governments or an official or employee of one, e.g., a police officer.  These petitions are counted as “paid” petitions in the Court’s statistics.</p>
<p>And a large percentage of the remainder of the “paid” petitions that the Court grants are indeed very highly paid petitions.  They bear, on the petition cover, the name of a member of a tiny cadre of Supreme Court lobbyists&#8211;er, extremely highly-paid Supreme Court “specialists”&#8211;whose actual specialty is getting the Chamber of Commerce contingent on the Court to read the petition.  And, with the exception of very wealthy individuals such as Conrad Black and Jeffrey Skilling,* persons of the non-corporate variety need not, or more accurately, <i>cannot</i> apply.</p>
<p>So, here’s how I illustrate to people of the human type the reality of the clownish formal and <i>de facto</i> rules and customs of this clownish institution: I advise them to take their $6,000 and buy actual lottery tickets with it.  Or travel to Las Vegas and have some fun.  Or just throw it into the closest large body of water.  The Great Lakes here in the upper Midwest would work just fine.</p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />*The Supreme Court granted both Black’s and Skilling’s cert. petitions, filed on their respective behalfs by members of that cadre, commonly known as “the elite Supreme Court bar.”  Elite here being a legal term of art meaning “wayyy out the price range of ordinary folk.”  Their petitions challenged as unconstitutionally vague a federal criminal statute upon which parts of their indictments were based.  They won.  In unanimous opinions, if I recall correctly, the Court ruled the statute unconstitutionally vague.  And with good reason: it was.  But countless others before them surely had challenged that statute as unconstitutionally vague, to no avail.  This follows an absolutely institutionalized pattern in that Court.</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/even-the-tragicomical-newly-released-supreme-court-cert-grant-statistics-dont-reveal-the-worst-of-it.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Rightwing Supreme Court Justices&#8217; Fair-Weather &#034;State Sovereignty” Canard</title>
		<link>./../../2013/01/the-rightwing-supreme-court-justices-fair-weather-state-sovereignty-canard.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2013/01/the-rightwing-supreme-court-justices-fair-weather-state-sovereignty-canard.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 04 Jan 2013 17:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Anthony Kennedy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Clarence Thomas]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[federalism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[George Orwell]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Roberts]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mad Hatter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Maoism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Supreme court]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2013/01/the-rightwing-supreme-court-justices-fair-weather-state-sovereignty-canard.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Two days ago, Dan posted an entry by run75441 titled “SCOTUS Chastises Congress and the Executive Branch.”  The post’s title wasn’t quite accurate; run’s post was about Chief Justice John Roberts’ annual state-of-the-judicial-branch report, in which he was writing in his capacity as administrative head of that branch, not in his actual judicial capacity, and [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Two days ago, Dan posted an entry by run75441 titled “<a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2013/01/scotus-chastises-congress-and-executive.html">SCOTUS Chastises Congress and the Executive Branch</a>.”  The post’s title wasn’t quite accurate; run’s post was about Chief Justice John Roberts’ <a href="http://articles.washingtonpost.com/2012-12-31/politics/36103796_1_federal-courts-congressional-leaders-fiscal-cliff">annual state-of-the-judicial-branch report</a>, in which he was writing in his capacity as administrative head of that branch, not in his actual judicial capacity, and not for the other justices.  </p>
<p>Run (who didn’t title the post; Dan did) deeply criticized Roberts for bragging about the austerity of the federal courts in recent years, including his own court, which, he also bragged, had decided on 64 cases in its last term.  That was down from, I think, 70 the term before, and the main reason for that reduction was that the ACA case consumed a full week of oral-argument slots&#8211; the full week at issue normally consisting of arguments in six&#8211;count ‘em, six!&#8211;cases; some full weeks consist of four arguments, leaving the justices slightly less exhausted than they are after the six-argument work weeks.  </p>
<p>Roberts implied&#8211;he did not say so, expressly, but he did imply&#8211;that Congress and the White House take a cue from the justices and force the federal government to make do with less money.  To which I suggest that the justices really lead by example, and get rid of their four-justices-apiece law clerks, who do most of their work for them and start doing their legally-mandated jobs themselves.  After all, the federal government at least doesn’t pay salaries to congressional lobbyists&#8211;the equivalent of Supreme Court law clerks.</p>
<p>Anyway, I posted a comment to run’s post, and then asked Dan to add it as an update to run’s post, which he did.  My comment said:</p>
<div dir="ltr">The Supreme Court is rarely in session.  It’s seasonal, part-time work.  They usually hear argument in 10 cases a month, seven months a year.  In December, they didn’t hear even that many.</div>
<div dir="ltr">There’s really sooo much that can, and should, be said about the issue of (virtually universal lack of) access to the Supreme Court, and its repercussions.  Roberts’ bizarre, cutesy annual report is … oh … I don’t know …characteristically hubristic? </div>
<p>Run responded to my comment, and I then responded to his, writing:</p>
<p><a name="more"></a>
<div dir="ltr">What’s especially outrageous is the type of situation you’re talking about [a federal habeas corpus case challenging the constitutionality of aspects of the proceedings in a state-court criminal case]: The Supreme Court almost never agrees to hear cases on “direct appeal” (a legal term of art) from state supreme courts, in criminal or civil cases, with the major exception that they do often agree to do so in criminal cases when it is the state (i.e., the prosecution) that is asking them to hear hear the case in order to overrule a (rare) state supreme court ruling in favor of the criminal defendant. In state-court criminal cases, when it is the defendant who is asking the Supreme Court to hear the case in order to overturn a conviction, on constitutional grounds, the Supreme Court seems to figure that the criminal defendant can file a habeas corpus petition in a lower federal court. </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Which they can, but the Supreme court has made that right an all-but-empty one&#8211;just a shell game, really&#8211;by interpreting a 1996 “jurisdictional” statute in a way that bars the lower federal courts from throwing out the state-court conviction on constitutional grounds in almost every case. With each passing Supreme Court term, the right to federal habeas review becomes even narrower, a seeming impossibility until it happens. In the last two years, the Supreme Court has treated that right as all but nonexistent. So the almost-total lack of access to the Supreme Court on direct appeal by state-court criminal defendants effectively removes access to constitutional review in federal court. </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">This is even truer in civil cases [including some that involve incredibly important, truly fundamental rights of the sort protected under international human rights laws, although they have nothing at all to do with, say, prison inmates; really&#8211;trust me on this], thanks to a set of perverse, gimmicky Supreme Court-created “jurisdictional” doctrines, which the Supreme Court has stood by and watched metastasize to remove any access to federal court in order to make a constitutional challenge, except for ExxonMobil, which asked the Supreme Court to limit the doctrine at issue, which the Court did, so narrowly as to apply in almost no other case, especially since the other, related doctrine actually bars access in the circumstance in which ExxonMobil was allowed to have it. (Sort of like Bush v. Gore.)</div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Anthony Kennedy, the leader of this state-courts-have-sovereignty-and-dignity! juggernaut, likes to say this is done in the name of liberty. (Isn’t everything the rightwing wants done in the name of liberty?!) Which reminds me of a political science class I once took on Maoism. [Maoism] included, basically, the routine use of Orwellian language, in which everything is the opposite of what its name or description indicates. </div>
<p>
<div dir="ltr">Of course, the current Supreme Court’s goal&#8211;the goal of the legal right since the early 1980s&#8211;is to turn the law into nothing but circuitous yellow-brick-road procedure: a dead-end labyrinth whose very purpose is its circuitry and fruitlessness. They’ve come incredibly close to succeeding.</div>
<p>There’s a whole lot more about this that can, and should, be said, and I plan to write in more depth about it.  Which will make me the only one writing for public consumption about it; the general news media covers only “substantive” legal issues (“substantive” being another legal term of art; legal issues are either “substantive” or “procedural.”)  And rarely covers even substantive issues that aren’t part of the culture wars debate.  Which is really nice for the legal right, because their justices and judges can, and do, do just about anything they want, completely under the radar. </p>
<p>But for now, I’ll just add that the judicial right, lead on this by Kennedy and Clarence Thomas, conflate state sovereignty with freedom, but, at least regarding those two and their wingy three colleagues and some (but not all of their lower-court compadres), do so only with respect (pun most definitely intended) to state courts.  To them, state legislative- and executive-branch actions (e.g., state statutes) are fair game for constitutional challenges, and they harbor no inhibition whatsoever about impinging upon state “sovereignty” in recognizing the Constitution’s <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Supremacy_Clause">Supremacy Clause</a> when striking down as unconstitutional state statutes that the political right doesn’t care much for; Texas’s colleague-admissions affirmative action law, say.  (Sit tight for the upcoming oral argument there in that case.)  And their summary reversal of the Montana Supreme Court’s ruling late last year upholding the constitutionality of Montana’s longstanding campaign-finance statute is another example that comes (very) quickly to mind.  My mind, anyway.</p>
<p>To be fair to Kennedy, and certainly to his credit, he&#8211;and he alone, among the Fab Five&#8211;does extend this principle to state statutes that liberals don’t like.  Texas’s criminal anti-sodomy statute is one example, but there are other important ones as well.  </p>
<p>But, in what appears to me to be nothing more than just <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Professional_courtesy">old-fashioned professional courtesy</a>, Kennedy effectively exempts state judicial branches from Supremacy Clause mandates to honor constitutional rights of individuals.  And state courts violate individual procedural and substantive rights, in criminal cases and in certain types of civil cases, with absolute abandon, comfortable in the knowledge that they can.  The result, far, far more often than not, is the very antithesis of freedom.  Except in the Matter Hatter-esque language that the legal right has found so useful.</p>
<p>So, next time Kennedy or Thomas writes an opinion singing the praises of state sovereignty&#8211;by which they almost always just mean state-court sovereignty&#8211;as advancing “freedom,” ask them (rhetorically, of course; they won’t actually hear you unless you retain <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Clement">Paul Clement</a> to speak to them for you, which was basically run75441’s point) whether they think that, say, German Jews in the mid- and late 1930s were freer because Germany was a sovereign state.  <br />I will, anyway.  Or maybe I’ll just ask the Mad Hatter.  Orwell lives.  These days, though, in this country it&#8217;s called &#8220;federalism.&#8221;</p>
<p>&#8212;-</p>
<p>Occasionally, one of my AB posts goes viral (relatively speaking), racking up a couple thousand views on statcounter.  This is one that I hope does.  Actually, I hope it gets a million hits. </p>
<p>Yeah.  A million hits would be good.</p>
<p>Is there such a thing as hitting the Supreme Court in effigy?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2013/01/the-rightwing-supreme-court-justices-fair-weather-state-sovereignty-canard.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>An Editorial on Robert Bork and his Legacy</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/an-editorial-on-robert-bork-and-his-legacy.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/an-editorial-on-robert-bork-and-his-legacy.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 27 Dec 2012 00:54:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Corporatism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[history]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jazzbumpa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[monopoly]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[obituaries]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Supreme court]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/an-editorial-on-robert-bork-and-his-legacy.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[On Wednesday, December 19, 2012 Robert Heron Bork died at age 85.  I did not mourn. Bork first became infamous in 1973 for his role in the &#8220;Saturday night massacre&#8221; when as Solicitor General, the number three position in the Justice Department, he carried out, under President Nixon&#8217;s orders, the firing of Watergate Special Prosecutor [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>On Wednesday, December 19, 2012 <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/12/20/us/robert-h-bork-conservative-jurist-dies-at-85.html?pagewanted=1&#038;_r=1">Robert Heron Bork died at age 85</a>.  <a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/john-cooks-gawker-bork-obituary-causing-furor-through-honesty-2012-12">I did not mourn</a>.</p>
<p>Bork  first became infamous in 1973 for his role in the &#8220;Saturday night  massacre&#8221; when as Solicitor General, the number three position in the  Justice Department, he carried out, under President Nixon&#8217;s orders, the  firing of Watergate Special Prosecutor Archibald Cox.  Bork inherited  this task when both Attorney General Elliot Richardson and Deputy  Attorney General William Ruckelshaus resigned in protest.  This much is  well known.  What sometimes gets left out of the discussion, though, is  that due to the manner in which Cox&#8217;s position was created and defined, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saturday_Night_Massacre">he could not be removed except for cause</a>.   Doing a good job of tracking down evidence relevant to the case he was  pursuing does not qualify as cause.  This was a defining moment in  Bork&#8217;s career, in which he conveniently chose power over principle.</p>
<p>Most  recently he was the senior judicial adviser to Mitt Romney’s  unsuccessful presidential campaign, but he is best known for being  rejected as a Supreme Court justice when nominated for that position in  1987 by Ronald Reagan.  After his nomination was defeated by  a 58-42 vote in the Senate, his name was verberized into a neologism  that was [<a href="http://www.propublica.org/article/was-petraeus-borked"><u>and occasionally still is</u></a>] used almost exclusively in the passive voice.</p>
<p>To be &#8220;borked,&#8221; as his supporters would have it, is to be subjected to  unfair criticisms based on distortions of your words, actions, and  beliefs.  But his radically reactionary views on <a href="http://www.nwlc.org/our-blog/romney-advisor-robert-bork-equal-protection-clause-doesn%E2%80%99t-protect-against-sex-discriminati">equal protection and sex discrimination</a> were typical of his extreme and perverse positions. The mere fact that he was able to speak out <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/1987/10/23/opinion/l-bork-hearings-showed-how-democracy-works-a-very-small-poll-tax-174787.html">in favor of a poll tax</a> speaks volumes.  In reality, the borking of Bork consisted of <a href="http://www.lawyersgunsmoneyblog.com/2012/12/robert-bork">subjecting him to valid criticism</a> based on <a href="http://www.salon.com/2012/12/19/robert_borks_nauseating_worldview/">the precise meanings</a> of his words, actions  and beliefs.  <a href="http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/newsdesk/2012/12/postscript-robert-bork-1927-2012.html#ixzz2FnPlFnfD">Jeffrey Toobin explains</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p>Bork was “borked” simply by being confronted with his own  views—which would have undone many of the great constitutional landmarks  in recent American history. As Senator Edward Kennedy put it in a  famous speech on the Senate floor, “Robert Bork’s America is a land in  which women would be forced into back-alley abortions, blacks would sit  at segregated lunch counters, rogue police could break down citizens’  doors in midnight raids, schoolchildren could not be taught about  evolution, [and] writers and artists would be censored at the whim of  government.” </p></blockquote>
<p>
<blockquote> Was Kennedy too harsh? He was not—as Bork himself demonstrated in the  series of intemperate books he wrote after losing the Supreme Court  fight and quitting the bench, in 1987. The titles alone were revealing:  ”The Tempting of America,” “Slouching Towards Gomorrah: Modern  Liberalism and American Decline,” and “Coercing Virtue: The Worldwide  Rule of Judges.” One of his last books may have summed up his views  best. Thanks in part to decisions of the Supreme Court—decisions that,  for the most part, Bork abhorred—the United States became a more  tolerant and inclusive place, with greater freedom of expression and  freedom from discrimination than any society in history. Bork called the  book, accurately, “A Country I Do Not Recognize.”  </p></blockquote>
<p>Indeed,  Bork&#8217;s words and actions were consistently anti-gay, anti-female,  anti-minority, always favoring government intrusion over citizen&#8217;s  rights, businesses over people, big business over small, and  corporations over government.  His supporters would argue that these  conclusions are based on principled positions, and that the outcomes,  however repugnant to idealists, are therefore legitimate.  I argue  instead that policies that consistently result in the contraction rather  than the expansion of basic human rights, and that continually  disadvantage definable target groups are corrupt at their core, and that  the negative results are inherent and predictable. </p>
<p>After his defeat, Robert Bork  gradually faded away from the public consciousness.  I can tell you, in  the intervening 25 years, I gave him virtually no thought at all.</p>
<p>But Bork had enormous, possibly even dominant influence on <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/wonkblog/wp/2012/12/20/antitrust-was-defined-by-robert-bork-i-cannot-overstate-his-influence/">the modern interpretation of anti-trust law</a>,  perhaps single-handedly redefining the scope and purpose of anti-trust  legislation.  Basically, Bork was pro-efficiency and anti-anti-trust.   He had swallowed whole the bait-bucket of Chicago-economic-school ideas of  market efficiency, and built the entire framework of his pro-trust  belief system on that invalid foundation.</p>
<p>It seems fair to say that it is in some part because of Bork&#8217;s  influence that we now have trans-national mega-corporations with huge oligopolies and near-monopolies.  These corporations have no inherent loyalty  to anyone nor anything.  In my view, the oligarchs that run them do not  even have a general sense of loyalty to stock-holders, let alone the  broader universe of stake-holders, who mainly exist to be exploited.</p>
<p>Efficiency, in and of itself is a good thing.  But it cannot be achieved  in a vacuum &#8211; frequently there are externalities that are largely negative.  For  one thing, the efficiencies are mainly internalized and do not  necessarily represent a more broadly efficient society.  Second, as a  market gets concentrated, competition decreases and the pressure to  improve, or even maintain status-quo efficiency slowly erodes.  This  ultimately leads to a situation where big, lumbering and inefficient but  extremely powerful entities control the economic and political  landscape.  Yes, Big Oil, Big Pharma, Big Insurance, Big Finance, I am  looking at you.</p>
<p>Perhaps worse, though, is the power asymmetry that results from size and  influence.  Suppliers, customers, and the public at large are  overwhelmed by the sheer might of these institutions, leading to even  greater concentrations of power and wealth.</p>
<p>The end  game is some version of economic collapse.  It happened in the  1930&#8217;s, and &#8211; due largely to neoclassical Chicago-style economic  thinking that has over the last 40 years willfully unlearned the lessons  of that time &#8211; it  happened again in 2008.</p>
<p>Most of the time, evil doesn&#8217;t  manifest as some cackling cartoon villain, mad-man on a murderous  rampage, or even an unjust war waged on false pretenses.  It results  instead, in a far more banal but  far-reaching way, from the highly refined ideas of men like Robert Bork  who value abstract concepts such as efficiency over the effects the  programs they institute have on the lives of real human beings.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/an-editorial-on-robert-bork-and-his-legacy.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>FOLLOW-UP to, “Do ‘Right to work’ Laws Violate the Constitution&#8217;s Contracts Clause?”</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/follow-up-to-do-right-to-work-laws-violate-the-constitutions-contracts-clause.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/follow-up-to-do-right-to-work-laws-violate-the-constitutions-contracts-clause.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 13 Dec 2012 19:07:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Contracts Clause]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Matthew Yglesias]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[PJS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Right-to-Work laws]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sec. 10]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Seth Ackerman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Supreme court]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Taft-Hartley Act]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/follow-up-to-do-right-to-work-laws-violate-the-constitutions-contracts-clause.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Last night, in a comment to my post from Tuesday, “Do‘Right to Work’ Laws Violate the Constitution Contracts Clause?”, reader PJR wrote: To a non-lawyer, it kinda looks like SCOTUS rejected the contracts argument in 1949, so unions would have to find someway to get the court(s) to reconsider&#8211;or is this wrong? If wrong, why [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div>Last night, in a comment to my post from Tuesday, “<a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/12/do-right-to-work-laws-violate.html?utm_source=feedburner&#038;utm_medium=feed&#038;utm_campaign=Feed%3A+blogspot%2FHzoh+%28Angry+Bear%29">Do‘Right to Work’ Laws Violate the Constitution Contracts Clause?</a>”, reader PJR wrote:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>To a non-lawyer, it kinda looks like SCOTUS rejected the contracts argument in 1949, so unions would have to find someway to get the court(s) to reconsider&#8211;or is this wrong? If wrong, why the heck haven&#8217;t unions tried this? ( http://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/335/525/case.html)
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>I began writing a response that I planned to post in the Comments section, but then realized that the post would be too long (wayyy too long) for that, and that the issue was important enough to post directly as a blog post, in follow-up to the initial post.  So, here’s the follow-up in response to PJS’s comment:
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212;-
</p>
</div>
<div>Hmm.  The opinion PJS links to, <i>Lincoln Union v. Northwestern Co</i>., from 1949, says that the Court earlier decided that the ‘right to work’ laws at issue in that case don’t violate the Contracts clause, but the opinion doesn’t elaborate except to cite, without comment, to a 1934 opinion, <i>Home Building &#038; Loan Assn. v. Blaisdell</i>.  
</p>
</div>
<div>But <i>Home Building &#038; Loan Assn</i>. had nothing to do with labor contracts.  In that case, the Court upheld the constitutionality of a Minnesota law that required mortgage holders to grant homeowners longer periods of time to begin again to repay their mortgages after missing payments, before the mortgage company could foreclose on the house.  The Court said this didn’t violate the Contracts clause because states must be allowed to address severe emergencies by requiring an altered “remedy” for completion of the contract—in that case, a longer time in which to repay the mortgage—as long as the legislation didn’t alter the ultimate amount owed. 
</p>
</div>
<div>The opinion recites the economic devastation of the Depression, and says that the Contracts clause must be interpreted to allow states some leeway to protect the state’s residents as long as the leeway wasn’t so great as to deprive the mortgage holder permanently of a property right—the right to eventual full payment of the mortgage. Then, after discussing two 1870s Supreme Court opinion that interpret the Contracts clause as absolute, the opinion says that it really is not, as long as the change is just temporary and in response to a real emergency.  (This is apart from the state’s right to permanently bar contracts or provisions in contracts that violate criminal or civil law—a separate “public policy” exemption that has existed since the founding; people (including corporate people) can’t simply contract away the criminal law or certain types of civil law.  Although lately the Supreme Court, in a series of 5-4 opinions, does pretty much allow <i>corporate</i> people to do <i>exactly</i> that.)  
</p>
</div>
<div>Yet, in <i>Home Building &#038; Loan Assoc</i>., the Court interpreted <i>Lincoln Union</i> as allowing states to declare exempt from the Contracts clause pretty much anything it wants, simply by declaring it public policy in the interest of the state’s citizens.  Here’s the extent of what that opinion says about the Contract clause issue:
</p>
</div>
<div>Second. There is a suggestion though not elaborated in briefs that these state laws conflict with Art. I, 10, of the United States Constitution, insofar as they impair the obligation of contracts made prior to their enactment. That this contention is without merit is now too clearly established to require discussion. See <i>Home Bldg. &#038; Loan Ass&#8217;n v. Blaisdell</i>, <a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?court=us&#038;vol=290&#038;invol=398#436">290 U.S. 398, 436 </a>-439, 239, 240, 88 A.L.R. 1481, and cases <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766" name="532">[335 U.S. 525 , 532] </a>  there cited. And also <i>Veix v. Sixth Ward Building &#038; Loan Ass&#8217;n</i>, <a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?navby=case&#038;court=us&#038;vol=310&#038;invol=32#38">310 U.S. 32, 38 </a>, 794; East New York Savings Bank v. Hahn, <a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?navby=case&#038;court=us&#038;vol=326&#038;invol=230#232">326 U.S. 230, 232 </a>, 70, 160 A.L.R. 1279.
</p>
</div>
<div>After “seeing” <i>Home Building</i>, I can say that that conclusory statement is clearly a deeply distorted interpretation of <i>Lincoln Union</i>.  Read <i>Home Building</i>.  You be the justice, er, the judge, about what it says.
</p>
</div>
<div>Ditto, and then some, for the other two referenced opinions.  <i>Veix v. Sixth Ward Building &#038; Loan Assoc</i>., decided in 1940, begins:
</p>
</div>
<div>In 1928 and 1929 appellant purchased prepaid shares of the appellee, a New Jersey building and loan association, paying the pay value of $200 per share. At that time the applicable New Jersey statutes provided that shares in such an association could be withdrawn by giving such written notice as the constitution or by-laws of the association provided, not to exceed 30 days; that withdrawals should be paid in the order in which notices were received, with not more than one-half of the receipts of any month being required to be used for payment of withdrawals, without the consent of the board of directors, until the oldest unpaid claim of withdrawal had been on file for six months; that no payment should be postponed for longer than six months from the date of notice; and that any member who had given notice could sue and recover the withdrawal value if it was not paid within six months of the notice. <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766" name="t1"></a><a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?navby=case&#038;court=us&#038;vol=310&#038;invol=32#f1">1 </a> 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>On April 22, 1932, these statutes were amended in four respects: (1) &#8216;total receipts&#8217; of an association, one-half of which were required to be used for the payment of withdrawals and which had not been previously defined, were defined as income on authorized investments, dues on shares of the association which were pledged with it to secure loans, and repayments from loans; (2) if in any one month the funds required to be payable for withdrawals were insufficient to pay all requested withdrawals, withdrawing members were to receive $500 each in the order of priority until the fund for withdrawals was exhausted; (3) no withdrawals were to be paid if the funds available for payment of matured shares were insufficient to pay all matured shares, the payment of which had been requested within thirty days after maturity; (4) so long as the funds of an association were applied as required by the amendment, no member who had filed his withdrawal notice should have a right to sue for the withdrawal value of his shares. <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766" name="t2"></a><a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?navby=case&#038;court=us&#038;vol=310&#038;invol=32#f2">2 </a>  In 1935 another amendment was passed providing that one-third of the &#8216;net receipts&#8217; of an association were to be payable for withdrawals, with &#8216;net receipts&#8217; defined as monies, other than borrowed monies, received by the association less operating expenses, payments on creditor obligations, payments for protecting the property of the association and reserves for any of these purposes. At the same time payments of withdrawals in the order in which notices had been received was continued but the payments were limited to $50 per member.
</p>
</div>
<div>And here’s its holding, and the explanation for it:
</p>
</div>
<div>In <i>Home Building &#038; Loan Association v. Blaisdell </i> <a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?navby=case&#038;court=us&#038;vol=310&#038;invol=32#f12">10</a> this Court considered the authority retained by the state over contracts &#8216;to safeguard the vital interests of its people.&#8217; The rule that all contracts are made subject to this paramount authority was there reiterated. Such authority is not limited to health, morals and safety. <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766" name="t11"></a><a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?navby=case&#038;court=us&#038;vol=310&#038;invol=32#f11">11 </a> It extends to economic needs as well. <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766" name="t12"></a><a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?navby=case&#038;court=us&#038;vol=310&#038;invol=32#f12">12 </a>Utility rate contracts give way to this power,  <a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?navby=case&#038;court=us&#038;vol=310&#038;invol=32#f12">13 </a> as do contractual arrangements between landlords and tenants. <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766" name="t"></a><a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?navby=case&#038;court=us&#038;vol=310&#038;invol=32#f">14 </a> </div>
<div>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The cases cited in the preceding paragraph make repeated reference to the emergency existing at the time of the enactment of the questioned statutes. Many of the enactments were temporary in character. We are here considering a permanent piece of legislation. So far as the contract clause is concerned, is this significant? We think not. &#8216;Emergency does not create (constitutional) power, emergency may furnish the occasion for the exercise of power.&#8217; <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766" name="t15"></a><a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?navby=case&#038;court=us&#038;vol=310&#038;invol=32#f15">15 </a>We think of emergencies as suddenly arising and quickly passing. The emergency of the depression may have caused the 1932 legislation, but the weakness in the financial system brought to light by that emergency remains. If the legislature could enact the legislation as to withdrawals to protect the associations in that emergency, we see no reason why the new status should not continue. When the 1932 act was passed commercial and savings banks, insurance companies and building and loan associations were suffering heavy withdrawals. The liquid portion of their assets were being rapidly drained off by their customers, leaving the long term investments and depreciated assets as an inadequate source for payment of the remaining liabilities. An acceleration or a continuance of this tendency to withdraw available funds threatened a quick end to the ability of the institutions to meet even normal demands. Such threatened insolvency demands legislation for its control in the same way that liquidation after insolvency does. Such legislation may be classed as emergency in one sense but it need not be temporary. <a href="http://www.blogger.com/blogger.g?blogID=5048766" name="t16"></a><a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?navby=case&#038;court=us&#038;vol=310&#038;invol=32#f16">16 </a> 
</p>
</div>
<div>And <i>East New York Savings Bank v. Hahn</i>, issued in 1945, pretty much sums it up:
</p>
</div>
<div>Since <i>Home Bldg. &#038; L. Ass&#8217;n v. Blaisdell</i>, <a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?court=us&#038;vol=290&#038;invol=398">290 U.S. 398 </a>, 54 S.Ct. 231, 88 A.L.R. 1481, there are left hardly any open spaces of controversy concerning the constitutional restrictions of the Contract Clause upon moratory legislation referable to the depression. The comprehensive opinion of Mr. Chief Justice Hughes in that case cut beneath the skin of words to the core of meaning. After a full review of the whole course of decisions expounding the Contract Clause-covering almost the life of this Court-the Chief Justice, drawing on the early insight of Mr. Justice Johnson2 in <i>Ogden v. Saunders</i>, 12 Wheat. 213, 286, as reinforced by later decisions cast in more modern terms, e.g., <i>Manigault v. Springs</i>, <a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?court=us&#038;vol=199&#038;invol=473#480">199 U.S. 473, 480 </a>, 26 S.Ct. 127, 130; <i>Marcus Brown Co. v. Feldman</i>, <a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?court=us&#038;vol=256&#038;invol=170#198">256 U.S. 170, 198 </a>, 41 S.Ct. 465, 466, put the Clause in its proper perspective in our constitutional framework. The <i>Blaisdell </i>case and decisions rendered since (e.g., <i>Honeyman v. Jacobs,</i> <a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?court=us&#038;vol=306&#038;invol=539">306 U.S. 539 </a>, 59 S.Ct. 702; <i>Veix v. Sixth Ward Ass&#8217;n</i>, <a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?court=us&#038;vol=310&#038;invol=32">310 U.S. 32 </a>, 60 S.Ct. 792; <i>Gelfert v. National City Bank</i>, <a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?court=us&#038;vol=313&#038;invol=221">313 U.S. 221 </a>, 61 S.Ct. 898, 133 A.L.R. 1467; <i>Faitoute Co. v. Asbury Park</i>, <a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?court=us&#038;vol=316&#038;invol=502">316 U.S. 502 </a>, 62 S.Ct. 1129), yield this governing constitutional principle: when a widely diffused public interest has become enmeshed in a network of multitudinous private arrangements, the authority of the State &#8216;to safeguard the vital interests of its people,&#8217; 290 U.S. at page 434, 54 S. Ct. at page 239, 88 A.L.R. 1481, is not to be gainsaid by abstracting one such arrangement from its public context and treating it as though it were an isolated private contract constitutionally immune from impairment.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>The formal mode of reasoning by means of which this &#8216;protective power of the state,&#8217; 290 U.S. at page 440, 54 S.Ct. at page 241, 88 A.L.R. 1481, is acknowledged is of little moment. It may be treated as an implied condition of every contract and, as such, as much part of the contract as though it were written into it, whereby the State&#8217;s exercise of its power enforces, and does not impair, a contract. A more candid statement is to recognize, as was said in<i> Manigault v. Springs</i>, supra, that the power &#8216;which, in its various ramifications, is known as the police power, is an exercise of the sovereign right of the government to protect the &#8230; general welfare of the people, and is paramount to any rights under contracts  between individuals.&#8217; 199 U.S. at page 480, 26 S.Ct. at page 130. Once we are in this domain of the reserve power of a State we must respect the &#8216;wide discretion on the part of the legislature in determining what is and what is not necessary.&#8217; Id. So far as the constitutional issue is concerned, &#8216;the power of the State when otherwise justified,&#8217; <i>Marcus Brown Co. v. Feldman</i>, <a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?court=us&#038;vol=256&#038;invol=170#198">256 U.S. 170, 198 </a>, 41 S.Ct. 465, 466, is not diminished because a private contract may be affected.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>In other words, a state can use what is in essence its police power to limit the state the absolute right to freely contract, but only “to safeguard the vital interests of its people.”  Suffice it to say that none of those three opinions gave any indication, much less outright held, that a vital interest of the people of any state was to be able to avoid payment of union dues, much less to avoid payment of lower union-administration fees, as a union-beneficiary employee in a union shop. 
</p>
</div>
<div>In any event, <i>Lincoln Union</i>, in pretending that <i>Home Building</i> and the other two New Deal era opinions say things contrary to what they actually say, dealt only with compulsory union <i>membership</i>, not with required non-union-member administrative fees paid to unions.  That case was decided two years after passage of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taft%E2%80%93Hartley_Act">Taft-Hartley Act</a>.  And Taft-Hartley itself bars required union membership, while also requiring that unions negotiate compensation and working conditions on behalf of all the employees within unionized categories, irrespective of whether the employee has chosen to join the union., and also requires the union to represent those employees in controversies between the individual employee and the employer other just as they do for union members in other words, to provide all the union benefits even to employees who opted out of union membership.
</p>
</div>
<div>In return, that law does allow the non-union employees to be required as a provision of the collective-bargaining agreement to pay union-administration fees.
</p>
</div>
<div>I don’t think the administrative-fee requirement is “materially” (a legalese term of art) the same as the pre-Taft-Hartley contractual agreements that barred employers from hiring people who will refuse to join the union. And, certainly, it does not involve addressing severe long-term emergency that even remotely brings it within the reach of the <i>Home Building &#038; Loan Assoc</i>. public-policy exemption from a narrow Contracts Clause interpretation. So, best as I can tell—and I am NOT an expert in labor law—the Supreme Court has never actually held that state ‘right to work’ laws do not violate the Contracts Clause.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>That said, although the rightwing justices normally are all for upholding the right of contract, when the shoe is on the pro-Democratic Party foot rather than the pro-Republican one (or is it the reverse? I’m not sure), they probably would not uphold that right in this circumstance.  These people are the ultimate hypocrites.  And stunningly, unabashedly so.  And they hold a bare majority on the Court.  </div>
<div></div>
<div>For now.
</p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />COOL UPDATE, <a href="http://jacobinmag.com/2012/12/the-shift-from-the-unions/">here</a>.  H/T <a href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/moneybox/2012/12/13/the_shift_away_from_unions_organized_labor_s_inevitable_terminal_decline.html">Matthew Yglesias</a>.</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/follow-up-to-do-right-to-work-laws-violate-the-constitutions-contracts-clause.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Brands and generics pharmaceuticals&#8230;</title>
		<link>./../../2012/12/brands-and-generics-pharmaceuticals.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/12/brands-and-generics-pharmaceuticals.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 09 Dec 2012 11:49:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[importing pharmaceuticals]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[pharmaceutical industry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Supreme court]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/12/brands-and-generics-pharmaceuticals.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The case is Federal Trade Commission v. Watson Pharmaceuticals et al, No. 12-416.   Via the New York Times comes this note: Last year, for the third time since 2003, the 11th Circuit upheld the agreements as long as the allegedly anticompetitive behavior that results — in this case, keeping the generic drug off the market [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The case is Federal Trade Commission v. Watson Pharmaceuticals et al, No. 12-416.  </p>
<p>Via the <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/12/08/business/justices-to-take-up-generic-drug-case.html?emc=tnt&#038;tntemail1=y&#038;_r=0" target="_blank">New York Times</a> comes this note:</p>
<blockquote><p>Last year, for the third time since 2003, the 11th Circuit upheld the agreements as long as the allegedly anticompetitive behavior that results — in this case, keeping the generic drug off the market — is the same thing that would take place if the brand-name company’s patent were upheld. </p>
<p>Two other federal circuit courts, the Second Circuit and the Federal Circuit, have ruled similarly. But in July, the Third Circuit Court of Appeals said that those arrangements were anticompetitive on their face and violated antitrust law. </p>
<p><a name="more"></a></p>
<p>The agreements are also affected by a peculiar condition in the law that legalized generic competition for prescription drugs. That law, known as the Hatch-Waxman Act, gives a 180-day period of exclusivity to the first generic drug maker to file for approval of a generic copy and to file a lawsuit challenging the brand-name drug’s patent. </p>
<p>Brand-name drug companies have taken advantage of that law, finding that they can settle the patent suit by getting the generic company to agree to stay out of the market for a period of time. Because that generic company also has exclusivity rights, no other generic companies can enter the market. </p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/12/brands-and-generics-pharmaceuticals.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Religious freedom, contraception, and law</title>
		<link>./../../2012/11/religious-freedom-contraception-and-law.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/11/religious-freedom-contraception-and-law.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 29 Nov 2012 13:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Supreme court]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/11/religious-freedom-contraception-and-law.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Lifted from a note from Beverly Mann in response to a query of mine, as a note of interest: Here&#8217;s a link to a long Politico article on those cases and on the prospects of their success: http://dyn.politico.com/printstory.cfm?uuid=67901EA4-2955-4FD7-A52E-1E8CB0EA8E56 Apparently it looks like the Supreme Court eventually will hear two or three of these cases, probably [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Lifted from a note from Beverly Mann in response to a query of mine, as a note of interest:</p>
<p>Here&#8217;s a link to a long Politico article on those cases and on the prospects of their success:</p>
<p><a href="http://dyn.politico.com/printstory.cfm?uuid=67901EA4-2955-4FD7-A52E-1E8CB0EA8E56">http://dyn.politico.com/printstory.cfm?uuid=67901EA4-2955-4FD7-A52E-1E8CB0EA8E56</a></p>
<p>Apparently it looks like the Supreme Court eventually will hear two or three of these cases, probably all at one time, and draw some line about which organizations and for-profit companies are entitled to be exempt from the contraception part of the mandate. But mainly, these lawsuits concern a federal statute called <em>The Religious Freedom Restoration Act</em>, which provides religious protections for these groups beyond what the Supreme Court has held that the First Amendment requires. That statute was passed in reaction to a Supreme Court opinion that defined the First Amendment&#8217;s Free Exercise clause more narrowly than a majority of Congress thought was appropriate.</p>
<p>The Politico article gives a pretty detailed rundown on this.</p>
<p><i>Beverly</i></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/11/religious-freedom-contraception-and-law.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>More corporate First Amendment Rights?</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/more-corporate-first-amendment-rights.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/more-corporate-first-amendment-rights.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 21 Oct 2012 02:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[corporations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[First amendment rights]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Supreme court]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/more-corporate-first-amendment-rights.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Via Truthout comes this report from PR Watch: In a new lawsuit against the Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC), big energy extractors are pushing for carte blanche in their interactions with foreign governments, making it harder to track whether their deals are padding the coffers of dictators, warlords, or crony capitalists. The United States Chamber of [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Via <a href="http://truth-out.org/news/item/12224-big-oil-and-the-us-chamber-of-commerce-fight-to-keep-foreign-bribery-flourishing">Truthout</a> comes this report <a href="http://prwatch.org/news/2012/10/11802/big-oil-and-us-chamber-fight-keep-foreign-bribery-flourishing">from PR Watch</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>In a new lawsuit against the Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC), big energy extractors are pushing for carte blanche in their interactions with foreign governments, making it harder to track whether their deals are padding the coffers of dictators, warlords, or crony capitalists. The <a href="http://www.sourcewatch.org/index.php?title=United_States_Chamber_of_Commerce">United States Chamber of Commerce</a>, <a href="http://www.sourcewatch.org/index.php?title=American_Petroleum_Institute">American Petroleum Institute</a>, the <a href="http://www.sourcewatch.org/index.php?title=Independent_Petroleum_Association_of_America">Independent Petroleum Association of America</a>, and the National Foreign Trade Council <a href="http://www.reuters.com/article/2012/10/10/sec-lawsuit-idUSL1E8LAM2L20121010">filed</a> a lawsuit on October 10, 2012 against <a href="http://www.sec.gov/news/press/2012/2012-164.htm">a new SEC rule,</a> which requires U.S. oil, mining and gas companies to formally disclose payments made to foreign governments as part of their annual SEC reporting. </p></blockquote>
<p><a href="http://www.chamberlitigation.com/api-and-chamber-commerce-et-al-v-us-securities-and-exchange-commission">Chamber of Commerce</a>  <i>National Chamber Litigation Center</i> quote says:</p>
<blockquote><p>On October 10, 2012, the Chamber and its association partners filed a <u><a href="http://www.chamberlitigation.com/sites/default/files/cases/files/2012/Complaint%20--%20API%20and%20Chamber%20of%20Commerce,%20et%20al.%20v.%20SEC%20(D.C.%20District%20Court).PDF">complaint with the U.S. District Court for the District of Columbia</a></u> and a <u><a href="http://www.chamberlitigation.com/sites/default/files/cases/files/2012/Petition%20for%20Review%20--%20API%20and%20Chamber%20of%20Commerce,%20et%20al.%20v.%20SEC%20(D.C.%20Circuit).pdf">petition for review with the U.S. Court of Appeals for the D.C. Circuit</a></u>, charging that the rule violates the First Amendment, the Administrative Procedure Act (APA), and the Exchange Act of 1934. The lawsuits allege that the SEC failed to conduct an adequate cost-benefit analysis as required by law, that the SEC grossly misinterpreted its statutory mandate to make a “compilation” of information available to the public, and that the regulation is incompatible with the First Amendment.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/more-corporate-first-amendment-rights.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Scotusblog roundup…fyi</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/scotusblog-roundupfyi.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/scotusblog-roundupfyi.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 03 Oct 2012 23:16:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Beverly Mann (Supreme court)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Supreme court]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/scotusblog-roundupfyi.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Beverly Mann makes Scotusblog roundup again: Monday’s oral arguments in Kiobel v. Royal Dutch Petroleum continued to generate press yesterday. Coverage of the arguments comes from Jess Bravin of the Wall Street Journal, Garrett Epps at The Atlantic, Alison Frankel at Thomson Reuters, Steven D. Schwinn at Constitutional Law Prof Blog, Trey Childress at PrawfsBlawg, Julia [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Beverly Mann makes <a href="http://www.scotusblog.com/2012/10/wednesday-round-up-154/#more-153166" target="_blank">Scotusblog roundup again</a>:<br />
<blockquote>Monday’s oral arguments in <a href="http://www.scotusblog.com/case-files/cases/kiobel-v-royal-dutch-petroleum/"><em>Kiobel v. Royal Dutch Petroleum</em></a> continued to generate press yesterday. Coverage of the arguments comes from Jess Bravin of the <a href="https://plus.google.com/109671482387268169423/posts/GcKDCQDfkq1?gpinv=AMIXal96SNS22tFiqm2MrXfalGEn-s6C7tTCPLBR_xW2ZWtvOQSJ5UcU2aGfl8m09wESzMlHFffDC5K4lq6P7J2KUumFMw_rVlosuMpr_emO2gJbDA6kkKI">Wall Street Journal</a>, Garrett Epps at The <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/national/archive/2012/10/the-supreme-courts-new-term-starts-with-echoes-of-its-last/263134/">Atlantic</a>, Alison Frankel at <a href="http://newsandinsight.thomsonreuters.com/Legal/News/ViewNews.aspx?id=58156">Thomson Reuters</a>, Steven D. Schwinn at <a href="http://lawprofessors.typepad.com/conlaw/2012/10/high-court-skeptical-of-nigerians-human-rights-claim-in-us-courts.html">Constitutional Law Prof Blog</a>, Trey Childress at <a href="http://prawfsblawg.blogs.com/prawfsblawg/2012/10/what-will-the-court-do-with-the-alien-tort-statute.html">PrawfsBlawg</a>, Julia Zebley at <a href="http://jurist.org/paperchase/2012/10/supreme-court-rehears-arguments-in-corporate-liability-case-from-last-term.php">JURIST</a>, Beverly Mann at <a href="http://www.angrybearblog.com/2012/10/justice-scalias-super-body-and-no-it.html">Angry Bear</a>, and Jeremy Leaming at <a href="http://www.acslaw.org/acsblog/high-court-%E2%80%98obsessed-with-corporate-power%E2%80%99-may-exempt-oil-giant-from-human-rights-law">ACSblog</a>, while commentary comes from Bruce Ramsey at the <a href="http://seattletimes.com/html/edcetera/2019323930_will_the_supreme_court_finally.html">Seattle Times</a>. Kali posted pictures taken at the Court after the <em>Kiobel</em> arguments on <a href="http://www.scotusblog.com/2012/10/yesterday-at-the-court-photos-from-the-plaza-after-kiobel/">this blog</a>.</p></blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/scotusblog-roundupfyi.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Justice Scalia’s Super Body (And, no, it has nothing to do with the Constitution’s Free Exercise Clause. Really.)*</title>
		<link>./../../2012/10/justice-scalias-super-body-and-no-it-has-nothing-to-do-with-the-constitutions-free-exercise-clause-really.html</link>
		<comments>./../../2012/10/justice-scalias-super-body-and-no-it-has-nothing-to-do-with-the-constitutions-free-exercise-clause-really.html#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 02 Oct 2012 20:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[AEDPA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Alien Tort Statute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Anthony Kennedy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Antonin Scalia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dye v. Hofbauer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Emily Bazelon]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Johnson v. Williams]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kiobel v. Royal Dutch Petroleum]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Samuel Alito]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Slate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Supreme court]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://angrybearblog.com/2012/10/justice-scalias-super-body-and-no-it-has-nothing-to-do-with-the-constitutions-free-exercise-clause-really.html</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[First, Justice Anthony Kennedy wants to know what possible connection there is between Esther Kiobel, the wrongs she says unfolded in Nigeria, and the United States. The answer the plaintiffs’ lawyer, Paul Hoffman, gives is that his clients live here because the U.S. government gave them asylum. Also, Royal Dutch Petroleum does plenty of business [&#8230;]]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>First, Justice Anthony Kennedy wants to know what possible connection there is between Esther Kiobel, the wrongs she says unfolded in Nigeria, and the United States. The answer the plaintiffs’ lawyer, Paul Hoffman, gives is that his clients live here because the U.S. government gave them asylum. Also, Royal Dutch Petroleum does plenty of business here. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Kennedy doesn’t like the sound of that. “Your position is that a U.S. company that allegedly commits a human rights violation could be sued in any court in the world?” he asks. Note the switch—now it’s our homegrown corporation, not a company called Royal Dutch, that’s the pirate.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Justice Antonin Scalia backs up Kennedy, asking whether it will be “some super body that decides what constitutes a violation” of human rights. This is not a superhero kind of super body. It’s the kind that usurps U.S. sovereignty. Hoffman tries to erase the image: The courts of nations around the world have long determined human rights norms, he says. But Scalia is with Kennedy: unhappy about a world in which U.S. corporations can be held liable for human rights abuses in foreign courts. Justice Samuel Alito doesn’t like Hoffman’s notion either, and Chief Justice John Roberts seems skeptical, too. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Hoffman next addresses all the ways his clients could still get kicked out of court, even if they make it past today’s tangle with the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alien_Tort_Statute">Alien Tort Statute</a>. They could be told to file suit in Nigeria, or the Netherlands or the United Kingdom, where Royal Dutch Petroleum is based. Hoffman concedes that it’s not clear from the record whether they’ve done so yet. (This is the doctrine called exhaustion, which is how it feels to be told to go back and start over somewhere else.) Kiobel and the other plaintiffs could also be told that another forum, outside the United States, is simply better. (This is the doctrine called <em>forum non conveniens</em>, the rare Latin phrase that makes sense without translation.)
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>&#8212; <i><a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/jurisprudence/2012/10/the_supreme_court_considers_whether_the_united_states_can_be_the_court_of_last_resort_for_aliens_who_have_suffered_human_rights_abuses_abroad_.single.html">Torture Inc.: The Supreme Court term begins with a knotty human rights claim against big oil</a>.</i>, Emily Bazelon, Slate, yesterday
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Pardon me.  But it sure sounds like Scalia’s complaint is really with—Can this be?—the Founders, who, by enacting a statute that gives federal courts jurisdiction to hear claims by aliens for torts “in violation of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_international_law" title="Public international law">law of nations</a>,” provided that it will be some super body that decides what constitutes a violation of human rights.  And (assuming that Scalia thinks there should be an “exhaustion” requirement, even though, clearly, there is not one in the language of the statute) who—those lame Founders!—failed to include an “exhaustion” requirement in the statute.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div></div>
<div>Ditto for Kennedy, who’s angry because he thinks that the very first Congress’s position was that a U.S. company that allegedly commits a human rights violation could be sued in any court in the world, even though the statute actually only provides for lawsuits in U.S. federal courts, not for lawsuits in other countries’ courts.  Or at least, he later explains, he’s angry, and worried, that if the United States Congress can pass a law that allows aliens to sue foreign corporations in United States courts for torts “committed in violation of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_international_law" title="Public international law">law of nations</a> or a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_United_States_treaties" title="List of United States treaties">treaty of the United States</a>, that might encourage other countries to retaliate and enact a similar, mirror statute.  And then, woe is Exxon Mobil. 
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Repeatedly during yesterday’s argument, Kennedy raised issues with such a policy.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Why didn’t President Washington veto that law, for Chrissake!? Instead, the jerk, and that Congress, left it to a future generation of justices to rewrite the statute to limit it to lawsuits against U.S. companies and foreign companies that commit torts against a U.S. alien in violation of the law of nations or a treaty of the United States. (A generation of justices that includes four who, only three months ago, railed against their five colleagues for what the four railers said was an unconstitutional rewriting of a statute, no less. A <a href="http://topics.nytimes.com/top/reference/timestopics/organizations/s/supreme_court/affordable_care_act/index.html">very high-profile</a>statute.) </p>
<p>Oh, but wait. That original Congress actually did write the Alien Tort Statute to say that. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alien_Tort_Statute">Verbatim</a>. Even though the statute could encourage other countries to retaliate and enact a statute of their own that allows a U.S. company that allegedly commits a human rights violation to be sued in a court in that other country for violations of the law of nations, as defined by some super body. </p>
<p>Other countries haven’t done that yet. But they could. Whether or not the Supreme Court rewrites the Alien Tort Statute to discourage them from doing so, they could. Too bad that didn&#8217;t bother President Washington enough for him to veto the statute.</p></div>
<p>
<div>Also repeatedly yesterday, Samuel Alito <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/national/print/2012/10/as-scalia-falters-will-alito-fill-the-void-on-the-right/263049/">reiterated his own demand at the earlierargument </a>to know what, pray tell, connection the events at issue in the case have with this country.  But a better question is, why is that any of the Supreme Court’s business?  As the Court’s conservatives—led obsessively in recent years by Kennedy and Thomas—repeatedly remind at the robotic urging of state attorneys general, the Constitution grants Congress, not the courts, the authority to determine what types of cases the lower federal courts have “subject-matter jurisdiction,” i.e., the legal authority, to hear.  </div>
<div></div>
<div>This congressional power <i>is</i> subject to the constraints of other parts of the Constitution—for example, the Fourteenth Amendment and the Supremacy Clause, which Kennedy, <i>et al</i>., forget (or pretend to forget) apply to limit state courts’ free rein lest those insignificant parts of the Constitution infringe upon the sovereign dignity (their words, not mine) of states, by which they mean the sovereign dignity of state courts.  But the Fourteenth Amendment was added to the Constitution by a new set of framers, not the vaunted ones of the late 1700s, so that part of the Constitution doesn’t matter very much to the state-courts&#8217;-rights-to-violate-the-constitutional-rights-of-individuals crowd.  Unless of course some state legislature has, say, infringed upon the equal protection rights of an upscale high school student in Texas who graduated just below the top 10% of her high school class.  Or some other state legislature has limited the rights of corporate people to buy state politicians. </div>
<div></div>
<div>The defendant oil company in <i>Kiobel</i> <i>v. Royal Dutch Petroleum</i> doesn’t claim that the ATS would violate the Constitution if it is interpreted to allow lawsuits against them, by aliens, in federal court.  They just argue that the statute <i>shouldn’t</i> allow this, because, well, the events at issue have no connection with the United States and no other country has a similar law.  This appears to be good strategy, since, at least when state-court criminal defendants raise constitutional challenges in separate habeas corpus proceedings in federal court, the defendants almost always lose because the Supreme Court has interpreted a 1996 “jurisdictional” statute as effectively delegating to state courts the authority to violate the Constitution’s many guarantees in criminal cases.  This requires the federal courts to ignore not only the Fourteenth Amendment and the Supremacy Clause but also the provision in the Constitution’s provision that bars the suspension of the right of habeas corpus.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Kennedy’s incessant refrain in these cases is that, well, this is what Congress intended, and under the Constitution it is Congress that has the authority to enact federal-court-jurisdiction statutes.  But, setting aside whether the Supreme Court’s interpretation of that 1996 statute is even conceivably an accurate reflection of the intent of that Congress in enacting it, and the expectation of President Clinton in signing it—It was an election year, but still … really?—Kennedy &#038; Co. never appear concerned with the many, many, <i>many</i> policy problems caused by, say, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lockyer_v._Andrade">thedramatic difference between </a>the right of a federal-court criminal defendant or prisoner, and the right of a state-court criminal defendant or prisoner to effectively assert constitutional rights.  That is, by the fact that the Supreme Court has interpreted that statute as effectively eliminating that right by state-court defendants or prisoners.   
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Or, say, by the utterly unexplained privileging of state judicial branches, which now are virtually free to violate individuals’ constitutional rights, at least if those individuals are criminal defendants, and the other two branches of state governments: the legislative and the executive branches.  Professional courtesy is, well, courteous, but there really legitimate reason to make it a constitutional principle?
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>Tomorrow, the Court will hear a case in which that very issue will be addressed.  Seven years ago, almost to the day, in a unanimous opinion issued in a case called <i><a href="http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/cgi-bin/getcase.pl?court=US&#038;navby=case&#038;vol=000&#038;invol=04-8384">Dye v. Hofbauer</a></i>, without full briefing and oral argument, the Court interpreted that 1996 statute, known as the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antiterrorism_and_Effective_Death_Penalty_Act_of_1996">Antiterrorism and Effective Death Penalty Act</a> (AEDPA), as requiring the state appellate courts to actually acknowledge the existence of a federal constitutional issue raised by the criminal defendant in the appeal, and then to actually analyze and rule on that federal constitutional issue, if the state courts were to be entitled to the “deference” that AEDPA requires the federal courts to accord the state courts when the state court ruling is challenged in federal court as unconstitutional.  A “deference” that in recent years has morphed into abdication—into a blatant flipping of the Constitution’s Supremacy Clause.  The case to be heard tomorrow is <i><a href="http://www.scotusblog.com/case-files/cases/cavazos-v-williams/">Johnson v. Williams</a></i>, and in it, the Court will decide whether to overrule <i>Dye</i>—explicitly or, more likely, in effect without saying that that’s what it is doing.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>All in the name of the Constitution, y’know.  The very same Constitution that is about to allow the justices to rewrite a jurisdictional statute written by the Founders, so that it complies with the policy preferences of the current Supreme Court majority.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>When I read the transcript of tomorrow’s argument in <i>Johnson</i>, I’ll be looking for inquiries by Kennedy and Alito about the many policy problems with AEDPA, especially as the flip-the-Supremacy-Clause interpretation of it has metastasized over the years.  I won’t be holding my breath waiting to read that in the transcript, though, because I don’t want to turn blue.
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div><i>Dye</i>, by the way, was the first opinion issued by the Court, in the early fall of 2005, after John Roberts was sworn in.  But that was then, and Kennedy hadn’t yet fully gained his sovereign-dignity-of-state-courts sea legs.  Nor had he yet managed to convince the sycophantic so-called liberals to quietly join him in this juggernaut.  All the better for them to go along to get along when it’s a case that—bet on it—will get no mainstream-media attention.  
</p>
</div>
<div></div>
<div>It’s not like <i>Johnson</i> is a noisy culture-wars case, after all.  Not at all like it is. 
</p>
<p>&#8212;-<br />UPDATED: Scotusblog&#8217;s Lyle Denniston posted <a href="http://www.scotusblog.com/2012/10/argument-preview-what-does-a-courts-silence-mean/">an excellent pre-argument rundown</a> on <i>Johnson v. Williams</i> this afternoon.</div>
<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>./../../2012/10/justice-scalias-super-body-and-no-it-has-nothing-to-do-with-the-constitutions-free-exercise-clause-really.html/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
